<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 16</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 16-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Our hero's destiny here brings him into the midst of another of those easy going civilisations that were so common in the world before the modern spirit introduced its uncomfortable doctrine of the necessity for living always at high pressure. Though we find him now at the antipodes, he is in the same sub-race as in Ireland in the thirteenth life, and the conditions have much in common. The climate is much better, so that the settlements are no longer confined to the sunny sides of the hills. Crops are far larger and fruit is more plentiful, and life generally is easier in all respects. But the race displays its characteristics, its love for the open air, its realisation of the proximity of the unseen world, its sun-worship, and its distaste for temples made with hands.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The men of this fifth sub-race had entered the country only a few centuries before, dispossessing tribes who were apparently a mixture of Turanian and Lemurian stock. These aborigines had offered no serious resistance to the invaders, but had retired to the hills and the less accessible parts of the country, where they still existed in large numbers. There was little intercourse between the two races, except that in various places small groups of the Turanians abandoned their unfriendly attitude and came and made settlements in the immediate neighbourhood of the white men, for whom they were usually willing to work when required. The untamed part of this earlier race was regarded with horror and aversion, chiefly because of the peculiarly objectionable form of their religion, which eventually led to their complete subjugation, as will be seen later.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Almost all our characters are present in this life, most of them of course among the superior race, but a few among the Turano-Lemurians. The rulers of the country was Viraj, and according to the custom of this branch of the race the King was also ipso facto the head of the Church, that is to say, the High Priest. Viraj, however, was a strong and somewhat stern ruler, who had a great genius for administration. He was little attracted to the priestly side of his work, although he performed such duties as had to be done with a sharp military brevity which was impressive in its way. His oldest son Surya was from an early age drawn much more to the priestly than to the kingly side of the royal office, and this characteristic was so marked that as soon as he came of age Viraj turned over to him all that part of the work, in order that he himself might plunge with renewed ardour into the organisation of his country.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Surya married Alcyone, who appeared this time in a female body as the daughter of the younger brother of King Viraj. She had a most intense reverence and affection for her husband, and shared with him his devotion to the priestly side of his office. Though Surya was the heir-apparent, many of the duties that would naturally have fallen to him were left to his younger brother Leo, in order that he might be able to devote all his time to a re-organisation of the priesthood and its methods. His first children were the twin boys Mars and Mercury; and as soon as these twins began to be able to express their preferences it was manifest that they were respectively incarnations of the two sides of the royal office; for Mars seemed to care comparatively little for the temple ceremonies, while he manifested the most intense interest in the administrative work of his grandfather. Although the affection between the twin brothers was most touching, they differed entirely on this point; for Mercury's devotion was all to the temple services, which he constantly attended with his mother. Even already Viraj and Surya had decided that if they both lived long enough the crown should pass from grandfather to grandson Mars, leaving Surya to devote himself to the work which he loved, and Mercury to inherit high position in due course, thereby establishing a separation between the kingly and priestly offices.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
As years rolled on Alcyone's family rapidly increased, all its members being characters well known to us. It was one of her greatest pleasures to dream of their future, imagining for them all sorts of distinguished destinies. Some of her dreams seem to have been actual previsions; and her husband Surya, who used to listen to her with an indulgent smile, was on one occasion at least greatly impressed by one of her visions so much so that he took the words out of her mouth and spoke himself as though inspired:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 You and I, my wife, and these flowers of our race, have a wondrous destiny before us. As you follow me now, so shall you and they follow me in that glorious future. Some of these who now call you mother shall pass in advance of you, and shall be my more immediate helpers in the work which I have to do. And when your share in that work comes, others of these your children shall stand round you as helpers and disciples. So the members of this our family shall not be separated as so often happens; again and again shall they be here together, so that it becomes a permanent family whose members shall meet in fraternal affection through the ages that are yet to come. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So when Viraj was gathered to his fathers it was Mars, not Surya, who was proclaimed King in his stead; and it was not long after he came to the throne before it was found necessary to take further control of that part of the island inhabited by the Turano Lemurians. These latter had an obscene form of religion which, among other unpleasantness, involved occasional human sacrifices usually sacrifices of especially beautiful children. These were sometimes selected from among their own families, but more frequently one of their tribes made a raid upon another in the hope of finding suitable victims. On one occasion, however, it was decided by the priests of this unpleasant form of worship that an unusually choice sacrifice was required, because an unknown infectious disease had broken out among their people. So the priests met in conclave and decided that, as ordinary methods had proved ineffectual in turning aside the wrath of their deities, a white child should be captured and sacrificed.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Their only hope of obtaining such a prize was through some of those of their tribe who were in close touch with the ruling race. There had been a certain amount of intermarriage between the races, although this was discouraged by the authorities, and it was from some of these mulatto families that the most powerful and most scheming of the priests were drawn. Among them were found just at this period two with whom we are acquainted, Lacey and Tripos.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Aided by a woman named Cancer, they resolved to steal a child from the white settlements, and after much lurking and watching they contrived to carry off Phra, one of the grandsons of Surya and Alcyone. It was some little time before he was missed, and still longer before his relations suspected what had happened; but as soon as the truth was realised the boy's father, Naga, hurriedly got together a few friends and retainers, and started out in pursuit. As they knew nothing of the secret hiding-places of the aborigines they would probably have failed in their quest, but for the aid given to them by some others of the mulattos who were thoroughly well disposed towards the white race. Assisted by these, Naga and his party were able to overtake the abductors and rescue the child before the tribe could be called together for the sacrifice. They made prisoners of the three people we have mentioned, and brought them before King Mars, who promptly had them executed, and furthermore issued an edict that the interior portion of the country should be brought directly under his rule, and that sacrifices of all sorts should be entirely suppressed. This was done, but the aborigines regretted their sanguinary faith, and were by no means well disposed towards the new regime.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This was on the whole a quiet and uneventful life, passed in a pleasant land and among an amiable people. They were not by any means unlike those of their race whom we have already described as living in Ireland a few centuries before. They were good farmers and bold seamen, hospitable and affectionate, showing a great reverence for old age. The great men among them were rather orators and poets than fighters; and certain amount of excellence along these lines was expected from the leaders of the people, as all judgements, sermons and public speeches  of any sort on great occasion were invariably delivered in extemporaneous verse. They were clever builders, weavers and dyers; and their woodcarving was remarkably good, intricate and detailed. The life was on the whole happy and simple one, with no striking events, and at the end of it Alcyone passed  peacefully away at the elevated age of eighty-eight.
</view>
</text>
</body>