<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 48</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 48-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The wonderful influence of the Lord Buddha changed for Alcyone the length of the interval between his lives, but it in no way affected the tendency to spend these lives in India. Once more we find him in the sacred land born in the nineteenth year of the reign of King Harsha (3726 Kali Yuga, or A.D. 624), near Kanyakubja, now Kanauj, on the Ganges. King Harsha was also called Siladitya; he came to the throne in the year A.D. 606. Alcyone was the son of a brahman named Jayasekara (Ant); the family was Buddhist by religion, though Brahman by descent.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Large numbers of people of all castes had at this period definitely embraced Buddhism as their religion, and they did not therefore recognise caste as such; but notwithstanding this, those among them who were Brahmans by descent were still socially recognised and treated as Brahmans by the others who held their ancestral religion. The bonds of caste were strong, but yet the restrictions were not so irksome as at present, because these Brahmans who became Buddhists certainly did not in any way lose caste by doing so, even though it involved receiving and eating with men of other castes who also professed Buddhism. The Brahman families who still held the Hindu religion intermarried quite freely with those Brahmans who embraced Buddhism, each party to the contract keeping to his or her religion without interfering with the other. However, those Brahmans who because Buddhists do not seem, as far as I can see, to have intermarried with people of lower castes, although socially they received them quite freely.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The period was a somewhat curious one, for in many ways it had the marks of an effete and worn out civilisation. Everything was highly specialised, and there was a great deal of luxury, while the virility which had characterised the race so markedly in the time of the Lord Buddha seemed to be absent. Everybody lived by rule down to the minutest circumstances of daily life; the civilisation was still a good and a noble one, but the people were doing things far more because it was the custom to do them then because they felt strongly moved towards goodness themselves. King Harsha was a man of tremendous energy and a great conqueror; he tried to reconstitute the empire of Ashoka, but succeeded only very partially. He was, however, a great patron of Buddhism, and gave huge donations to its monasteries and temples.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone's name in this life was Upasena, though he was far better known by that of Dhammalankara, which he took afterwards, upon assuming the yellow robe. His mother was a good and pious woman, and he owed much to her early training. He had a strong religious sense, and as a boy he was always planning what he would do for Buddhism in the future. Another side of him which seemed somewhat incongruous was that he had a curious mechanical genius, and invented for the use of the household several useful little machines.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It was the fashion of the time for fathers to talk about dedicating their sons to the monastic life, and greatly to applaud any young man who adopted it; but the strange artificiality of the period showed itself again in the fact that though almost every boy born of Buddhist parents put on the robe for a year or two, and lived during that time in the monastery as did the others, the number who really made this permanently their life was comparatively small. In Alcyone's case, however, the pious mother was eagerly enthusiastic for the life of the Order, and at an early age she fired her  son with the same enthusiasm, so that he promised her to make this his vacation.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
That promise stood him in good stead in a time of trial, for he was scarcely more than fifteen when he fell deeply in love with Ajax an unusually lovely young lady who was some sort of cousin of his. The girl reciprocated his feelings, for he was strikingly handsome boy. Their affection was deep and true and passionate, and after their mutual confession of it and their pledges of undying love it would certainly have followed the usual path, but for the boy's recollection of that promise to his mother.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He said nothing of the matter to his father and mother, but he had a long and terrible struggle with himself, principally because though he felt clear as to the direction in which his duty lay, inclination was clear to point out to him that perhaps he had no right, even though prepared to make the sacrifice himself, to force similar sacrifice upon Ajax. It cost him much to make his decision, and caused him many days of great mental anguish; but at last he decided that at all costs to himself his true vocation must be followed, and the promise to his mother must be kept, and that against the disappointment of his cousin, if he took one course, he must set the even greater disappointment of his mother, if he took the other.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So he spoke to Ajax and told her all; and though at first with many tears she tried to shake his resolution, when she found that it was unalterable she also rose to the height of the sacrifice, and declared that since he intended to join the Sangha she also for his sake, since she could never forget him or love another, would take up the religious life and become a nun. This she did, and she faithfully kept her vow.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Young as he was, this love affair had an enormous influence in his life. In many ways it made a man of him, there and then; and when the scene was over, and vows of eternal fidelity yet also of eternal separation had been exchanged, he went straight to his mother, told her the whole story from beginning to end, and announced that he could keep his vow only if he were allowed instantly to become a samanera , or probationer, and so were permitted to enter the monastery. The mother understood, and though she wept for the suffering through which her son had passed, she at the same time rejoiced that he had been strong enough for this great act of renounciation, and that now he was really resolved to dedicate his life to the noblest of all objects. So the boy went with her to his father, and rather announced his intention of assuming the yellow robe than asked permission to do so. The father applauded the idea, though he himself was far from wishing to imitate it, and the great ceremony of the upsampada , or consecration, took place as soon as possible.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It was very different in its ornate ritual from the simple yet most impressive ceremony by which the Lord Buddha Himslef had received him during his previous birth. Then he had simply bowed before the Lord, had answered searching questions, and made some promises; he was then taken aside by Dharmajyoti, and he cast off his ordinary dress and put on the yellow robe of those that help the world. Then, dressed in that symbol of his new life, he returned and prostrated himself at the feet of the Lord, who blessed him solemnly as His new pupil, and told him to see to it that his life proved worthy of the robe which now he wore.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
That was the custom of the Lord, but by this time the whole affair had become an elaborate ritual and the occasion for a great feast, to which all friends of the family were invited. The candidate was dressed with the greatest magnificence, all the family jewels being heaped upon him; he wore the crown of a prince, and robes made in imitation of the state dress of the King. In all this uncomfortable finery he held a kind of final reception, at which all his friends came and congratulated him and offered him presents, he presiding for several days over the feasting, and all honour being paid to him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Upasena went through all this because it was expected of him, yet in the midst of all this apparent triumph he had no feeling but utter boredom and the keenest impatience for the time when all should be over. One feature which caused him much of suffering was that the cousin whom he loved so dearly was compelled by family custom to take part in all this entertainment, and to offer her congratulations with the rest.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At last came the day of the ordinance ceremony, when he appeared before the head of the monastery. Aldebran who sat to receive him with all his monks mustered around him. One by one he took off all his jewels, his crown and his gorgeous robes, and cast them at the feet of the chief abbot, announcing that he had done with them for ever and with all that they symbolised. Bending before the abbot, clad in one simple white robe only, he then had to submit to a long and weary catechism, and to hear the recitation of a great number of texts; but at last the vow of the Order was solemnly administered to him, and he was allowed to go with his chosen teacher (for every applicant must choose one among the elder monks for his responsible teacher) into a sort of vestry, where he cast off even his white robe and put on instead the beautiful robe of the Sangha.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
That dress at least had been unchanged through all the centuries of his sojourn in the heaven world; and even as he endued himself with sojourn in the heaven-world; and even as he returned himself with the three robes which were henceforth to represent all his worldly possessions, the act seemed somehow strangely familiar to him, and there came to him a half-memory of the glorious Presence in which ones before he had performed the symbolical act. Then he went out again into the great hall of monastery, and prostrated himself at the feet of the chief abbot, even as twelve hundred years before at the feet of the Lord Himself, and so once more he took upon himself the life of the ascetic, though this time at the age of fifteen instead of forty-two.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He plunged into his new studies with ardour, in order to help him to forget his love or rather, not to forget but to sanctify it, and to raise it to a higher level. The monastery to which he belonged was a great and rich one, and among other things it was noted for its magnificent library. Dhammalankara devoted himself to this, even beyond the studies that were expected from him. He seemed to have a love for the books, and applied to the librarian for permission to arrange them and keep them in order, and in a surprisingly short time he knew the title and the exact place of every book in that vast library.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So passed some years of eager work, his mother coming often to see him and to talk with him, though now as a monk he might not even touch her hand. Some natural maternal sorrow she felt, that she could no longer embrace her boy; yet this was far outweighed by the solemn joy that now he had entered upon his upward course, and that her richest hopes had been fulfilled. Once it had been she who blessed him and breathed her vows over him; now she rejoiced to receive a blessing at his hands, and loved to recite her daily precepts at his dictation.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Though she might no longer embrace him, there was no law to prevent her from looking at him when he passed through the streets unconscious of her fond regard. She watched him then with a joy and pride which had perhaps a certain amount of justification, for he was certainly by far the handsomest monk in the monastery, and the beautiful primrose colour, though as that fades with constant washing and they are dyed again and again, they become a rich deep orange, and eventually if not renewed, a rather dirty brown. His father too came occasionally, but had little to say except platitudes, though he also was gratified at the appearance of his son, and at the reputation for diligence and sanctity which he had already acquired.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Unfortunately others besides his mother were attracted to his handsome face, and among them Scorpio a woman of considerable notoriety in her own line of life and of doubtful well, no, scarcely doubtful reputation. She saw him passing in the street, and was smitten  by an unholy affection for him; she came to hear him preach and tried to catch his eye, but without success. Then she came to consult him privately and to seek for advice, for which however he referred her to older monks, not seeming to observe the various obvious hints which she threw out.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Finding this ineffectual, she invited him to her house to recite the texts of blessing for a sick person a call which he could not refuse to obey; and while there she tried in various ways to entrap him, contriving to expose herself before him as a temptation to break his vows. The young man, however was filled with disgust, and made his escape at the earliest convenient opportunity, so that Scorpio's lust was turned to hate, and she vowed to compass his disgrace and overthrow. Many men were in her toils, and were quite ready to help her in her schemes, so she worked out an exceedingly ingenious plot, inducing a certain girl to accuse him, and herself (with every appearance of reluctance) bearing false witness against him, and bringing several men to support the charge from different sides.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone of course indignantly denied the whole thing, but the case was pressed, and brought before the chief abbot. He however, being an astute man, and somewhat shrewd questions, which exposed contradictions in the story of the accusers. He soon discovered sufficient to warrant him in laying the matter before King Harsha, who promptly enquired into it, laid bare the whole nefarious plot, and banished the woman and her fellow-conspirators, confiscating all their wealth and transferring it to Alcyone's temple. The chief abbot, though thus entirely convinced of Alcyone's innocence, still thought it desirable to remove so handsome a young monk for a time from the place where such plots were so easily possible, and so he sent him out upon a pilgrimage to the great Buddhist shrines, which occupied him for more than a year.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A year or two before this, when he was just twenty years of age, his monastery had entertained a celebrated Chinese pilgrim. Hiuen Tsang, who had been received as a distinguished visitor, to whom every possible honour was paid. On that occasion Alcyone was one of hundreds of monks who joined in a great procession which was arranged by the King himself an extraordinary procession, many parts of which must have seemed to the spectators in no way religious. Although the monks and the gorgeously caprisoned temple elephants took part in it, there were also men dressed as wild beasts, and others dancing and showing a curious sort of sword-play with long sticks, at which they were extremely clever. Still others were dressed to imitate aboriginal tribes, hillmen and foreigners, some apparently being intended for Greeks or Romans, with faces painted white.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The great procession was undoubtedly effective, though the rejoicings of the occasion came near to being marred by an appalling accident, for some Hindu fanatic (probably insane) rushed at the King and attempted to kill him. He was however seized and disarmed before he could effect his nefarious purpose, and King Harsha at the time took no notice whatever, but ordered the cortege to proceed as though nothing had happened. Afterwards, however, he made strict enquiry into the affair, and banish a number of Brahmans who were accused of complicity in the plot.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The King went in great state to Prayag (now Allahabad), and there went through a curious ceremony of renounciation, or extravagant charity, giving away to the poor or to the temples all his jewels, his crown, and even his royal robes. Unfortunately, only a few years later, in the year 648, King Harsha died, and the great Empire, which he had built up so labouriously and at the cost of so much bloodshed, fell rapidly to pieces.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Immediately after his death his prime minister, a man of the name of Arjuna, seized upon the supreme power. He was, however, able to assert it over only a small part of the country that had owned Harsha's sway; and in less than two years he was summarily suppressed by a Mongolian army. After that there seem to have been several claimants to sovereignty, and presently a prince named Vasudharman ruled for some tithe not, however ever Harsha's Empire, but over a far smaller state or subdivision, or it called Panchala. Through all this disturbance the city of Kanyakubja seems to have been strangely little affected; its temples at any rate were entirely uninjured, and experienced no greater trouble than certain fluctuations in revenue, the Buddhist or the Hindu temples reaping the greatest profit according to the religion of the ruler who happened to be uppermost at the time.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When Alcyone was sent on his pilgrimage he visited all the important Buddhist shrines in the north of India, and therefore naturally to a great extent retraced the steps of his previous incarnation, though he knew nothing of this. Twice, however, he had a curious vision which involved the recollection of some of the more striking scenes of that previous incarnation. The first time was at Buddha Gaya itself, where, meditating in devotional ecstacy under the Bo-tree, he had a very clear and vivid presentment of the wonderful scene of the Illumination. The other occasion was in the garden near Rajgriha, where on two successive days he was able to recall two pictures from the past his own solemn pledge of future attainment given to the Buddha, and that scene in the garden when first he took his cousin Mizar to hear the teaching of the Lord. He visited Sarnath also, and found there a magnificent grey granite lion pillar erected on the spot where the great Master used to preach. This pillar was at the centre of a huge semicircle of other pillars facing towards the great dagoba, while behind them, outside of the curve of the semicircle, were arranged the enormous and thickly populated monastery buildings.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone regretted the death of King Harsha , who had been a good friend and patron of his monastery; but , as I have said, the political troubles and disturbances of the next few years made wonderfully little difference to the temples or the monasteries. It is true that they missed the active  patronage of the King, but the crowds of pilgrims came and went in spite of the wars, and even the Mongolian army felt as deep respect for the temples of the Buddha as did the ordinary inhabitants of the country. Some six years after King Harsha's death, Alcyone's old friend and helper Dharmajyoti visited the monastery, but this time he was the celebrated teacher and preacher Aryasanga. He remained for some time in Kanyakubja, attracting huge crowds by his eloquence. Indeed they would fain have had him settle there altogether, but he had set his heart upon carrying the purer teaching of the Buddha into the highlands of Tibet, and so he would not tarry on his way.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Naturally the old tie at once reasserted itself, though however it may have been with Aryasanga, Alcyone at any rate did not know the reason of the compelling attraction which instantly and at first sight drew him to the feet of the great revivalist. Aryasang smiled upon the younger man and drew him quickly into close relations with himself, and when in a few months the time came for his further journey towards the hills, Alcyone was one of those whom he chose to accompany him. The good abbot Aldebran also thought much of Alcyone, but was quite willing to let him go upon an expedition as this.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
For many days they travelled, far up into the mountains, in the leisurely fashion of those days, making halts of weeks in duration at various monasteries on the way, Aryasanga always preaching to the monks and the people, and inspiring them with his own fiery zeal and enthusiasm. Many a time on such occasions he appointed Alcyone to speak to the people, and he always aquitted himself well. Their first long stay was at a monastery in a beautiful valley in Nepal, and here Aryasanga and his band remained for nearly a year, teaching the monks, organising the religion generally over a large section of the country, and making this monastery a kind of headquarters for their reformed faith. It was at this monastery a kind of headquarters for their reformed faith. It was at this monastery that Arayasanga left to his successors that wonderful book of extracts which he called The Book of the Golden Precepts, which commenced with the Stanzas of Dzyan, and included many quotations from the writings of the great Nagarjuna included many quotations from the writings of the great Nagarjuna included many quotations from writings of the great Nagarjuna (Mercury), of whom in an earlier life in Greece he had been so devoted a follower when he was Kleineas, and Nagarjuna was Pythagoras.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then after staying there for nearly twelve months he went on over the mountains to Lhassa, he left Alcyone at the Nepalese monastery to help and direct the studies of the community which he had reorganised; and it was Alcyone who prepared and added to that book the reports of the discourses of Aryasanga, three of which Madame Blavatsky has translated for us in The Voice of the Silence, so that we owe that priceless volume to his care in reporting, just as in this present incarnation we owe to him our possession of the exquisite companion volume, At the Feet of the Master.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
For some two years he remained there, and then returned to his own monastery at Kanyakubja, in 657. The old abbot was unfeignedly glad to see him and received him with great honour. Though still quite a young man, he was regarded with great respect because of his close association with the revered Aryasanga. He gradually acquired a considerable reputation of his own, both for learning and for intuition. People came even from great distances, and after hearing their stories (if the case was difficult one and beyond his own judgement) he would pass into a condition of deep meditation, from which he always emerged with some inspiration as to what he should say to the people. The advice which he gave was always sound and wise, and it produced a great impression upon the minds of his visitors. He retained still his early love for books, and in addition to his other work he held for some years the post of librarian to the monastery.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In 667 there came to him an embassy from the temple in Nepal, praying him to return thither and become abbot of that monastery, since there was no one among the monks who felt himself worthy to take his place. Alcyone was much divided in mind, and hesitated long with regard to this matter; he loved his work and his books in Kanyakubja, and he could not but feel that he was of use to the many who came thither to consult him. But at the same time the temple in the hills represented the work of his great friend and teacher Aryasanga, and to help that also seemed a duty. After long consultation with the chief abbot, who had always remained his firmest friend, he decided to accede to the summons. The old abbot blessed him sorely, but yet that he thought on the whole that it was his duty to go.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So once more he entered the wonderful hill country, and dwelt for ten years in that lonely monastery, directing the work, keeping alive the organisation of Aryasanga, and guiding and stimulating the faith of a great mountain district. All this time, however, one of his chief objects was to train the Nepalese monks to manage their own monastery; from the first he selected Phoenix, the man whom he thought most suitable, and prepared him to take his own place and to set him free to return to India as soon as might be. There was much work, however, to be done, and it was not until 677 that at last he turned his face southward again. Even then it was only upon receipt of an urgent message from Aldebran, his own chief abbot at Kanyakubja, who was by this time ninety years of age, and wrote that he found himself no longer able to administer the complicated affairs of that great monastery, and that there was no one into whose hands he could so confidently deliver his charge as those of his dearly loved pupil.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So Alcyone solemnly installed as abbot of the Napalese monastery the successor whom he had been so carefully training, and giving them all a final and solemn benediction, he turned his back for the last time upon that wonderful snowy range, and journeyed into the warmer country of the plains below. He was received with a popular ovation, and treated with the greatest reverence by all. The chief abbot welcomed him with tears of joy, and would have delivered at once into his hands the insignia of office. Alcyone, however, preferred to arrange that though he himself would do all the work and take all the responsibility, his old teacher should retain the nominal position as long as he lived. The old man lingered on for some happy years, but Alcyone practically ruled everything, and ruled it wisely and well, so that when Aldebran died there was really no break in the continuity of the management.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone in his old age remained as enthusiastic as ever, but was gentler than in the days of his youth, and though he preached constantly against the great luxury of the times, he contrived to do so without alienating his audience, because he never attacked it fiercely or characterised it as wickedness, as did so many other reformers, but simply gently and persistently reminded his hearers that all this also would pass away, and that attachment to objects leads always to sorrow. He established and extended the influence which his old patron Aldabran had gained for his temple, and he made it distinctly a powerful factor for good, not only in the town, but in the whole of this Kingdom of Panchala. The times were troubled and there was much disturbance, but the influence of Alcyone and his predecessor aided much to hold steady a large proportion of the more influential of the people of the city.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Often the leader of some of the rival factions would come to him to plead the justice of their cause and ask for his blessing upon their warfare; but his answer was always the same that no cause however good , could make wrong right or justify slaughter and oppression; that the teaching of the Buddha was clear, that men should live together in peace and in love, and that it mattered little who bore the burden of ruling the country, so long as its inhabitants lived according to the precepts of the Good Law. So he died at last in the odour of sanctity in the year 694, and though in the line of his successors there were few men who were not more worldly than he, the prestige which he and his teacher had given to the monastery clung round it like a halo for some centuries to come, and even the barbarous invaders from the north usually respected the lives of its monks, though sometimes they robbed it of its treasures.
</view>
</text>
</body>