<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 45</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 45-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Faithful once more to Hindustan, our hero took birth in the year 2180 B.C. at small town called Mopa, in the kingdom of Wardha, in what is now the Nagpur district. His name was Bhrojagohallamarshi, and his father, Albireo, was a Brahman of the highest type a thoroughly good man, earnest, steady, persevering and charitable. His mother, Leo, was a worthy helpmate to such a husband, so Alcyone may be considered distinctly fortunate in his parents. His education was carefully supervised, and was of a somewhat more modern type than in the earlier incarnations. Enormous numbers of verses were still learnt by heart; indeed Alcyone acquired at quite an early age the title of Dwivedi, and later on that of Trivedi, for learning by heart two and three Vedas respectively a stupendous task. But he also learnt grammar, geography, astrology, arithmetic and medicine the last of rather remarkable character. He was considered a most promising boy, and later in life was respected as an unusually learned man. He spoke at least four languages the older Sanskrit; some dialect derived from it, which was then the common language of the people; and also two other which were probably aboriginal languages.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When he came of age he married a beautiful girl, Algol, and chose as his profession that of a schoolmaster, in which he was eminently successful. He was always kind and gentle with his boys, and was idolised by them; they would do anything for him, and take any trouble to please him, and he on his part spared no pains to make them understand whatever he taught them. He greatly enjoyed his life and work, and as his home life was also happy one, this incarnation may be considered a propitious one in its earlier years, although it closed with disaster and undeserved disgrace.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In 2150, when he was only thirty years of age and had still quite young children, his country was invaded by some neighbouring king. Alcyone did not at all like fighting, and he regarded the whole affair as a ridiculous waste of time; nevertheless, he took his place in the ranks, and bore his part bravely in what had to be done. The Wardha army, however, was defeated, and Alcyone was compelled to take his young family and fly from his home to escape massacre. They wandered in exile for three years, sometimes suffering greatly from privations; but at the end of that time the invader was himself attacked from another direction, and a successful revolution restored the previous ruling line of Wardha, so that Alcyone was able to return to his beloved school.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The ravages of war had been followed by famine; his old pupils were all scattered, and only a moiety could be gathered together again. He had now another spell of quiet life, during which he gradually built up his school until it exceeded its former strength, and he was much delighted to find that his eldest son Libra had inherited his power of teaching and his love for that profession, and so made an able assistant.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The shadow that was to darken his life began to loom over him in 2127; his youngest daughter Mizar, whom he loved tenderly, was then fifteen, and an undesirable suitor appeared for her hand in the person of our old histrion Scorpio a man of more than twice her age, already noted for a life of debauchery, and credited with the possession of a most violent and vindictive temper. The man, however, was rich, powerful, and a scion of a family which it was not well to offend; so though Alcyone was absolutely determined that he would not give his daughter to such a person, the refusal could not be made as abrupt and decided as he would have wished it to be. The undesirable suitor absolutely declined to take a negative answer, and persisted in thrusting himself at all times and seasons upon the poor girl, until his persecution became a nightmare to her.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone was at last driven to tell him in no measured terms that his proposals could not under any circumstances be accepted, and indeed to forbid him to enter the house. The man was violently indignant, and swore, with much abusive language that not only would he have the girl in spite of her father, but that his revenge upon that father for daring to insult him should be one of no ordinary character. Alcyone was much troubled about this affair, because, although he could not possibly have done otherwise, he still knew well that this man had powerful connections if he chose to use them, and that a rich and unscrupulous man is always a dangerous enemy. However, he heard nothing more of the matter for a time, and he hoped that the undesirable suitor had had his fleeting fancy attracted towards some other object.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
But one night he heard screams proceeding from his daughter's room, and, catching up a dagger and rushing in half-dressed, he found the villain, with two other men to help him, in the very act of carrying off his daughter, with evidence of peculiar outrage. Though only thus partially armed, and only one against three, he rushed at once upon the ravisher and stabbed him to the heart. The other men fled, although one of them wounded him in his flight. He could not seriously regret the act which had been forced upon him, but nevertheless he knew that to kill a member of a rich and powerful house was a dangerous action, no matter now great the provocation may have been; so he judged it wise to have himself carried at the earliest dawn in a litter to the court of the Raja, so that he himself might state his case before a complaint could be filed against him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He told the whole truth to the king, exactly as it had occurred. The Monarch had little difficulty in believing the story, for the dead man's character was well known, and Alcyone's reputation was a good one. The Raja expressed perfect sympathy and assured him that the law should not punish him for the deed, which he considered entirely justifiable; but at the same time powerful enemies, from the subtler forms of whose vengeance even he, the king, might not be able to shield him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Meanwhile the Raja forestalled any complaint or criticism by himself issuing a notice announcing the death of the ravisher, and the circumstances under which it had taken place, adding a free pardon to Alcyone, and an expression of his belief that no brave man could have acted otherwise than he had done. After that there was nothing more to be said, and the majority of his people heartily approved the manifesto; the injured family thought it politic to appear to agree with the general verdict, but at the same time they gave elaborate funeral ceremonies to their kinsman, and contrived in various small ways to make it apparent that they were by no means ready to forget and forgive the stain that had fallen on their name.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
From this time onwards Alcyone's life was never free from all kinds of intrigues and accusations; and he soon began to realise that this was due not merely to the physical plane persecution of a powerful family, but also, and much more, to a determined attempt from the astral plane to compass his ruin. Indeed, the dead man showed himself to him many times in dreams, always threatening him with the absolute certainty of destruction at his hands. Alcyone was a brave man, but this perpetual pressure from unexpected quarters soon began to get upon his nerves. He never knew what would happen next, but he knew quite certainly that something would happen, that it would be something unpleasant, and that it would come upon him suddenly from the quarter from which he least expected it. Mysterious losses fell upon him;; pupils were withdrawn from him on the most flimsy excuses; and he began to see that shortly he would be in serious monetary difficulties.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It happened that he had a rich and childless uncle (Cancer), who had the reputation of a miser of the most pronounced type. As Alcyone was his nearest living relation, and it had always been understood that he was to be his heir, he bethought himself of applying to this somewhat unpleasant old man for financial assistance. The old man, refused him with contumely, and assured him that no single coin of whatever money he possessed should ever by any chance pass into his hands. Alcyone was not unnaturally indignant at this treatment, and perhaps spoke somewhat unwisely; but he certainly cherished no resentment against the old man, and he was much horrified when, the next night, he found a strong and almost irresistible suggestion coming into  his head to go and kill this somewhat unworthy relation, and relieve his most pressing necessities by the use of the miser's store.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Such a suggestion coming into his mind so strongly quite confounded him, and he could not in the least understand it, until suddenly he seemed half to see and half to sense behind it the form of the suitor whom he had been obliged to kill; and he realised that this diabolical suggestion was only another of that man's methods of trying to injure him. This once understood, the suggestion was instantly and finally repudiated, and he thought little more of it. until suddenly news arrived that his old curmudgeon  of an uncle had mysteriously disappeared and then, a little later, that his body had been found, showing clear traces of murder.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The next news that he had after this was brought by the officers of the law, who came to arrest him for the commission of the crime. He of course protested his innocence, but they simply laughed at what he said, and told him that he could explain all that to the judge, but that they did not think that he would succeed in persuading him to believe him. He lay in prison for some time, and was then brought up for trial. The case as represented against him utterly confounded him; his own dagger had been found concealed in his uncle's room, and the wounds upon the body had obviously been made by that, or some exactly similar weapon. Two men swore to having seen him enter his uncle's house on the night in question, and his uncle's servant testified to having admitted him, and afterwards having heard the sounds of a struggle of some sort, and heavy groans proceeding from the door closed in some way that made it impossible to open it, and when some hours afterwards he succeeded in making his way in, he found no one there, though the blood and the traces of the struggle were evident.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Other men testified to having clearly seen Alcyone carrying a huge load in a sack, which might well have been a human body, a few hours later during the same night; and he had been walking in the direction of the place where the body was afterwards found. The servant positively identified the body as that of his master; as it had been hidden under water, the face had been eaten away by fishes, and was not therefore actually recognisable, but there was no mistake as to the clothes and general shape and appearance of the corpse.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In the face of such circumstantial evidence the judge could scarcely hesitate; but when, even at the last moment, thinking of the unblemished reputation of Alcyone, he delayed to pronounce the sentence, another witness appeared who, passing beneath the window of the dead man's room, had heard a furious altercation, in which he had recognised the voices of Alcyone and his uncle, the latter crying for mercy and the former angrily refusing it. the witness declared that he had waited for a time to see what would come of it, and watched until he saw Alcyone come forth bearing the sack upon his shoulders as previously described, and with an expression of great fear upon his countenance and obvious bloodstains upon his clothing. A cloak of his with bloodstains on it was produced in court; and the judge reluctantly pronounced the death penalty, adding to it remarks of deep regret that one who had been so universally respected for many years should, in a moment of revengeful passion, have been guilty of so barbarous a deed. Alcyone of course protested his innocence all through, but as the proofs accumulated he seemed quite stunned, and at last he could only say:  I do-not believe that my uncle is dead; but at least his disappearance will kill me. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He was sent back to prison and condemned to die at daybreak the next morning. That evening in his cell he received a visit from a foreign priest who had passed through the town some two years previously, as he was making a pilgrimage to all the principal shrines of India. Alcyone had offered entertainment to this visitor on that occasion, and he had spent two or three weeks in his house. The stranger's name was Sarthon (but we know him as Mercury), and he was a priest initiated into the Egyptian Mysteries. He and Alcyone had many a time discussed religious matters and Alcyone had learnt much from him, being especially struck by the identity, according to Sarthon's explanation, of two religions which exteriorly differed as much as did the Egyptian and the Hindu.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
On this last night of his life Sarthon, who was now passing through the town on his way back to Egypt, called upon him, and after condoling with him, gave him a peculiar message which he said was communicated to him by One who was of far greater power in the Mysteries than himself. It was to the effect that although his condemnation seemed unjust, in reality it was not so, for this death was not for the alleged murder of an old man(who indeed was still alive), but for other actions committed far back in the past; that he should make cheerfully and bravely this final payment of that ancient debt, since by it his way should be cleared of much that obstructed it, and hereafter the Path to the Hidden Light and the Hidden Work would lie clear before him; and, said Sarthon:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 I myself to whom you have shown hospitality, shall take your hand and conduct you along it; for this work is given to me by Him whom none can disobey. Therefore have no fear, for all this is well, though it seems so ill; and those whom you love will not suffer through your death. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Saying this he left him with a gesture of farewell, and next morning at sunrise Alcyone was duly beheaded. Not three days had passed before the supposed victim of the murder was captured by some of the Raja's officers, and brought before him. Then the whole plot was revealed; but the old uncle declared to the last that this was no act of his, that the rejected suitor had appeared before him to hide himself, and to arrange everything so as to throw the blame of his disappearance upon his nephew.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Raja (Orpheus), hearing this, ordered the arrest of all the witnesses, yet did not put them to death because, though examined separately, they all without connivance agreed in the same story, every one of them bearing witness that he had been forced into the part he took by the dead man, who was well known to them all. The Raja, however, made, special offerings to the Gods in atonement for having put an innocent man to death, and decreed a large pension to the wife of the man who had been unjustly executed, with a special grant to the daughter in connection with whom all this difficulty had first arisen. So Mercury's prophecy came true, and as far as money went, those whom he loved did not lose by his death; but it was a terrible  affliction to his sons, who held the family of the dead ravisher responsible for it, and commenced a bitter feud against them in consequence, which lasted for many generations. The other part of Mercury's prediction has also been fulfilled, for from the life which closed with this undeserved decapitation began the rapid progress along the Path of the Hidden Light and the Hidden Work which has culminated in this present life in the  entry upon the stream', which has made Alcyone a  member of the Great White Brotherhood which exists but for the helping of the world. And Mercury leads him still, in fulfilment of that promise made thousands of years ago.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Orpheus, the local King, owed allegiance to the overlord Rama, the grandson and Successor of Mars. Rama had married Alcyone's aunt Osiris, so that it is probable that by appealing to family influence Alcyone might have obtained some further consideration of his case; but he had a feeling that as a matter of principle such influence should not be used. Also his father Albireo had in youth seriously differed in opinion from the other members of the family on certain points, and had gradually withdrawn himself from them. So Alcyone felt that it would be improper to claim relationship now just because he happened to be in undeserved trouble.
</view>
</text>
</body>