<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 35</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 35-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The car of Juggarnant (properly Jagannath, the Lord of World), in the town of Puri on the Bay of Bengal, is famous in every civilised country, and we were regaled in our nurseries upon gruesome stories of the iniquities connected with it. Why so much excitement was aroused by the garbled accounts of it given by early missionaries, it is somewhat difficult to say, for not even the most bigoted sectarian could pretend that all the slaughter which the temple of Jagannath has seen since its foundation equals in horror and cruelty one day of the ghastly tortures of the Christian Inquisition. But nevertheless Jagannath has a world-wide reputation, and there seems reason to suppose that, though it by no means deserves it now, it may have done so some thousands of years ago. The glimpse which we had of its methods at the close of the twenty-eighth life of this series prepares us to find that unpleasant practices were still going on there in 10,429 B.C., when Alcyone was born at a coast-town called Kanura, only a few miles from Puri.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
His father Brihat had been a great Aryan leader, but now that the invading bands had reached the Sea, he had a great reputation as a wise and holy man, full of devotion. Alcyone's mother in this life was Uranus, an earnest and devoted woman. The eldest children of this couple were two sisters, twins, Neptune and Siwa, and these two had a great influence over Alcyone. Mizar also appears as a sister, four years younger that Alcyone, whom he loved and protected, and Mizar was devoted to him in return.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone was earnest, eager, and easily impressible. He responded at once to true affection, but shrank into stolidity if treated unkindly. He had an intense admiration for his father, his mother and his elder sisters. He was extremely  sensitive, and to some extent psychic and clairvoyant when young sufficiently so at least to see nature-spirits and sometimes to hear voices, especially one which occasionally gave him counsel at crises in his life. He was always fond of the sea, and was perpetually swimming in it, or rowing sailing on it; and as a small boy he would have liked nothing better than to be a sailor. On one occasion he was some distance out in a small boat with a clumsy sail, when he was caught by a sudden squall of great severity. The people watching on shore thought that he must inevitably be lost, but just at the critical moment the voice told him to keep his presence of mind, and gave him directions what to do, so that he brought in his boat in safety, in a way which could not have been surpassed by the most experienced seaman, and by the use of a manoeuvre of which few would have thought.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He was much interested in all religious ceremonies, and performed them solemnly and effectively. His father, seeing this, was encouraged to hope that he might have the priestly vocation, which was the dearest wish of his heart for him. The boy was delighted at the idea, and his sisters also encouraged it, so he was entered as a novice, and was proud of it. his life in the temple was pleasant to him, for all the priests were attracted by his charming ways, and thus every one helped him and made his work easy. The religion seems to have been principally Sun-worship, and it is curious to note that they spoke of their Deity always as the  Sea-born Sun . When Alcyone came to man's estate he married Ajax, and in the course of the years had a family of twelve children.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In the neighbouring town of Puri there was still a great centre of one of the forms of the old Atlantean religion of the darker sort the worship of an entity which required human sacrifices, but in return for them seems to have displayed a large number of manifestations of various kinds which were popularly regarded as miracles. Because of these marvellous results, members of Brihat's band were occasionally drawn away to follow the priests of this magic, much to their leader's sorrow, for he regarded all members of the band which he had led into India as though they were his children, so that this other temple was a considerable source of annoyance to him, and among his immediate followers there was a strong feeling against it. Alcyone, who had an inquiring turn of mind, was curious about anything in the way of phenomena, and once paid a visit to this temple, on the occasion of a certain festival on which there was to be a special display. His handsome appearance attracted the notice of one of the priests there, who made persistent effort to gain some control over him. He successfully resisted these with some assistance and advice from his father, but found them exceedingly trying. The voice which occasionally intervened in his affairs seems to have been that of a kindred spirit, for it on several occassions suggested lines of investigation, and put him upon the track of all sorts of curious and out-of-the-way things.     
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
On one occasion this voice gave him the startling information that there were people living in the interior of the earth, and when he developed a keen interest in this it offered to give him ocular demonstration of the fact by leading him to a certain cave by which he would gain admission into their dwelling-place or rather, as was represented, one of their dwelling-places. He eagerly accepted this offer, but it was unfortunately coupled with a condition that he should tell no one of the expedition, if he wished to undertake it. He doubted much as to the wisdom of this course, but eventually to make the journey and attempt to verify the statement, but stipulated that a certain bosom-friend, Demeter, should be allowed to accompany him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Demeter was another young priest, a son of one of the chief priests of the same temple; and the original reason of the bond between them was that Demeter also could see nature-spirits, and could sometimes hear the same inner voice.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This stipulation seemed for some time to be an insuperable difficulty, but eventually the mysterious inner voice yielded on that point only, however, on, condition that both the young men took a specially solemn vow that they would tell no one of their journey nor indicate to anyone else the way which was to be shown to them. In compliance with the terms of this agreement they had to pretend to set forth in 10,402 upon a pilgrimage to certain northern shrines; that is to say, the pilgrimage was genuine enough, for they really visited the shrines, but the true object of the expedition was known to none but those who undertook it. The journey which they had to take was a long one for those days, and occupied some months, but in due course and after many adventures they found themselves in the neighbourhood of the spot that had been indicated to them.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The inner voice would not permit to take with them say servant or attendant for the final effort, but directed them to provide themselves with food for many days, and also with a supply of torches to light them during their exploration. With considerable trouble they found the entrance to a cavern which was apparently quite unknown to the tribes living in the neighbourhood. They entered it with considerable misgivings, not caring, when it came to the point, to trust themselves in its intricacies, for indeed it seemed to be a perfect labyrinth. For a long time it led them merely into the heart of the mountain, without making any specially appreciable descent, but eventually the course of the naturally-arched passage which they had been directed to follow turned steeply downwards, and they  had to do an amount of downward climbing which was exceedingly awkward and perilous for them, hampered as they were with bundles of torches and packages of food.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
How far down they actually penetrated they had no means of knowing, nor could they estimate with any sort of accuracy the time which the descent occupied, but their underground journey must have been altogether a matter of many days. They suffered a good deal from the pressure of the atmosphere, which was great at that depth, and alarming to them, as of course they did not in the least understand it. The temperature also increased slightly, but not seriously enough to interfere in any way with their advance, though the conditions made the violent exertion of progress over so rough a road exceedingly trying. They had many narrow escapes, more than once only just avoiding serious accidents. Though they knew nothing of such matters it seems probable that they were travelling down a kind of fault or fissure, which may perhaps have been caused by an earthquake, or possibly by some volcanic outburst of long ago. Fortunately, plenty of water was usually available, although once or twice in that confined and heated atmosphere they suffered considerably from the want of it.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After a long time spent in this slow progress they became conscious of a faint and inexplicable luminosity in the heavy atmosphere which surrounded them, and presently they came out onto a cavity so vast that they were unable to see its limits. It seemed to be full of this curious pale radiance, by means of which, however, they were able to see distinctly enough to dispense altogether with the torches. Their eyes required great deal of adjustment to this extraordinary light, so that for some time they could not at all calculate the distance of objects, and met with some awkward falls in consequence. Everything felt abnormally heavy to them, and every motion seemed somehow a violent effort. They soon discovered that this enormous cavity was inhabited not only by animals but also by human beings, though these last were in various ways unlike any others that they had ever seen. The impression conveyed to them was that the inhabitants of this strange inner world had at some time or other in the far past belonged to the outer, though it would appear that the people themselves held rather the opposite idea, and thought of themselves as original, and of those who had escaped into the outer world as men upon whom some dismal fate had fallen.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The men whom they saw were wild-looking, and somehow indescribably strange and inhuman. They seemed to constitute a numerous community, and there were many things about them which were inexplicable to our explorers. They had no means of communicating with them, except by gestures, but it was evident that their arrival excited great wonder. If these primitive cave-men had ever had communication with any humanity on the surface of the earth it must have been long ago, for their characteristics at this day differed widely from those of any of the known races.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The utter strangeness of everything daunted the spirits of our explorers, and although their interest was naturally intense they often wished that they had never undertaken the adventure. The life in the midst of which they found themselves was in so many ways quite incomprehensible to them. The inner voice directed them only occasionally, and they had no means of obtaining the information on hundreds of points which they were naturally so eager to acquire. They were unable to form any opinion as to the nature of the diffused radiance which filled the vast cavern. The vegetables which grew in it, and the animals which moved among them, were alike strange to them. The people seemed to be in many ways what we should call savages, for they had no visible dwellings of any sort, nor was it clear that they engaged in any definite work, such for example as the cultivation of their soil. They appeared to live partly upon the flesh of certain semi-reptilian animals which they caught, and partly upon a huge fungoid growth which was exceedingly common, a sort of gigantic toadstool.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Our adventurers shrank with horror from the reptilian form of food, which the inhabitants devoured raw indeed there was nothing whatever to show that they knew of fire in any of its forms but since the stores which our friends had brought with them were running low, and they had no certainty of being able to replenish them, they did eat the fungus, and found it to be sustaining, though far from palatable. It seemed to have a curious exhilarating or almost intoxicating effects upon their unaccustomed organisms.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The people were evidently greatly astonished to see their visitors, and indeed at first fled from them in fear, but presently they ventured to approach and examine them more closely. Nothing in the nature of clothing was seen, and the colour of the people was an unpleasant and curious livid kind of lead-colour, probably produced by this strange diffused light. Women were seen among them and also, large numbers of children. They may have been a remnant of some early Lemurian race, for they had many of the characteristics of the blue egg-headed people, who at one time occupied a considerable portion of the Lemurian continent. Among other things, they were now somewhat below the ordinary height of men, though broad and squat in appearance, whereas the ancient Lemurian races from which they might have sprung were distinctly taller and looser in build than the men of later races. If, however, they did originally come from that stock, they must have been considerably modified by long ages of sojourn under these unearthly conditions. They may have belonged to a different evolution altogether, or perhaps to that of the Inner round, in which case they would afford an opportunity of human incarnation to those individualised animals for whom there is now no humanity sufficiently primitive on the surface of the earth.       
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
These people still exist at the present day. There are many of these cavities and some of them are peopled by tribes much more advanced than those encountered by our adventurers. The mental body of these people is not at all highly developed. Their speech is an unholy compound of clicks and grunts, helped out with a good deal of clumsy gesture. No ceremonies have so far been observed among them. Marriage is between one man and one woman in many cases, but in other cases not. There seems no sign of rank, nor any kind of government indeed, there is nothing to govern. Sometimes there are quarrels, but all on a small scale. As regards property they may be said to own some sort of weapons. The majority of them have no clothing. There is no day and night with them; they mostly throw themselves down to sleep after taking a meal. The children sometimes amuse themselves with dances. There are plenty of rivers, and the people swim in them in a curious dog-like fashion.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Our two friends abode among these extraordinary savages for a period which, measured by day and night, would have been perhaps a couple of weeks. Their difficulties were considerable, and a great portion of each day had to be devoted to sleep, as they never both slept at the same time, feeling it always necessary that one should be on the watch. The savages seemed to have no evil intentions towards them, and indeed to be on the whole rather afraid of them, though full of curiosity, but at the same time they could not trust them, and it is also certain that some of the reptiles were carnivorous, and probably poisonous. There was a good deal of vegetation, specially in the neighbourhood of water; nothing of any great size, except what might be called a sort of gigantic grass, a kind of bamboo which could not support itself, but crept along the ground. There were also spiky plants of the general appearance of aloes, and various kinds of cactus and rushes and sedges and that kind of thing, but all of a curious bleached unhealthy colour, many of them darkish, but none really green.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After they had become somewhat accustomed to this weird and uncomfortable condition of affairs, the voice directed Alcyone and his friend to proceed straight out into the cavity and to walk for many hours in a straight line, leaving the great wall. They soon lost sight of the wall in this curious diffused luminosity, and felt strangely lost in this nightmare of a world, with no certainty of getting out of it again. But they continued walking in spite of the difficulties of the atmosphere, and at last came upon a different type of people, who by comparison with the others might be said to be quite advanced, for they had places to live in, though they were only hollowed out of the ground chambers in the rock. But these people wove a sort of matting. They did not seem to know fire, but they may be said to have kept domestic animals. They had a kind of goat, of which they drank the milk. Their settlement was pitched round a number of boiling springs or geysers, and in these boiling springs they cooked the flesh of their goats, also that of some turtle like creatures. It may have been the same race, but it was certainly a stage further advanced. They could draw to a certain extent, and also they engraved or scratched signs upon the rocks according to some primitive scheme, consisting entirely of round impressions (cup-shaped marks) arranged in a form which signified something so many in a straight line meaning one thing, and so many arranged in an angle something else. These were not letters, but ideograms, or signs for certain things. The marks were produced by grinding a sharpened edge into the rock. They had thus a series of intelligible signs, but no idea beyond the making of these round depressions.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
They made also a kind of string or rope out of their reeds, and the women were beginning to wear coloured stones. Our friends came in one place upon a kind of pocket of precious stones, and carried them away with them fine specimens, splendid gems, which proved on their return to the upper world to be of great rarity. These people, who might be said to be a little more advanced, sometimes smeared themselves with colour, for there was coloured mud to be found in connection with the boiling springs. We noticed a sort of rose-colour, green, and yellow (which may have been sulphur); it was something like the  paint-pots  in the Yellowstone Park. To swoop out the mud these people used flat stones.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Eventually our friends found their way back, with great difficulty, to the hole by which they had entered the cavity. They had still some of their original food, though it was hard and dry, and they also took with some of the fungus. They made a fresh bundle of torches out of the bamboo, but they were not satisfactory, as they often went out. However, they were able to relight them, as they carried with them the primitive instrument for fire-making which they had brought with them a stick and string and a little cup. At last they struggled up to the surface again, but with great difficulty in climbing, and came out into the daylight dazzled and bewildered. Indeed, they had to remain in the cavern for more than a day, in order to get their eyes gradually used to the daylight. They had a curious feeling of sickness, arising apparently from the change in the density of the air; this sickness,  lasted for a good many hours, but they were thankful indeed to get back again.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The voice told Alcyone that this experience was necessary for him, that now he had a wider knowledge of the possibilities of life and evolution, so that he might understand and sympathise more fully, and that later on he would know more about all this. But now he was to go home again, to rejoin his family, and to prepare himself for another great trial which was to come. The two friends agreed to say nothing of their story anywhere in the places through which they passed, but to reserve all mention of it until they reached home. There they told the story to Alcyone's father and the family circle. The father said:  Yes, there is a tradition, not among us, but among the Atlanteans, of such underground races of men.  Something of the story was also told by Demeter to some other people outside; but they supposed it to be mere fabrication. The family of course knew it to be true, and fully realised what a wonderful experience it was.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone did well in the temple life, and held some offices important for one so young. As time went on he more and more helped his father in his work, and the father grew to rely more and more upon him, the affection between them becoming steadily stronger. He also, in addition, obtained some recognition and fame on his own account. In 10,387 the great sorrow of his life came to him. He undertook a journey to visit some distant shrines in the south, of the sites of those now called Rameshwaram and Srirangam. His sons, Helios and Achilles, now splendid young men of twenty, begged to accompany him, and he and Ajax agreed, thinking that the experience of the voyage would be of interest to them. He took ship in a trading vessel, a large one for those times, and thus he commenced a leisurely voyage down the coast, calling at various ports on the way.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The interest of the voyage was great, and father and sons enjoyed it; but after they had been some weeks on their way a fearful storm arose, and lasted for many days, sweeping them far out of their course into quite unknown seas, and reducing their ship to a helpless wreck, leaking in the most serious manner. They drifted for days in a desperate condition, keeping the vessel afloat only by constant work, so that all, sailors and passengers alike, were absolutely worn out. When they were at the last point of exhaustion they saw land ahead of them, which heartened them to make a final effort to keep afloat and to try somehow to reach it. the direction of their drift appeared to be carrying them some miles to the north of the land, which was only an island of no great size. They debated the advisability of casting themselves into the sea, but they were too weak to swim, and a number of sharks were already following the drifting vessel. They thought of breaking up some part of the ship and making a kind of rough raft, but while they were feebly trying this they saw a fleet of canoes put off from the shore. Soon they were surrounded by a horde of shrieking savages, who greeted them with a shower of arrows, and then sprang on board and massacred the exhausted Indians with clubs.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone's sons were murdered before his eyes, and he himself was also struck down, though only stunned. When he came to himself the savages were looting the ship; as soon as he was seen to be alive a savage rushed at him to kill him, but another , who seemed to be in authority, interfered, and he was bound with a piece of rope, and thrown into one of the canoes. He thought at first that he was the only survivor, and when he remembered the death of his sons, he wished that he died with them; but presently another living man was discovered, a member of the crew, and he also was bound and thrown into the canoe beside Alcyone. Alcyone had always spoken kindly to the sailors, and was known by them as a holy person, so this man was deeply sorry to see him in such a pass. He had small comfort to give, for he said that, though he did not know exactly where they were, he had but little doubt, from the general direction of the storm, that they had fallen among a set of the most bloodthirsty and ferocious cannibals known.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The savages presently decided to tow the vessel to their island a proceeding which they accomplished only very slowly, and with a prodigious amount of noise. They succeeded in getting it just within the entrance of a small cove before it actually sank, so that it remained resting on the sand, with its decks just awash. The savages, being expert divers, were able by degrees to break it up, and to take from it all that they considered of value. As soon as they had recovered from the labour of the towing, preparations were made for a great feast. The glad news of the capture of this great store of food was somehow communicated to other parts of the island, apparently by means of columns of smoke, so that large bodies of savages gathered. The bodies of the Indians who had been killed on board the ship were almost all recovered, and the savages proceeded to build an enormous fire and to cook them. The amount that these cannibals were able to eat was most surprising, and by the end of the second day of the feast they were all in a comatose condition.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
They had however, taken the precaution to secure Alcyone and his sailor companion before they went to sleep. They were kept strongly under guard, but were not otherwise ill-treated, and they were plentifully supplied with food in the shape of a coarse kind of yam. It was painfully evident to the captives that they were being reserved for another day's feasting, and they felt that their only hope of preserving their lives was to escape as soon as possible, and they agreed that they would never be likely to find a better opportunity than this time when all the savages were overcome with heavy sleep. An armed man was guarding the hut into which they had been thrown, but he also had eaten enormously, and they had good reason to hope that presently he might slumber like the rest. Unfortunately they were securely bound, as indeed they had been ever since their capture, their bonds being partially relaxed for a few moments only when food was brought to them. Also they were naked, and entirely without weapons of any kind, everything having been torn away from them. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone cared little for his life now that his sons were dead, and had he been alone he would probably have made no effort to escape the impending fate; but when he said something of that sort to the sailor, the latter though speaking very hesitatingly and respectfully tried to cheer him up, and asked whether there were not other dear ones at home in India for whom it might be worth while to live. This reminded him of his father and mother, his wife and Mizar, and he thought how sad they would be if death overtook him, so for their sake he roused himself to listen to the plans which the sailor suggested. The first necessity was to get free somehow from their bonds, which were very painful, and it had to be done silently, as the guard was only a few feet from them. The sailor had various schemes, but they all involved springing upon the guard (unless he accommodatingly fell asleep), overpowering or even killing him, and then making a rush for the shore, and seizing the first boat that came in their way; for they agreed that escape inland was an impossibility, as they could never maintain themselves, nor hide themselves from the savages.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Before attempting a hazardous voyage in an open boat a store of provisions was absolutely necessary, and also plenty of water, but they had no idea where to find either of these things, and they were unlikely to have time to search for them. Anyhow the first point was to free themselves from the ropes. As the guard looked in upon them at frequent intervals, this was an undertaking of no slight difficulty. But presently these intervals became longer, and at last he was absent so long that the sailor set to work to gnaw at the rope that bound him to the wall of the hut. After incredible labour he succeeded in severing it; Alcyone tried to do the same, but could make little progress. The sailor then rolled over to him, and began to gnaw the cord which tied his hands. After a long time and much anxiety this effort was at last successful, though at the cost of great suffering to the sailor; then Alcyone set to work to untie the sailor's bonds, and as soon as that was achieved they were both quickly free, though their limbs were swollen and painful, and they could not use them easily.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After rubbing and chafing other a little they peeped cautiously out and saw the sentinel crouched in a heap just before the door of the hut, evidently fast asleep. No one else seemed to be moving, so with infinite caution, inch by inch, they glided past him, Alcyone picking up the spear which had fallen from his hand and lay beside him. The savages lay about round the ashes of their fires like the dead upon a battle-field and, so far as our adventurers could see, no watch was being kept. They could see nothing eatable anywhere, so they were compelled to enter a hut in search of provisions, and unfortunately in doing this they somehow awoke a woman, who at once raised a warning cry. Two men started up at the door of the hut, and barred their way, but they were still dazed with sleep, and before they could do anything effective Alcyone drove his spear into one of them, while the sailor sprang unarmed upon the other, bore him to the ground, and then stunned him with a blow from his own club. The woman's shouts, however, were awakening more savages, so our heroes started at full speed for the sea. Only one of the cannibals was in time to interpose himself between them and the object of their desires, and the sailors disposed of him with the club, which he still retained. They reached the shore, pushed off hurriedly the smallest of the canoes which they found drawn up on the beach, threw themselves into her, and commenced to paddle with feverish haste. A boat was put off after them, but they had a good start and both of them were expert rowers, so they were able to keep their distance until they got well out to sea. The pursuing boat persevered for some time; but presently, seeing that they did not gain upon the fugitives, the savages gave up the chase with a yell of disgust and hatred, and sent after them a final flight of arrows, one of which wounded the sailor in the leg.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The escape was thus an accomplished fact, but they were entirely without food and water, afloat on a great ocean in a small canoe, with no idea where or which way to steer. they knew only that India lay to the west of them, but they knew, also that it must be many hundreds of miles away, and that both wind and waves were carrying them decidedly eastward. they agreed that their only hope was speedily to reach some uninhabited island, for in this part of the world inhabitants meant cannibals. But meantime no island was in sight but that which they had left, to which they dared not return, and they were beginning already to suffer terribly from thirst. Seeing that fish seemed numerous the sailor lay in wait in the bows of the boat, and after several attempts succeeded in spearing one with the weapon which Alcyone had taken from the sentinel. He offered his prize respectfully to Alcyone, who however refused to touch it, as he had never in his life eaten any living creature. When convinced that he would on no account partake of it, the sailor himself devoured it raw.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Shortly afterwards he began to complain of acute shooting pains in his limbs, and of strange lassitude, and presently he laid down his paddle, and collapsed in the bottom of the boat. Alcyone was much concerned, but there was nothing that he could do, and in an hour or so the sailor was dead. Evidently the arrow which had wounded him was poisoned. Alcyone sorrowed greatly for the loss of one who, though so different in rank, had become really a friend in these few days of crowded adventure and excitement. The swollen and puffy body soon showed unmistakable signs that the soul had finally left it, so Alcyone had to throw it overboard, and it drifted in sight of him until it was torn to pieces by sharks.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Night fell, and the wind freshened, and he had great trouble in preventing the swamping of his canoe as the sea rose. Dawn came at last, and he was still afloat, and the sea had gone down somewhat, but his sufferings from thirst were horrible. The day wore slowly on, the wind remaining steady. The heat of the sun was intense, and though he relieved himself a little by constantly throwing water over his head and body he had a day of great misery. Night came again, and there was at last a coolness, and as the sea was quiet he had occasional snatches of sleep; but he was nevertheless weak and faint when the second morning dawned. When the sun rose he saw a faint blur of land, ahead of him but to the south, and the sight revived him enough to induce him to make an effort to paddle in that direction. Again he suffered much from the fierce heat of the sun, and the violent exertion of incessant paddling under such conditions; but he did manage to draw steadily nearer to the goal, and at last, about three o'clock in the afternoon, with a final struggle, he ran his canoe on the beach of a tiny island, and threw himself down on the sand.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After a short rest the remorseless glare of the sun forced him, exhausted as he was, to struggle to his feet again, and wander inland in search of water. This he did not at first find, but he saw a grove of coconut trees, and contrived to break open of the fallen fruit, and drank the contents. This refreshed him, and he made further investigations, first securing the boat by drawing it high on the shore, out of reach of the waves. He found a small spring and some fruit-trees a kind of wild banana and some wood-apples; and he threw himself down in the shade by the spring, and slept the sleep of utter weariness. When he awoke the night had passed, and it was dawn once more. He felt much better, and started to make an exploration of his island. It was small, but thickly covered with trees, and it was dawn once more. He felt much better, and started to make an exploration of his island. It was small but thickly covered with trees, and there was a little spring of good water, so he thought himself fortunate, especially as it seemed to be entirely uninhabited. He soon saw, however, that there was only enough fruit to support him for a few days, and he debated within himself what he should do. His nautical knowledge told him that India lay to the west, and that it was impossible to reach it, not only because of the great distance, but also because at this season of the year the prevailing wind and current were unfavourable. He could go only eastward, and he remembered vaguely that he had heard from sailor friends about these cannibal islands, and that they were much nearer to the east side of the bay than to the Indian coast. He did not in the least know how long it would take him to reach the mainland of the continent, so he felt that he must start as soon as he could, so that his provisions might, if possible, last through the voyage.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He determined to gather all the fruit, store it in his boat, and try to get off the following morning, thus making sure of one more good night's rest. He had the good fortune to find some yams, which added largely to his scanty store, so he finally decided to stay one more day in order to make a rough sail for his canoe by plaiting some palm-leaves. Being entirely naked he had of course no knife with him, but with great trouble he contrived to drag off a stick which would make an apology for a mast, and to tie it in its place in the canoe by knotted coconut fibres. His primitive sail had to be attached to the stick in the same manner, and the whole arrangement was absolutely insecure and unsatisfactory. But still he discovered by experiments that it would pull his canoe along as fast as he could paddle it, and that therefore as long as the wind remained light, it would at least save his arms, or slightly increase this speed. His most serious difficulty was that he had no vessel to carry water. The best that he could do seemed to be to take with him as large a number of cocoanuts as possible, but that number after all was only small, as the canoe was not built to carry much in the way of freight. He took with him then all the fruits and yams that he could find in his tiny territory, and added to this as large a heap of cocoanuts as he thought safe, weighing down his boat merely to the water's edge.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He started at daybreak the following morning and found that his sail acted on the whole better than he expected, but he was acutely conscious that at the first real puff of wind the whole thing would infallibly go over. He rowed for an hour or so at intervals, being exceedingly anxious to hasten the voyage as much as possible, and at the same time to economise his strength, because he knew neither how long it would last nor what kind of reception he would be likely to meet with at its end. During the day he made what he felt under the circumstances to be satisfactory progress, and the wind was so gentle and so steady that he was able to doze a good deal during the night. The next morning found him out of sight of his friendly little islet, and entirely alone in the centre of a vast horizon. All day long he moved on, with little of incident to break the monotony, though his store of food and cocoanuts was diminishing with alarming rapidity. Three more days and nights passed without any change worth chronicling, and by this time he had little food or water left, but yet there was no sign of any sort that he was approaching the mainland.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
During the next night he was dozing as usual when he was suddenly rudely awakened by the rough movement of the boat, and in a moment found his sail torn away from its mast and carried off into space. It was a squall which lasted only a few minutes, and was accompanied by a heavy shower of rain, but nevertheless it had robbed him at one stroke of his principal means of progression. He still rowed at intervals whenever he felt equal to it, but did not press himself greatly, as he had after all no certain knowledge of the directions in which he had to progress. The next day he suffered greatly from the sun's heat, from which on the previous day the sail had to a certain extent protected him, and as the days passed on, and food and drink entirely failed him, he sank into a sort of stupor of weakness. He was almost too apathetic to be despairing, but  he had little hope to be of good cheer, since all his suffering was karmic, and he would certainly be saved in the end. This encouraged him greatly and gave him strength to bear up for two days more, and at the end of the end of that time he entirely lost consciousness.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When he recovered it to be found himself on board a small trading vessel in a sadly weak and emaciated condition, but still alive and able with great difficulty to move and to speak a little. None of the people of the ship spoke any language which she could understand, and he wondered much how he came to be there, as he found himself unable to recall anything of his past, nor did he even know for the time his own name. The sailors of the little vessel were kind to him in their rough way, and shared with him such coarse food as they had, so that he became slowly somewhat more like himself again, but still he could not recover his memory. The phenomenon was a curious one, for it seemed as though his astral and etheric bodies had been somehow dragged awry by the long-continued suffering, and all his earnest efforts to remember were for the present unsuccessful. He could understand nothing that was said to him, and had to try to communicate with the kindly sailor by means of signs.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After some days they  reached a port a city of some importance, but the place was utterly strange to him, and everyone there spoke this language which he could not understand. The people were not Indians, but were apparently of some Mongoloid race, with a sprinkling of darker men who had probably some relics of Lemurian blood in their reins. He was distinctly therefore a stranger in a strange land, and though his good-natured sailor companions took him before some person who was evidently in authority, and seemed to be explaining his case, he was left quite in ignorance as to what they intended to do with him. It was evident that many questions were put to him, but he could only shake his head, and indeed he felt that even if the language had been intelligible to him he could have told practically nothing about himself.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He did not of course understand what was passing, but it afterwards transpired that he had been assigned practically as a kind of slave to a certain man who employed him to do light work in his fields. He did willingly enough such work as was assigned to him, feeling grateful for the food and lodging accorded to him, and realising that, unless he himself could remember something more clearly, he must just take anything which came in his way. To speak of his recovering his memory is perhaps too definite an expression, for he did not actually realise that he must have had a past, just as other people had, but it simply seemed to be missing.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then it came to him suddenly in the middle of the night, as he was sleeping with other labourers in a kind of large hut or shed. He seemed to wake from sleep and see his father, and with that came a rush of recollection of his home and of all his previous life. He father spoke to him, adjuring him to return to his sorrowing family, telling him that he himself was growing old and surely needed his help. Alcyone sprang to his feet and rushed to embrace his father, but of course found nothing in the spot where he had stood. He was intensely excited by this sudden recovery of memory, and was most anxious to start at once for his home, but did not in the least know how to set about this. His exceedingly imperfect acquaintance with the language of the people among whom he found himself made it practically impossible to explain to them so complicated  and unusual a case. He could only assert clumsily and brokenly that he had seen his father, and must go.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It does not seem that any objection was offered to his departure either by his companions or employer, but he was confronted with serious difficulties in that he could not make himself understood, nor did he know to whom to apply for any sort of assistance. His knowledge of the geography of the country was limited. He realised that there was some kind of land connection somewhere to the north, and that it  might be possible to return to India by that route but he knew nothing whatever as to the distance except that it must be great, nor had he any idea of the kind of country to be traversed, or by whom it was inhabited. He made his way from the inhabited. He made his way from the island farm at which he had been working back to the port once more, and there for some little time he made a precarious living by doing odd jobs in various ways connected with shipping. His idea was that, as he knew something of a sailor's work, he might possibly find a ship sailing to some Indian port, and might work his way at last to some place near home. He visited many ships, but found none that were going across the bay.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He encountered, however, one friendly captain who could speak a few words of his language, and consequently took a great interest in him, and tried to help him. To this man he told the outline of his story, and the captain assured him that he might have to wait for the years before he met with a vessel going to his own part of the world, which indeed was only vaguely known to the captain, by reputation. This new friend strongly advised him to take any vessel which he could find gong up the coast northward, to go with it as far as it went, and then to leave it and try for another one which would take him further along. In that way he said that by two or three stages he would certainly be able to get back to some port on the Indian peninsula, and might even meet eventually with a vessel which would touch at his own port.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He saw the wisdom of this advice, and when the captain further offered to come with him to act as interpreter for him and try to find him a berth on some ship that was northward bound, he fell in thankfully with the proposed arrangement. The captain was as good as his word, and he found him a berth upon a small trading vessel which, though in a slow and leisurely manner, carried him some hundreds of miles northwards. He left this craft at the northern extremity of her voyage, and contrived to ship himself upon another somewhat similar vessel bound still further north, and so in the course of a year he eventually got back to the mouths of the Ganges. When once more among people who spoke a variant of his language he felt himself not far from home, and with but little difficulty contrived to put himself on board a vessel which called at the port from which he had sailed on that disastrous voyage, now three years ago.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
His wife and family greeted the long-lost wanderer with the wildest demonstrations of joy; they had given him up for lost, but his father, Brihat, had always maintained that he was alive and well, and would return to them in due course, for he declared that on two occasions he had clearly seen him once in a small open boat, apparently far out at sea, and on another occasion dressed as a labourer, and amidst a great number of other similar people lying sleeping in a kind of shed. After three years of such an entirely different existence it took him some time to accustom himself to the routine of the priestly work, but he was indeed glad to take it up again and to find himself once more among those who had so long mourned him as dead. The story of his adventures was soon noised abroad, and he had to tell his tale over many times to large numbers of enquires. No one knew what to make of the loss of memory, although there were some few who had vaguely heard of similar cases.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
His extraordinary adventures made him a person of mark, and his great-grandchildren were never tired of making him repeat the story to them, the report of these adventures reached the ears of Orpheus, the ruler of that part of the country, and he sent for Alcyone in order to hear his account at first-hand. It impressed him greatly, and he decreed a pension to Alcyone as some sort of compensation for his sufferings
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The rest of his life seems to call for no special comment. His father Brihat died in 10,378, and he was appointed as his successor. This naturally brought him into a continuous round of all the old temple ceremonies, and under these influences on several occasions the voice which had so often  directed him during the earlier years was heard by him again, though it had apparently altogether abandoned him during the period of his adventures and for some years subsequently. It manifested in these later years only rarely, but among other things it foretold to him the exact day of his death, which took place in 10,356.
</view>
</text>
</body>