<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 21</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 21-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The next appearance of our band of Servers is in South India, and on this occasion Orion , who has been wandering in outer deserts for some thousands of years, finds his way back into the group-but in a very peculiar way. He was born in 21540 as a girl in one of the hill tribes of the Nilgiris, a clever, good looking and unscrupulous young person. She had no intention of living the life of the hill tribes, so she engaged herself to serve a noble Tamil lady, and was appointed to attend upon her daughter Iota, to whom she speedily made herself indispensable. In this Tamil family was an heirloom an enormous emerald credited with magical powers. It had been magnetised in Atlantis by one of the Lords of the Dark Face, and it was supposed to earn for its possessor whatever he most desired, but it always brought misfortune in the end, and those who used it became tools of the original magnetiser. Iota persuaded her father to give her this wonderful stone, and by its means to arrange for her a marriage with a neighbouring King. By the power of the stone this plan was carried through, and the King sent an escort to bring his bride to him. Iota took with her three attendants, Orion being one of them, and on the journey Orion contrived to murder her young mistress and then personated her. Her plot succeeded and she was duly married to King Theodoros, to whom she made a good and clever wife. It is to the credit of Orion that in her new surroundings she did not forget her brother Egeria, whom she had dearly loved, but sent secretly for him, had him educated as befitted her new station and eventually married him to one of the ladies of the court, though never openly acknowledging him as her brother.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Ten years later, for reasons of state, the King took a second wife Nu, a princess of a neighbouring house. After all these years the murder of Iota atlast came to light, and Orion's true status was discovered. Her husband was indignant at the outrage on his pride, and promptly condemned her to death. When thrown into prison she invoked the Lord of the Emerald, and he appeared to her and ordered her to throw the emerald out of the window to Sigma, one of the little children of the second wife Nu, who was playing outside. As soon as this was done he ordered Orion to take poison, and as she left her body the little girl Sigma fell down dead in the courtyard, and Orion was pushed into her body. When they went to lead out the queen to execution she was of course found dead in her cell.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In Sigma's body she was contracted in marriage to Leo, the prince of a neighbouring kingdom, in what is now the Telugu country, and after they were married she induced her young husband to bring about his father's abdication, so that she herself might be queen of the country. Alcyone was born in the year 21,467 as their eldest son, and there were four other children. When Alcyone was eleven years old his mother Orion fell ill of some internal disease which was found to be incurable. As soon as she knew that death was drawing near, she told again approached to the Lord of the Emerald, who told her that he would help her once more to take another body, but that it must be that of her daughter Theseus, whom she loved dearly. For some time she refused this. But at last increasing suffering drove her to accept it. So she drowned Theseus, hung the emerald round the child's neck and then threw herself into the water and sank. When she recovered consciousness she was in the body of Theseus, and so, instead of being Alcyone's mother, she was now, as far as outward appearance went, his sister.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The politics of the time were complicated and troublous, and Alcyone, though anxious to do his duty, was more interested in his studies than in affairs of state. He learned whatever was customary for boys of his class and time, and was proficient in riding, shooting, swimming, and the various sports of the race. When he came of age he married  Herakles, who was the daughter of a neighbouring Raja, and they were happy together in their religious studies. The Priest Mercury was a neighbour and close friend.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In order to save the King Leo from certain defeat at the hands of a coalition of neighbouring States, Alcyone's mother Orion had induced Leo to place it under the suzerainty of the Atlantean Emperor, Jupiter, and there was much discontent among the people about this. A few years after , when Orion had had to change bodies, and could therefore no longer direct Leo's policy, the discontent broke out into open rebellion, and Leo was defeated and killed. Sirius (the son of Gimel, an Atlantean Noble) was sent sent over from Atlantis by Jupiter to be governor of the Kingdom which was thus made a province of the vast Atlantean Empire. Sirius made friends with Alcyone and Orion, at first perhaps from motives of policy, but the friendship quietly ripened into real affection. He fell in love with Orion and demanded her hand from her brother Alcyone, who gladly gave it, and a close tie united the two families and also that of the priest Mercury. This made the government  of the province an easy matter, as the official heads of both the parties in it were now so thoroughly united. In fact the three families were almost like one, and made a kind of little society of their own, in which all sorts of interesting problems were discussed.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
We find that the language commonly used then in India was not Sanskrit, and ceremonies usually began with the word  Tau , not with  Aum . The doctrines of reincarnation and karma were commonly known to the people. The Teacher (Mercury) knew of the Great ones behind who sometimes helped. Some of the expressions which are familiar to us now were in use then also, as for example:  I am That . Mercury told the people that of all the qualities that they  could develop, all the qualifications they could possess, the most important was the power to recognise that all was That.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 you cut down a tree,  He said  that is the life of the tree; dig up a stone, That is what holds the particles of stone together; That is the life of the sun, That is in the clouds, in the roaring of the sea, in the rainbow, in the glory of the mountain  and so on. These words are taken from a discourse of Mercury on death. In a book from which he read to the people there were well known phrases, such as:  One thing is the right ,while the sweet is another; these two tie a man to objects apart. Of the twain it is well for who taketh the right one, who chooseth the sweet, goeth wide of the aim. The right and the sweet come to a mortal; the wise sifts the two and sets them apart. For ,right unto sweet the wise man prefereth; the fool taketh sweet to hold and retain .(Kath Upanishad; words in Meads translation.) The wording in Mercury's book was not actually identical, but it was clearly the same set of verses.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
There was another saying  if one is killed, and I am the slain, yet I  am I also the sword of the slayer, and none slays or is slain because all are one. There is no first nor last, no life nor death, because all are one in him. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The books which Mercury used did not come from the Aryans; this book from which he read (evidently the original of the Katha Upnishad) was written in the city of the Golden Gate by one who was a member of the brotherhood. It belonged to a great collection, and had been handed down through many centuries. The Nachiketas story had not yet been connected with it.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In one temple there were no images at all. The religion was not sun-worship at least not exclusively; rather a worship of the power of nature. Outside the temple was a large bull in stone, facing the temple and looking in. inside there was a curious arrangement a depression, instead of a raised alter. Two or three steps led upto a great low square platform, paved with beautiful tiles, and then there was depression in the centre with a railing round it. People threw flowers in the depression, in the middle of which was a slab which was specially holy; it had some markings on it, but we could make nothing of them.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In another temple there were many images which were set in niches in its back wall. The people wore a different dress from those in the former temple, and there were men who were distinctly priests, which was not the case in the other. The images sat cross-legged, and had not more than the natural number of arms. This was the old form of Jainism, presumably, and the images of Tirthankar. Some images were naked; others, which had a lose garment over them, were probably regarded as dressed, or perhaps a conventional symbol was intended.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In another temple a long way to the north, there was already a lingam. Up there the trimurthy was fully recognised, though the names were not those used now. In one cave-temple there was a gigantic face carved out of the rock which was three faces in one though it was so arranged that only one face could be clearly seen at a time. There was a great temple in South India which also contained a Trimurti. We tried to discover the meaning of the name attached to it, to see what idea was connected with it in the mind of its priest, and we found that one priest thought of it as:  He whose life flows through all.  While another had the idea that the three persons were:  He who opens the gates, He who guides the stream, and He who closed the gates.  We saw no specimens here of the many-armed images which are so plentiful at the present time.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 The priest had strong ideas about a  Lake of Light,  which was also Death and Life and Love; all streams led into the Lake of Light, whence so ever they seem to begin. There were traces also of the theory that all we see is illusion but the only Reality is the Lake of Light.  We live in the Lake of Light and donot know it. We think of ourselves separated, but we are each a drop in the lake.  The priest seemed to be perpetually urging the people to get behind the illusion of, the senses, and to realise that That was the real Presence behind all and the separated forms were the separated drops:  When they fall in again they are all one,  they said,  and it is we ourselves who make all the sorrow and trouble. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
They had a prayer to the   Lords who Are the Lights , who consist of the Light .
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
What is written above represents something of what was taught to the people, but in this small and strictly private family circle , mercury was willing to go, a little further, and expound the true meaning of the symbol , and give far more information about the lake of life and the Lords who are the light. He told them of a great teacher, who might be invoked by certain prayers and ceremonies, whose blessing might be called down upon them if they asked for it earnestly and with pure heart. They invoked him at their meetings, and a response always came, and on two special occasions He even showed Himself. This Great One was He whom we know as the Mahaguru, and His special connection with this group was that He had, in a previous birth, founded their religion and arranged that He would, as the founder, respond to certain invocations made under proper conditions by it's true adherents. He threw into the mind of mercury the solution of his problems and the answers to their questions on religious matters, and once or twice certain personal directions were given to them, though this was a rare occurrence.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The priest Mercury had married Ulysses. The pleasant intercourse between the families and their study of the questions which  so deeply interested them went on harmoniously for years, and the first break in the party occurred in the year 21423 BC, when Orion confessed her black magic to Mercury and Sirius, threw the magic emerald into the sea, and retired to an ascetic life, with a view of atoning for her deeds. She handed over her children to the care of a friend Helios, and four years later the latter married Albireo, a young brother of Alcyone.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The children of these families all grew up together, and naturally fell in love with one another, so that when they became men and women there was a good deal of intermarriage between them. Achilles took to wife Mizar, while Uranus married Vega, and Hector Selene. Aldebran however, caused much trouble to the family through becoming involved with and marrying a woman of bad character (Gamma), who ruined his life, and left him a miserable wreck when she finally abandoned him, and ran away with Pollux, who was a rich but dissolute merchant.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Vajra was also a source of anxiety to his mother Herakles, because he developed a wandering disposition,, and became a great traveller in search of knowledge and experience. He, however, wrote a brilliant account of his travels, which was read over and over again by the family group, and practically learnt by heart by the younger members. Alcyone was so interested in some of its glowing descriptions that he actually undertook no less than three difficult and dangerous journeys in order to see the places of which his son had given so attractive an account. In the course of these he met with various adventures, the most serious being that he was once captured by robbers and held for ransom, though he contrived to escape by disguising himself as a woman. In another case he was carried off his feet while trying to wade across a swollen river, and was swept down more than a mile, and nearly drowned. He also accompanied Sirius on several of the latter's official tours through the province; indeed, Sirius delegated many of his powers to him, being anxious to show the people what thorough accord existed between the Atlantean power and their old royal family. The tie between these two men was singularly close, and, though of different races, they seemed always to understand each other perfectly. Sirius, who was patriotic, told Alcyone much of the glories of Poseidonis and the City of Golden Gate, and fired him with great enthusiasm about it and an intense desire to see it, which bore fruit much later in life.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Herakles died in 21396 B.C. at the age of seventy, and Sirius, to whom she had been a particularly close friend, mourned her loss quite as much as Alcyone, and accorded her the most gorgeous obsequies. This left Alcyone much alone, and he clung more than ever to his friend Sirius, who fully returned his affection, so that the two old men were like brothers. For thirty years Sirius had been visiting regularly every month his wife Orion, who was living as an ascetic; and when she died in 21392 B.C., he felt himself unable to stay any longer in India, and applied for leave to resign his Governorship and return to Poseidonis. Alcyone, though seventy-five years of age, immediately announced his intention to accompany him, and actually did so.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The two septuagenarians had a prosperous voyage, and Alcyone found the splendors of the capital even greater than he had expected. Few of those whom Sirius had known forty-four years ago were still living to greet him. The Emperor Jupiter was long ago dead, and his son Mars reigned in his stead; he received the two old men with great honour, and gave them honorary posts at his court, distinguishing them with many marks of favour. He must have felt drawn to them, for he set his court astrologers to calculate the particulars of their connection with him, and was informed that both had worked with him more than once in the past, and that both were destined to serve him in some mighty work far in the future, when nearly a quarter of a lakh of years had been added to the roll of time. None of them then understood this prophecy, but it is evident that it will be fulfilled in the Californian community about 2750 A.D.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Vajra who had accompanied his father, soon took a prominent position under the Emperor and enjoyed his fullest confidence. Sirius and Alcyone lived together in the same house as brothers for ten years, and both died in 21382, hale and hearty to the last. During these ten years they jointly prepared a book upon Southern India, which was highly esteemed, and was regarded for centuries in Poseidonis as the classical work on its subject. It was in two volumes, one treating of the different races and their customs, and the other of the various religions the latter embodying much of the teaching given to them long before by the priest Mercury.
</view>
</text>
</body>