<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 34</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 34-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The next life takes us back again to India, and gives in many ways a great contrast to the last one. Our hero was born in the year 11,182 at a place called Ranthambhor in Rajputana. He was the son of an Aryan chief owning a good deal of land and much respected, a man of strong character, but somewhat harsh. Caste, as such, had not yet distinctly appeared, but the family to which Alcyone belonged was one of the most highly regarded, and several members of it had become priests in various temples, so that we may regard it as distinctly Brahman. His mother was a good housewife and a capable woman, but always immersed in small matters, and with comparatively little of spirituality about her nature. His mother was a good housewife and a capable woman, but always immersed in small matters, and with comparatively little of spirituality about her nature.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone as a child was keen and active, but reserved in nature. He was more affectionate with his uncle. Percy than with either his father or his mother naturally enough, for Percy had been his eldest son in Peru, while they had not then been related to him. This uncle lived in the same house, and his influence had much to do with forming the child's mind. Percy was of a speculative and inquiring turn of mind, and was much interested in all kinds of occult influences and in researches connected with them. Though he did not remember their Peruvian relationship, he was strongly attracted towards Alcyone from the first, and the tie between them was greatly strengthened when he discovered that the boy was exceedingly sensitive, and responded much more readily than he himself did to some of the occult influences which he had learnt how to evoke.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He tried a number of mesmeric experiments with Alcyone, and attained unexpected success, finding that when he had thrown him into a trance various entities could speak through him, and he could also be used as an instrument for clairvoyant investigation. Although he himself constantly mesmerised Alcyone he never permitted anyone else to do so, and he also taught Alcyone how to mesmerise others, and how to invoke nature-spirits. He set him to practice crystal-gazing, and automatic writing with a stylus. In this way, he constantly received communications from various dead people and also from living entities, and after a time these not only wrote through him, but even began to use him as a medium and to speak though him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
These two people, then, the uncle and the nephew, lived a kind of inner life of their own, for Alcyone's parents, though they knew all about what was taking place, were but little interested in it, and inclined to regard it as somewhat useless and nonsensical, though quite glad to share in the credit when Alcyone's clairvoyance happened to discover something useful, as once or twice happened. Various other phenomena took place, many of them by no means unlike those with which we meet in modern Spiritualism, but these were regarded by those who knew of them with a good deal of hesitation and suspicion, some holding them with a certain respect, as a kind of inspiration. The young Alcyone occasionally passed into a trance during which materialisation occurred.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
All this was under the control of a kind of spirit-guide who called himself Narayan to whom they paid great respect, regarding him as a divine manifestation. This entity promised to take care of the medium under all conditions, to protect and develop him, and he held out hopes of great occurences later when the boy should be grown up. Among other things he advised the practice of psychometry, and accordingly they took a great deal of trouble to procure suitable specimens, such as fragments of stone, small articles of various kinds from different countries, and anything that might be supposed to have been connected with any ancient civilisation. Alcyone soon proved apt at this work. They held many sittings, and acquired by degrees a vast amount of information about the earlier stages of the world's history, about hill-tribes and primitive men and prehistoric animals. By means of some articles which had been brought from Central Asia they got on the track of that early fifth Root-Race civilisation; by means of other objects which had been brought from Atlantis, Alcyone had visions of the great City of the Golden Gate, and also a series of pictures from Atlantean history. Indeed they compiled by degrees books of history of all the three places early India, Central Asia, and Atlantis itself. The entity calling himself Narayan commented on what they saw, and sometimes gave explanations. In this way they produced by degrees quite a mass of literature, and it said that Percy had no other object in life than the prosecution of these studies.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
  Many of those who came to ask for help or advice were suffering from various diseases, and Narayan met with considerable success in prescribing for these, having chiefly a small set of herbal remedies, which on the whole worked well. His prescriptions had quite a modern air about them, for he always insisted vehemently  upon fresh air and cleanliness, and the observation of hygienic rules. His anatomical and surgical knowledge was limited, but still he could evidently see what he was doing, and was able to diagnose the condition of the internal organs, and therefore either to deal with them successfully or to say that they could not be dealt with. There was considerable uncertainty, however, about the whole thing, as in some cases the entity calling himself Narayan did not appear when required, and in other cases he apparently refused to prescribe, or at least did not manifest or take any notice.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
As Alcyone grew older he was definitely attached to the temple at which they worshipped, for the performance of ceremonies. On one occasion when a number of pilgrims were present, Narayan impressed him to address the crowd, so that we have here the phenomenon of a kind of trance-speaking. Narayan did not completely obsess Alcyone, as the latter still retained a certain consciousness of what was going on, and was able to sit or stand without falling; but at the same time he did not usually know what was coming, so that the speech was given through him as an instrument rather than by him. The address which he gave to the piligrim on the first occasion greatly pleased and impressed Adrona, the head priest in charge of the temple, who happened to hear it, and he at once saw that Alcyone possessed in this a talent of an unusual order, which might be of the greatest value in enhancing the reputation of the temple. He therefore encouraged Alcyone to yield himself to this influence of Narayan, though it is doubtful whether he really believed the high claims made by the spirit-guide.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
From this time forth the young Alcyone took a position of considerable importance in the temple, and addresses and sermons were not infrequently given through him, tough they were never able to calculate with certainty whether the communicating entity would or would not manifest himself on any given occasion. Besides what may be called public sermons, a great many private messages were given to persons who came from all parts of the country, to ask various questions or to beg for boons of different kinds. Some of these answers were in the usual cryptic style peculiar to oracles, but on the other hand some were quite definite, and conveyed real information, which was at times distinctly valuable as enabling people to recover lost articles, to gain information with regard to missing relations, and so on.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Although a great deal of public and semi-public work was done in this way in connection with the temple, Percy and Alcyone continued, as opportunity offered, what may be called their private seances, and at these a number of remarkable phenomenon manifested themselves. On several occasions small objects were brought to them, which were alleged to have come from great distances. They had also now and then manifestations of spirit-lights, and the carrying about of objects. Materialisations were not common, but still they did occasionally take place, and in this way they began to know the appearance of several of these spirit-people. Undesirable as mediumship undoubtedly is, it did not in any way injure Alcyone's health. Their seances and sermons and psychometrisations continued with varied success for quite a number of years, and all this time Alcyone was making his position more secure in the temple.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The fame of Alcyone's achievements along these various lines was noised abroad, and people came from all parts of the country to this temple, thereby adding greatly to its revenues. The King of the country on one occasion sent for Alcyone, to see whether any advice would be given through him towards the curing of a painful disease consequent upon an accident while hunting. Fortunately on this occasion Narayan was available, and though the instructions which he gave were not palatable to the King he nevertheless followed them, though under protest, and was shortly entirely cured, which of course brought still greater fame to Alcyone. In many cases also communications from dead people were given through Alcyone, though the spirit-guide exercised rather a rigid censorship over this, and often declined to permit any attempt in this direction. However, in some cases, what could now-a-days be called tests were given, and on one occasion a valuable missing treasure was discovered through the information supplied by Narayan.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The private seances with Percy and the psychometry were continued, though naturally the opportunities for them were now comparatively few. At one of these private seances a new influence suddenly manifested itself, which gave quite a fresh direction to their investigations. I have mentioned that occasionally small objects were brought from a distance, and at a certain sance a beautiful carved seal was produced in that way, Narayan telling them through Alcyone that he was ordered to bring it and to direct that Alcyone should psychometrise  it. The result of the psychometrisation was startling, for this seal came from Peru, and was one of those which had been officially used by his uncle Mercury in the previous incarnation. Its effect was to bring before him with the greatest vividness first one or two special scenes from that incarnation, and then practically the whole of it, so that he spent many hours, day after day, in living over again all its most striking events.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In all these scenes the figure of Mercury was the most prominent, and Alcyone's strong attachment to him and deep reverence for him made these pictures more of a reality to him than the very life which he was really living. Until now his instinct had always been to consult the spirit-guide, and to abide in all cases by his advice when any question arose for decision; but in this psychometric image of Mercury he found himself in the presence of so much greater wisdom,  and also of an altogether purer and higher attitude towards everything, that he constantly yearned to consult the uncle of his former life instead of the spirit-guide of this. But of course the pictures of the Peruvian life, intensely vivid and realistic as they were, were still only pictures, and the characters in them could only repeat the parts, which they had really played some eight hundred years before.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A problem of some difficulty arose as to the way in which the temple influence should be used with regard to the succession to the throne of the country. The chief priest of the temple was distinctly in favour of one who was not the rightful heir, because he could obtain his support in certain schemes which he had in hand. Alcyone himself, on the other hand, felt that to use the power of the temple in favour of one who was emphatically not a good man would be not only a highly improper thing in itself but distinctly a failure in duty, and so he was in considerable trouble with regard to this matter. The advice of Narayan was to fall in with the wishes of the chief priest, since greater power would probably accrue in that way to the temple authorities; but Alcyone felt strongly dissatisfied with this, and earnestly desired to have the opinion on this subject of the uncle upon whose wisdom he found himself so constantly learning in the scenes from old Peru. It must be understood that in examining these pictures psychometrically, he found them not merely as pictures, but was able, as it were, to enter into that form and to live over again, with all its original intensity, the life of authority and experiment which he had led in those earlier centuries, and he had when doing this a curious double consciousness, for the memories of the Indian life were present in his mind even while he was living over again the older Peruvian existence.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
   During this period of indecision he was going back psychometrically by means of the seal into that older life, and constantly he made a passionate appeal to the Peruvian uncle for counsel in his present Indian difficulty; or rather perhaps for the support which he felt sure that that uncle would have given to his own conviction of the side of what seemed to him right. Suddenly, and in answer to this appeal, there came something which he had never seen before; a kind of vivid and greatly intensified life came into the form of the uncle in his mental picture into reality and changed before his eyes into a commanding Indian figure, which materialised itself so as to be visible to Percy as well as to him, and spoke to him with great emphasis in reply to his appeal.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Mercury told him that he had really been his uncle long ago in old Peru, but now was born again in a distant part of India. He then proceeded to give him definite advice, first of all upon the subject at issue, and then on a more personal matter. He told him that his intuition was right, and that the influence of the temple should be used only in favour of the rightful heir to the throne, and charged Percy to put that message before the chief priest with all the force of which he was capable. Then Mercury, in his new form, told Alcyone most impressively that he had embarked upon a dangerous course in submitting  himself as he had done to the will of Narayan; that he should do so no longer, but should use only such of his powers as could be exercised in full consciousness and without any yielding of his body to the use of any other entity whatever; that he had a great work to do in the far distant future, to do which he must be keenly sensitive and yet absolutely positive; that therefore this training had been necessary, but that now there had been enough of it.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone gladly and eagerly accepted this advice, but asked his new monitor how he was to make the required change how, after so many years of complete submission to Narayan, he could now suddenly succeed in resisting. Mercury replied that he himself knew much of these matters and would assist him; that while it was impossible for him to come to him in the physical body, he would yet give him astrally such instruction as was necessary, and that here and now he would enable him altogether to cast off the influence of Narayan and the possibility of that undesirable kind of mediumship, by throwing him into a trance which should last for years, and enable his various vehicles to grow too strong ever again to be used by any other than himself. Turning then to Percy, he gave him minute directions as to the treatment of the body of Alcyone during this lengthened rest, and charged him to take the greatest care of it. Then, fixing his piercing eyes upon Alcyone, he made over him a few mesmeric passes, under the effect of which Alcyone passed immediately into a deep trance, but with a smile of ineffable happiness upon his face.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In that strange trance his physical body lay for a period of seven years, exactly as Mercury had foretold, and all this time the latter's directions were implicitly followed by Percy, who took the greatest care that every detail should be carried out exactly as it had been ordered. This prolonged trance was of course regarded by the temple authorities as a miracle of the first order, and it was indirectly the cause of an enormous increase in the revenues, as the whole affair became noised abroad, and pilgrims came by thousands from distant parts to see the sleeping priest.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
During the trance, the consciousness of Alcyone rested almost entirely upon the mental plane; it was in fact the consciousness of the ego in close contact with the ego of Mercury, both apparently under the direction of, and it were bound together by and in, a still higher consciousness, which was directing both to some great end at present unexpressed. All this time Alcyone's physical body lay rested in perfect health, all its particles gradually changing in the natural course of events, while his astral and mental bodies were being steadily moulded by the pressure of these higher influences. When, at the end of this long sleep, he awoke in the most natural manner on the very day that had been fixed by Mercury, he was in the physical brain entirely unconscious of all that had passed, remembering only the appearance and the words of Mercury, just as though what had happened then had taken place only the evening before.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When Percy informed him of the lapse of years he was at first utterly incredulous, and only by slow degrees and by the most convincing proofs could he be brought to understand the astonishing fate which had overtaken him. From that moment however, his mediumship ceased entirely, although his sensitiveness and his power of psychometry remained. He was no longer amenable to the influence of Narayan, of whom indeed he never heard again, nor did any other entity speak through him for the rest of his life. People continued to flock to him for the curing of various diseases; this was now no longer done though him as before, but by a careful experiment he found that in many cases he himself by his own insight was able to diagnose and to cure their ills.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He had of course a greater reputation than ever, in consequences of his long trance, but when at the urgent solicitation of the chief priest he resumed his temple addresses, he found that he had now to prepare and to think them out entirely for himself, though he had certainly a greatly enhanced power of thought and capacity of expression. He tried again and again the psychometrisation of the Peruvian seal, and found himself able to call up the whole of the older life as vividly as before; yet never again did the loved form of his Peruvian uncle change into its modern Indian presentment, nor was he able to come into touch on the physical plane with him to whom he owed so much.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The communication made by Percy to the chief priest of the temple seven years before had led to the priest's throwing the weight of the temple influence into the scales in favour of the rightful heir Orpheus, and in consequence of that this heir had since come to the throne. There was naturally therefore a close link between the temple and the palace, and the new King, mindful of what he owed to Alcyone, showed marked favour to him in every way, so that on the passing away of the chief priest at an advanced age, Alcyone was at once appointed as his successor, and administered the affairs of the temple until the day of his death.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At the age of twenty-two he had married a good young lady, Cygnus, who was always kind and faithful to him, though there was nothing about her character which calls for any special remark. She bore him nine children. Naturally all of these children played at trying psychometry, and Osiris proved to be even more successful with it than his father. They all survived him, and all did well in the world, as his influential position enabled him to place them satisfactorily. He died in the year 11,111, at the age of seventy-one, deeply reverenced by a wide circle of people.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Mercury was in physical incarnation at this time, but  far away in the south of India, where most of our characters were gathered round him. He did not meet Alcyone in this incarnation upon the physical plane.
</view>
</text>
</body>