<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 43</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 43-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
We find ourselves once more in that most wonderful of the old civilisations which had its seat on the banks of the Nile. It was in the reign of the Pharaoh Unas, the last sovereign of the fifth dynasty which ruled over the joyous sons of mighty Khem, that Alcyone was born as the daughter of Ajax and Bellatrix. Her name was Hatshepu. Her father was the nextdoor neighbour of a great Court official, named Anarseb (Markab), and Markab's eldest son was Sirius, whose name this time was Menka. The comradeship of previous lives soon asserted itself, and Sirius and Alcyone, being playmates, became much attached to each other.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone's elder brother Uranus was very kind to them, and gave up much time to teaching them various things. Demeter, another little girl about the same age, a cousin of Alcyone, was also a great friend a partially clairvoyant child who had wonderful visions. Sirius and Alcyone liked to listen to the descriptions of what she saw, and Alcyone was several times able to see these things too, by touching Demeter. Sirius could not do this, so the girls told him that boys were not fit for such privileges, being too coarse and masculine!
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
They played together amidst the lovely gardens for which Egypt was so famous gardens which contained cleverly arranged artificial hills, dales and lakes. There was water everywhere, surrounded often by marble or polished granite steps and pillars; there were flowers growing on every foot of grass and hanging over every wall, while the huge blossoms of the lotus covered many of the ponds. The children were as thoroughly at home in the water as on the land, and enjoyed their early life immensely under the warm Egyptian sun.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Naturally Sirius and Alcyone had long ago arranged to marry as soon as they grew up, but unfortunately an unforeseen obstacle presented itself. There was among the chief priests of the city a man whom few liked and everybody feared a man against whom nothing was certainly known but a great deal was suspected. Everyone who offended him or opposed his will invariably died shortly afterwards, but the deaths could never in any way be traced to him. He had a son (Scorpio) who was decidedly a chip of the old block; he had all his father's unpleasant peculiarities and was vulgar and offensive in addition.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When Alcyone was a well grown handsome girl of about fifteen, Scorpio happened to see her; his passion was aroused by her beauty, and he made some approaches which she rejected with scorn. He drew off with some sort of muttered apology, but with an evil look. The difficulty thus placed in the way of their gratification only intensified his wicked desires and he determined to obtain possession of her at any cost, even if he had to marry her. He soon saw that marriage would be the only way in which he could hope to attain his wishes, and so he prepare an elaborate plot. He worked at his scheme for a long time, until it was diabolically ingenious and complete. He got hold of certain letters of her father's, and by skilful forgeries and interpolations transformed them into evidence of complicity in a plot against the Pharaoh.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then he sought an interview with Alcyone, and explained that these documents had fallen into his hands, and that his duty and interest alike demanded that he should at once place them before the King, by which he would obtain much credit and great reward; but that because of his great love for her he was willing to take the risk of suppressing them, if she on her part, by giving herself and her wealth to him, would indemnify him for the loss of this reward, and make his interests identical with those of her family. It, however, she said a work about this to her father or anyone else, he would instantly lodge the documents in the proper quarter.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This troubled Alcyone greatly; for her father's seals and signatures were undoubtedly genuine, and she knew that he was in the habit of expressing rather revolutionary opinions, and although she had occasionally a doubt, she feared that the letters must really be his. Also this seemed an opportunity to so something really heroic, such as she and Demeter and Sirius had often talked about to save the family at the cost of what to her was more than life. She felt herself precluded from consulting anybody, and  she saw no way to escape, so she yielded to this fellow's representations and announced to her astonished family that she intended to marry him. But she did not trust him, and so she stipulated that she must have those incriminating letters in her hands before the marriage ceremony.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The whole thing was a horrible business for her, especially when her mother questioned her as to whether she really liked this man, and she had to pretend that she did, while all the time her heart was full of loathing. Sirius also was much shocked and pained when he heard the news; he said that, though he could never love anyone but Alcyone, he was quite willing she should marry someone else if she really wished it, and if it was best for her, but that he could not believe that she could commit such an outrage on good taste as to marry that particular person. He insisted upon hearing her decision from her own lips, and even then he told her that he could not really believe it, but thought that she must be under some enchantment. He came near guessing the truth, which terrified her greatly, and made her try the more earnestly to deceive him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Her elder brother Uranus was away from home at this time, or it is probable that he would have solved the difficulty. As it was, she carried out her bargain and resolved to make the best of it, but her life was never really a happy one, though so far as the physical plane was concerned she had luxuries enough. Her husband disliked Sirius and was jealous of him, so she could see but little of her old lover. In 4017 Sirius' mother died, at the birth of a little son(Vega). Not long after this Markab died also, and Sirius had the household upon his hands, and as he also succeeded to some of his father's offices he was immersed in business affairs. He still remained faithful to the memory of Alcyone, and refused to consider the question of any other marriage, though there were many advantageous offers.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone had two children, Taurus and Virgo, and obtained some consolation in loving them, but was always haunted by the fear that they would grow  up like father. Her life was really a long martyrdom, for she never forgot her love for Sirius, and never could learn to like her husband, though she tried to do her duty to him. When her brother Uranus returned he was amazed and indignant about her marriage; he questioned her closely, and discussed the matter with Sirius, and his suspicions came near to the truth. His sister begged him not to press her any further as the deed was now done and could not be undone, and they must all make the best of it.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
She had other children, but they all died, and her dreary life dragged on for twenty years. Her husband's fiery passion had died away long ago, but he never ill treated her, and she preferred his neglect to his attentions while she had no objection to any other intrigues in which he might engage. Now that he was quite careless as to what she did and where she went, she contrived to see Sirius much more frequently.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Some change had been introduced into the life of the latter by the circumstances connected with a certain military expedition to the far south, in which a young noble named Ramasthenes (Mercury) had been taken prisoner. This young captive was entertained in turn by several of the Egyptian captains, and spent two years in the house of Sirius. His interest in philosophy and occult problems was marked, and as Uranus, Sirius and Alcyone all delighted in them also, there was much discussion. Now Mercury was introduced to certain high authorities of one of the chief temples by Castor, who was also an officer in Egyptian army, and had been with Sirius at the time when Mercury was taken prisoner. The father of Castor had been one of the most munificent patrons of this temple, and had held certain important lay offices in connection with it, to which Castor had succeeded, so that he was a person of great influence with the priests, and his recommendation carried Mercury at once into the heart of things. The latter at once became an enthusiastic student of the Mysteries, in which he immersed himself for years, though still keeping in touch with his friends.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In 3998 Alcyone was at last released from her long penance by the death of her husband, and of course Sirius immediately wanted her to marry him. She resisted on some theory that she was now unfit, being polluted by contact with her late husband, but the persistence of Sirius overcame her scruples, and she at last consented to marry him as soon as the year's interval after the death of her previous husband (which custom demands) should have expired.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Sirius was happy in the prospect, but once more his hopes were dashed to the ground. His younger brother Vega got into serious trouble; he had forced a connection with a woman of low type, discovered her in infidelity to him, and killed her and her paramour, and then ran away and hid himself to escape the consequences of the murder. Sirius gave up all business, and devoted himself to searching for Vega, and after the expenditure of much time and trouble he succeeded in finding him in a state of illness and destitution in a far-away city. A death sentence had been passed upon him by the Pharaoh, and it was only with great difficulty, and much distasteful reference to his own services that Sirius was able to get this commuted for a fine so heavy that he had to sell the ancestral home in order to pay it. He was thus reduced to comparative poverty, but he recovered Vega, who had entirely reformed, and they lived together happily enough in their obscurity.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Under these circumstances he could no longer ask Alcyone to marry him, as in order to do so she would have been legally compelled to give up the small pension which was all that her first husband had left her. She would willingly have shared poverty with Sirius, but feared to add to his burdens; and they both felt that since such unforeseen obstacles had twice arisen to prevent their union , perhaps the Gods did not wish them to marry.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone attached herself to the chief temple, and studied under Mercury, who had made wonderful progress in mystic lore, while Sirius devoted himself to the uncongenial task of trying to make money in order to buy back his ancestral home. It took him nearly twenty years to do this, but he succeeded at last, and then once more, at the age of sixty, he discussed with Alcyone the subject of marriage. She had long been devoted to the temple services and studies, and had made great advancement in them, and in order to marry she would have had to give up the position which she had gained in the temple work, so after thinking the offer over carefully and consulting Mercury and Uranus, they both agreed, though with certain pangs of regret, that they would still continue to offer their lives separately as a sacrifice to the Gods, as they had done hitherto. Cygnus, one of the students in the temple, had long ago fallen in love with Alcyone, and had several times asked her to marry him, but without success.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Vega married an old playmate of his childhood, Ursa, the daughter of an Indian king who had been driven from his kingdom and had taken refuge on the banks of the Nile. They lived happily and had two beautiful children, Andromeda and Draco, and Sirius and Alcyone hovered over these children as though they had been their own. Quite a class of students were by this time working under the direction of Mercury, and this was the principal; interest of the latter part of Alcyone's life.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Sirius died in 3967, and Alcyone mourned deeply for him, until one day he appeared to her and told her that to mourn for him, was unworthy of a student of the Hidden Light, and reminded her of the teaching which the Mysteries gave them as to the coming forth by day. Often as they had talked over it all, it was now for the first time that he made her fully realise of how little importance death is, and how entirely the dead and the living are one family.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This cheered her greatly, and she could often feel quite clearly his presence near her, though it was only twice that she actually saw him, once as above described, and once just before her own death, which occurred in 3960, at the age of seventy five. He told her then that he had cast a horoscope, or somehow made a calculation, about the remote future, and had discovered that, because they both had sacrificed themselves in this life for the sake of duty, they would meet once more at the feet of Mercury, after the passage of nearly six thousand years, and after that they would part no more; so she passed away quite peacefully and happily.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Orion also appeared in this life, under the name of Kepheren, as the son of Achilles, another near neighbour of the Indian king and the Anarseb family, in his childhood he played constantly with Vega, the little brother of Sirius. He was eight years old when the Captive Ramasthenese came to reside in the house of Sirius, and he used often to sit at the stranger's feet and listen to this talk. He was entered as a kind of day-scholar at the temple, and eventually became a pupil of Ramasthenes. Unfortunately, however, he formed some undesirable acquaintances, and was led away into the dissipations of the city life which for the moment he preferred to that of the temple. When it was definitely known that he had renounced the temple, the Pharaoh Unas offered his daughter Helios to Orion in marriage, and the ceremony was celebrated with much pomp and magnificence. Orion ardently loved his young wife, but nevertheless he realised that he had made a mistake in giving up the temple, and he never ceased to regret this. His wife died young but left behind her three children of whom the eldest Ptah-hotep(whom we know as Selene) was an unusually studious youth. He later became a learned man, and wrote a widely celebrated book on The Wisdom of Egypt . He lived to an extreme old age, one hundred and ten years, and was much respected for his great erudition.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Orion's later days were somewhat lonely, as all the friends for whom he cared passed on before him. Towards the end of his life he came to poverty. Evidently this royal life in Egypt under such remarkably favourable conditions was intended to be the climax towards which many previous incarnations had led. But choice must always be free, and Kephren chose wrongly, thus postponing the designed culmination.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Erato also took his part in this life, though he was born far away at Ajmere in Rajputana, as the son of the chieftain Deneb, and married the daughter of the suzerain Mars. In his youth he went to the wars with his father, and was presently sent along with him by Mars on an important embassy to Egypt. Among the officers who received the embassy were Sirius and Castor, with whom Erato at once struck up a friendship. The embassy was housed on the bank of the Nile in the neighbourhood of the group of friends to which reference has already several times been made, and Erato was readily admitted to intimacy with it. After his return to India he again took part in the constant wars of the period, and eventually had the misfortune to kill his own younger brother by accident in one of the battles. This sad occurrence induced him to leave his wife and children and become an ascetic. He wandered for a long time in the forests until at last he found an old man, Spica, living in a cave, who sheltered him and offered him instruction. Under his tuition Erato grew calm and resigned, and it was in that cave that he died at the age of forty-five.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Rhea was present in this life as the wife of Kallesarthon, the officer in charge of the expedition which captured Ramasthenes. The officer in charge of the expedition which captured Ramasthenes. The latter had been the pupil of Jupiter, an old man who was killed in that same expedition. His daughter Alcestis was taken prisoner at the same time by Kalesarthon, and was subsequently married by Castor, although he had already two wives living. Alces had a younger sister to live with her in Egypt, as they had no other relations living. When Pyx grew up she married Zeno, the son of Ulysses.
</view>
</text>
</body>