<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 41</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 41-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After a short life spent in solitude, quite apart from her usual friends. Alcyone this time returned to the bosom of her group to the very heart of it. Indeed, for once more she sat at the feet of Mercury, once more she married Mizar, and for the second time in the recorded lives she and Sirius were twins. They were born in the year 5635 at Girnar, in Kathiawar, and were the children of the local Raja, Corona. Alcyone had an extraordinary sympathy with her twin brother, always knew what was happening to him, and could sometimes foretell things about him. When quite a little boy , Sirius once had a fall from his horse, struck his head and was insensible for a few minutes. At the same moment, at home, some miles away, Chandrakirti (Alcyone) cried,  Oh, he is falling,  and herself fell in a faint. Again one day he was lost for a time, and his mother Leo was very anxious, because there was a suspicion that he had fallen down a well, and the mother began reproaching his attendant for not taking proper care of him. The little sister, however, lisped:   It is all right, mother, you need not scold Biru. My brother is on the mountain, and he is very tired. I am also just as tired, and as soon as he comes in we shall both go to bed; but he is quite safe. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The twins were always both ill together and recovered together, and they seemed each to know what the other was thinking or still more they seemed to think together, always liking the same people and things. Perhaps as they grew up the rapport was not quite so perfect in every detail; they still had the same thoughts, but one would emphasize some of them more than the other did. It was commonly said by the people that they had only one soul between them, though in reality they had evolved along quite different lines. They were exceedingly alike physically, except that the brother was a little taller; and one of Alcyone's great jokes was to dress in brother's clothes and see for how long she could deceive his servants into believing her to be their young master; and her aptitude was so great that she succeeded in this about nine times out of ten, and even several times went out for long rides with his grooms and attendants without being discovered.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Their characteristics, however, were decidedly different; the brother was slower and steadier, while the sister was brilliant but impulsive, and sometimes choleric and impatient. She insisted on being educated with him on learning everything that he learnt, and so acquired a set of accomplishments somewhat unusual for an Indian girl. When, at the age of fourteen, he had his first experience of going to battle, she demanded to be allowed to go too. Naturally their father would not permit this, and even Sirius, in all the pride of his new armour, said that it was not proper for a girl to fight, and, much more, that he could not fight well himself if he knew that his dear sister was in danger.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
She was indignant, and  went and shut herself up in her room in high dudgeon; privately , however, she had determined to go in spite of them all, and go she did, disguised in the dress of a boy, Mizar (the son of Andromeda, a prominent noble at the Court) who was desperately but hopelessly in love with her, and so would do anything for her. He had been a play-fellow of the twins, and had long worshipped the small Alcyone, without daring to aspire to the hand of the daughter of the King.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When Alcyone found herself in the battle she was distinctly nervous, but she kept as close to her brother as she could, and had the good fortune to be able to save his life, for while he was fighting with one man, another rushed at him from behind. Alcyone saw this, flung herself between them with a shout, and contrived in doing so to throw the assailant off his feet, though she too fell, entangled with him. In a moment he was on his feet again, with spear uplifted to kill her, but Sirius had recognised her voice as he was in the act of killing his previous antagonist. He swept round like lightning, and with the same swing of his sword cut off the arm which held the spear, but only just in time. Then he appointed some of his men to guard his sister, finished the battle  ( which he won) and rode home in triumph with her beside him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He could not chide her for her presence, because after all she had saved his life, as he had saved hers, but he made her promise not to do it again by describing in her what a terrible shock it was to him when he heard her voice again and realised that she was in danger, and how it took the strength from his arm and from his heart though, as she instantly remarked,  enough of it seems to have remained to cut off a man's arm . However, she kept her promise, and after this she never went into battle with him again. Though all such times were occasions of much greater agony for her than if she had actually been with him, for she seemed to sense whenever danger approached him, and she felt acutely that this time she was not there physically to ward it off.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When the time came for her marriage there was an eligible offer from the son of a neighbouring Raja, but she absolutely refused to leave her brother. Her father was annoyed, but Sirius joined his pleadings to hers, and eventually a compromise was arranged. The suitor was refused, but on condition that Alcyone should marry Mizar, the eldest son of an important noble of the Court. Naturally he was overjoyed, and Alcyone was well content, for she had stipulated that her husband should come and live in a wing of the palace, so that she might not be seperated from her brother. Cygnus, a younger brother of Mizar, was also hopelessly in love with Alcyone, and devoted his life to her service, remaining unmarried until her death; but afterwards he married Egeria.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A few years later Sirius himself married, but fortunately Alcyone approved of the bride (Orion) who came all the way from Amer, in the Jaipur State. The years which followed were on the whole very happy ones, though Alcyone had anxieties when her husband and her brother were away fighting. Presently, the Raja (Corona) died, and Sirius became King, and was more than ever involved in affairs of State. Orion and Alcyone became bosom friends and were together; they were commonly called the two Queens.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Both felt a strong attraction for the wonderful temple on the great hill which towers above Girnar. It was and is truly marvellous building, like a vast mediaeval castle of marble, court opening out of court, and hall out of hall, in bewildering confusion, with matchless carvings and lovely traceries on every hand. It was built on the side of a steep mountain, and the only entrance to it was through a single narrow gateway in a rugged picturesque gorge. So sharp were the slopes that hardly two of its halls were on the same level, and when one looked down upon the huge building from the neighbouring summit, it had a curious effect of a forest of gleaming white marble domes, growing precariously up and down half-a-mile of steep hillside.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The stupendous temple had an absolute fascination for the two Queens; the were constantly having themselves carried up there in their palanquins, and when their dearly loved husbands were away from home, fighting in some of the petty wars of the period, they spent much more time up there than in their palace below, even though instead of their wide marble halls they had only a tiny guest-chamber hollowed out of the rock with , however a prospect from its little window of fifty miles of fertile plain. It was up there that Queen Orion insisted on retiring (much to the dismay of her court physicians) when her first child was to be born, and up there in that tiny rock chamber Alcyone nursed her through the affair. Alcyone greatly loved this temple, and built from her own private purse a new shrine for it, and a lovely marble hall with many pillars. Saturn was the Head of the great Temple, and under him as officiants were Mercury, Brihat, Vajra and Herakles. Helios, Naga and Achilles were eager young postulants in the same temple, but Helios died early. Mercury was the special advisor of the two Queens, and also of Sirius. The pious example of these two great ladies was widely followed all through the kingdom, and the cause of religion was greatly promoted thereby.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Sirius had a good deal of trouble with his eldest son Gamma, who was wayward and of bad disposition. Alcyone had no patience with him and thought he ought to be sternly repressed, but his father was usually gentle and forbearing with him, and quite at the end of his life that attitude was justified. Though he caused trouble over and over again in the meantime and indeed was really responsible for his father's death. Because some dishonourable and treacherous actions of his had been discovered, he had fled from the court and had joined a hostile army which was invading the country. In the battle which ensued he wounded his father severely in the side with a spear, but fled in horror when he saw him fall. Sirius had himself put into a litter and still directed the rest of the battle, which was a complete victory for him. The son Gamma was captured, and was deeply repentant for his deeds.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When later the same enemy gathered a new force and again attacked the country, the reformed Gamma led the troops against them, and won a final victory over them by a desperate deed of valour, leading a forlorn hope to certain death, but thereby gaining the day.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When Sirius wounded by Gamma, had fallen from his horse in that previous battle. Alcyone also had fallen at home, crying :  He is hurt; He will die! 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
She suffered just as he did, lingered on for months as he did, and finally died on the same day without any reason but sympathy with her wounded brother. She could not however forgive or receive her nephew Gamma, who had caused the death of his father Sirius; and even after Gamma died bravely in the effort to atone, she still said that it was the least he could do, and not half enough to expiate his wickedness. Alcyone herself had seven children, to whom she was a good and loving mother.
</view>
</text>
</body>