<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 20</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 20-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone was born in a female body in the year 21759  B.C., not far from where Chittagong now stands. She was the daughter of Brihat and Neptune, and was one of a family of four. Her elder brother was Uranus and her younger sister was Mizar, but both of these died young: Uranus at the age of eighteen and Mizar, in child-birth, at the age of fifteen. There was also a younger brother, Vulcan, who was taught from boyhood by the Priests in the temple. The father Brihat seems to have been both ruler and Priest of a small community or kingdom. Astrology was a prominent factor in the religious ideas of the day, and Alcyone's horoscope was cast with great elaboration. It destined her to a marriage with Saturn, who was a distant relation, and it foretold that she should bear a child of remarkable power and holiness, and directed that all her early life should be arranged as a preparation for this coming event. The instructions were obeyed, and she was specially instructed by the Priests with a view to this.
</view>
</text>
<text>
<view lang="en">
Her childhood was a happy one. We see her as a graceful, beautiful child, with long streaming black hair. The only mode of dressing the hair was to catch it back from the face with golden clasps, in which were mounted most magnificent diamonds, so large that they looked like brilliant stars against her dark locks. The hair was washed daily and anointed with magnetised oil, which was supposed to stimulate the intellectual faculties. She was carefully secluded from all possible trouble or difficulty. Her only sorrow was the death of her elder brother Uranus, to whom she was profoundly attached.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At the age of fifteen she was duly married to Saturn with great pomp, and a year later a noble boy was born (Surya). There was great rejoicing over this event, and every care was taken of the child of promise. Alcyone was very sensitive and impressionable, and when the child was about to come to her she had a wonderful dream in which she saw a bright star leave the sky and enter her. This dream caused her to be considered a holy person. She was also clairvoyantly conscious  of the presence of the ego when it attached itself to her.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Everything seemed to promise for her a long and brilliant life under the most favourable conditions; yet all these expectations were disappointed, for her life was abruptly terminated at the age of seventeen by an accident in which she voluntarily sacrificed herself in order to save her child. The circumstances were as follows:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone's house formed part of a great suite of buildings erected round a sort of square which was within the palace of the King. A slave-woman, who was changing the water in a glass vase containing gold-fish, was called away on some other business, and set the vase down on a table in the full rays of the sun. The glass acted as a lens, and the sun-rays, streaming through it, converged on some neighbouring wood-work and set it on fire. The house was built entirely of wood, richly gilded, and the flames spread like lightening in every direction, blazing  up like a furnace. Alcyone was, at the moment, at some little distance off, but as the servants rushed off in every direction shouting and screaming, her attention was attracted, and she flew, fleet as a deer, towards the burning house.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The baby had been left with his nurse in an upper room, but she had gone out, confiding her charge to some fellow-servants. These fled downwards on the alarm of fire, forgetting the baby, and the terrified nurse, rushing for the child, fell back at the sight of the blazing staircase, which was the only way to the nursery. Wringing her hands, she screamed out:   The child! the child , but dare not face the roaring flames which barred the road.  My boy?  gasped Alcyone, and sprang up through the sea of fire. Several of the stairs had already fallen, leaving only in some places the supporting wooden bars not yet burned through, though blazing. Desperately she plunged on, climbing, slipping, leaping across the gaps through which the flames flaring upwards, caught her garments and scorched her flesh. Surely no human strength would suffice to carry her to the top! But mother's love is omnipotent, and, in less time than it takes to tell it, she reached the room where the baby lay. Smoke was pouring into it, and she wrapped an unburnt fragment of clothing across her mouth and crawled along the floor. The babe, crowing at the dancing flames, stretched out chubby arms to his mother, and, catching him up, she pressed his face into her bosom and fled downwards with her boy close wrapped in her arms. Again she crossed that burning torrent, her body nude, her hair blazing, the diamonds dropping from it, flashing back the flames. Somehow she reached the bottom, the open air, and fell prostrate outside, shielding the babe even as she fell. He was unhurt, but she was dying, and in less than an hour she breathed her last. More out of her body  than in it, too terribly injured to retain feeling, she was scarce conscious of suffering, and her last smile seemed to be on the freed astral form, as it bent over the rescued boy. Is it not the karma she made, by  dying for Surya then, being reaped in the present opportunity given to Alcyone to serve the Blessed one again?  
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After its mother's death the child was taken in charge by his aunt Viraj (Saturn's sister), who was even then an advanced ego, and has since become an important member of the Occult Hierarchy. She was psychic, and through her Alcyone was still able to help and care for the child. The aunt never allowed any of the servants to touch the baby, and swung him herself in the garden in a sort of cradle hung up between the trees. There, in the quiet grove, Alcyone would speak to her from the astral world about the child, who was thus brought up altogether in a holy atmosphere and soon became a wonder, at the age of seven delivering teaching in the temple, so that people from all quarters came to hear him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It seems as though from time to time the members of the present Hierarchy of Adepts were born together in different countries to assist in the founding of a new religion, or of a magnetised centre, we see them also spreading the religion and sending expeditions to other distant centres, as in the previous life in North America, where an expedition was sent to Yucatan. In the present one, some twenty-five years after Alcyone's death, we see Surya sending one north to the city of Salwan. Some of the party lost their lives from the hardships endured; and among these was Alcyone's younger brother Vulcan, at the age of about thirty-five.
</view>
</text>
</body>