<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 25</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 25-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The cradle of the great Aryan race was on the shores of the Central Asian Sea, which (up to the time of the cataclysm which sunk the island of Poseidonis beneath the waters of the Atlantic Ocean) occupied the area which is now the Gobi Desert. The great founder of the race, the Manu Vaivaswat, had established his colony there after the abortive attempt in the highlands of Central Arabia, and after a long period of incubation and many vicissitudes the race had become great and powerful. Several times during the ages of its existence had the Manu sent forth huge hosts to establish sub-races in various parts of that vast continent, and at the time of which we have now to write once more this virile nation was outgrowing its boundaries. During its history the Manu had incarnated again and again to direct it, but at the time of Alcyone's birth (18,885 B.C.) he had not shown himself physically among his people for many centuries, and so there had been time for differences of opinion to arise as to exactly what his intentions had been.
</view>
</text>


<text>
<view lang="en">
A section had grown up among them who argued that now that the new race was definitely established, and there was no danger that the type could be lost, the strictest ordinances of the Manu as to not mingling with other races were no longer intended to be operative. Consequently certain families allowed themselves to intermarry for political purposes with some of the rulers of the Tarter races. This was considered as a crime by the more orthodox , and it led to so much friction that eventually those who held the wider opinion established themselves as separate community which in course of time grew into a considerable kingdom. They themselves, however, seem soon to have abandoned the idea of intermarriage with the other races, so that there was practically no perceptible difference of type between the two tribes, but this did not in the least heal the religious division, which on the contrary seems to have been accentuated by the passage of time. The great bulk of the Aryans regarded with horror this tribe which had once intermarried, and would have no dealings with them. The adoption or development of difference in language among them still further emphasised the division, and they were regarded as a hostile race for centuries before the rapidly increasing orthodox Aryans occupied their original territory after many battles, and finally drove them out into the desert.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The cultivable land round the shores of the Gobi Sea was a limited area, and the great central orthodox kingdom of the fifth root-race occupied all the best part of it. This separated race had therefore to be content with much less desirable territories, and they settled chiefly in valleys around the northern hills. The central race increased so  rapidly that it was constantly pressing upon these independent tribes and trying to annex their valleys. The orthodox people were so extraordinarily bigoted and intolerant that they could not mix peacefully with these others who differed from them, but regarded them as demons to be exterminated, so that for the most part no compromise was possible.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Mars who was at this time King of one of the tribes which constituted this seceding race, had long been much troubled by the incursions of the orthodox, and though he had contrived to resist them so far, he knew that he could not hope to do so indefinitely, for his tribe, though large and well organised, was a mere handful compared to the multitudes of the central race. Unless he fought persistently against them his race would speedily be exterminated, and it seemed as though the most determined resistance could only postpone for a while this inevitable end. In his perplexity on this point he had frequently asked counsel from his religious teacher Jupiter; the latter always strongly advised against fighting, but did not tell him how he was to maintain the existence of his people.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The difficulty was constantly becoming more acute and the danger more imminent, when in answer to many prayers and appeals there came at least to Mars a vision which decided his course of action. Both the orthodox and those who were considered unorthodox venerated equally the memory of the Manu, and gave him all but divine honours, so when he appeared to Mars in a dream, and gave him counsel as to his difficulties, he gladly accepted the solution offered.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Manu told him that the dilemma in which he found himself was not the result of any play of chance forces, but had been arranged long before hand as part of his plan. He announced that it was his desire that Mars, whom he had specially chosen for the work, should lead the vanguard of the greatest migration in history that he should take his tribe and journey westwards and southward for many years, until he reached a certain sacred land which was prepared for him a land of unexampled fertility, in which great spiritual as well as material progress could be attained. Here he should settle and flourish exceedingly; and he was specially enjoined to treat well and kindly all the tribes and races with whom he came in contact, fighting with them only when actually compelled. He was to enter upon this promised land and move slowly onward to its extremity, and it was foretold to him that the tribes of the orthodox empire, who were pressing so hard upon him, would rejoice over his departure and exult in their occupation of his lands; but that in the future they also should find his people in possession of the most desirable part of the promised land, and that their efforts to oust them would be unsuccessful. He was further told that he himself in future lives would take no inconsiderable part in the direction of these migrations, and that as a reward for all this hard work he and his wife Mercury would have the privilege in the future of doing an even greater work such work as the Manu himself had done. The prophesy referred specially also to his sons Herakles and Alcyone, and expressly stated that work of a similar nature awaited them still further in the future.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This vision at once lifted Mars out of all his perplexities and filled him with enthusiasm for the mighty mission confided to him. He ordered a great assemblage of all his people, and told them what he had seen and heard, and what he had decided to do, and he spoke so convincingly that he carried the entire tribe with him and infected it with his own zeal. He instructed them to gather together great stores of food in its most probable forms, and to drive with them the strongest and best of their flocks and herds. He consulted his astrologers as to the best day for the start, and just before it he planned and carried out a successful raid upon the territory of his orthodox enemies, gaining thereby a great amount of property which was useful to him, and having his own people safe out of the way and far on their journey before reprisals could be attempted.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
There was amongst his subjects a considerable party who regarded this migration as a wild scheme and the vision of Mars as a delusion. The head of this recalcitrant party was Alastor, and he declared that his conscience would not allow him to follow a leader whom he believed to be under the guidance of some evil or diabolical power which was deceiving and misleading him, and causing him to undertake a mad enterprise which could only end in the utter ruin of those who were foolish enough to follow him. To this tirade Mars replied that he would force no man to accompany him, for he wanted none but loyal and willing-cooperators, and that Alastor and his followers might stay behind if they pleased. Only a comparatively small number of Alastor's party were prepared to take so extreme a step, and most of his friends urged him to reconsider his determination. He however remained obstinate, declaring that he and his band of Adullamites were the only people who were really faithful to the commands of the Manu, since they stayed in the country where he had established them and refused to be diverted from their manifest duty by hysterical dreams and pretended revelations.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Mars wasted no more time over him, but told him that he might go to the destruction in his own way. Alastor did stay behind, and displayed a certain amount of evil ingenuity in his endeavour to make the best of the situation. As has already been said, Mars had organised a raid upon the orthodox, and naturally their ruler fitted out a punitive expedition to crush the audacious mountaineers. Alastor boldly went out to meet this army, announced himself as the head of one of two rival parties existing in the mountain kingdom, and offered his support to the invaders on condition of good treatment for himself and his people. He stated that for a long time he had been convinced that the men of his own tribe were wrong in having long ago intermarried with Atlanteans, and that he had often wished to join himself to the orthodox empire, but had been prevented from doing so by Mars. He described the route taken by the latter in his migration, and offered to show the invaders how, by taking a short cut across the hills, they could overtake him and probably defeat his people. The orthodox leader thought it best to accept his offer of assistance, and promised him the lives of his followers in return for this treachery. The expedition plunged into the mountains under Alastor's guidance in the effort to intercept Mars; but being unused to and unprepared for high altitudes its members suffered exceedingly, and were when after many hardships they succeeded in meeting Mars they were defeated with great slaughter. The leader, however, escaped and promptly put Alastor and his myrmidons to death.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
True to his instructions, Mars endeavored to avoid fighting as far as he could. When he approached any organised kingdom he always sent his embassy to its ruler announcing that he and his people came in peace and amity, in obedience to a divine command, and that all that they desired was to be allowed to pass quietly on their way to carry out the orders which they had received. In most cases the required permission was readily given, and often the inhabitants of the countries through which they passed received them hospitably, and sped them on their way with gifts of food. Sometimes a chieftain was alarmed by the report of their numbers, and refused them admission within his frontiers, and when that occurred Mars turned aside from the direct line of his course, and sought for a more friendly ruler. Two or three times he was savagely attacked by predatory tribes, but his hardy mountaineers found no great difficulty in beating them off.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Under these conditions Alcyone's early life was as unsettled and adventurous one. He was about ten years old when his father decided upon the migration, and consequently at an age to enjoy to the full the constant change and adventure of it. He had as it were two sides to his character one frankly boyish and fond of all this excitement and variety, and the other dreamy and mystical. He dearly loved both of his parents, but he seems to have specially associated his father with the former of these moods and his mother with the latter. On some days he rode by his father at the head of the caravan, or dashed on far in front on some sort of scout duty, keen and active and very much on the physical plane; on others he remained behind with his mother, often riding curled up in one of the panniers on the back, often riding curled up in one of the panniers on the back of some draught-animal, buried in his own visions and taking no heed of the country through which they were passing.       
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 In this latter condition he seemed to be living not in the present but in the past, for he had often extraordinarily vivid visions (most often really of past incarnations, though he did not know that) which he regarded as so entirely private and scared that he would hardly ever speak of them even to his mother, and ever at all to any one else. These visions were of varied character, some of them connected with lives which we have already investigated, but others which are at present unknown to us. In many of these scenes his father and mother appeared, and he always recognised them, under whatever veil of race or sex they might be hidden. Sometimes, when a rare wave of confidence swept over him, he would describe these visions to his mother, making them marvellously picturesque and life-like. He called them his picture-stories, and he would say:  Mother, in this story you are a priest in the temple,  or  In this you are my mother, just as now,  or again,  In this you are my little baby, and I carry you in my arms. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Whenever he said These things his mother felt herself identified with the figure in the vision, and her memory was as it were awakened by his. She remembered now that when she was herself a child she used to have similar recollections, though as she grew older they faded from her mind; and she realised that her son was seeing what she used to see. In one of his most splendid visions that which he liked best of all neither his father nor mother appeared, but he saw himself as a young girl filled with intense love and determination, rushing through raging flame and suffocating smoke to rescue a child who was the hope of the world a memory of the life in Burma three thousand years before. But he had also other memories in which his parents bore no part, and some of these were far less desirable.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
One curious set of visions which came now and then appeared to image some ceremonies of the darker magic, evidently from a remote past. They were indescribably weird, yet thrilling and they excited a feeling of inexpressible horror and loathing which was yet somehow mingled with a kind of savage ecstasy. There was about them a distinct sense of something radically unholy and evil something from which Alcyone's present nature shrank with terror and disgust, while he was yet keenly conscious that there had been a time in the far-distant past when it had filled him with a fierce joy when he had somehow been able to revel in what now he utterly abhorred. He disliked these visions intensely, yet occasionally they asserted themselves, and when one had commenced he seemed compelled to play his part in it to the end. Of these he had never been able to speak to his mother, though she had twice noticed the prostration which followed them, for he came out of them in a condition of profuse perspiration and utter nervous exhaustion. But he said only his dreams had been terrifying, but that he could not describe them.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 It is not easy to recover the actual subject matter of these evil visions, but they evidently reflected some of the wild orgies of the darker worship as practiced in Atlantis something of the same order as the alleged witches' Sabbath of the Middle Ages a kind of riotously sensual adoration of some strange personification of evil belonging to an existence which humanity has now altogether transcended. Its devotees appear among other things to have been able by the use of some potion or unguent to assume animal forms at will and to levitate these transformed physical bodies. In looking back involuntarily  upon these unholy revels Alcyone always saw himself with a partner always the same partner; and he knew that it was for the love of that partner that he had thrown himself into this cult of evil, that her seduction had drawn him into it and taught him to enjoy it. Yet even amidst his horror he knew that she had had herself no evil purpose in doing this that it was because she loved him that in reality she would have died rather than  harm him, and that it was only her ignorance which permitted her to be used as a lure by malicious powers behind. These unpleasant visions came to the boy but rarely, and they would not have merited such detailed mention but for the fact that a few years later they were shown to have a close connection with one of the recurrent characters in our story.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Some time before the birth of Alcyone a certain Mongolian chieftain had come to take refuge in the kingdom of Mars. This chieftain was the younger brother of a reigning chief who was (apparently not unreservedly) decidedly unpopular with his people. The younger, on the contrary, was universally liked, and there was a conspiracy, though entirely without the young man's knowledge, to dethrone the elder brother and set him up in his stead. This was discovered and suppressed, but as it was impossible to persuade the elder brother that the younger had not been privy to it, he had to flee for his life, and it was in this way that he came to seek refuge with Mars. He and two or three friends who had escaped with him proved harmless and indeed desirable members of Aryan tribe, so they settled down and were accepted without further question.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
They had brought their wives and children with them; so they formed a kind of minor community within the tribe, living amongst it but not intermarrying with it. This young chieftain (Taurus) had several children, but the only one that comes into our story is Cygnus, a daughter who was about the same age as Alcyone, with whom she fell violently in love. They played together often as children, but along with many others, and it does not seem that Alcyone specially differentiated her from the rest, though he was always affectionate to all. As they grew older, the boys and girls drew more and more apart in their games, and so he saw less of her, but she never for a moment forgot him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When she was seventeen her father married her to Aries, who was the son of one of his companions. He was much older than she was, and she had no affection for him, but her wishes were not consulted in the matter; it was entirely an affair of policy. Her husband was not a bad man, and was never unkind to her, but he was absorbed in his studies and had no attention to spare for his young wife, whom he regarded rather as part of the necessary furniture of a home rather than a sentient being who might possibly have claims upon him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
For a long time she fretted silently against this, being all the time madly in love with Alcyone, and seeing him only occasionally and casually. At last there came a time when he was sent on ahead of the main body on a dangerous scouting expedition; hearing of this and fearing that he might be killed, she seems to have been reduced to desperation, and she fled from her husband, dressed herself in male attire, and joined the small band of men whom he was taking on this perilous expedition. Alcyone succeeded in carrying out the instructions of Mars, but only at the cost of the loss of many of his men, and among others Cygnous was fatally wounded and her sex discovered.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
She was carried before Alcyone, and when he recognised her she asked to be left alone with him for a few moments before her death. Then she told him of her love and her reason for thus following him; he was much surprised, and deeply regretted that he had not known of her affection before. As he stood beside her his mind was persistently haunted by the most vivid presentment of his old vision of the wild orgies of Atlantean magic, and like a glare of lightening it burst upon him that Cygnus was identical with the female companion of that strange old witchcraft. He was so struck by this revelation that his manner showed it, and she, who had known something in childhood of the visionary side of his nature, at once divined that he was seeing something non-physical, and set her will with all her remaining strength to see it too. She had not been at all psychic during life, but now as death approached, the veil was to some extent broken through by her earnest effort, and as she seized his hand the vision which he saw opened before her eyes also. She was horror stricken at his evident horror, but at the same time in a way delighted also, for she said:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 At least you loved me then, and though through ignorance I led you into evil, I swear that in the future I will atone for this and regain your love by loyal and ungrudging service to the uttermost. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Saying this she died, and Alcyone mourned over her, regretting that he had not known of her love for him, for had he done so, he might have prevented her untimely end. When opportunity offered he told the story of this strange experience to his mother, and she agreed with him that without doubt his vision did represent the events of previous incarnations, and that she, his father, his sister, his elder brothers and Cygnus had really borne in those lives the parts which the visions assigned to them. The story of which this particular incident brought the recollection will be found in Man : Whence, How and Whither, p 122 .
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The strong influence of his mother Mercury over Alcyone seemed to increase rather than decrease as the years rolled on, and though the vision of his childhood now visited him but rarely he still remained impressible as far as she was concerned, and frequently caught her thought even when at a distance from her. For example, on one occasion when her sons were out on a scouting expedition clearing the way through the hills for the main body of the caravan, she became aware through a dream of an ambush into which Herakles and his party were in danger of falling. The whole scene was so vividly before her eyes, and the natural features of the country so deeply engraved on her mind, that she could not but feel sure that the danger was a real one. She called before her some natives of the hill-country who happened to be in the camp, described minutely to them the place which she had seen, and asked whether they recognised it. They immediately replied that they knew it well, and asked how she came to know it, since it was more than a day's march ahead. When she heard this she was even more certain than before, and as it was clearly impossible to send a messenger to Herakles in time, she tried to convey a warning by thought.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Herakles, however, was so full of business and the cares of the expedition that he was not amenable to thought impressions just then; but fortunately Alcyone, who was in charge of a smaller body of men in a neighbouring ravine, caught the feeling that his mother was in deep anxiety, and, turning his thought strongly in her direction, read the whole affair from her mind like a vision, and at once changed his course, led his own party up an almost impossible cliff and across some intervening spurs of the mountain, and reached his brother just in time to prevent him from falling into the ambush, thus unquestionably saving his life, for the arrangements of the hill savages were so well made that the total destruction of his party was a certainty. But with the warning which Alcyone gave, the Aryans were able to turn the tables on the savages and descend upon them from above while they were watching in fancied security, so that they were driven away with great slaughter and a clear way through the mountains was opened for whole tribe.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Soon after this Mars thought it well that Alcyone should marry. The young man had no special desire in the matter, but was quite willing to accede to his father's wish; so he consulted his mother, and she suggested several young ladies whom she considered suitable, and eventually Alcyone selected Theseus. She made him a good wife, though she was somewhat jealous and exacting. He had seven children, among whom was Neptune, who afterwards married Hector, and one of their children was Mizar, who was always Alcyone's favourite granddaughter; and specially devoted to him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Many years were occupied in the westward journey through the hilly country, and sometimes the tribe suffered considerable hardships, but on the whole they got on well and lost remarkably few men, considering the difficulties of the route. When at last they reached the great plains of India their progress was far easier, especially as their first entry upon them was into the dominions of a great King named Podishpar (Viraj) who welcomed them with the greatest hospitality, recognising them and their work, and doing everything in his power to help them on their way. In the first place he assigned to them a tract of fertile ground on the banks of a river, and supplied them with  grain to sow there, so that not only did they stay encamped there for a whole year enjoying his hospitality, but they had an enormous store of grain to take on with them when they finally departed. A few of them, worn out with the ceaseless travelling of the past thirty years, settled permanently in the kingdom of this friendly potentate, but the great majority decided to push on.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At parting King Podishpar gave to Mars a book of the Atlantean scriptures and a talisman of extraordinary power a cube of wonderful centre. He also sent embassies in advance to many friendly monarchs with whom he was in alliance, telling them of the coming of the Aryans and asking them to receive them kindly. Thus their way was smoothed for them, and the weariness of the constant travelling was reduced to a minimum. The talisman was well known all over the north of India, and all who saw it did reverence to its bearer. It was supposed to confer good fortune and invincibility upon its possessor, but when Viraj gave it to Mars he said proudly:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
  I have no longer need of it, for I am invincible without it, and I carve out my own fortune with my sword. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
For Podishpar had a huge two-handed sword with a golden hilt in which a magnificent ruby was set, and this sword was popularly reported to possess magical properties, so that he who held it could never feel fear, nor could he be injured in battle; and he also commanded the service of certain genie or spirits, much as Aladdin commanded the slaves of the lamp. As a further proof of goodwill, and in order to cement the alliance between them, King Podishpar asked Mars for his daughter Brihat as a husband for his son Corona, and Mars gladly acceded to the request. Brihat had previously married Vulcan, one of the subordinate leaders of the Aryan host; but Vulcan had been killed in one of their fights with the savages. It is evident from this that there was then no prejudice against the re-marriage of a widow.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Here and there, for one reason or another, bands of men dropped away from the great host of Mars as the years rolled on, and settled at intervals along the line of his route. In the course of some centuries these small settlements developed into powerful tribes, who subjugated the people round about them, and for themselves considerable kingdoms. They were always arrogant and intolerant, and so tiresome with their constant aggressions that about a thousand years later the Atlantean kingdoms banded them together against them, and, with some help from the Divine Ruler of the Golden Gate, finally defeated them and drove them with great slaughter down into the south of the peninsula, where the descendants of Mars were then ruling. Here they found refuge, absorbed into the mass of the population. The higher classes of the south country, though from longer exposure to the Indian sun they have become somewhat darker, are as fully Aryan as any of the northern people, having mingled only very slightly with the highest Atlantean blood.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Still, in spite of these defections there was scarcely any reduction in the number of the followers of Mars, as the births among his people were largely in excess of the deaths. Alcyone might be said to know no life but this peripatetic existence, and even his children had been born into it and grew up in it. but the open air and constant exercise were health-giving, and they enjoyed their perpetual pilgrimage through these lands of the sun. Mars, who was now growing somewhat old, divided his great host into three parts, and gave them into charge of his three sons, Uranus, Herakles and Alcyone, so that he himself was relieved from all worry about details. And retained only a general supervision. His wife Mercury, however, had so great a reputation for wisdom that all the people came to her for counsel in special difficulties, and her three sons trusted greatly to her intuition.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
King Podishpar had told Mars that since his instructions were to press on to the south of India he would recommend him to a certain ally of his, King Huyaranda (sometimes called Lahira) who had the kingdom next in size to his own. In fact these two monarchs at this period governed between them by far the greater part of India. One ruled the north and the other the south, and they were separated by a broad belt of smaller kingdoms, quite insignificant by comparison.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
King Huyaranda (whom we know as Saturn) held rather a curious position, for though he was the autocratic and undisputed monarch of the country, the leader of its armies and the dispenser of justice, there was in the background an even greater power that of a High Priest who was also a kind of religious ruler a person never seen by the people, but yet regarded with the utmost awe. He lived apart from all the rest of the world in the strictest seclusion, in a magnificent palace which stood in the midst of a enormous garden surrounded by lofty walls of the garden, and even his attendants were not permitted to leave it. He communicated with the outer world only through his representative, the deputy High Priest, and no one but this deputy was supposed to ever see him, for when he wished to walk in his garden every one was ordered to keep out of the way. The reason for all this seclusion was that he was regarded as the earthly mouthpiece of Mahaguru, and it was supposed that unless he was kept scrupulously apart from all contact with ordinary people he could not be pure enough or calm enough to be an absolutely perfect channel for the messages from on high.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The relations between the King and his invisible High Priest seem to have been not unlike those which existed in old days between the Shogun and the Mikado in Japan, for the former did nothing of any importance without consulting the latter. At this time the High Priest bore the name of Byarsha, and was a man of great strength and wisdom the Great One known to us as Surya, whose life Alcyone had saved at the cost of her own, three thousand years before in Burma.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When the embassy from King Podishpar reached King Huyaranda and announced the impending arrival of Mars and his host, King Huyaranda at once consulted Surya as to the attitude which he ought to adopt. The reply of the High Priest was that this migration had been ordered by the gods, and that the tribe who came were the precursors of mighty nation from whom many great teachers of the world should come. The King was advised to receive them with all honour, and to assign them tracts of land near all his principal cities, so that those of them who wished might spread themselves over the country and settle in it. but for those who preferred to remain as a separate community an almost unoccupied district near the foot of the Nilgiris was to be set apart, that they might dwell there after the customs of their forefathers.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The oracle spoke several years before the arrival of Mars, so when he came he found everything in readiness for him. King Huyaranda sent his own son Crux to receive him at the frontier of the kingdom, and when he approached the capital he himself came forth to meet him at the head of a splendid procession, and treated him with the utmost deference. He explained to Mars the instructions which he had received with regard to him, and Mars at once accepted all the arrangements suggested, thankful to find that at last his wanderings were over and his heavy responsibility at an end. In a wonderfully short time the behests of the High Priest were carried out, and the Aryans were peacefully established as a recognised part of the population of this great southern kingdom.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Before their arrival Surya had issued a curious manifesto about them, instructing his people as to how they were to receive and regard these  high-nosed strangers from the north.  He especially described them as fitted by their nature for the priestly office, and decreed that the ranks of the priesthood should be recruited from them, and that the offices should also as far as possible be hereditary among them.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Those of them who wished were to be free to mingle with his own people and devote themselves to warlike or commercial pursuits, but those who were willing to take up the priestly work were to have every facility for living as a class apart from the rest, to be maintained by gifts from the rest, but to own no personal property.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The deputy High Priest, through whom these and all other decrees were promulgated to the outer world, was at this time a very old man, whom we know as Osiris, and when because of advancing age he begged to be relieved from the onerous duties of his office, by way of setting an example to the nation Surya asked Mars to send him one of his sons to take the vacant post. Mars felt himself greatly honoured  by this request, and said that he held himself and all who belonged to him entirely at the disposal of the Messenger of the Gods; but that as he himself was now old and wished to retire from worldly affairs he would prefer it if his elder son Herakles could be left to take upon him his cares and to carry on the traditions and reputations of the chieftainship, and if his younger son Alcyone could be permitted to receive the signal mark of esteem which Surya destined for his family. (It should be mentioned that Uranus had already adopted the hermit life, and established himself in a cave in the Nilgiris, and when approached on the subject he firmly declined to return to the ordinary world.)
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Surya was graciously pleased to accept the arrangement suggested by Mars, so Alcyone suddenly found himself in the curious position of the representative in the outer world of what was really the chief power in the kingdom the only person who ever met that august potentate face to face, and consequently the channel for all communications with him, even those from the King Huyaranda himself. He was much oppressed at first by the seriousness of the responsibility, but as he learnt the routine of his business and came to know Surya better he found that he could easily fulfil the duties of his position. The  principal difficulty was that of selection to decide which of the score of cases which came before him each day were worth submitting, he had to decide himself; but by watching Surya's judgements he acquired much wisdom, and soon had a great reputation for acumen and even-handed justice.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The actual courts of law were of course not in his hands, though even there his advice carried great weight; but many people in difficulty asked advice from the priests instead of applying for legal redress, and when the decision of the High Priest or his deputy was once given it was never questioned. This responsibility  in itself was a liberal education for Alcyone, and the constant close association with Surya was helpful to him. There was always the guidance of Mahaguru in the background, but this was given to Surya only, usually in dream or meditation, but some time by direct and audible voice. On one occasion Alcyone was privileged to receive a few words of kindly commendation in that way from Mahaguru, which greatly encouraged him in his arduous labours and gave him a new stimulus. He held this responsible office for nearly thirty years, until his death at the age of seventy-nine, and during all this time Surya seemed to grow but little older.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When Alcyone was about sixty years old he lost his mother, which was a great grief to him, and would indeed have been insupportable but for the consolation and help given to him by Surya. Shortly afterwards his wife Theseus followed his mother, and during the last seventeen years of his life his household was managed by his favourite granddaughter Mizar, who was deeply attached to him and understood him better than anyone else. At the death of Mars, Herakles succeeded to the chieftainship of the tribe, but the office soon became merely nominal, as the Aryans settled down as part of the nation among whom they lived, though the priestly caste never intermarried with it. Later, however, as Crux died without issue, Herakles was unanimously called upon by the people to ascend the vacant throne, and so an Aryan dynasty was firmly established in the south of India. All Brahmanas of the south, commonly called the dark Caucasians, are unquestionably descended from the tribe whose arrival we have described, though from long residence in tropical lands they  are a good deal darker than their ancestors.
</view>
</text>
</body>