<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 44</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 44-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This time Alcyone returned to his beloved motherland of India, and also to the male sex, having been five times feminine.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He was born in a town called Narsingarh, near the Vindhya Hills, the the year 3059 B.C. His name was Shivarshi, and he was born into an old and noble family, though much reduced in the world-poor but proud. The great traditions handed down from father to son were the memory of its ancient greatness, and imposed the necessity of maintaining the dignity and re-establishing the position. It still retained a considerable estate, but had no money to cultivate or stock it, and also money had been borrowed on it in some way.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone's father Taurus was a good man at heart, but stern and proud; the mother Virago was rather weak and complaining, though well-meaning. Their life was one of a certain amount of privation because everything had to be sacrificed to the family pride. The old profuse charities could not now be lavished, but some scanty show of them must be; appearances must somehow be kept up before the outer world, even though food ran short. They lived in a rambling old castle, only a small part of which was really habitable, most of it being desperately in need of repairs. Alcyone was the second son, the eldest being Pollux; they were remarkably alike to face, though absolutely different in disposition. As they grew up Alcyone was deeply religious, reliable and painstaking, while Pollux was careless and dissolute, and a source of much trouble to his family.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Nevertheless it was to the eldest son that the father booked to mend the fortunes of his house, not by his own exertions, but by a fortunate chance. Pollux happened to have been born at a certain conjunction of the planets, on the name-day of the local ruler; and consequently by the advice of his astrologers that ruler had bequeathed great wealth to him, though he had seen him only as a baby, and knew little of his later life. In all ways, therefore, Alcyone had to  be sacrificed to Pollux; for example, when they grew up Alcyone fell deeply in love and wished to marry, but could not do so because Pollux, being the eldest, must marry, in order to carry on the family, and a brave show must be made at his wedding, and there was not money enough for two.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So Pollux married Adrona, but did not long remain faithful to her; he got himself entangled in some disreputable transactions and finally disappeared with another woman (Melpo). The father felt that all this bad behaviour of Pollux, and also his disappearance, must at any cost be kept from the knowledge of the Raja, lest he should withdraw his legacy; so he ordered Alcyone to personate Pollux (which he could easily do, as there was a close resemblance between them), and, though this was most distasteful to him, he had to obey.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So it was given out that it was Alcyone who had gone on a journey, and that, because of that, Pollux had to change his mode of life and stay more at home, Alcyone entirely avoided the friends and the haunts of Pollux, and in this way escaped detection. He held the position of Pollux for some years, and gradually built up for him a reputation vastly better than his own. He entirely declined however to take his brother's wife, as the father wished him to do. When Pollux returned penniless, and without the unfortunate woman, they forgave him and he resumed his place in the family Alcyone, of course, being supposed to have returned from his journey; but Pollux did not live up to the reputation which Alcyone had made for him, and so caused much trouble.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Finally he committed a serious crime, and, for the sake of the family honour and the legacy Alcyone sacrificed himself and took the blame for this action upon himself. The result was that he was condemned and cast into prison. The family recognised his heroism on its behalf, and did all that it could for him; but even with their best endeavours he had a miserable time, for the prison was horrible in many ways; he had to herd indiscriminately with real criminals, and the prisoners were habitually left without proper or sufficient food. It was the custom that they should stand in turn at a grating and beg from the passers-by, and in that way they were usually able to eke out a precarious existence. His father contrived to send some little food daily to Alcyone, even though the store at home was frequently insufficient; but even this miserable dole Alcyone could not take wholly for himself, when he saw the still greater suffering of some of the weaker prisoners.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This horrible imprisonment dragged on for some time; and in the meantime Pollux pursued his evil ways and got himself into still further difficulties; at last Aqua, a sympathetic younger sister to whom Alcyone had been especially kind, could not bear this condition of frightful injustice any longer, so she escaped from the house without her father's leave, went before the Raja, and told him the whole truth. This involved a terrible exposure, and brought great public disgrace on the family; the old father committed suicide out of shame; the eldest son Pollux was banished; and the Raja removed Alcyone from prison and appointed him to an office in his service.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The father being dead and the elder brother away, Alcyone was now the head of the family, and inherited all its traditions and obligations, and also its debts and difficulties. The salary of his office was sufficient to prevent starvation and to keep the house going in a modestly comfortable way, but it was not at all enough to restore the long-lost glories of the family. Alcyone therefore pondered often over the state of affairs, and wondered what he could do to carry out the life-long wish of his father, which he regarded as a sacred charge laid upon him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After a time he decided to go and consult Neptune, the chief Brahman of a neighbouring temple, who had a great reputation for sanctity and wisdom. The Brahman heard his tale sympathetically, and after much consideration advised him to undertake a short pilgrimage to a certain well-known shrine, and there to offer up a series of special prayers and meditations to the deity. This advice he accepted; he performed the necessary ceremonies, and prayed earnestly to the deity to help him in this matter, not for the sake of the money, but because of his father's command.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
During these days of special prayer he had to live and sleep in the temple, as near as might be to the image of the deity. On the last night of his stay he had an exceedingly vivid dream, which told him to go home to his castle, to go down into a certain unused dungeon among its foundations, and there to take up the stones of the floor and to dig to a certain depth. He returned home, but doubted whether he should pay attention to the dream; eventually, however, he thought that because of its peculiar vividness it might have been sent to him by the deity in answer to his prayer, and that at any rate it would cost but little trouble to make the search as suggested.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He followed carefully the instructions given to him, and discovered under the dungeon floor a magnificent treasure of golden vessels and precious stones, which had presumably been buried by some ancestor when some danger impended, as so often happened in Indian history. This splendid trove put matters right for him, for its value was more than sufficient to enable him to free his land from its encumbrances, and to sow it and stock it; indeed it left him much over, wherewith to build a temple and some rest-house and to organise many processions in gratitude to the deity who had sent him the dream.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The rest of his life passed in his native city, but never left it for any length of time except for certain pilgrimages which he undertook. He was always a deeply religious man, of devotional type, kind and gentle with his family and dependants, and charitable towards the poor. As soon as he was relieved by the finding of the treasure of the immediate pressure of financial worries, he turned his attention to study and devoted to it a definite portion of time each day, and presently acquired a great reputation as a learned and holy man. When his eldest son grew up to years of discretion and had proved  himself a wise and capable manager, Alcyone abdicated his position and retired to spend the remainder of his days in study, religious conversation and exercises, not in the jungle, but in a sort of small wooden house or shed in a garden upon his own estate. Here he died peacefully at an advanced age.
</view>
</text>
</body>