<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">APPENDIX</view>
</title>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
THE MOON CHAIN
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
THE names of individuals who have been traced through the ages-- adopted from “Rents in the Veil of Time,” with many subsequent additions-- have been as far as possible relegated to Appendices. In a book intended for the general public, too many of these names would be wearisome. On the other hand, they are of great interest to Fellows of the Theosophical Society, many of whom may thus trace some of their former incarnations. We have retained these names in the text where the exigencies of the story required it, and have added large numbers, family relationships, etc., in the form of Appendices.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
P. 35. Individualised on Globe D, in the fourth Round of the Moon Chain: MARS and MERCURY; probably many others who have become Masters in the Earth Chain. Yet loftier Beings individualised in earlier Chains. Thus, the MAHAGURU and SURYA dropped out of globe D of the seventh Round of the second Chain at its Day of Judgment, and came to globe D of the third, or Moon Chain, in the fourth Round-- as primitive men, with second Chain animals ready for individualisation. JUPITER was probably with these, and VAIVASVATA MANU-- Manu of the fifth Race on the fourth Round of the Earth Chain.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
P. 38. Individualised on globe D, in the fifth Round: Herakles, Sirius, Alcyone, Mizar, and probably all those later called Servers, who worked together through the ages-- see the next paragraph. Many others, who have made great progress along other lines, probably individualised during this Round. Also individualised on globe D, in the fifth Round: Scorpio, and many of that ilk; but they dropped out again at the Day of Judgment in the sixth Round. These were first noticed in the sixth Round, evidently at the same stage as Herakles, Sirius, Alcyone and Mizar; and therefore must have individualized in the fifth Round.
</view>
</text>


<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
IN THE CITY OF THE GOLDEN GATE
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
ABOUT 220,000 B.C.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
IN these lists all the people recognised up to the time of writing will be named, whether given in the text or not, so as to enable the reader to draw, without much trouble, a genealogical chart, if he likes to do so.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
MARS was Emperor, the Crown Prince Vajra, the Hierophant of the State, MERCURY, Ulysses was Captain of the Palace Guard. In the Imperial Guard were recognised: Herakles, Pindar, Beatrix, Gemini, Capella; Lutetia, Bellona, Apis, Arcor, Capricorn, Theodoros, Scotus, Sappho. Herakles had as servants three Tlavatli youths-- Alcmene, Hygeia and Bootes-- who had been captured in battle by his father, and given to him.
</view>
</text>


<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
ANCIENT PERU
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
WHEN the articles on ancient Peru appeared in the Theosophical Review, Mr. Leadbeater wrote the following introduction to them, and it is useful to reprint it here. It was written in 1899.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When, in writing on the subject of clairvoyance, I referred to the magnificent possibilities which the examination of the records of the past opened up before the student of history, several readers suggested to me that deep interest would be felt by our Theosophical public in any fragments of the results of such researches which could be placed before them. That is no doubt true, but it is not so easy as might be supposed to carry out the suggestion. It has to be remembered that investigations are not undertaken for the pleasure of the thing, nor for the gratification of mere curiosity, but only when they happen to be necessary for the due performance of some piece of work, or for the elucidation of some obscure point in our study. Most of the scenes from the past history of the world which have so interested and delighted our enquirers have come before us in the course of the examination of one or other of the lines of successive lives which have been followed far back into earlier ages, in the endeavour to gather information as to the working of the great laws of karma and reincarnation; so that what we know of remote antiquity is rather in the nature of a series of glimpses than in any way a sustained view-- rather a gallery of pictures than a history.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Nevertheless, even in this comparatively casual and desultory manner, much of exceeding interest has been unveiled before our eyes-- much not only with regard to the splendid civilisations of Egypt, of India and of Babylonia, as well as to the far more modern States of Persia, Greece, and Rome, but to others on a scale vaster and grander far even than these-- to which, indeed, these are but as buds of yesterday; mighty Empires whose beginnings reach back into primeval dawnings, even though some fragments of their traces yet remain on earth for those who have eyes to see.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Greatest perhaps of all these was the magnificent and world-embracing dominion of the Divine Rulers of the city of the Golden Gate in old Atlantis; for with the exception of the primary Aryan civilisation round the shores of the Central Asian sea, almost all Empires that men have called great since then have been but feeble and partial copies of its marvellous organisation; while before it there existed nothing at all comparable to it, the only attempts at government on a really large scale having been those of the egg-headed sub-race of the Lemurians, and of the myriad hosts of the Tlavatli mound-builders in the far west of early Atlantis.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Some outline of the polity which for so many thousands of years centred round the glorious City of the Golden Gate has already been given in one of the Transactions of the London Lodge; what I wish to do now is to offer a slight sketch of one of its later copies-- one which, though on but a small scale as compared to its mighty parent, yet preserved to within almost what we are in the habit of calling historical periods much of the splendid public spirit and paramount sense of duty which were the very life of that grand old scheme.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The part of the world, then, to which we must for this purpose direct our attention is the ancient kingdom of Peru-- a kingdom, however, embracing enormously more of the South American continent than the Republic to which we now give that name, or even the tract of country which the Spaniards found in possession of the Incas in the sixteenth century. It is true that the system of government in this later kingdom, which excited the admiration of Pizarro, aimed at reproducing the conditions of the earlier and grander civilisation of which I have now to speak; yet, wonderful as even that pale copy was acknowledged to be, we must remember that was but a copy, organised thousands of years later by a far inferior race, in the attempt to revivify traditions, some of the best points of which had been forgotten.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The first introduction of our investigators to this most interesting epoch took place, as has already been hinted, in the course of an endeavour to follow back a long line of incarnations. It was found that after two nobly-borne lives of great toil and stress (themselves the consequence, apparently, of a serious failure in the one preceding them), the subject (Erato) whose history was being followed was born under favourable circumstances in this great Peruvian Empire and there lived a life which, though certainly as full of hard work as either of its predecessors, yet differed from them in being honoured, happy and successful far beyond the common lot.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Naturally the sight of a State in which most of the social problems seemed to have been solved-- in which there was no poverty, no discontent, and practically no crime-- attracted our attention immediately, though we could not at the time stay to examine it more closely; but when afterwards it was found that several other lines of lives in which we were interested had also passed through that country at the same period, and we thus began to learn more and more of its manners and customs, we gradually realised that we had come upon a veritable physical Utopia-- a time and place where at any rate the physical life of man was better organised, happier, and more useful than it has perhaps ever been elsewhere.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
No doubt there will be many who will ask themselves: “How are we to know that this account differs from those of other Utopias-- how can we feel certain that the investigators were not deceiving themselves with beautiful dreams, and reading theoretical ideas of their own into the visions which they persuaded themselves that they saw-- how, in fact, can we assure ourselves that this is more than a mere fairy-story?”
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The only answer that can be given to such enquiries is that for them there is no assurance. The investigators themselves are certain-- certain by long accumulation of manifold proofs, small often in themselves, perhaps yet irresistible in combination-- certain also in their knowledge, gradually acquired by many patient experiments, of the difference between observation and imagination. They know well how often they have met with the absolutely unexpected and unimaginable, and how frequently and how entirely their cherished preconceptions have been overset. Outside the ranks of the actual investigators there are a few others who have attained practically equal certainty, either by their own intuitions, or by a personal knowledge of those who do the work; to the rest of the world the results of all enquiry into a past so remote must necessarily remain hypothetical. They may regard this account of the ancient Peruvian civilisation as a mere fairy-tale, in fact; yet even so I think I may hope for their admission that it is a beautiful fairy-tale.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
I imagine that except by these methods of clairvoyance it would be impossible now to recover any traces of the civilisation which we are about to examine. I have little doubt that traces still exist, but it would probably require extensive and elaborate excavations to enable us to acquire sufficient knowledge to separate them with any certainty from those of other and later races. It may be that, in the future, antiquarians and archaeologists will turn their attention more than they have hitherto done to these wonderful countries of South America, and then, perhaps, they may be able to sort out the various footprints of the different races which one after another occupied and governed them; but at present all that we know (outside of clairvoyance) about old Peru is the little that was told to us by the Spanish conquerors; and the civilisation at which they marvelled so greatly was but a faint and far distant reflection of the older and grander reality.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The very race itself had changed; for though those whom the Spaniards found in possession were still some offshoot of that splendid third sub-race of the Atlanteans, which seems to have been endued with so much more enduring power and vitality than any of those which followed it, it is yet evident that this offshoot was in many ways in the last stage of decrepitude, in many ways more barbarous, more degraded, less refined, than the much older branch of which we have to speak.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This little leaf out of the world' s true history-- this glimpse at just one picture in nature' s vast galleries-- reveals to us what might well seem an ideal State compared to anything which exists at the present day; and part of its interest to us consists in the fact that all the results at which our modern social reformers are aiming were already fully achieved there, but achieved by methods diametrically opposite to most that are being suggested now. The people were peaceful and prosperous; no such thing as poverty was known, and there was practically no crime; no single person had cause for discontent, for everyone had an opening for his genius (if he had any) and he chose for himself his profession or line of activity, whatever it might be. In no case was work too hard or too heavy placed upon any man; everyone had plenty of spare time to give to any desired accomplishment or occupation; education was full, free, and efficient, and the sick and aged were perfectly and even luxuriously cared for. And yet the whole of this wonderfully elaborate system for the promotion of physical well-being was carried out, and so far as we can see could only have been carried out, under an autocracy which was one of the most absolute that the world has ever known.
</view>
</text>




<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
PERU
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
ABOUT 12,000 B.C.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
THIS is one of the largest of the gatherings of those who are now working in the Theosophical Society. MARS was Emperor at the time, and the lists begin with his father and mother. There were three families of the time among which they were distributed, those descended from JUPITER, SATURN, and Psyche.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
JUPITER married VULCAN and had two sons-- MARS and URANUS. The family of MARS by his marriage with BRIHASPATI consisted of two sons, Siwa and Pindar, who respectively married Proteus and Tolosa. Siwa and Proteus also had two sons, Corona and Orpheus, Corona marrying Pallas, and having as sons, Ulysses and OSIRIS, and as daughter, Theodoros-- Ulysses marrying Cassiopeia, VIRAJ being their son; OSIRIS marrying ATHENA, and Theodoros marrying Deneb; Orpheus marrying Hestia, by whom he had two sons-- Thor and Rex-- who respectively married Iphigenia and Ajax. Pindar and Tolosa had three daughters, Herakles, Adrona and Cetus, and one son-- Olympia. Herakles married Castor; Adrona, Berenice; Cetus, Procyon; and Olympia, Diana.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
URANUS married Hesperia, and had three sons-- Sirius, Centaurus and Alcyone-- and two daughters-- Aquarius and Sagittarius. The wife of Sirius was Spica, and Pollux, Vega and Castor were their sons, and Alcestis and Minerva their daughters. Fides was an adopted son and married Glaucus. Pollux married Melpomene and had three sons-- Cyrene, Apis, Flora-- and two daughters-- Eros and Chamaeleon. Apis married Bootes, Eros, Pisces, and Chamaeleon, Gemini. Vega married Pomona and they had one son, Ursa, who espoused Lacerta, and two daughters-- Circe and Ajax, the latter marrying Rex. Ursa' s family included Cancer (daughter), Alastor (son), Phocea (daughter), and Thetis (son). Of these, Alastor married Clio and had one daughter, Trapezium, and a son, Markab. Castor married Herakles, and they had as issue: Vajra and Aurora (sons), the latter marrying Wenceslas, and daughters Lacerta, Alcmene, and Sappho, who respectively married Ursa, Hygeia and Dorado. Alcestis married Nicosia and they had a son-- Formator. Minerva married Beatus. The next son of URANUS was Centaurus, who married Gimel, their son being Beatus. Alcyone had Mizar as his wife, and their children were-- Perseus, Leo, Capella, Regulus and Irene (sons), and Ausonia (daughter). Perseus married Alexandros. Leo married Concordia, and they had as children-- Deneb, whose wife was Theodoros, Egeria, whose husband was Telemachus, Calliope, whose wife was Parthenope, Iphigenia, whose husband was Thor, and Daleth, whose husband was Polaris. Capella married Soma and they had two sons-- Telemachus and Aquila-- and one daughter-- Parthenope, who married Calliope. Telemachus married Egeria and they had a son, Beth. Ausonia married Rama. Regulus married Mathematicus, and they had a daughter, Trefoil, who married Aquila. Irene married Flos. Of the daughters of URANUS, Aquarius married Virgo, and Sagittarius, Apollo.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The second great family of this period was that of SATURN, who had VENUS as his wife. Their children were six-- Hesperia (daughter) who married URANUS: MERCURY (son) who married Lyra (by whom he had two sons, SURYA and Apollo, and one daughter, Andromeda, who married Argus); Calypso (son) who married Avelledo, by whom he had one son, Rhea (who married Zama and had two sons, Sirona and Lachesis) and one daughter, Amalthea; Crux (daughter) married NEPTUNE, by whom there were five children-- Melete, son, (married Erato, sons Hebe, Stella), Tolosa, daughter (married Pindar), Virgo, son, (married Aquarius-- son, Euphrosyne, who married Canopus), Alba, daughter, (married Altair), Leopardus, son, (married Auriga); Selene (son) who married Beatrix, and by whom there were six children, Erato, daughter, who married Melete, Aldebaran, son, who married Orion (children: Theseus, wife Dactyl; Arcor, husband Capricorn-- children, Hygeia, wife Alcmene; Bootes, husband Apis; Gemini, wife Chamaeleon; Polaris, wife Daleth-- Fomalhaut, son; Arcturus, husband Nitocris; and Canopus, husband Euphrosyne); Spica, daughter, who married Sirius, Albireo, son, who married Hector, Leto, son, who married Fons (children; Norma, wife Aulus, Scotus, wife Elsa, Sextans, husband Pegasus) and Elektra; Vesta (son) who married Mira, by whom there was one son, Bellatrix (married Tiphys, sons Juno, who weds Minorca, and Proserpina, who espouses Colossus), and four daughters; Orion, who married Aldebaran, Mizar, who married Alcyone, Achilles, who married Demeter, (children: Elsa, husband Scotus; Aletheia, wife Ophiuchus, to whom are born two sons, Dorado and Fortuna-- who respectively marry Sappho and Eudoxia; Aries and Taurus, sons, and Procyon, wife Cetus) and Philae, who married Cygnus.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The third family was that of Psyche, whose wife was Libra. To them were born: Rigel-- daughter, who married Betelgueuse, and by whom there were six children: Altair, wife Alba (son Ara, marries Pepin); Hector, husband Albireo (sons, Pegasus, wife Sextans, Berenice, wife Adrona); Auriga, husband Leopardus (daughter Flos, married Irene; Viola, wife, Elektra (daughter, Aulus, married Norma, son, Nitocris, married Arcturus); Cygnus, wife Philae (daughter, Minorca, married Juno); and Demeter, whose wife was Achilles-- Mira, whose husband was Vesta; and Algol, whose wife was Iris, and by whom there were five children: Helios, wife Lomia (daughter, Mathematicus, married Regulus); Draco, wife Phoenix (son Atalanta, married Herminius); Argus, wife Andromeda (daughters, Pepin, married Ara, and Dactyl, married Theseus); Fons, daughter, and Xanthos, son. Boreas is also noticed as one of the characters.
</view>
</text>




<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
ON THE SHORE OF THE GOBI SEA
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
ABOUT 72,000 B.C.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
THE MANU had MARS, Vajra, Ulysses, VIRAJ and Apollo as grandsons; MARS married MERCURY, and they had as sons: Sirius, Achilles, Alcyone, Orion and one daughter, Mizar. Sirius married Vega, and had as children: Mira, Rigel, Ajax, Bellatrix and Proserpina, all massacred. Achilles married Albireo, and had a daughter, Hector. Alcyone married Leo, and had as sons: URANUS and NEPTUNE, and as daughters SURYA and BRIHASPATI; all these were saved from the massacre, and, as a woman, SURYA married SATURN, saved at the same time, and VAIVASVATA MANU , VIRAJ and MARS were their children; in the next generation, Herakles was the son of MARS. Returning to the children of MARS and MERCURY, Mizar married Herakles, the son of VIRAJ, and they had three sons: Capricorn, Arcor, Fides, and two daughters, Psyche and Pindar. Corona married Deneb, and had two sons, one of whom was Dorado. Adrona had Pollux as son. Cetus married Clio. Others seen were Orpheus, VULCAN and VENUS, who were both saved, and JUPITER, the head of the community. Vega and Leo were sisters, as were Albireo and Helios, the latter a very pretty and coquettish young lady. Scorpio appeared among the Turanian assailants.
</view>
</text>




<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
IN SHAMBALLA
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
ABOUT 60,000 B.C.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
MARS, a Toltec Prince from Poseidonis, married JUPITER , the daughter of the MANU. They had VIRAJ as son, who married SATURN and of them VAIVASVATA MANU was born.
</view>
</text>




<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
IN THE CITY OF THE BRIDGE, AND THE VALLEY OF THE SECOND SUB-RACE
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
ABOUT 40,000 B.C.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Two families chiefly provided the emigrants, Corona and Theodoros, who sent two sons, Herakles and Pindar, and Demeter and Fomalhaut sent their sons, Vega and Aurora, and their daughters, Sirius and Dorado; their remaining son Mira and daughter Draco remained with them in the City. In the City were also Castor and Rhea. Lachesis, who married Amalthea, had Velleda as son; and Calypso who ran away with Amalthea; Crux, a foreigner, with Phocea, came as visitors.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Herakles married Sirius, and they had as children: Alcyone, Mizar, Orion, Achilles, URANUS, Aldebaran, Siwa, Selene, NEPTUNE, Capricorn, and some others unrecognised. Alcyone married Perseus, and VULCAN, Bellatrix, Rigel, Algol, and Arcturus were their children. Mizar married Deneb, and their children were Wenceslas, Ophiuchus, and Cygnus, with many unrecognised. Orion married Eros, and had Sagittarius, Theseus and Mu in his family. Achilles married Leo, and had as children Ulysses, Vesta, Psyche, and Cassiopeia. URANUS married Andromeda, and MARS and VENUS were born to them. Aldebaran married Pegasus, and Capella and Juno were among their children. Selene married Albireo, and MERCURY appeared in their family; she married MARS, and they had VAIVASVATA MANU as son. Capricorn married her first cousin, Polaris, and their children were Vajra, Adrona, Pollux, and Diana.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Pindar married Beatrix, and they had Gemini, Arcor, and Polaris as children. Gemini married a foreigner, Apis, and Spica and Fides were born to them as twins.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The children of Sirius are given above; his brother Vega married Helios, and they had children Leo, Proserpina, Canopus, Aquarius, and Ajax. Aurora married Hector, and one of their children was Albireo. Dorado had a daughter Aletheia, who married Argus.
</view>
</text>




<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
IN THE CITY OF THE BRIDGE AND THE VALLEY OF THE THIRD SUB-RACE
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
ABOUT 32,000 B.C.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
THE MANU was married to MERCURY, and had Sirius as a younger son. Sirius married Mizar, and had as children: Alcyone, Orion, VENUS , Ulysses, Albireo and SATURN , and went to the valley. Alcyone married Achilles, who was the daughter of Vesta and Aldebaran, and had Libra as a brother. Orion married Herakles, an Akkadian, and they had six sons: the eldest, Capella, was a fine horseman; Fides, a good runner, slim and lightly built; Dorado, a fair rider and first-rate at games, fond of a game like quoits, throwing rings on upright posts; Elektra, Canopus and Arcor, the third, fifth and sixth. As daughters there were: Gemini, who, by a strange repetition of the story of eight thousand years before, married Apis, an Arabian, who had travelled thus far from his home; Fortuna, Draco, Hygeia, a very fat girl, to whom the baby Capricorn clung with much energy, and a passionate child, Polaris, who was seen on her back, screaming vigorously, because an animal had carried off her toy. Albireo married Hector, and Pegasus, Leo and Berenice were found in her family. Pallas and Helios were in the valley, as said in the text.
</view>
</text>




<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
IN THE EMIGRATION
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
ABOUT 30,000 B.C.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
VAIVASVATA MANU as leader. His Captains: MARS (wife, NEPTUNE), Corona (wife, OSIRIS) his brother, VULCAN (wife, VENUS), Theodoros, (wife, Aldebaran), VAJRA. In body-guard: Ulysses, Herakles, Sirius, Arcor, Leo, Alcyone, Polaris. MERCURY married Rama, Vajra married URANUS. Ulysses married Spica. Herakles, son of Mars, married Psyche, and had Capella, Dolphin, Lutetia and Canopus, as sons and a daughter, Daphne. Sirius married Achilles, and, Aurora, Dorado. Capella married Bellatrix. Leo married Leto. Alcyone married Fides, and had as children Cygnus, Mira, Perseus, Proserpina, Demeter; Polaris married Minerva. Vega married Helios, Castor married Aries, and had a son Lachesis who married Rhea. Calypso married Amalthea; Tolosa was among their children. Velleda had among his children Cyrene and Sirona. Markab was a soldier, and married Clio. Vesta, Mizar, Albireo, Orion, Ajax, Hector, Crux and Selene were also seen. Trapezium was an insurgent chief.
</view>
</text>


<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
THE FIRST ARYAN IMMIGRATION INTO INDIA
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">18,875 B.C.</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
MARS married MERCURY, and had sons URANUS, Herakles, and Alcyone, daughters, BRIHASPATI and Demeter; BRIHASPATI married first VULCAN and after his death Corona the son of VIRAJ, and had one son, Trefoil, who married Arcturus, and five daughters: Fides, who married Betelgueuse; Thor, who married Iphigenia; Rama, who married Perseus; Daedalus, who married Elsa; and Rector who married Fomalhaut. SATURN was king in South India, and had Crux as son; SURYA was High Priest, and OSIRIS, Deputy High Priest.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Herakles married Capella, and had as sons, Cassiopeia, Altair and Leto, as daughters, Argus and Centaurus. Alcyone married Theseus, and had four sons: Andromeda, Betelgueuse, Fomalhaut and Perseus, and three daughters, Draco, NEPTUNE , and Arcturus. Demeter married Wenceslas, and had as sons Elsa, Iphigenia and Diana, who married respectively, Daedalus, Thor, and Draco. Cassiopeia married Capricorn, and had Cetus, Spica and Adrona as sons, Sirona as daughter; Spica married Kudos, Altair married Polaris, and had Tolosa as son Leto married Gemini. Argus married Andromeda and had among her sons Arcor, who married Mizar, the daughter of NEPTUNE and Hector; the latter had also Siwa and Orpheus as sons. Diomede married Orpheus. Regulus and Irene were daughters of Arcor and Mizar. Argus married a second husband, Mathematicus, and had three daughters, Diomede, Judex who married Beatus, and Kudos. Centaurus married Concordia. Of Alcyone' s sons: Andromeda married Argus as said, and died early; Betelgueuse married Fides, and had as sons, Flos, and Beatus who married Judex, Fomalhaut married Rector, Perseus married Rama, Draco, Diana, NEPTUNE , Hector, and Arcturus, Trefoil. Alcyone' s wife, Theseus, was the daughter of Glaucus and Telemachus, and the latter had a sister, Soma. Alastor was in Central Asia. Taurus, a Mongol, had Procyon as wife, and Cygnus as daughter, who married Aries.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
AN ARYAN IMMIGRATION INTO INDIA
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
17,455 B.C.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
JUPITER married SATURN and had MARS as his son and MERCURY as his sister. MARS married NEPTUNE, and had sons, Herakles, Siwa and Mizar, daughters OSIRIS, Pindar and Andromeda. Herakles married Cetus, and had, as sons, Gemini and Arcor; as daughters, Polaris who married Diana, Capricorn who married Glaucus, and Adrona. Siwa married Proserpina, Mizar married Rama, and had as sons: Diana and Daedalus; as daughters; Diomede and Kudos, OSIRIS married Perseus.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
VULCAN married Corona, and their three daughters, Rama, Rector, and Thor, married respectively Mizar, Trefoil and Leto. Psyche, a friend of Mars, married Arcturus, and had as sons, Alcyone, Albireo, Leto and Ajax; as daughters, Beatrix, Procyon and Cygnus. Alcyone married Rigel and had as sons: Cassiopeia who married Diomede; Crux who married Kudos, and Wenceslas who married Regulus. They had also three daughters: Taurus who married Concordia, Irene who married Flos, and Theseus who married Daedalus. Albireo married Hector, and had a daughter Beatus who married Iphigenia. Leto married Thor, and had a son, Flos. Ajax married Elsa, Beatrix, Mathematicus, and Cygnus, Fomalhaut. Capella, another friend of MARS, married Judex, and had as sons Perseus, who married OSIRIS, and Fomalhaut, who married Cygnus. The daughters were Hector, Demeter, who married Aries, and Elsa, who married Ajax. Vajra married Orpheus, and had Draco and Altair as sons, BRIHASPATI, URANUS and Proserpina as daughters. Draco married Argus, and had as son Concordia, who married Taurus. Altair married Centaurus, and their daughter, Regulus, married Wenceslas. Betelgueuse married Canopus, and had Spica and Olympia as sons, Rigel as daughter. Spica married Telemachus, and had two sons, Glaucus and Iphigenia, whose marriages are mentioned above. Castor married Pollux, and had as sons Aries and Alastor, and three daughters, Minerva, Sirona and Pomona.
</view>
</text>


<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
AN ARYAN IMMIGRATION INTO INDIA
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
15,950 B.C.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
SURYA was father of MARS and MERCURY. MARS married BRIHASPATI , and had sons, JUPITER , Siwa and VIRAJ; daughters, OSIRIS, URANUS, and Ulysses. JUPITER married Herakles, and they had as sons: Beatrix who married Pindar, Aletheia who married Taurus, and Betelgueuse; and as daughters: Canopus who married Fomalhaut, Pollux who married Melpomene, and Hector who married NEPTUNE . URANUS married Leo, and Ulysses, Vajra; the latter had as sons: Clio, who married Concordia, Melpomene, and Alastor, who married Gemini; as daughters: Irene, who married Adrona, Sirona, who married Spica, and Beatus, who married Soma.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
MERCURY married SATURN, and their sons were: Selene, Leo, Vajra and Castor, and their daughters, Herakles, Alcyone and Mizar. Selene married Aurora, and had as sons: Wenceslas who married Crux, Theseus who married Lignus, and Polaris who married Proserpina; as daughters: Taurus who married Aletheia, Arcturus who married Perseus, and Argus who married Draco. Leo married URANUS, and had as sons: Leto, who married Demeter, Draco, and Fomalhaut-- both married as above-- and as daughters: Centaurus who married Altair, Proserpina, and Concordia who married Clio, Castor married Iphigenia. Alcyone married Albireo, and had four sons: NEPTUNE who married Hector, Psyche, married Clarion, Perseus married Arcturus, and Ajax, Capella; the daughters were Rigel who married Centurion, Demeter who married Leto, and Algol who married Priam. Mizar married Glaucus, and had two sons, Soma and Flos. The daughters, Diomede and Telemachus, married respectively Trefoil and Betelgueuse; VULCAN married Cetus and had one son, Procyon, and three daughters, Olympia, Minerva and Pomona. Arcor married Capricorn and had four sons: Altair, Adrona, Spica, Trefoil, and four daughters: Pindar, Capella, Crux, and Gemini. Corona married Orpheus, and had three sons: Rama who married VENUS, Cassiopeia who married Rector, and Aries; of the daughters, Andromeda married Daedalus, Elsa, Mathematicus, and Pallas, Diana. Thor married Kudos; his sons were Mathematicus, Diana and Daedalus-- who married three sisters as above-- and Judex; the daughter was Rector.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At the one pole of human evolution there stood at the date of this immigration the four KUMARAS, the MANU and the MAHAGURU; far down towards the other, Scorpio, the high priest Ya-uli.
</view>
</text>



<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
IN NORTHERN INDIA
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
12,800 B.C.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
MARS and MERCURY were brothers. MARS married SATURN, and had two sons, Vajra and VIRAJ, and two daughters, VULCAN and Herakles. Vajra married Proserpina, and had three sons, Ulysses, Fides and Selene, and three daughters, Beatrix, Hector and Hestia. VIRAJ married OSIRIS, VULCAN married URANUS, and Herakles, Polaris. Ulysses married Philae, and had three sons: Cygnus who married Diana, Calliope who married Parthenope, and Pisces, Ajax; the daughters were Bellatrix who married Thor, Aquarius who married Clarion, and Pepin who married Lignus. Returning to the sons of Vajra we have: Fides who married Iphigenia, and had three sons: Aquila who married Sappho, Kudos, Concordia, and Beatus, Gimel. They had four daughters: Herminius married to Nicosia, Sextans to Virgo, Sagittarius to Clio, Parthenope to Calliope. Selene married Achilles and had two sons: Aldebaran marrying Elektra, and Helios marrying Lomia. There were five daughters: Vega marrying Leo, Rigel marrying Leto, Alcestis marrying Aurora, Colossus marrying Aries, and Eros marrying Juno. Of Vajra' s daughters, Beatrix married Albireo, and had two sons, Berenice who married Canopus, and Deneb. The daughters, Pindar and Lyra, married respectively Capella and Euphrosyne. Hector married Wenceslas, and had as sons: Leo, Leto, Norma marrying Melete, Nicosia marrying Herminius; the daughters were: Ajax married to Pisces, arid Crux married to Demeter. Hestia married Telemachus; their sons were: Thor, Diomede married to Chrysos; the daughters were Sappho, Trefoil, Minorca married to Lobelia, and Magnus to Calypso. Herakles, the daughter of MARS, married Polaris; their three sons, Viola, Dorado, and Olympia, married respectively Egeria, Dactyl and Mira; the daughter, Phoenix, married Atalanta. Voila and Egeria had four sons: Betelgueuse married to Iris, Nitocris married to Brunhilda, Taurus to Tiphys and Perseus to Fons; one daughter, Lomia, married Helios, the other, Libra, married Boreas. Dorado and Dactyl had sons: Centurion married to Theodoros, Pegasus to Priam, Scotus to Ausonia; daughters; Arcturus to Rector, and Brunhilda to Nitocris. Olympia married Mira, and had four sons: Clarion married Aquarius, Pollux, Cancer, Procyon, Avelledo, and Capricorn, Zama. The daughter, Arcor, married Centaurus. Phoenix, the daughter of Herakles, who married Atalanta, had three sons: Gemini, Lignus and Virgo, who married Adrona, Pepin and Sextans; there were three daughters: Daleth married Regulus, Dolphin married Formator, and Daphne, Apis. That finishes the descendants of MARS.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
MERCURY, his brother, married VENUS, and had NEPTUNE and URANUS as sons, OSIRIS, Proserpina and Tolosa as daughters, URANUS married VULCAN, and had two sons, Rama and Albireo, who married Glaucus and Beatrix; and two, daughters, BRIHASPATI and ATHENA , who married Apollo and JUPITER . Rama and Glaucus had Juno and Ara as sons, who married Eros and Ophiuchus; their daughters were four: Canopus married to Berenice, Diana to Cygnus, Chrysos to Diomede, and Judex to Irene. Albireo, marrying into the family of Vajra, had his children noted above. BRIHASPATI and Apollo had three sons: Capella, married to Pindar, Corona and Siwa; their daughter Proteus married Rex. OSIRIS married VIRAJ, and had as sons JUPITER and Apollo, the latter married BRIHASPATI. The daughter, Pallas, married Castor; they had five sons: Clio who married Sagittarius, Markab who married Cetus, Aries who married Colossus, Aglaia who married Pomona, and Sirona, who married Quies. That finishes the descendants of MERCURY.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Algol married Theseus, and had as son, Alcyone, who married Mizar, the daughter of Orpheus and sister of Psyche. Alcyone and Mizar had five sons: Fomalhaut married to Alexandros, Altair to Alba, Wenceslas to Hector, Telemachus to Hestia, Soma to Flos; their three daughters were: Iphigenia married to Fides, Glaucus to Rama, Philae to Ulysses. Fomalhaut and Alexandros had three sons: Rex, who married Proteus, Rector, who married Arcturus, and Leopardus; their three daughters were: Melete, who married Norma, Ausonia, who married Scotus and Concordia, who married Kudos.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Altair and Alba had three sons: Apis, who married Daphne, Centaurus, who married Arcor, and Flora; their daughters were Chamaeleon, Gimel who married Beatus, and Priam who married Pegasus. The children of Wenceslas are given among the descendants of MARS, as are those of Telemachus, Iphigenia, and Philae, while those of Glaucus are among the descendants of MERCURY. Soma and Flos had four sons: Alastor married to Melpomene, Boreas to Libra, Regulus to Daleth, Irene to Judex; the two daughters, Phocea and Daedalus, married Zephyr and Leopardus.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Aletheia took Spes to wife, and had two sons, Mona and Fortuna, and four daughters: Achilles, Aulus, Flos and Alba. Mona married Andromeda, and they had as sons: Lobelia who married Minorca, and Zephyr who married Phocea; their daughters were: Adrona who married Gemini, Cetus who married Markab, Melphomene who married Alastor, and Avelledo who married Procyon. Fortuna married Auriga, and their two sons, Hebe and Stella, married Trefoil and Chamaeleon; their daughters were: Iris, Tiphys, Eudoxia married to Flora, and Pomona to Aglaia. Aulus married Argus, and they had three sons: Calypso married to Magnus, Formator to Dolphin, and Minerva; the daughters, Elektra and Ophiuchus, married Aldebaran and Ara.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Psyche, the brother of Mizar, married Mathematicus, and they had three daughters: Egeria, Elsa, who married Beth, and Mira. Elsa and Beth had Aurora, Demeter and Euphrosyne as sons, who married Alcestis, Crux and Lyra; their daughters were: Theodoros married to Centurion, and Fons to Perseus.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Draco married Cassiopeia; their sons were: Argus, Beth, Atalanta and Castor, who married Pallas; his daughters were: Andromeda, Dactyl, Alexandros, Auriga. Vesta was also present.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">
THE ARYANISATION OF EGYPT
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
IN the body of this book we have three times referred (on pp. 250, 293, 341) to the expedition sent forth from South India by the MANU for the express purpose of Aryanising the noble families of Egypt. While the book is going through the press some further investigations have been made, which are found to throw additional light upon the subject, and to some extent to link it up with accepted Egyptian history. The earlier part of the book being already in type, all that we can do is to append here an article which has been written to explain the later discoveries.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Referring to our remark on p.341 that “Manetho' s history apparently deals with this Aryan dynasty,” we now see that he-- quite reasonably-- begins with the reunification of Egypt under the MANU, and that the date which our researches assign to that reunification (though not yet verified with perfect exactitude) comes within a few years of 5,510 B.C., which is the latest selection by the most distinguished living Egyptologist for the commencement of the First Dynasty. The new Egyptological theories now make the date of the Pharaoh Unas about two hundred years earlier than we do.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Others of our characters, besides the few whom MARS took with Him, are to be found in Egypt in 13,500 B.C.; a full list of all these will be given when the Lives of Alcyone appear in book form.
</view>
</text>



<text>
<view lang="en">
In the sixth life of Alcyone we followed the first of the great Aryan migrations from the shores of what was then the Central Asian sea to the south of the Indian Peninsula. The religious kingdom that the Aryans established there was, as centuries rolled on, used by the MANU as a subsidiary centre of radiation, as we have already said.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
From South India likewise was sent forth the expedition destined to bring about the Aryanisation of Egypt, which was carried out in much the same way and by many of the same egos who five thousand years previously had played their part in the migration from Central Asia to which reference has just been made.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
About the year 13,500 B.C., (shortly after the time of the thirteenth life of Alcyone and the twelfth life of Orion, when so many of our characters had taken birth in the Tlavatli race inhabiting the southern part of the Island of Poseidonis) VIRAJ was ruler of the great Indian Empire. He had married BRIHASPATI, and MARS was one of their sons. The MANU appeared astrally to the Emperor, and directed him to send MARS over the sea to Egypt by way of Ceylon. VIRAJ obeyed, and MARS departed upon his long journey, taking with him (according to the instructions received) a band of young men and women, of whom twelve are recognisable: Ajax, Betelgueuse, Deneb, Leo, Perseus and Theodorous among the men, and Arcturus, Canopus, Olympia, VULCAN, Pallas and OSIRIS among the ladies.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
On their arrival in Egypt, then under Toltec rule, they were met by JUPITER, the Pharaoh of the time. He had one child only-- his daughter SATURN-- his wife having died in child-birth. The High-Priest SURYA had been directed in a vision by the MAHAGURU to receive the strangers with honour, and to advise JUPITER to give his daughter to MARS in marriage, which he did; and in a comparatively short time marriages were arranged among the existing nobility for all the new-comers.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Small as was this importation of Aryan blood, in a few generations it had tinged the whole of the Egyptian nobility, for since the Pharaoh had set his seal of august approval upon these mixed marriages, all the patrician families competed eagerly for the honour of an alliance with the sons or daughters of the new-comers. The mingling of the two races produced a new and distinctive type, which had the high Aryan features, but the Toltec colouring-- the type which we know so well from the Egyptian monuments. So powerful is the Aryan blood that it still shows its unmistakable traces even after centuries of dilution; and from this time onward an incarnation among the principal classes of Egypt counted as a birth in the first sub-race of the fifth root-race.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Many changes took place as the centuries rolled by, and the impetus given by the Aryan rejuvenation gradually died out. The country never reached so low a level as the parallel civilisation of Poseidonis, chiefly because of the retention of Aryan tradition by a certain clan whose members claimed exclusively for themselves direct descent from the royal line of MARS and SATURN. For more than a thousand years after the Aryanisation this clan ruled the country, the Pharaoh being always its head; but there came a time when for political reasons the reigning monarch espoused a foreign princess, who by degrees acquired over him so great an influence that she was able to wean him from the traditions of his forefathers, and to establish new forms of worship to which the clan as a whole would not subscribe. The country, weary of Aryan strictness, followed its monarch into license and luxury; the clan drew its ranks together in stern disapproval, and thence-forward its members held themselves markedly aloof-- not declining offices in the army or in the service of the State, but marrying only among themselves, and making a great point of maintaining old customs and what they called the purity of the religion as well as of the race.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After nearly four thousand years had passed, we find a condition of affairs in which the Egyptian Empire, its religion and even its language were alike degenerate and decaying. Only in the ranks of the conservative clan can we find some pale reflection of the Egypt of earlier days. About this time, among the priests of the clan arose some who were prophets, who re-echoed in Egypt the message that was being given in Poseidonis-- a warning that, because of the wickedness of these mighty and long-established civilisations, they were doomed to destruction, and that it behoved the few righteous to flee promptly from the wrath to come. Just as a considerable proportion of the white race of mountaineers left Poseidonis, so the members of the clan in a body shook off the dust of Egypt from their feet, took ship across the Red Sea and found a refuge among the mountains of Arabia.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
As we know, in due time the prophecy was fulfilled, and in the year 9,564 B.C., the island of Poseidonis sank beneath the Atlantic. The effect of the cataclysm on the rest of the world was of the most serious character, and for the land of Egypt it was specially ruinous. Up to this point Egypt had had an extensive western seaboard, and although the Sahara Sea was shallow, it was sufficient for the great fleets of comparatively small ships which carried the traffic to Atlantis and the Algerian Islands. In this great catastrophe the bed of the Sahara Sea rose, a vast tidal wave swept over Egypt, and almost its entire population was destroyed. And even when everything settled down, the country was a wilderness, bounded on the west no longer by a fair and peaceful sea, but by a vast salt swamp, which as the centuries rolled on dried into an inhospitable desert. Of all the glories of Egypt there remained only the Pyramids towering in lonely desolation-- a desolation which endured for fifteen hundred years before the self-exiled clan returned from its mountain refuge, grown into a great nation.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
But long before this, half-savage tribes had ventured into the land, fighting their primitive battles on the banks of the great river which once had borne the argosies of a mighty civilisation, and was yet again to witness a revival of those ancient glories, and to mirror the stately temples of Osiris and Amun-ra. Professor Flinders Petrie describes five of these earlier races, which overran different parts of the country and warred desultorily among themselves.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
An aquiline race of the Libyo-Amorite type, which occupied a large part of the land, and held its own longer than any other, maintaining for centuries a fair level of civilisation.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A Hittite race with curly hair and plaited beards.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A people with pointed noses and long pigtails-- mountaineers, wearing long, thick robes.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A people with short and tilted noses, who established themselves for some time in the central part of the country.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Another variant of this race, with longer noses and projecting beards, who occupied chiefly the marshland near the Mediterranean. All these are observable by clairvoyance, but they have mingled so much that it is often difficult to distinguish them; and in addition to these, and probably earlier in the field than any of them, a savage negroid race from the interior of Africa, which has left practically no record of its passing.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Into this turmoil of mixed races came our clan, priest-led across the sea from its Arabian hills, and gradually made its footing sure in Upper Egypt, establishing its capital in Abydos, and slowly possessing itself of more and more of the surrounding land, until by weight of its superior civilisation it was recognised as the dominant power. All through its earlier centuries its policy was less to fight than to absorb-- to build out of this chaos of peoples a race upon which its hereditary characteristics should be stamped. A thousand years had passed since their arrival, when, in the twenty-first life of Alcyone, we find MARS reigning over an already highly-organised empire; but it was fourteen hundred years later still before the MANU Himself (they have corrupted His name to Menes now) united the whole of Egypt under one rule, and founded at the same time the first dynasty and His great city of Memphis-- thus initiating in person another stage of the work begun by His direction in 13,500 B.C.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Clio and Markab were noticed among a group of Egyptian statesmen who disapproved of the Aryan immigration and schemed against it. Clio' s wife Adrona, and Markab' s wife Avelledo were implicated in their plots. All four of them were eventually exiled, as was also Cancer, the sister of Adrona.
</view>
</text>
</body>