<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Beginnings of the fifth root race</view>
<view lang="ru">Начало Пятой Коренной Расы</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
THE statement in The Secret Doctrine that the fifth Root Race began one million years ago appears, as already stated, to refer to the beginning of the choosing of materials by the Lord Vaivasvata, the Race Manu. He was a Lord of the Moon, taking the first step in Initiation on Globe G of the seventh round, where also He attained Arhatship. About a million years ago, then, He chose out from the ship-load which included our 1,200-year group, a few people whom He hoped to shape for His Race, and with whom He therefore kept up a connection. Four hundred thousand years later, He picked out some more. It was rather like looking over a flock of sheep, and choosing out the most suitable. Of these, numbers would be dropped out on the way, and the selection would be thus narrowed down from time to time.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Утверждение в книге "Тайная Доктрина" которое говорит о том, что пятая Коренная Раса берёт начало один миллион лет назад, означает то, что в это время Лорд Вайвасвата — Ману Расы — начал выбирать материал для неё. Он был Лордом Луны и принял первое посвящение на планете G в седьмом Раунде и там же стал архатом. Около миллиона лет назад он выбрал из группы душ в которой были наши 1,200-летние эго несколько людей на которых он рассчитывал, что они подойдут для его расы и по этой причине поддерживал с ними связь. 400,000 лет спустя он выбрал ещё нескольких. Это было похоже на процесс выбора наиболее подходящих овец из стада. В дальнейшем пути часть из выбранных душ будет отброшена и выбранная группа станет меньше.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The isolation of a tribe from the white fifth sub-race (the moon-coloured race, as the Stanzas of Dzyan poetically describe it) which lived in the mountains to the north of Ruta, was the first decisive step in the building of the Race, and this took place about 100,000 B.C. The fifth sub-race, it may be said in passing, was addicted to mountains generally, and the Kabyles of the Atlas Mountains are its best modern representatives. Their religion was different from that of the Toltecs living in the plains, and the Manu took advantage of this to isolate the sub-race. Then His Brother the Bodhisattva, who became later the Lord Gautama Buddha, founded a new religion; and people coming into that were segregated off, and bidden to keep apart, intermarriage with other tribes being forbidden. His disciples went out into other lands and gathered a few together, who, later, joined the main body. They were told that one day they would journey far away into another land, which became to them ` the promised land,' and that they were under a King and Lord, physically unknown to them; they were thus kept in a state of preparation for the coming of the great One who was to lead them forth; He was going to guide His people to a place of safety, where they would escape the coming catastrophe-- that of 75,025 B.C.1 (¹ Usually called that of 80,000 B.C.) Some of the Hebraic story was probably derived from these facts, although the separation of the people who were known in history as Hebrews came later. These ancestors of theirs were literally a ` chosen people,' set aside for a great purpose.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Изоляция племени от пятой белой подрасы которая жила в горах на севере Руты — стала первым решительным шагом на пути к созданию Расы который был сделан 100,000 лет до н.э. Пятая подраса, между прочим, быстро привыкла к горам и кабильцы из Атласских гор могут выступить как её лучшие современные представители. Их религия была непохожа на религию толтеков которые жили на равнинах, чем и воспользовался Ману для изоляции подрасы. Затем пришёл его брат — Бодхисаттва, который позже стал известен как Лорд Гаутама Будда — и основал новую религию которая предписывала её сторонникам держаться обособленно и не вступать в браки с другими племенами. Его последователи объединились и выбрали себе земли. Им сказали, что однажды они отправятся на другую землю очень далёкую от их настоящего дома — "Обетованную Землю" — куда их поведёт Король или Лорд пока что им неизвестный и они ждали пришествия этого Великого который поведёт их за собой, чтобы спасти и увести в безопасное место, ибо 75,025 лет до н.э. случится великая катастрофа. Возможно, некоторые факты были заимствованы в еврейскую историю, хотя отделение людей которые сейчас известны под этим именем произошло позднее.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The immediate cause of the emigration was the impending subdual of the white sub-race by the Dark Ruler, and the wish of the Manu to withdraw His people from that influence. So, in 79,797 B.C., He called them to the coast, that they might be shipped off through the Sahara Sea, whence they travelled forwards on foot by the south of Egypt to Arabia. A small fleet of ships, thirty in number, was provided; the largest did not seem to be over 500 tons, and three were cutter-like vessels, carrying only provisions. They were clumsy-looking ships, sailing fairly well on a wind, but tacking very badly. Some had oars as well as sails, and these were certainly not well adapted for a long sea-voyage. However, they had to cross open water only as far as the mouth of the Sahara Sea (which was a crooked sort of bight opening into the Atlantic), and then to sail along its almost land-locked waters. The fleet carried over about two thousand nine hundred persons, deposited them on the shore at the eastern end of the Sahara Sea, and returned to the place of embarkation for another set. The voyage was performed three times, and the little nation, made up to nine thousand men, women and children by the additional few from elsewhere, set forth eastwards on foot.1 (¹ Five-sixths of the nine thousand were from the fifth sub-race; one-twelfth were Akkadian, and one-twelfth Toltec, each the best of its kind.) They had with them a number of animals also, looking like a cross between a buffalo and an elephant with something of the pig, reminding one rather of a tapir, a half-and-half sort of beast. These were used for food when other supplies ran short, but were regarded as too valuable for such use ordinarily. The whole process of embarkation, debarkation, settling down to wait for their comrades, and preparing for the journey on foot, occupied some years, and the Manu, with some other great Officials, was then sent by the Head of the Hierarchy to lead them to the high plateau of Arabia, where they were to remain for a time.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Немедленным следствием эмиграции стало то, что люди белой подрасы попали под влияние Тёмного Правителя и Ману собрался их освободить от этого влияния. Он созвал их на побережье с тем, чтобы они могли отплыть через море Сахара куда они пришли своими ногами с юга Египта. В их распоряжении была небольшая флотилия из 30-ти кораблей, самый большой из которых не превосходил пятисот тонн; было также три корабля которые везли исключительно провизию. Корабли выглядели весьма неуклюже и хотя они очень неплохо плыли под ветром, их конструкция и скрепление было очень плохим. На некоторых кораблях были вёсла вдобавок к парусам, но они определённо не были приспособленны к длительному путешествию. Флотилия перевезла около 2,900 людей, высадила их на восточном побережье Сахары и вернулась обратно, чтобы забрать следующую группу. Таким образом флотилия пересекла море три раза и маленькая нация из мужчин, женщин и детей общим числом в 9,000 человек, отправилась на восток уже пешком. <sup>5</sup>/<sub>6</sub> из 9,000 принадлежали пятой подрасе, <sup>1</sup>/<sub>12</sub> была из аккадцев и <sup>1</sup>/<sub>12</sub> из толтеков -- лучшие среди своих подрас. С ними были животные, похожие на гибрид буйвола и слона с чем-то от свиньи. Их использовали в пищу когда есть было нечего, хотя они считались очень ценными для столь незатейливого применения. Весь процесс с погрузкой, выгрузкой и ожиданием оставшихся друзей перед пешим походом занял несколько лет, после чего Ману с другими Великими по указанию главы Иерархии повели нацию к высокому плато в Аравии где они должны были остаться на время.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Atlanteans had conquered Egypt and were ruling the country at this period. They had built the pyramids, on which Cheops put his name many thousands of years later; when Egypt was swamped by a flood, some seventy-seven thousand years ago, the people tried to climb these pyramids for safety, as the waters rose, but failed in consequence of the smoothness of their sides. This great Atlantean civilisation perished; then came the flood, and a negroid domination, and another Atlantean Empire, and an Aryan (13,500 B.C.)-- all perhaps before that which history recognises as ` Egyptian' . But we must not follow this fascinating by-way.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Атланты к тому времени уже завоевали Египет. Они построили пирамиды которым Хеопс дал своё имя много тысячелетий спустя. Когда Египет затопило примерно 77,000 лет назад, люди пытались спастись на этих пирамидах, но их гладкие стороны не позволили это сделать. После цивилизации Атлантов пришёл потоп и негры получили власть, за ними пришла другая империя Атлантов, а за ними Арийская (13,500 bc) -- по видимому всё это случилось до периода правления тех, кого история называет "Египтянами".
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Suffice it that a splendid Toltec civilisation was flourishing in Egypt when our emigrants passed along its borders, and the Egyptian Ruler, following the Toltec tradition that other races existed in order that the Toltecs might exploit them, tried to bribe them into remaining in his land. Some succumbed to the temptation and remained in lower Egypt, in defiance of the Manu' s command, to become, a little later, slaves to the dominant Toltecs.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Когда наши эмигранты шли вдоль границ Египта, правитель толтекской цивилизации живущей в этой стране, следуя давней традиции которая говорила, что другие расы существуют для того, чтобы вступить в их империю, попробовал заманить их в свои земли. Некоторые поддались искушению и остались в нижнем Египте.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The rest reached Arabia by way of the route which is now the Suez Canal, and were settled down by the Manu in groups, in the various valleys of the great Arabian highlands. The country was sparsely inhabited by a negroid race, and the valleys were fertile when irrigated. But the emigrants did not much like their new quarters, and while the majority of the people, who had been prepared by Vaivasvata Manu in Ruta, were even fanatically devoted to Him, the younger generation did a good deal of grumbling, for it was pioneer work, not a ` personally conducted Cook' s tour' .
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Оставшиеся добрались до Аравии по маршруту который мы сейчас знаем как Суэцкий канал. Ману разделил их на группы и расселил по многочисленным деревням в великих высокогориях Аравии. Земли уже были заселены немногочисленными неграми и долины были плодородными когда их орошали. Однако эмигранты не очень любили свои новые земли: в то время как основная часть подготовленная Вайвасватой была фанатично предана ему, молодое поколение ворчало по поводу своей пионерской работы.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
We found in one of the valleys a large number of the 1,200 and 700 years' groups, including many members of ` the family,' and their devotion certainly ran into violent fanaticism. They proposed to kill all the people who were not wholly devoted to the Manu, and prepared to fight the deserters, who had settled down comfortably in Egypt. This drew down upon them the wrath of the Egyptians and a considerable slaughter followed, our fanatics being completely wiped out. Mars and Corona gallantly resisted the Egyptian onslaught, while a side party, with Herakles-- a young unmarried man-- among them, mistaking the direction of the enemy, was annihilated by the Egyptians; Vaivasvata Manu, came up with reinforcements and turned the fortunes of the day, driving back the Egyptians; a side party of them, in turn, was attacked by a larger force, among which Sirius, the father of Herakles, was prominent, furious at finding his son among the dead; knowing the country, they shepherded the Egyptians into a crater-like depression, with steep sides covered with loose rocks; these rocks they joyfully hurled down on their surrounded foes, and the last we saw of Sirius on this occasion was his ride down the steep slope on an avalanche of stones, waving his spear, and shouting a war-song of an uncomplimentary nature, to become part of the gory mass of crushed men and heavy stones which filled the lowest part of the crater.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В одной из долин мы нашли большое число 1,200 и 700-летних групп которые включали многих членов "семьи" и их преданность часто переходила в яростный фанатизм. Они предложили убивать всякого, кто не был полностью предан Ману и даже собрались биться с дезертирами которые остались в хороших условиях Египта. Это навлекло на них гнев египтян и наши фанатики были полностью уничтожены. Марс и Corona храбро отражали стремительную атаку египтян, в то время как другая сторона с Гераклом — молодым неженатым мужчиной — среди них, была уничтожена египтянами. Вайвасвата Ману пришёл с подкреплением и вернул фортуну на свою сторону, отбросив египтян назад. Часть их была атакована превосходящими силами с Сириусом — отцом Геракла — отчаянно и яростно пытающегося найти сына среди убитых. Хорошо зная местность, они завели египтян в кратероподобную яму с крутым склоном. Они самозабвенно кидались камнями в своих окружённых противников и последнее, что мы видели — это как Сириус, махая копьём и крича воинственную песню нелестного содержания, обрушил лавину камней которая заполнила нижнюю часть кратера.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The few Egyptian soldiers who finally escaped and reached Egypt were incontinently put to death, as having disgraced the army by their defeat.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Немногие солдаты египетской империи, которые смогли бежать и добраться до своей страны, были немедленно преданы смерти как опозорившие армию своим поражением.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After this there was peace for a time for the colonists, and they cultivated their valleys, which were rather cold in winter, and blazingly hot in summer. They had brought seeds of various kinds from Atlantis, and some of these were suitable to their new home; they grew some tasteless fruits resembling apples, and, on the slopes of the hot part of the valley, they raised a very large fruit, as large as a man' s head, which, in stickiness and general messiness, was like a date. A kind of crater, where the sun was reflected from the rocks, served as a forcing-house, and they produced there a fruit of the size of a coconut, of which they seemed to be inordinately proud. It was nutritious, and, boiled in water, it yielded sugar by evaporation of the water, while the residuum of the fruit gave a flour, which the people made into a sort of sweet bun. Sirius had two of these buns in his cloth when he rode down the hill-side of death.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
После этой войны настало мирное время для колонистов и они начали орошать свои земли, которые становились весьма холодными зимой и обжигающими летом. Из Атлантиса они взяли с собой семена, некоторые из которых оказались пригодны для нового дома. Они выращивали безвкусные фрукты чем-то напоминающие яблоки, а на горячей стороне долины вырос один очень большой — размером с голову человека — фрукт который своей липкостью и неаккуратностью напоминал финик. Некоторое подобие кратера в котором камни отражали лучи солнца служил теплицей и в нём они вырастили фрукт размером с кокос и по видимому испытывали по этому поводу неумеренную гордость. Он был питательным и после того, как его варили в воде он давал сахар в испарениях воды, в то время как осадок представлял собой муку из которой люди делали нечто похожее на сдобные булочки.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In a succeeding incarnation, Herakles appeared as a tall, slim, and rather striking-looking young woman, hanging a somewhat squawky baby-brother-- Sappho-- up to a tamarind-like tree in a bark cradle.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В следующей инкарнации Геракл был обнаружен в теле высокой, стройной и очень привлекательной женщины держащей на руках пронзительно кричащего младенца Саппхо в колыбели из коры дерева похожего на тамаринд.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The selection from the fifth Atlantean sub-race grew and multiplied exceedingly, and became a nation of several millions in about two thousand years; they were quite isolated from the world in general by a belt of sand, which could only be crossed by caravans carrying with them plenty of water, and there was only one way across it with grass and water, about where Mecca now stands. From time to time emigrants left the main body, some settling in the south of Palestine and some in the south of Egypt; and these movements were encouraged by the representatives of the Manu, for the plateau was limited in size and became crowded to an uncomfortable extent. The least desirable type were sent away as emigrants, while He preserved unmixed within His belt of desert the most promising. Suggestions were made from time to time that a caravan of settlers should go off, make a colony, or found a city; among one of these the horse was developed. Occasionally He Himself incarnated, and His descendants formed a class apart of a somewhat improved type. But generally He was not physically present, but directed affairs through His lieutenants, of whom Jupiter and Mars were the most prominent.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Люди когда-то выбранные из пятой атлантической подрасы стремительно росли и размножались и через две тысячи лет превратились в многомиллионную нацию. Они были изолированы от остального мира широким песчаным поясом который можно было пересечь лишь на караване с огромным запасом воды и лишь один путь с растительностью и водой вёл к ним — путь на месте которого сейчас стоит Мекка. Время от времени люди покидали дома и шли на юг Палестины и юг Египта; эти перемещения поощрялись представителями Ману, так как плато было ограничено в размере и уже было населено сверх разумной меры. Наименее желательные представители изгонялись, а наиболее обещающие оставлялись Им в пределах песчаного пояса. Люди часто говорили о том, что надо бы отправить караван, чтобы тот нашёл хорошее место и основал колонию или город. Однажды Он сам воплотился и его дети основали класс людей улучшенного типа, но обычно Он не имел физического тела и управлял через своих наместников среди которых Юпитер и Марс были самыми выдающимися.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The people were pastoral and agricultural, not settling in large cities, and the plateau became thickly populated till, at the end of about three thousand years, it resembled a single huge village; then He sent out a very large number of people to Africa to found a big colony, so as to reduce the numbers in the central settlement. This colony was, later, quite exterminated.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Люди были в основном пастухами и землепашцами и не строили больших городов, поэтому вскоре плато было плотно заселено и к концу третьего тысячелетия напоминало одну большую деревню. Он отправил большое число людей в Африку основать колонию с тем, чтобы уменьшить численность центрального поселения. Позже, эта колония почти полностью вымерла.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It was only a few years before the catastrophe of 75,025 B.C., that-- on receipt of a message from the Head of the Hierarchy-- He selected about seven hundred of His own descendants to lead them northwards. He had made these people once more into an unorthodox sect, stricter in their lives than those around them, and they were not looked on favourably by the orthodox, among whom they lived; He advised them therefore to follow Him to a land where they might live in peace, escaping from the persecutions of the orthodox, a land which was distant several years' journey. Even His own lieutenants were not apparently admitted to His confidence, but were simply following out His directions; among these were several who are now Masters, and others who have passed onwards, away from our Earth.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Всего за несколько лет до катастрофы 75,025 лет до н.э. Он получил сообщение от главы Иерархии и выбрал 700 людей среди своих людей и повёл их на север. Они вступили в секту которую Он создал и ортодоксальные люди, которые жили вокруг, смотрели на них с неодобрением. Тогда Он предложил им последовать за собой на землю где они смогут жить в мире в далеке от гонений ортодоксальных людей. Это путешествие требовало нескольких лет и даже Его наместики были непосвящены в детали и просто следовали Его приказаниям. Срели них были люди которых мы сейчас знаем как Мастеров, а также те, кто ушёл далеко вперёд и покинул Землю.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The number of His followers being small, they made a single caravan, and the Manu sent a message to the Ruler of the Sumiro-Akkad Empire, praying for peaceful passage through his dominions-- including the present Turkey in Asia, Persia and the countries beyond; He reached the borders of that Empire without difficulty, and the Emperor proved friendly; his passport carried Him right into Turkestan, and then He had to treat with a Confederation of Turanian feudatory States, including what is now Tibet. He passed between mountain-ranges, of which the present Tianshan range was one; these marked the boundaries of the Gobi Sea, and stretched up to the Arctic Ocean. He had passed through Mesopotamia and Babylonia, slanting north, and the mountains He had to cross were not of great height; the Turanian Confederation gave permission for His passage, partly because His people were not numerous enough to cause apprehension, and partly because He stated that He was carrying out a mission imposed upon Him by the Most High. After some years of journeying He reached the shores of the Gobi Sea, but, bearing in mind the message He had received, He did not remain in the plain, but turned into the hills to the north, where a great shallow sea stretched northward to the Arctic Ocean and thus to the Pole. The Lemurian Star was much broken up by this time, and its nearest point was about a thousand miles to the north. He posted some of His followers on a promontory looking out to the north-east, but the greater number settled down in a fertile crater-like depression, something like the ` Devil' s Punch-bowl' in Surrey, but much larger; this was more inland, though from an adjoining peak they could catch sight of the sea. From this promontory, which stood high, they could see the Gobi Sea, and the land where later they were to settle. This was to be their dwelling until after the great catastrophe, then close at hand. The White Island was to the south-east and was entirely out of sight, though later, when covered with lofty temples, became visible from this spot. The promontory and adjoining land were formed of shelves of rock, which would be very little harmed by earthquakes unless the whole land was broken up. Here He was to remain till all danger was passed; and a few years were left in which to settle down. Many of the people died on the journey and after arrival, and He Himself reincarnated to improve the type more quickly.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Его последователи были немногочислены и одного каравана оказалось достаточно. Ману отправил сообщение правителю Шумеро-Аккадской Империи в котором просил пропустить их с миром через его владения, включавшие в себя сегодняшнюю Турцию, Персию и некоторые страны за ними. До границ Империи Ману добрался без проблем и Император встретил Его дружелюбно. С его разрешения Ману прошёл до Туркестана и там был вынужден обратиться к Конфедерации Туранских Феодальных Земель в число которых тогда входила земля называемая в наши дни Тибетом. Он пошёл между горными цепями среди которых была современная Тянь-Шань. Эти горы окружали море Гоби и тянулись до самого Арктического океана. Он прошёл через Месопотамию и Вавилонию и взял немного севернее. Горы которые ему предстояло перейти были не очень большой высоты. Туранская Конфедерация дала разрешение пройти, частично из-за немногочисленности каравана который не вызывал опасений, частично из-за его слов о том, что на него возложена миссия Высочайшими. Путешествие длилось ещё несколько лет и Он достиг берегов моря Гоби, но помня однажды полученное сообщение, Он не остался на равнине и повернул в сторону холмов на севере где неглубокое море растянулось до Арктического океана и Полюса. К тому времени Лемурийская Звезда была сломана и её ближайший луч лежал в тысяче миль севернее. Он отправил нескольких людей на один выступ с которого можно было смотреть на северо-восток, в то время как остальные расположились в огромном плодородном кратере. С того выступа было видно море Гоби и земля на которой они позже должны были жить. Это место должны было стать их временным домом в котором они будут жить до великой катастрофы. Белый Остров на юго-востоке был полностью скрыт от взора, хотя позже, когда на нём появились прекрасные храмы, его можно было разглядеть с этого места. Выступ и прилегающая земля состояли из скалы и потому землетрясения не могли сколь-нибудь значительно их повредить, разве что вся земля оказалась бы разрушена. Здесь Он должен был оставаться пока все опасности не пройдут своим чередом. На заселение оставалось несколько лет. В путешествии умерло много людей и даже он сам перевоплотился с тем, чтобы быстрее улучшить тип людей.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
These people, as said above, were really His own family, being His physical descendants, and, as bodies died, He packed the egos into new and improved ones.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Эти люди, как уже было отмечено, представляли собой его настоящую семью, его физических наследников, и когда тела умерали он переразмещал освободившиеся эго в новых улушенных телах.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In Atlantis the reincarnated Metal-Man was again ruling, none the wiser, apparently, for his previous experiences. He was in possession of the City of the Golden Gates, and the nobler types of the Atlanteans were much oppressed.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В Атлантисе реинкарнировался Металлический Человек и его правление было немногим мудрее прежнего. Он оказался во власти Города Золотых Врат и более благородные типы людей подавлялись.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The City was suddenly destroyed by the rushing in of the sea through huge fissures caused by explosions of gas; but, unlike the catastrophe in which the island of Poseidonis sank within twenty-four hours, these convulsions continued over a period of two years. Further explosions occurred, new cracks were made, earthquakes shook the land, for each explosion led to a further disturbance. The Himalayas were heaved up a little higher; the land to the south of India was submerged with its population; Egypt was drowned, and only the pyramids were left standing; the tongue of land which stretched from Egypt to what are now Morocco and Algeria disappeared, and the two countries remained as an island, washed by the Mediterranean and the Sahara Sea. The Gobi Sea became circular, and land was thrown up, now Siberia, separating it from the Arctic Ocean; Central Asia rose, and many torrents, caused by the unprecedented rainfall, cut deep ravines through the soft earth.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Город был мгновенно уничтожен водой из моря, прорвавшейся через трещины образованные взрывами газа, но в отличие от катастрофы которая погрузила остров Посейдонис под воду за 24 часа, это землетрясение продолжалось в течении двух лет. Следующие взрывы создавали всё больше трещин и землетрясений. Гималаи приподнялись ещё немного, земля на юге Индии погрузилась под воду вместе с населением, Египет утонул и лишь его пирамиды остались над водой. Земля соединявшая Египет и Марокко исчезла и образовался остров который омывали Средиземноморское море и море Сахара. Море Гоби стало круглым и из под воды показалась земля которую мы сейчас знаем как Сибирь — эта земля отделила Гоби от Арктического океана. Выросла центральная Азия и невиданные дожди вырезали в мягкой земле множество потоков.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
While these seismic changes were in progress, the Manu' s community was left undisturbed by absolute cleavage or change of surface; but the people were constantly terrified by the recurring earthquakes, and were almost paralysed by the fear that the sun (which had been rendered invisible for a year by masses of cloud, largely composed of fine dust) had gone out for ever. The weather was unspeakable. Terrible rains fell almost incessantly; masses of steam and clouds of dust enveloped the earth and darkened the air. Nothing would grow properly, and they were exposed to severe privations; the community, originally composed of seven hundred people, which had increased to a thousand, was reduced by these hardships to about three hundred. Only the stronger survived; the weaker were killed off.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Во время этой сейсмической активности люди Ману оставались в безопасности, но многие пришли в ужас от постоянных землетрясений, а годовое отсутствие солнца за массами облаков из пыли почти парализовало людей страхом потому-что те решили, будто солнце уже не выйдет никогда. Погода была неописуема. Сильные дожди почти не прекращались, а массы облаков из пара и пыли окутали Землю и оставили мало света. Ничто не росло и люди были в постоянной нужде, группа которая раньше состояла из 700 людей и даже выросла до 1,000 теперь уменьшилась до 300 человек. Выжили только сильнейшие, а более слабые умерли.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At the end of five years, they had again become settled; the punch-bowl depression had become a lake; some years of warm weather followed the years of disturbance; much virgin soil had been thrown up, and they were able to cultivate the land. But the Manu was growing old, and an order came to Him to bring His people to the White Island. To hear was to obey.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Через пять лет люди опять смогли жить нормально. Кратер превратился в озеро, пришли несколько лет тёплой погоды, а плодородная земля выброшенная на поверхность позволила людям выращивать пищу. Ману становился старым. Ему пришёл приказ взять своих людей и вести их на Белый Остров.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
There, by the Head of the Hierarchy Himself, the great plan of the future was unrolled before Him, stretching over thousands upon tens of thousands of years. His people were to live on the mainland, on the shores of the Gobi Sea, and they were to increase and grow strong. The new Race was to be founded on the White Island itself, and when it had increased, a mighty City was to be built on the opposite shore for its dwelling, and the plan of the City was suggested. There was a mountain range running along the shores of the Gobi Sea, some twenty miles distant, and low hills stretched out from that range to the shore; there were four great valleys, running from within the ranges to the sea, entirely separated from each other by the intervening hills; He was to plant certain selected families in these valleys, and develop therein four separate sub-races, which then were subsequently to be sent to different parts of the world. Also He was to send some of His own people to be born elsewhere, and then bring them back, and thus form new admixtures-- for they would have to marry into His family; and when the type was ready, He would have again to incarnate in it and to fix it. For the Root Race also some admixture was needed, as the type was not quite satisfactory.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Там сам Глава Иерархии развернул перед ним великий план будущего который растянулся на десятки тысяч лет. Его люди должны были жить на побережьях Гоби, расти и становиться сильнее. Новая Раса должна была начать свой путь на Белом Острове и когда она станет достаточно сильной, на противоположном берегу должен был быть построен могущественный город для их проживания. По берегам Гоби протянулись длинные горные цепи в 20-ти милях от моря и между морем и горами простирались холмы. Четыре огромные долины между горными цепями лежали возле моря разделяемые холмами. Его задачей было поселить в этих долинах четыре больших семьи и когда эти семьи вырастут в четыре разных подрасы они должны быть отправлены в разные части мира. Несколько его людей должны были родиться в далеке от долин и затем прийти и создать семьи с людьми из его семьи. Когда новый тип людей будет готов, он сам должен родиться и закрепить результат. Коренная Раса нуждалась в вмешательстве извне, так как её люди ещё не были удовлетворительно развиты.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Thus a main type and several sub-types had to be formed, and the differences were to be started in the comparatively early days, thus obtaining five groups to develop on different lines. It is interesting to notice that after refining His people for generations and forbidding marriage with those outside themselves, He yet found it necessary, later, to introduce a little foreign blood, and then to separate off the posterity of that foreign ancestor.
</view>
<view lang="ru">

</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Manu proceeded to settle His people (about 70,000 B.C.), bidding them build villages on the mainland, there to increase and multiply for some thousands of years. They had not to begin at the beginning like savages, for they were already a civilised people, and used a good deal of labour-saving machinery. In one of the towns dotted rather widely along the coastline, we noticed a number of familiar faces. Mars, a grandson of the Manu, was the head of the community and, with his wife Mercury and his family-- among whom were Sirius and Alcyone-- lived in a pleasant house, surrounded by a large garden and fine trees.1 (¹See Appendix III.) Corona was there, and Orpheus, an elderly and stately gentleman, very dignified and much respected. Jupiter was the ruler of the province-- if we may so call the whole settlement of the embryonic Race numbering about seven thousand souls-- wielding an authority which was delegated to him by the Manu, the recognised King of the community, residing at Shamballa.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Таким образом создавались главный тип и четыре дополнительных. Различия между ними закладывались уже в первые дни с тем, чтобы получить пять групп идущих по пяти путям. Интересно заметить, что после очищения своей подрасы через многие поколения и запрета создавать браки с людьми за пределами подрасы, он сам счёл нужным внести немного иностранной крови и отделить потомков этого иностранного родителя.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
As we were observing this town, there came galloping in a tumultuous band of men, who had evidently been out on a foray; they were riding on rough-looking animals, resembling horses, and were headed by Vajra; they drew up at the house of Mars, who was Varja' s brother, soon after galloping off again, as tumultuously as they came; and we followed them to another town, also on the shores of the Gobi, where we found Viraj as Chief. His son, Herakles, was in the band of raiders, wherein also we Observed Ulysses.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Пока мы наблюдали за городом, буйная банда людей, очевидно совершавших набег, подбиралась к городу. Они сидели на грубо выглядящих животных, похожих на лошадей. Предводителем банды был Vajra. Они заехали в дом Марса, который был братом Vajra, перед тем как уехать обратно. Мы последовали за ними в другой город на берегах Гоби и нашли в нём Viraj в качестве Главы. Среди банды мы обнаружили Геракла и Ulysses.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
More familiar faces were seen here; Cetus and Ulysses were at feud; they had first quarrelled over an animal, which both claimed to have killed, then over some land which both wanted, and finally over a woman whom both desired. Pollux and Herakles were great friends, Pollux having saved the life of Herakles in a foray, at the imminent risk of his own. One of the daughters of Herakles, Psyche, a big bouncing girl, attracted our attention at the age of fourteen, for she was carrying in her arms a small brother, Fides, when she was attacked by a large goat; the goat had big horns, curling at the base and spiked at the top, but the girl was not daunted; she seized the goat by the horns and turned it head over heels, and then, picking it up by the hind-legs, she banged it vigorously on the ground. The child Fides seemed to be rather a family pet, as we noticed Herakles carrying him about on his shoulder.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Мы также увидели много дургих знакомых лиц. Кетус и Ulysses постоянно враждовали, сначала из-за животного которое должно быть добычей одного, но каждый утверждал, что добыча только его, затем из-за земли на которую оба претендовали и наконец из-за женщины которую оба желали. Поллюкс и Геракл были хорошими друзьями: Поллюкс спас жизнь Геракла в набеге, несмотря на большой риск погибнуть самому. Она из дочерей Геракла — Психея, большая сильная девочка — привлекла наше внимание когда ей было 14: она несла на руках своего младшего брата Файдса который попался большому козлу; этот козёл имел большие витые и острые рога, но девочка не испугалась, а схватила козла за рога и виртуозно свалила его на землю. Файдс был чем-то вроде домашнего животного, так как Геракл нёс его перекинув через плечо.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Much excitement was caused some years later by the Manu, who was then a very old man, sending for Jupiter, Corona, Mars and Vajra; on their return, obeying His order, they selected some children from the settlement, and sent them over to Shamballa; these children were the best in the community and have since risen to the position of Masters. They were Alcyone' s sons, Uranus and Neptune, and his daughters Surya and Brihaspati; Saturn and Vulcan, boys, and Venus, a girl, were also selected. A few women were sent with them to take care of them, and the children were brought up in Shamballa; in due course Saturn married Surya, and the Manu was reborn as their eldest son, to restart the Race on a higher level.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Несколько лет спустя Ману — в то время очень старый человек — вызвал большое оживление среди людей, послав за Юпитером, Corona, Марсом и Vajra за тем, чтобы те привели к нему нескольких детей из поселения и направили их в Шамбалу. Эти дети были лучшими среди того сообщества и с тех пор стали Мастерами. Это были дети Алкиона — Уран и Нептун, Surya и Brihaspati, а также Сатурн, Вулкан и Венера. С ними отправили несколько женщин, чтобы те заботились о них в Шамбале. Сатурн женился на Surya и Ману родился вновь в качестве их старшего сына, чтобы продолжить развитие Расы на новом уровне.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
For meanwhile things had been moving on the mainland. Soon after the removal of the above-named children, the Turanians swept down on the community like a devastating flood, for this was the event of which the Manu had forewarned His lieutenants and from which the children were saved; the assailants were bravely beaten back several times, but horde succeeded horde. At last the bulk of the fighting men were killed, and the battle became a mere massacre, not a man, woman or child being left alive. Our old friend Scorpio was the Chief of one tribe, once more renewing his perennial conflict with Herakles. A number of promising children were cut off; but, after all, it did not much matter, for they all went out of earth-life together, grandparents, parents and children, and were ready to come back when the Manu founded His family. Mars returned earlier, and was born in Shamballa as a younger brother of the Manu, while Viraj was His sister.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В это время на континенте, вскоре после того, как указанные дети ушли, Туранцы обрушились на сообщество как наводнение. Именно об этом Ману предупреждал своих наместников и из-за этого дети были своевременно перемещены. Несколько раз нападавшие были отброшены назад, но одна орда сменяла другую и не было им конца. Когда большая часть мужчин была убита, битва превратилась в резню в которой ни женщины ни дети не остались в живых. Наш старый друг Скорпио был главарём одной банды которая продолжила неизменный конфликт с Гераклом. Немногие дети были спасены, но это уже не имело большого значения, ибо они всё равно покинули земную жизнь в ожидании когда Ману создаст новую семью в которую они смогут вернуться. Марс вернулся раньше и родился в Шамбале младшим братом Ману, в то время как Viraj была его сестрой.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then, everything began over again, but on a higher level; they invented, or re-invented, many useful things, and in some thousands of years there was a populous and flourishing civilisation. Our old friends were there among the pioneers, Herakles, this time, as the son of Mars. Those of the group of Servers then in birth worked hard under the direction of their leaders, trying to carry out their will. Thick-headed and stupid they often were, and they made many mistakes, but loyal and whole-hearted they always were, and that bound them closely to those they served.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Снова всё началось сначала, но уже на более высоком уровне. Они открывали вновь и изобретали новые вещи и через несколько тысяч лет они создали густонаселённую и цветущую цивилизацию. Наши старые друзья были среди пионеров. Геракл в то время был сыном Марса. Те служители которые родились и напряжённо работали под управлением своих лидеров, волю которых они несли в мир, были часто тупоголовыми и совершали много ошибок, но они были преданы всем сердцем и были очень близки к тем кому служили.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Houses were built of great size, to accommodate several generations (in fact, all the members of a family), and were strongly fortified, with only one entrance, and the windows opening into a large courtyard in the middle, where the women and children could be in safety. After a time, strong walls were built round villages and round towns, as additional defences, for the savage Turanians were constantly hovering on the outskirts of the community, terrifying the inhabitants by their wild yells and sudden onslaughts. The outlying villages were in a continual state of alarm, the dwellers on the sea-coast being left more at peace.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Дома строились огромными и вмещали несколько поколений (фактически всю семью). Они были серьёзно укреплены и имели только один вход. Окна выходили на большой двор в котором женщины и дети были в безопасности. Вокруг деревень и городов были построены прочные стены которые защищали от диких туранцев, постоянно нападающих на окраины и пугающих мирных жителей дикими воплями и внезапными атаками. Внешние деревни были в постоянном напряжении, позволяя жителям побережья быть в относительном спокойствии.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When the Race had again grown to the proportions of a small nation, there was another determined onslaught of the Turanians, and finally another massacre, with only, once more, a few children and their nurses saved and brought up in Shamballa. It is noteworthy that even the bloodthirsty Turanians did not attack the White Island, for they held it in the deepest veneration. Thus the Race-type was ever preserved, even when the bulk of it was twice swept away, and on each occasion the Manu and His lieutenants incarnated in it as soon as possible and purified it still further, ever approaching the type at which He aimed.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Когда Раса опять доросла до небольшой нации случилось следующее нападение туранцев которые вырезали всех, кроме немногих детей и их нянек, заблаговременно отправленных в Шамбалу. Надо заметить, что даже кровожадные туранцы не нападали на Белый Остров, ибо он внушал им сильнейшее благоговение. Таким образом люди этой Расы сохранялись и даже когда большая её часть дважды вырезалась, Ману со своими помошниками воплощался как можно скорее и очищал Расу ещё лучше чем ранее, приближая её состав к желаемому.
</view>
</text>
</body>