<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">CONCLUSION</view>
<view lang="ru">Заключение</view>
</title>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> THE FEDERATION OF NATIONS </view>
<view lang="ru"> Федерация Наций </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
THE whole object of this investigation was to obtain such information as was possible about the beginnings of the Sixth Root-Race and the community founded by the Manu and the High-Priest for that purpose. Naturally therefore no special attention was directed to any other part of the world than this. Notwithstanding, certain glimpses of other parts were obtained incidentally, and it will perhaps be interesting to note these; but they are put down without attempt at order or completeness, just as they were observed.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Весь смысл этого исследования в том, чтобы собрать сколько можно информации о начале шестой Коренной Расы и колонии основанной Ману и Высшим Жрецом для этой цели. Естественно, что из за этого другим частям мира не уделялось внимания. Несмотря на это, какие то части случайно попали в обзор и, возможно, будет интересно обратить на них внимание, хотя они были упомянуты без попытки полного описания.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Practically the whole world has federated itself politically. Europe seems to be a Confederation with a kind of Reichstag, to which all countries send representatives. This central body adjusts matters, and the Kings of the various countries are Presidents of the Confederation in rotation. The rearrangement of political machinery by which this wonderful change has been brought about is the work of Julius Caesar, who reincarnated some time in the twentieth century in connection with the coming of the Christ to reproclaim the W ISDOM . Enormous improvements have been made in all directions, and one cannot but be struck with the extraordinary abundance of wealth that must have been lavished upon these. Caesar, when he succeeds in forming the Federation and persuades all the countries to give up war, arranges that each of them shall set aside for a certain number of years half or a third of the money that it has been accustomed to spend upon armaments, and devote it to certain social improvements which he specifies. According to his scheme the taxation of the entire world is gradually reduced, but notwithstanding, sufficient money is reserved to feed all the poor, to destroy all the slums, and to introduce wonderful improvements into all the cities. He arranges that those countries in which compulsory military service has been the rule shall for a time still preserve the habit, but shall make their conscripts work for the State in the making of parks and roads and the pulling down of slums and the opening up of communications everywhere. He arranges that the old burdens shall be gradually eased off but yet contrives with what is left of them to regenerate the world. He is indeed a great man; a most marvellous genius.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Весь мир фактически превратился в политическую федерацию. Европа похожа на Конфедерацию с чем то вроде Рейхстага в который все страны посылают своих представителей. Центральный совет решает все дела, а Короли разных государств по очереди занимают пост Президента Федерации. Подобная удивительная реорганизация политической системы стала возможна благодаря усилиям Юлия Цезаря, который получил инкарнацию где то в двадцатом веке в связи со скорым пришествием Христа, который решил напомнить людям о Мудрости. Во всех направлениях проделана невероятная работа и нельзя не поразиться тому богатству которое для этого потребовалось. Цезарь, после того как организовал Федерацию и заставил страны бросить войны, сказал, чтобы каждая страна откладывала половину или треть трат на вооружения каждый год в течении определённого числа лет и тратила эти средства в социальной сфере в соответствии с его планом. Следуя этой схеме налогообложение всего мира постепенно сходит на нет, но при этом сохраняется достаточно денег, чтобы кормить всех бедных, убрать все трущобы и внести в каждый город замечательные новшества. Он сказал, чтобы страны с принудительной военной службой пока сохраняли этот обычай, но призывников направляли на работу для государства: делать парки, дороги, сносить трущобы и создавать повсюду коммуникации. Он сделал так, что проблемы постепенно начали исчезать, а также думал над тем, как за счёт их остатков преобразить мир. Он в самом деле великий человек и потрясающий гений.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
There seems to have been some trouble at first and some preliminary quarrelling, but he gets together an exceedingly capable band of people-- a kind of cabinet of all the best organisers whom the world has produced-- reincarnations of Napoleon, Scipio Africanus, Akbar and others-- one of the finest bodies of men for practical work that has ever been seen. The thing is done on a gorgeous scale. When all the Kings and prime ministers are gathered together to decide upon the basis for the Confederation, Caesar builds for the occasion a circular hall with a great number of doors so that all may enter at once, and no one Potentate take precedence of another.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Первое время, кажется, были сложности и временные конфликты, но он собрал удивительно способную команду людей — группу лучших организаторов которых знал мир — реинкарнации Наполеона, Scipio Africanus, Акбар и другие — в лучших человеческих телах для практической работы которые когда либо были. Всё делается в грандиозном масштабе. Когда все Короли и премьер министры собираются вместе для решения дел касающихся Конфедерации, Цераль для этого случая строит круглую комнату с огромным числом дверей, чтобы все могли войти одновременно и ни один властитель не предшествовал другому.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> THE RELIGION OF THE CHRIST </view>
<view lang="ru"> Религия Христа </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Caesar arranges all the machinery of this wonderful revolution, but his work is largely made possible by the arrival and preaching of the Christ Himself, so we have here a new era in all senses, not merely in outward arrangement, but in inner feeling as well. All this is long ago from the point of view of the time at which we are looking, and the Christ is now becoming somewhat mythical to the people, much as He was to many people at the beginning of the twentieth century. The religion of the world now is that which He founded; that is the Religion, and there is no other of any real importance, though there are still some survivals, of which the world at large is somewhat contemptuously tolerant, regarding them as fancy religions or curious superstitions. There are a few people who represent the older form of Christianity-- who in the name of the Christ refused to receive Him when He came in a new form. The majority regard these people as hopelessly out-of-date. On the whole the state of affairs all the world over is obviously much more satisfactory than in the earlier civilisations. Armies and navies have disappeared, or are only represented by a kind of small force used for police purposes. Poverty also has practically disappeared from civilised lands; all slums in the great cities have been pulled down, and their places taken, not by other buildings, but by parks and gardens.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Цезарь занимается организацией всей этой великой революции, но его работа во многом возможна благодаря прибытию и наставлениям Самого Христа, так что здесь начинается во всех смыслах новая эра, не просто во внешних проявлениях, а изнутри. Всё это происходит задолго до того времени которое мы рассматриваем и Христос становится опять мифическим персонажем для людей, как и в начале 20-го века. Религия мира стала тем, что Он основал и это была Религия, ибо не было никакой другой хоть небольшой важности, однако некоторые всё же уцелели и на них мир презрительно смотрит как на странные верования. Есть несколько людей верующих в старое Христианство — они отказались признавать Христа когда он пришёл к ним в новой форме. Большинство людей считают их безнадёжно отставшими от жизни. В целом состояние дел во всём мире стало намного удовлетворительнее чем в прежних цивилизациях. Пропали армии и морские военные флотилии, за исключением небольших вооружённых частей выполняющих роль полиции. Бедность практически ушла из цивилизованных стран, все трущобы в больших городах заменили не другими зданиями, а парками и садами.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> THE NEW LANGUAGE </view>
<view lang="ru"> Новый Язык </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This curious altered form of English, written in a kind of short-hand with many grammalogues, has been adopted as a universal commercial and literary language. Ordinarily educated people in every country know it in addition to their own, and indeed it is obvious that among the upper and commercial classes it is rapidly superseding the tongues of the different countries. Naturally the common people in every country still speak their old tongue, but even they recognise that the first step towards getting on in the world is to learn the universal language. The great majority of books, for example, are printed only in that, unless they are intended especially to appeal to the uneducated. In this way it is now possible for a book to have a much wider circulation than it could ever have had before. There are still university professors and learned men who know all the old languages, but they are a small minority, and all the specially good books of all languages have long ago been translated into this universal tongue.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Причудливо изменённый английский, похожий на скоропись с некоторыми особенностями, признан универсальным коммерческим и литературным языком. Обычный образованный человек в любой стране помимо своего родного языка знает ещё и этот; очевидно, среди высших и коммерческих классов он быстро вытесняет остальные языки разных стран. Естественно, что люди в любой стране говорят на старом родном языке, но даже они понимают, что первый шаг наверх в обществе это новый универсальный язык. Большинство книг написаны только на нём; исключение — книги призванные обратиться к необразованным. Таким образом аудитория книги стала гораздо больше чем когда либо раньше. Всё ещё есть профессора и учёные, который знают все старые языки, но они — меньшинство. Все хорошие книги давно переведены на этот универстальный язык.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In every country there is a large body of middle and upper class people who know no other language, or know only the few words of the language of the country which are necessary in order to communicate with servants and labourers. One thing which has greatly contributed to this change is this new and improved method of writing and printing, which was first introduced in connection with the English language and is therefore more adapted to it than others. In our community all books are printed on pale sea-green paper in dark blue ink, the theory being apparently that this is less trying to the eyes than the old scheme of black on white. The same plan is being widely adopted in the rest of the world. Civilised rule or colonisation has spread over many parts of the world which formerly were savage and chaotic; indeed almost no real savages are now to be seen.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В каждой стране есть большая группа среднего и высшего классов которые не знают других языков или знают лишь несколько слов из национального языка, которые необходимы для общения с слугами и рабочими. Одна и важных особенностей это новый и улучшенный метод письма и печати, который сначала был введён для английского языка и лишь затем адаптирован для других. В нашем сообществе все книги напечатаны тёмно синими чернилами на бумаге светло-зелёного морского цвета; несомненно есть теория о том, что этот способ менее нагружает глаза чем старая схема "чёрным по белому". Этот принцип широко применяется и в остальном мире. Правила цивилизации широко распростанились на многие части мира, который ранее были дикими; хотя настоящей дикости мы почти не заметили.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> THE OLD NATIONS </view>
<view lang="ru"> Старые Нации </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
People have by no means yet transcended national feelings. The countries no longer fight with one another, but each nation still thinks of itself with pride. The greatest advantage is that they are not now afraid of one another, and that there is no suspicion, and therefore far greater fraternity. But on the whole, people have not changed much; it is only that now the better side of them has more opportunity to display itself. There has not as yet been much mingling of the nations; the bulk of the people still marry in their own neighbourhood, for those who till the soil almost always tend to stay in the same place. Crime appears occasionally, but there is much less of it than of old, because the people on the whole know more than they did, and chiefly because they are much more content.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Люди так и не преодолели национальные чувства. Страны больше не воюют друг с другом, но каждая нация всё ещё думает о себе с гордостью. Но в этом отношении сделан огромный шаг вперёд, ибо они больше не боятся друг друга и не подозревают в каких то делах. В целом люди не сильно изменились, просто для их лучшей стороны появилось больше возможностей себя проявить. Между народами нет заметного смешения и основная их часть заключает браки среди своих соседей, а те кто вырос на земле почти всегда там остаются. Преступления изредка совершаются, но в общем их намного меньше чем раньше, частично из за того, что люди стали знать больше, но главным образом из за большего удовлетворения жизнью.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The new religion has spread widely and its influence is undoubtedly strong. It is an entirely scientific religion, so that though religion and science are still separate institutions, they are no longer in opposition as they used to he. Naturally people are still arguing, though the subjects are not those which we know so well. For example, they discuss the different kinds of spirit-communion, and quarrel as to whether it is safe to listen to any spooks except those who have been authorised and guaranteed by the orthodox authorities of the time. Schools exist everywhere, but are no longer under the control of the Church, which educates no one except those who are to be its own preachers. Ordinary philanthropy is not needed, since there is practically no poverty. There are still hospitals, and they are all Government institutions. All necessaries of life are controlled, so that there can be no serious fluctuations in their price. All sorts of luxuries and unnecessary things are still left in the hands of private trade-- objects of art, and things of that kind. But even with this, there is not so much competition as division of business; if a certain man opens a shop for the sale of ornaments and such things, another one is not likely to start in business close by, simply because there would not be enough trade for the two; but there is no curtailing of liberty with regard to that.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Новая религая широко распространилась и её влияние бесспроно сильно. Это всецело научная религия и хотя институты религии и церкви по прежнему разделены, они больше не противостоят друг другу как раньше. Естественно, люди по прежнему спорят, но предмет споров не тот, что нам так хорошо известен. Например они обсуждают раные виды духов и спорят о том, безопасно ли прислушиваться к советам привидений помимо тех, что "одобрены" ортодоксальными авторитетами того времени. Школы есть везде, но Церковь их не контролирует, а сама обучает лишь тех, кто станет священником. Обычная филантропия не нужна, так как почти нет бедности. По прежнему есть госпитали, как и все остальные государственные институты. Все необходмые товары контролируются и потому их цена не испытывает значительных колебаний. Все виды роскоши и других бесполезных вещей существуют и находятся в руках частных торговцев — предметы искусства и другие вещи. Но даже здесь нет большой конкуренции; если какой то человек хочет открыть магазин для продажи орнаментов, другой не станет строить бизнес рядом, просто потому что там нет места двум людям для торговли; однако ничто не мешает так сделать.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> LAND AND MINES </view>
<view lang="ru"> Земли и Рудники </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The conditions as to the ownership of private land and of mines and factories are much changed. A large amount at least of the land is held nominally from the King, on some sort of lease by which it reverts to him unconditionally at the end of a thousand years, but he has the right to resume it at any intervening period if he chooses, with certain compensations. In the meantime it may descend from father to son, or be sold or divided, but never without the consent of the authorities. There are also considerable restrictions as to many of these estates, referring to what kind of buildings may be erected on them. All factories for necessaries are State property, but still there is no restriction which prevents anyone from starting a similar factory if he likes. There is still some mining, but much less than of old. The cavities and galleries of many of the old mines in the northern parts of Europe are now used as sanatoria for the rare cases of consumption or bronchial or other affections, because of their equal temperature in summer and winter. There are also arrangements for raising metal from great depths, which cannot exactly be called mines, for they are much more like wells. This may be considered a modern and improved type of mine. Little of the work is done down below by human beings; rather machines excavate, cut out huge slices and lift them. All these are State property in the ultimate, but in many cases private owners rent them from the State. Iron is burnt out of various earths in some way, and the material is obtained with less trouble than of old.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Условия владения частной землёй и рудниками сильно изменились. Большие территории номинально принадлежат Королю, а часть их сдаётся в аренду и после, через тысячу лет, возвращается к нему, но аренду можно продлить, уплатив определённую компенсацию. В своё время она может перейти от отца к сыну, быть продана или поделена, но всегда с согласия властей. На все эти территории наложены заметные ограничения, например на здания которые можно строить там. Все фабрики необходимых товаров находятся в собственности у государства, хотя не возбраняется кому либо создать самому похожую фабрику. Всё ещё остаётся немного работающи шахт, но их намного меньше чем раньше. Во многих старых шахтах на севере Европы штольни используют как санатории для редких случаев туберкулёза или других заболеваний лёгких, из за неизменной температуры как зимой так и летом. Есть предприятия для извлечения металлов с огромных глубин, однако их нельзя назвать рудниками, так как они больше похожи на колодцы. Их также можно рассматривать как современные улучшенные шахты. На большой глубине люди мало что делают; обычно машины выкапыют огромные куски породы и поднимают их вверх. Всё это собственность государства, но во многих случаях сдаётся в аренду частным лицам. Железо выжигают из самых разных земельных пород и в общем этот процесс намного проще чем был раньше.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> THE GOVERNMENT OF BRITAIN </view>
<view lang="ru"> Правительство Британии </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Government of England has been considerably changed. All real power is in the hands of the King, though there are ministers in charge of separate departments. There is no parliament, but there is a scheme the working of which is not easy fully to comprehend in the rapid glimpse which is all that we had. It is something more or less of the nature of the referendum. Everybody has a right to make representations, and these pass through the hands of a body of officials whose business it is to receive complaints or petitions. If these representations show any injustice, it is rapidly set right without reference to the higher authorities. Every such petition is attended to if it can be shown to be reasonable, but it does not usually penetrate to the King himself, unless there are many requests for the same thing. The monarchy is still hereditary, still ruling by the claim of descent from Cerdic. The British Empire appears to be much as in the twentieth century, but it was an earlier federation than the greater one, and it naturally acknowledges permanently one King, while the World-Federation is constantly changing its President. Some of what used to be Colonial Governors now hold their offices by heredity, and are like tributary monarchs.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Правительство Англии заметно изменилось. Вся реальная власть находится в руках Короля, хотя есть министры для управления разными отраслями. Нет парламента, но есть схема, работу который не просто понять полностью, бросив лишь быстрый взгляд — а это всё, что мы имели. Она более менее похожа на референдум. Каждый имеет право на голос и всё это проходит через руки официальных представителей, чья работа заключается в приёме жалоб и прошений. Если эти голоса указывают на какую либо несправедливость, она быстро устаняется без обращения к высшей власти. Каждое предложение рассматривается если его считают полезным; предложения не доходят до самого Короля, кроме случаев многих одинаковых запросов. Монархия по прежнему наследственная и правление идёт от потомков Cerdic. Британская Империя оказалась похожа на себя в 20 веке, хотя та была не столь великой, и она естественно признаёт одного Короля, тогда как Мировая Федерация постоянно меняет своего Президента. Должность похожая на колониального монарха осталась и теперь она передаётся по наследству; она похоже на должность монарха в подчинённой стране.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> LONDON </view>
<view lang="ru"> Лондон </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
London still exists, and is larger than ever, but much changed, for now all over the world there are no fires, and consequently no smoke. Some of the old streets and squares are still recognisable in general outline, but there has been a vast amount of pulling-down, and improvements upon a large scale. S. Paul' s Cathedral is still there, preserved with great care as an ancient monument. The Tower has been partly reconstructed. The introduction of one unlimited power has produced great effects here also, and most things that are wanted seem to be supplied on the principle of turning on a tap. Here also few people any longer cook in private houses, but they go out for meals much as they do in the community, although things are served here in a different manner.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Лондон по прежнему существует и он стал больше чем когда либо, так как во всем мире теперь нет огней и потому нету дыма. Некоторые старинные улицы и скверы всё ещё узнаваемы, но большое количество улучшений их постепенно скрывает. Кафедральный собор святого Павла всё ещё здесь — он тщательно сохранён как предмет древности. The Tower частично обновлён. Появление единой неограниченной энергии внесло огромные изменения и большинство необходимых вещей похоже предоставляются по принципу нажатия кнопки. Здесь люди также редко готовят еду сами; обычно они идут за едой как и в колонии, хотя здесь организация другая.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> OTHER PLACES </view>
<view lang="ru"> Другие Места </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Taking a passing glance at Paris, it also is seen to be much changed. All the streets are larger and the whole city is, as it were, looser. They have pulled down whole blocks, and thrown them into gardens. Everything is so hopelessly different. Glancing at Holland, we see a country so thickly inhabited that it looks like almost a solid city. Amsterdam is, however, still clearly distinguishable, and they have elaborated some system by which they have increased the number of canals and contrived to change all the water in all of them every day. There is not any natural flow of water, but there is some curious scheme of central suction, a kind of enormous tube system with a deep central excavation. The details are not clear; but they somehow exhaust the area and draw into that all sewage and such matters, which are carried in a great channel under the sea to a considerable distance and are then spouted out with tremendous vigour. No ships pass anywhere near that spot, as the force is too great. Here also, as in the community, they are distilling sea-water and extracting things from it-- obtaining products from which many things are made-- articles of food among others, and also dyes. In some of the streets they grow tropical trees in the open air by keeping round them a constant flow of the power in its heat aspect.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Бросив мимолётный взгляд на Париж, мы нашли его также сильно изменённым. Все улицы стали шире, а весь город будто стал бесформенным. Целые кварталы превратились в сады. Всё столь безнадёжно изменилось. Глядя на Голландию, мы видим её столь плотно населённой, что она больше похожа на сплошной город. Амстердам, однако, по прежнему легко отличим; там придумали некую систему, которая увеличила число каналов и сделали так, что все они обновляют воду каждый день. Здесь нет естественного потока воды; вместо этого — любопытная схема с центральным насосом, вроде огромной трубы с глубокой центральной ямой. Детали неясны, но они каким то образом стягивают в эту зону все нечистоты и проносят всё это по длинному каналу под морем, где на большом удалении под огромным напором выливаются. Корабли не плавают поблизости от этой зоны, ибо сила очень велика. Здесь также как и в колонии очищают морсую воду и добывают из неё минералы — материалы из которых сделаны многие вещи, в частности пища и красители. На некоторых улицах они выращивают тропические деревья на открытом воздухе, за счёт той энергии, которая греет их по периметру.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Centuries ago they began by roofing in the streets and keeping them warm, like a green-house; but when the unlimited power appeared they decided to dispense with the roofs, about which there were many inconveniences. In passing glimpses at other parts of the world, hardly anything worth chronicling was seen. China appears to have had some vicissitudes. The race is still there and it does not seem to have diminished. There is a good deal of superficial change in some of the towns, but the vast body of the race is not really altered in its civilisation. The great majority of the country people still speak their own tongue, but all the leading people know the universal language.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Столетия назад они начали покрывать улицы крышей, чтобы сделать их тёплыми, как теплицы, но с появлением неограниченной энергии оказалось, что от крыш лучше отказаться, ибо они вызывали много сложностей. Бросая взгляды на другие части мира, трудно заметить что то достойное внимания. Китай, как оказалось, имеет те же vicissitudes. Раса по прежнему живёт там и похоже не уменьшилась. Появилось много поверхностных изменений в некоторых городах, однако в целом эта раса не изменилась. Большинство людей этой страны всё ещё говорят на родном языке, но все устремлённые люди знают универсальный язык.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
India is another country where but little change is observable. The immemorial Indian village is an Indian village still, but there are no famines now. The country groups itself into two or three big kingdoms, but is still part of the one great Empire. There is evidently far more mixture in the higher classes than there used to be, and much more intermarriage with white races; so that it is clear that among a large section of the educated people the caste system must to a great extent have been broken down. Tibet seems to have been a good deal opened up, since easy access is to be had to it by means of flying machines. Even these, however, meet with occasional difficulties, owing to the rarity of the air at a great height. Central Africa is radically changed, and the neighbourhood of the Victoria Nyanza has become a sort of Switzerland full of great hotels.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Ещё одна страна где едва ли заметны какие либо изменения это Индия. Бессменные Индийские деревни по прежнему здесь, однако голода уже нет. Страна сгруппировалась в 2-3 больших королевства, но все они — часть одной великой Империи. Среди высших классов, очевидно, стало больше кровосмешений чем было принято, а также стало больше браков с белыми людьми. Ясно, что среди большой группы образованных людей принцип кастовой системы в большой степени нарушен. Тибет значительно приоткрылся миру, так как летающие машины делают доступ к нему совсем несложным. Хотя они сталкиваются с определёнными трудностями из за разрежённости воздуха на столь большой высоте. Центральная Африка радикольно изменилась и земли рядом с озером Виктория стали похожи на Швейцарию заполненную большими отелями.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> ADYAR </view>
<view lang="ru"> Адьяр </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Naturally it is interesting to see what has happened by this time to our Headquarters at Adyar, and it is delightful to find it still flourishing, and on a far grander scale than in older days. There is still a Theosophical Society; but as its first object has to a large extent been achieved, it is devoting itself principally to the second and third. It has developed into a great central University for the promotion of studies along both these lines, with subsidiary centres in various parts of the world affiliated to it.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Естественно, нам интересно узнать, что стало к тому времени с штаб квартирой в Адьяре и мы были приятно удивлены, что она по прежнему цветёт, причём в гораздо большем масштабе чем когда либо. Здесь по прежнему располагается Теософическое Сообщество, но с тех пор как его первая цель была в большой степени достигнута, оно посвящает себя, главным образом, второй и третьей целям. Оно развилось в огромный центральный Университет, посвящённый развитию учений вдоль этих двух путей, с филиалами в разных уголках мира.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The present Headquarters building is replaced by a kind of gorgeous palace with an enormous dome, the central part of which must be an imitation of the Taj Mahal at Agra, but on a much larger scale. In this great building they mark as memorials certain spots by pillars and inscriptions, such as: “Here was Madame Blavatsky' s room”; “Here such and such a book was written”; “Here the original shrine-room”; and so on. They even have statues of some of us, and they have made a copy in marble of the statues of the Founders in the great hall. Even that marble copy is now considered as a relic of remote ages. The Society owns the Adyar River now, and also the ground on the other side of it, in order that nothing may be built over there that may spoil its prospect, and it has lined the river-bed with stone of some sort to keep it clean. They have covered the estate with buildings, and have acquired perhaps an additional square mile along the sea-shore. Away beyond Olcott Gardens they have a department for occult chemistry, and there they have all the original plates reproduced on a larger scale and also exceedingly beautiful models of all the different kinds of chemical atoms. They have a magnificent museum and library, and a few of the things which were here at the beginning of the twentieth century are still to be seen. One fine old enamelled manuscript still exists, but it is doubtful whether there are any books going back as far as the twentieth century. They have copies of The Secret Doctrine, but they are all transcribed into the universal language.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Сегодняшнее здание штаб квартиры заменено на грандиозный дворец с впечатляющим куполом, центральная часть которого имитирует Тадж Махал в Агре, только в большем масштабе. В этом здании они отметили колоннами и надписями определённые места: "Здесь была комната мадам Блаватской", "Здесь была написана такая то книга", "Здесь была усыпальница" и так далее. Они даже сделали статуи некоторых из нас, а мраморные копии статуй Основателей поставили в главном холле. Но даже те мраморные копии сейчас рассматриваются как реликвии. Сообществу принадлежит река Адьяра вместе с землёй на другом берегу, чтобы быть уверенным в том, что не построят чего нибудь, что бы закрыло вид на дворец. Русло реки они облицовали каким то камнем, чтобы сделать воду чистой. Они застроили окрестности зданиями и получили, возможно, дополнительную квадратную милю вдоль побережья реки. Вдали, за садом Олькотта, у них есть кафедра оккультной химии,а в ней все оригинальные plates воспроизведены в большом масштабе и необычайно изящные модели всех видом химических атомов. У них есть ошеломляющий музей и библиотека с неколькими предметами из двадцатого века, которые сохранились до тех времён. Мы заметили один старый эмалированный манускрипт, но трудно сказать, есть ли там книги времён 20-го века. Есть также копии книги "Тайная Доктрина" переведённой на универсальный язык.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> THE THEOSOPHICAL SOCIETY </view>
<view lang="ru"> Теософической Сообщество </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Society has taken a great place in the world. It is a distinct department in the world' s science, and has a long line of specialities which no one else seems to teach. It is turning out a vast amount of literature, possibly what we should call texts, and is keeping alive an interest in the old religions and in forgotten things. It is issuing a great series somewhat resembling the old ` Sacred Books of the East,' but on a more magnificent scale. The volume just issued is number 2,159. There are many pandits who are authorities on the past. Each man appears to specialise on a book. He knows it by heart and knows all about it, and has read thoroughly all the commentaries upon it. The literary department is enormous, and is the centre of a world-wide organisation. Though they still use English, they speak it differently, but they keep the archaic motto of the Society written in its original form. The Society' s dependencies in other parts of the world are practically autonomous big establishments and universities in all the principal countries; but they all look up to Adyar as the centre and origin of the movement and make it a place of pilgrimage. Colonel Olcott, though working in the community in California as a lieutenant of the Manu, is the nominal President of the Society, and visits its Headquarters at least once in every two years. He comes and leads the salutations before the statues of the Founders.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Сообщество играет большую роль в мире. Оно представлено отдельным департаментом в научном мире и рассказывает о тех предметах, которым, кажется, никто другой не учит. Оно пишет огромное число текстов и поддерживает интерес к темам древних религий и других забытых вещей. Оно выпускает болшую серию книг похожих на "Священные Книги Востока", только в более впечатляющей форме. Только что вышел том с номером 2,159. Есть много гуру, считающихся авторитетами в вопросах прошлого. Каждый человек занимается какой то книгой. Он знает её сердцем, знает всё об этом и прочитал все комментарии к ней. Литературное министерство огромно и является центром всемирной организации. Хотя они по прежнему говорят на английском, их речь изменилась, однако они сохранили оригинальный девиз Сообщества. Связи Сообщества с остальным миром — практически автономные большие университеты и организации во всех ключевых странах. На Адьяр смотрят как на источник этого движения и к нему совершают паломничества. Колонел Олькотт, несмотря на работу в Калифорнии в качестве помошника Ману, также является Президентом Сообщества и навещает штаб квартиру не реже чем раз в два года. Когда он приходит, он приветствует статуи Основателей.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> THREE METHODS OF REINCARNATION </view>
<view lang="ru"> Три Метода Реинкарнации </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
As in the examination of the Californian community a great many people were seen who were clearly recognisable as friends of the twentieth century, it seems desirable to enquire how they manage to be there-- whether they have been taking a number of rapid incarnations, or have calculated their stay in the heaven-world so as to arrive at the right moment.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Изучая колонию в Калифорнии мы нашли много людей, которые оказались нашими друзьями в двадцатом веке. На кажется, есть смысл узнать как они оказались там. Возможно они приняли несколько быстрых последовательных инкарнаций, возможно они рассчитали своё пребывание в дэвачане так, чтобы прибыть в нужный момент.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The enquiry leads in unexpected directions and gives more trouble than had been anticipated, but at least three methods of occupying the intermediate time have been discovered. First, some of the workers do take the heaven-life, but greatly shorten and intensify it. This process of shortening but intensifying produces considerable and fundamental differences in the causal body; its effects cannot in any way be described as better or worse, but they are quite certainly different. It is a type which is much more amenable to the influence of the Devas than the other, and this is one of the ways in which modifications have been introduced. That shorter heaven-life is not shut in a little world of its own, but is to a great extent open to this Deva influence. The brains of the people who come along that line are different, because they have preserved lines of receptivity which in other cases have been atrophied. They can be more easily influenced for good by invisible beings, but there is a corresponding liability to less desirable influences. The personality is less awake, but the man inside is more awake in proportion. Those who take the longer heaven-life focus practically all their consciousness in one place at once, but people of this other type do not. Their consciousness is more equally distributed on the different levels, and consequently they are usually less concentrated upon the physical plane and less able to achieve in connection with it.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Такое исследование ведёт в неожиданные места и встречает больше проблем чем ожидалось. Тем не менее мы обнаружили по крайней мере три способа времяпровождения между инкарнациями. Есть группа рабочих которые заняли время небесной жизнью, но заметно сократили и ускорили её. Такой процесс сокращения и усиления создаёт заметные и фундаментальные изменения в каузальном теле. Эти эффекты нельзя описать ни плохо ни хорошо, но можно сказать, что они несомненно есть. Этот способ гораздо больше полагается на влияние Дэв чем другой и это один из путей, которым вносятся изменения. Эта короткая небесная жизнь не закрывает свой маленький мир, а в большой степени открывает его влиянию Дэв. Мозг у людей идущих по этому пути не такой как у других, потому что они сохранили вид восприимчивости который другие утратили. Они намного легче подвергаются добрым влияниям невидимых существ, но с другой стороны у них есть соответсвующая подверженность менее желательным влияниям. Личность менее активна, но зато пропорционально более активен внутренний человек. Люди которые провели более длительную небесную жизнь фокусируют почти всё своё сознание в одном месте сразу же; люди этого типа так не делают. Их сознания более ровно распределены на разных планах и потому они менее сконцентрированы на физическом плане и менее способны получать пользу от него.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
There are others to whom a different opportunity has been offered, for they were asked whether they felt themselves able to endure a series of rapid incarnations of hard work devoted to the building of the Theosophical Society. Naturally, such an offer is made only to those who bring themselves definitely to a point where they are useful-- those who work hard enough to give satisfactory promise for the future. To them is offered this opportunity of continuing their work, of taking incarnation after incarnation without interval, in different parts of the world, to carry the Theosophical Movement up to the point where it can provide this large contingent for the community. The community at the time when it is observed is much larger than the Theosophical Society of the twentieth century; but that Society has increased by geometrical progression during the intervening centuries-- so much so that although practically all the hundred thousand members of the community have passed through its ranks (most of them many times), there is still a huge Society left to carry on the activities at Adyar and the other great centres all over the world.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Есть другая группа людей которым предложили другую возможность; у них спросили, чувствуют ли они в себе силы совершить серию быстрых инкарнаций для тяжёлой работы создания Теософического Сообщества. Конечно, такое предложение сделали лишь тем, кто сделал себя полезным для этой работы — тем, кто усердно работал и потому давал хорошие надежды на будущее. Им предложили возможность продолжить свою работу, принять несколько инкарнаций без промежутков в разных частях мира, чтобы подвести Теософическое Движение к состоянию, в котором оно будет способно предложить достаточно людей для колонии. К периоду который мы изучали, колония стала многочисленнее чем Теософическое Сообщество двадцатого века. Однако в течении промежуточных столетий Сообщество росло в геометрической прогрессии — так быстро, что почти все члены стотысячной колонии прошли через Сообщество (большинство из них много раз). По прежнему есть огромное Сообщество для ведения дел Адьяра и другой деятельности в разных центрах по всему миру.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
We have seen already two methods by which persons who are in the Society in the twentieth century may form part of the community of the twenty-eighth century-- by the intensification of the heaven-life, and by the taking of special and repeated incarnations. Another method is far more remarkable than either of these-- one which is probably applied in only a limited number of instances. The case which drew attention to this was that of a man who had pledged himself to the Master for this work towards the conclusion of his twentieth century incarnation, and unreservedly devoted himself to preparation for it. The preparation assigned was indeed most unusual, for he needed development of a certain kind in order to round off his character and make him really useful-- development which could only be obtained under the conditions existing in another planet of the chain. Therefore he was transferred for some lives to that planet and then brought back again here-- a special experiment made by permission of the Maha-Chohan Himself. The same permission was in some cases obtained by other Masters for Their pupils, though such an extreme measure is rarely necessary.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Мы рассмотрели два метода, которыми люди из Сообщества двадцатого века могут принять участие в работе колонии в 28 веке — сделав небесную жизнь более интенсивной или приняв серию специальных быстрых инкарнаций. Ещё один метод гораздо более примечателен чем любой из этих двух — возможно он применим лишь к ограниченному числу случаев. Наше внимание привлёк случай, когда один человек к концу инкарнации в двадцатом веке заручился поддержкой Учителя и полностью посвятил себя подготовке к этой работе. Однако подготовка оказалась очень необычной, ибо ему нужно было развить определённые черты характера и подровнять свои качества, чтобы сделать себя по настоящему полезным. Это возможно лишь в условиях которые существуют на другой планете цепи. Поэтому его на несколько жизней переместили на ту планету и потом вернули обратно — это был особый эксперимент на который дал разрешение сам Махачохан. Аналогичные разрешения в некоторых случаях получили и другие Учителя для своих учеников, но такие крайние меры редко необходимы.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Most of the members of the community have been taking a certain number of special incarnations, and therefore have preserved through all those lives the same astral and mental bodies. Consequently they have retained the same memory, and that means that they have known all about the community for several lives, and had the idea of it before them. Normally such a series of special and rapid incarnations is arranged only for those who have already taken the first of the great Initiations. For them it is understood that an average of seven such lives should bring them to the Arhat Initiation, and that after that is attained seven more should suffice to cast off the remaining five fetters and attain the perfect liberation of the Asekha level. This number, fourteen incarnations, is given merely as an average, and it is possible greatly to shorten the time by especially earnest and devoted work, or, on the other hand, to lengthen it by any lukewarmness or carelessness. The preparation for the work of the community is an exception to ordinary rules, and although all its members are definitely aiming at the Path, we must not suppose that all of them have attained as yet to the greater heights.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Большинство членов колонии приняли серию особых инкарнаций и потому сохранили одни и те же астральные и ментальные тела на протяжении всех жизней. Как следствие, они сохранили ту же память и потому во всех жизнях знали о будущей колонии и эта идея всегда была перед ними. Обычно такая серия специальных и быстрых рождений совершается тем, кто уже получил первое великое Посвящение. Для них вполне ясно, что семь таких жизней приведут их к Посвящению Архата и что ещё семь жизней будут достаточны, чтобы сбросить пять оков и стать совершенно свободным на уровне Асекха. Это число — 14 жизней — всего лишь среднее количество жизней, так как возможно сильно сократить это время за счёт усердной и тщательной работы или, напротив, продлить, если работать небрежно и невнимательно. Подготовка к работе в колонии — исключение из общих правил и, хотя все члены колонии несомненно стремяться к Пути, мы не должны полагать, будто все они уже достигли больших высот.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A certain small number of persons from the outside world, who are already imbued with the ideals of the community, sometimes come and desire to join it, and some at least of these are accepted. They are not allowed to intermarry with the community, because of the especial purity of race which is exacted, but they are allowed to come and live among the rest, and are treated exactly like all the others. When such members die they reincarnate in bodies belonging to the families of the community.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Определённое число людей из внешнего мира, которые уже прониклись идеалами сообщества, иногда приходят и желают присоединиться к нему и некоторых из них принимают. Им не позволяют заключать браки с членами сообщества, из за требуемой особой чистоты расы, но им позволено прийти и жить среди них и на них будут смотреть точно также как и на членов сообщества. Когда такие люди умирают, они рождаются в качестве детей семьи сообщества.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Manu has advanced ideas as to the amount of progress which He expects the community as a whole to make in a given time. In the principal Temple He keeps a kind of record of this, somewhat resembling a weather-chart, showing by lines what He has expected and how much more or less has been achieved. The whole plan of the community was arranged by our two Masters, and the light of Their watchful care is always hovering over it. All that has been written gives only a little gleam of that light-- a partial foreshadowing of that which They are about to do.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Ману имеет продуманные идеи насчёт величины прогресса, который Он ожидает от сообщества в целом на конец отведённого промежутка времени. В главном Храме Он хранит запись этого — нечто похожее на диаграмму с погодой, на которой линиями указано, что Он ожидает увидеть и насколько колония продвинулась к цели. Весь план колонии создан двуми нашими Мастерами и свет Их всевидящего внимания постоянно освещает его. Всё что написано — лишь слабый проблеск этого света, лишь небольшой просвет в тени с видом на то, что Они собираются сделать.
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> HOW TO PREPARE OURSELVES </view>
<view lang="ru"> Как Себя Подготовить </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It is certainly not without definite design that just at this time in the history of our Society permission has been given thus to publish this, the first definite and detailed forecast of the great work that has to be done. There can be little doubt that at least one of the objects of the Great Ones in allowing this is not only to encourage and stimulate our faithful members, but to show them along what lines they must specially develop themselves, if they desire the inestimable privilege of being permitted to share in this glorious future, and also what (if anything) they can do to pave the way for the changes that are to come. One thing that can be done here and now to prepare for this glorious development is the earnest promotion of our first object, of a better understanding between the different nations and castes and creeds.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Несомненно не без умысла ровно в это время в истории нашего Сообщества дано разрешение опубликовать это — первое определённое и детальное предсказание великой работы которая будет сделана. Едва ли можно сомневаться, что по меньшей мере одна из целей Великих — позволить этому не только ободрить и помочь нашим преданным членам, но и показать вдоль каких путей им стоит развивать себя, если они желают получить неоценимую привелегию разделить великую работу, а также замостить себе дорогу к будущему которое придёт. Одно из того, что можно сделать здесь и сейчас для подготовки к великолепному развитию это добросовестное продвижение нашей первой цели, лучшего понимания различий между нациями, кастами и религиями.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In that everyone of us can help, limited though our powers may be, for every one of us can try to understand and appreciate the qualities of nations other than our own; every one of us, when he hears some foolish or prejudiced remark made against men of another nation, can take the opportunity of putting forward the other side of the question-- of recommending to notice their good qualities rather than their failings . Every one of us can take the opportunity of acting in an especially kindly manner toward any foreigner with whom we happen to come into contact, and feeling the great truth that when a stranger visits our country all of us stand temporarily to him in the position of hosts. If it comes in our way to go abroad-- and none to whom such an opportunity is possible should neglect it-- we must remember that we are for the moment representatives of our country to those whom we happen to meet, and that we owe it to that country to endeavour to give the best possible impression of kindliness and readiness to appreciate all the manifold beauties that will open before us, while at the same time we pass over or make the best of any points which strike us as deficiencies.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В этом может помочь каждый из нас, какими бы ограниченными не были наши силы, ибо каждый из нас может попытаться понять и принять качества наций непохожих на нашу; каждый из нас когда слышит глупость или предвзятую оценку человека другой нации может воспользоваться возможнстью и показать другую сторону вопроса — сторону хороших качеств, а не недостатков. Каждый из нас может воспользоваться возможностью действовать исключительно мягко в отношении любого иностранца, с которым нам доведётся встретиться и почувствовать великую истину, что когда страниик посещает нашу страну, все мы времененно становимся для него семьёй. Если кому либо из нас случится побывать за границей — и если появится такая возможность, не следует пренебрегать ею — мы должны помнить, что в это время мы являемся представителями нашей страны для тех, кто нам повстречался и мы должны приложить все усилия, чтобы создать наилучшее впечатление о мягкости и готовности принять все разнообразные красоты открывающиеся перед нами, в то время как мы должны обойти вниманием или выделить лучшее из того, что нам показалось неполноценным.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Another way in which we can help to prepare is by the endeavour to promote beauty in all its aspects, even in the commonest things around us. One of the most prominent characteristics of the community of the future is its intense devotion to beauty, so that even the commonest utensil is in its simple way an object of art. We should see to it that, at least within the sphere of our influence, all this is so with us at the present day; and this does not mean that we should surround ourselves with costly treasures, but rather that, in the selection of the simple necessaries of every-day life, we should consider always the question of harmony, suitability and grace. In that sense and to that extent we must all strive to become artistic; we must develop within ourselves that power of appreciation and comprehension which is the grandest feature of the artist' s character.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Ещё один способ котоым все мы можем помочь подготовке --- это желание выявить красоту во всех её аспектах, даже в самых обычных вещах которые нас окружают. Одна из выдающихся характеристик сообщества будущего это его сильное стремление к красоте, потому что даже простейшая посуда является в своём роде предметом искусства. Следует заметить, что даже в пределах нашего влияния всё это существует в наше время; это не значит, что мы должны окружать себя дорогими скоровищами; мы должны проявлять чувство гармонии в вопросах повседневной жизни. В этом смысле мы все должны стремиться к искусству, мы должны развивать в себе ту силу восприятия и понимания, которая является ключевой в характере художника.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Yet, on the other hand, while thus making an effort to evolve its good side, we must carefully avoid the less desirable qualities which it sometimes brings with it. The artistic man may be elevated clear out of his ordinary every-day self by his devotion to his art. By the very intensity of that, he has not only marvellously uplifted himself but he also uplifts such others as are capable of responding to such a stimulus. But unless he is an abnormally well-balanced man, this wonderful exaltation is almost invariably followed by its reaction, a correspondingly great depression. Not only does this stage usually last far longer than the first, but the waves of thought and feeling which it pours forth affect nearly everybody within a considerable area, while only a few (in all probability) have been able to respond to the elevating influence of the art. It is indeed a question whether many men of artistic temperament are not, on the whole, thus doing far more harm than good; but the artist of the future will learn the necessity and the value of perfect equipoise, and so will produce the good without the harm; and it is at this that we must aim.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Развивая таким образом лучшие качества, мы должны тщательно избегать менее желательные проявления которые с ними связаны. Человек искусства может полностью очистить себя от мусора обычной жизни своим стремлением к искусствам. Самим стремлением к этому он не только изумительно поднимает себя, но и других, которые способны ответить на этот стимул. Но за исключением редких случаев необычайно сбалансированных людей, такая прекрасная экзальтация почти неизменно порождает реакцию — сильную депрессию. Этот этап не только длится гораздо дольше первого, но и волны мыслей и чувств изливаемые им, действуют почти на всех на заметном расстоянии, тогда как лишь немногие способны были среагировать на возвышающее влияние искусства. Не получится ли так, что группа из многих людей искусства приносит в целом больше вреда чем пользы? Это, в самом деле, вопрос. Артисты будущего знают о необходимости и значении совершенного равновесия и потому создают добро без вреда. Это то, к чему мы сейчас должны стремиться.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It is obvious that helpers are needed for the work of the Manu and the Chief Priest, and that in such work there is room for all conceivable diversities of talent and of disposition. None need despair of being useful because he thinks himself lacking in intellect or ecstatic emotion; there is room for all, and qualities which are lacking now may be speedily developed under the special conditions which the community will provide. Goodwill and docility are needed, and perfect confidence in the wisdom and capability of the Manu; and above all the resolve to forget self utterly and to live only for the work that has to be done in the interests of humanity. Without this last, all other qualifications “water but the desert”.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Ясно, что такие помошники нужны в работе Ману и Высшего Жреца и что в такой работе есть место для всех мыслимых талантов и склонностей. Никому нет нужды отчаиватся в своей бесполезности, потому что он сам думает, будто лишён интеллекта или сильных эмоций. Есть место для всех и качества которых не хватает, могут быть быстро развиты в особых условиях предлагаемых колонией. Нужны добрая воля и восприимчивость, а также полное доверие мудрости и возможностям Ману. И, наконец, выше всех стоит умение забывать себя и жить лишь для работы которая должна быть сделана в интересах человечества. Без последнего, все остальные качества — "water but the desert".
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Those who offer themselves to help must have in some sort the spirit of an army-- a spirit of perfect self-sacrifice, of devotion to the Leader and of confidence in Him. They must above all things be loyal, obedient, painstaking, unselfish. They may have many other great qualities as well, and the more they have the better; but these at least they must have. There will be scope for the keenest intelligence, the greatest ingenuity and ability in every direction; but all these will be useless without the capacity of instant obedience and utter trust in the Masters. Self-conceit is an absolute barrier to usefulness. The man who can never obey an order because he always thinks that he knows better than the authorities, the man who cannot sink his personality entirely in the work which is given to him to do and co-operate harmoniously with his fellow-workers-- such a man has no place in the army of the Manu, however transcendent his other qualifications may be. All this lies before us to be done, and it will be done, whether we take our share in it or not; but since the opportunity is offered to us surely we shall be criminally foolish if we neglect it. Even already the preparatory work is beginning; the harvest truly is plenteous, but as yet the labourers are all too few. The Lord of the Harvest calls for willing helpers; who is there among us who is ready to respond?
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Те, кто предлагает свою помощь должны иметь что то вроде духа армии — духа полного самопожертвования, преданности Лидеру и доверия Ему. Они должны, помимо всего прочего, быть лояльными, послушными, усердными и бескорыстными. Они также могут иметь много других качества и чем больше их тем лучше, но эти должны быть обязательно. Здесь будет место для острейшего интеллекта, для величайшей гениальности и для любых других способностей, но всё это будет бесполезно без способности к немедленному подчинению и полного доверия к Учителям. Самомнение — принципиальное препятствие на пути к полезности. Человек который не считает возможным подчиниться приказу потому что думает, будто он лучше знает, что делать чем начальство, человек который не может полностью погрузиться в работу которая ему дана и гармонично сотрудничать с коллегами, не найдёт себе места в армии Ману, какими бы выдающимися ни были его остальные качества. Всё это лежит перед нами и это надо сделать; и это будет сделано, примем ли мы в этом участие или нет, но раз уж нам предлагается такая возможность, было бы крайне глупо ей пренебрегать. Уже сейчас ведётся подготовительная работа и результаты жатвы богаты, но работающих по прежнему слишком мало. Хозяин Жатвы обращается к стремящимся помошниками. Есть ли среди нас те кто готов ответить?
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en"> EPILOGUE </view>
<view lang="ru"> Эпилог </view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
IT is obvious that the outline of the Californian community and of the world of the twenty-eighth century is but an infinitesimal fragment of the ` Whither' of the road along which humanity will travel. It is an inch or two of the indefinite number of miles which stretch between us and the goal of our Chain, and even then a longer ` Whither' stretches beyond. It tells of the first small beginnings of the sixth Root Race, beginnings which bear much the same proportion to the life of that Race, as the gathering of the few thousands on the shore of the sea that washed the south-eastern part of Ruta bore to the great fifth Root Race that is now leading the world. We do not know how long a time is to elapse from those peaceful days to the years during which America will be rent into pieces by earthquakes and volcanic outbursts, and a new continent will be thrown up in the Pacific, to be the home of the sixth Root Race. We see that later the strip in the far west of Mexico, on which the community exists, will become a strip on the far east of the new continent, while Mexico and the United States will be whelmed in ruin. Gradually will that new continent be upheaved, with many a wild outburst of volcanic energy, and the land that was once Lemuria will arise from its age-long sleep, and lie again beneath the sun-rays of our earthly day.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Очевидно, что краткий обзор Калифорнийской колонии и мира 28-го века всего лишь маленький фрагмент ответа на вопрос "Куда?" — дороги по которой пойдёт человечество. Это всего лишь дюйм или два из неизвестного числа миль которые соединяют нас и цель нашей Цепи, но даже тогда ответ на вопрос "Куда?" тянется ещё дальше. Он говорит нам о первых маленьких начинаниях шестой Коренной Расы, начинаниях которые вносят в жизнь Расы столько же, сколько сбор нескольких тысяч человек на берегу моря, которое омывало юго-восточную часть острова Руты, созданный для великой пятой Коренной Расы, которая сейчас лидирует в мире. Мы не знаем, сколько времени пройдёт с тех мирных дней до момента, когда Америку расколют землетрясения и вулканы и образуется новый континент из Тихого океана, который станет домом шестой Коренной Расы. Мы видим, что полоса на дальнем западе от Мексики, где живёт колония, станет далёкой восточной частью нового континента, когда Мексика и Америка будут лежать в руинах. Постепенно этот новый континент поднимется многими мощными вулканическими выбросами и земля, когда то бывшей Лемурией, вновь проснётся из долгого сна и ляжет под лучами солнца.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It may be supposed that a very long period will be occupied by these great seismic changes, ere the new land will be ready for the new Race, and its Manu and its Bodhisattva will lead it thither.

Then will come the ages during which its seven sub-races will rise, and reign, and decay; and from the seventh the choosing of the germs of the seventh Root Race by its future Manu, and the long labours of that new Manu and of His Brother the new Bodhisattva, until it shall, in turn, grow into a definite new Race and inherit the earth. It also will have its seven sub-races, to rise, and reign, and vanish-- vanishing as the earth itself falls asleep, and passes into its fourth obscuration.

The Sun of Life will rise on a new earth, the planet Mercury, and that fair orb will pass through its day of ages, and again that Sun will set and the night will fall. A new rising, a new setting, on the globes F and G of our Round, and the ending of the Round, and the gathering of its fruits into the bosom of its Seed Manu.

Then, after long repose, the fifth, sixth and seventh Rounds, ere our terrene Chain shall vanish into the past. Then onwards yet, after an Inter-Chain Nirvana, and still there are fifth and sixth and seventh Chains yet to come and to pass away, ere the Day of the High Gods shall decline to its setting, and the soft still Night shall brood over a resting system, and the great Preserver shall repose on the many-headed serpent of Time.

But even then the ` Whither' stretches onward into the endless ages of Immortal Life. The dazzled eyes closed; the numbed brain is still. But above, below, on every side, stretches the illimitable Life who is GOD, and in Him will ever live and move and exist the children of men.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Надо полагать, что пройдёт много времени когда уляжется вся сейсмическая активность, перед тем как будет готова новая земля для новой Расы и её Ману и Бодхисаттва поведут её дальше.

Затем пройдут эпохи в течении которых седьмая подраса будет зарождаться, править и умирать. Из неё будут выбраны семена седьмой Коренной Расы её будущим Ману и последует долгая работа нового Ману и Его Брата нового Бодхисаттвы, пока она не вырастет в сформировавшуюся Расу и унаследует планету.

Солнце Жизни поднимется над новой землёй — Меркурием — и эта красивая планета пройдёт через свою череду эпох и затем опять Солнце сядет и наступит ночь.

Затем, после долгого отдыха, придут пятый, шестой и седьмой Раунды, пока наша Земная цепь не останется в прошлом. Затем, после долгой Нирваны между Цепями, придут пятая, шестая и седьмая Цепи и уйдут и День Высших Богов начнёт подходить к концу. Мягкая спокойная Ночь накроет отдыхающую систему и великий Спаситель заснёт на многоголовой змее Времени.

Но даже тогда, "Куда" тянется ещё дальше, в дали бесконечных эпох Бессмертной Жизни. Ослеплённые глаза закрыты, а оцепеневший мозг спокоен. Но вверху, внизу и с каждой стороны есть бесконечная Жизнь Бога и в Нём всегда будут жить дети человечества.
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
PEACE TO ALL BEINGS
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Мир всем существам.
</view>
</text>
</body>