<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      The Civilisation of Atlantis
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Цивилизация Атлантиса
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      ¹ A good account of this may be read in The Story of Atlantis by W. Scott-Elliot. The writers of
      the present book were among the collaborateurs who collected the materials therein so ably arranged
      and presented; so the ground is very familiar to us.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Хороший отчёт об этой цивилизации можно прочитать в "Истории Атлантиды". Авторы данной книги были
      среди сотрудников, собиравших материал, который был в ней столь удачно представлен и расположен,
      так что тема эта нам хорошо знакома.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      ATLANTIS peopled many countries with its sub-races, and built many splendid civilisations. Egypt,
      Mesopotamia, India, North and South America, knew them, and the Empires they raised endured for
      long, and reached a point of glory that the Aryan Race has not yet over-topped. The chapters
      XI-XIII on Peru and Chaldea in the present work show remnants of their greatness, and these may be
      supplemented by some additional details.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Атланты своими подрасами населяли множество стран и построили много великолепных цивилизаций. Их
      знали Египет, Месопотамия, Индия, Северная и Южная Америка, и воздвигнутые ими империи сохранялись
      долгое время, достигнув такой славы, которой арийская раса пока что не смогла превзойти. Главы
      данной работы о Перу и Халдее показывают остатки их величия, и к ним можно добавить некоторые
      дополнительные подробности.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Mr. Scott-Elliot thus describes the famous City of the Golden Gates: “A beautifully wooded
      park-like country surrounded the city. Scattered over a large area of this were the
      villa-residences of the wealthier classes. To the west lay a range of mountains, from which the
      water-supply of the city was drawn. The city itself was built on the slopes of a hill, which rose
      from the plain about five hundred feet. On the summit of this hill lay the Emperor' s palace and
      gardens, in the centre of which welled up from the earth a never-ending stream of water, supplying
      first the palace and the fountains in the gardens, thence flowing in the four directions, and
      falling in cascades into a canal or moat which encompassed the palace grounds, and thus separated
      them from the city which lay below on every side. From this canal four channels led the water
      through four quarters of the city to cascades which, in their turn, supplied another encircling
      canal at a lower level. There were three such canals forming concentric circles, the outermost and
      lowest of which was still above the level of the plain. A fourth canal at this lowest level, but on
      a rectangular plan, received the constantly flowing waters, and in it turn discharged them into the
      sea. The city extended over part of the plain, up to the edge of this great outermost moat, which
      surrounded and defended it with a line of waterways extending about twelve miles by ten miles
      square.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      М-р Скотт Эллиот так описывает знаменитый город Золотых Врат: "Великолепная лесистая местность,
      подобная парку, окружала город. Виллы представителей более богатого класса были разбросаны вокруг
      на обширном пространстве. На западе простиралась горная цепь, откуда в город поступала вода. Сам
      город был выстроен на склонах холма, который возвышался на 150 метров над равниной. На вершине
      этого холма находился дворец императора, окруженный садами, посреди которых бил ключом никогда не
      иссякающий родник воды, снабжая ею прежде всего дворец и другие фонтаны в саду, а затем,
      разделившись на четыре части, этот родник протекал по четырем различным направлениям и падал
      каскадом в нечто вроде канала или рва, окружавшего территорию дворца, отделяя таким образом его от
      города, простиравшегося внизу со всех сторон. Четыре канала, которые выходили из этого рва,
      отводили воду в четыре квартала города, образуя каскады, снабжающие в свою очередь водой следующий
      окружной канал, расположенный уровнем ниже. Было три таких канала, расположенных концентрическими
      кругами, причём внешний и самый нижний всё же лежал выше уровня равнины. Четвёртый канал,
      находившийся на этом низшем уровне, был прямоугольной формы, принимал постоянно стекающие воды и
      выносил их в море. Город занимал часть равнины до края этого большого наружного канала, окружавшего
      и защищавшего его прямоугольной водной преградой, простиравшейся в одном направлении на двенадцать,
      а в другом — на десять миль.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      “It will thus be seen that the city was divided into three great belts, each hemmed in by its
      canals. The characteristic feature of the upper belt, that lay just below the palace grounds, was a
      circular race-course and large public gardens. Most of the houses of the court officials also lay
      on this belt, and here also was an institution of which we have no parallel in modern times. The
      term ` Strangers' Home' amongst us suggests a mean appearance and sordid surroundings; but this was
      a palace where all strangers who might come to the city were entertained as long as they might
      choose to stay-- being treated all the time as guests of the Government. The detached houses of the
      inhabitants and the various temples scattered throughout the city occupied the other two belts. In
      the days of the Toltec greatness there seems to have been no real poverty-- even the retinue of
      slaves attached to most houses being well fed and clothed-- but there were a number of
      comparatively poor houses in the lowest belt to the north, as well as outside the outermost canal
      towards the sea. The inhabitants of this part were mostly connected with the shipping, and their
      houses, though detached, were built closer together than in other districts.”
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Таким образом можно видеть, что город был разделён на три больших пояса, окружавшихся каналами.
      Характерной чертой верхнего пояса, который следовал сразу же за дворцовой территорией, было круглое
      поле для скачек и огромные публичные сады. Большинство домов придворных сановников находились в
      этом же кругу; там же было и учреждение, которому нет аналогии в наши времена. Термин
      "странноприимный дом" внушает нам представление о бедном здании в убогих окрестностях, но в
      Атлантиде это был настоящий дворец, где все посещающие город иностранцы получали гостеприимство так
      долго, как это им нравилось — к ним относились, как к гостям правительства. Отдельные частные дома
      и разбросанные по городу различные храмы занимали два других пояса. Во времена величия толтеков,
      настоящей бедности, похоже, не существовало — даже свита рабов, прислуживавших в большинстве домов,
      была хорошо накормлена и одета. Однако же были конечно сравнительно бедные жилища, они находились в
      нижнем круге, на севере от города, равно как и за последним каналом, в сторону моря. Большинство
      жителей этой части города были связаны с мореходством, и их дома, хотя и не были скучены, но всё же
      стояли друг к другу ближе, чем в остальных кругах."
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Other large towns, built on the plains, were protected by immense banks of earth, sloping towards
      the town, and sometimes terraced, while, on the outward side, they were faced with thick plates of
      metal, clamped together; these were supported on great beams of wood, the uprights being driven
      deeply into the earth; when these were in place, and connected with heavy crossbars, the plates
      were attached to them, overlapping like scales, and then the space between the earth-work and the
      barrier was filled with earth, solidly rammed together. The whole formed a practically impregnable
      barrier against the spears, swords, and bows and arrows which were the usual weapons of the time.
      But such a city necessarily lay open to assaults from above, and the Atlanteans carried the making
      of air-ships-- aeroplanes, we should call them now-- to a high pitch of excellence; and, if such a
      city were to be attacked, these birds-of-war were sent to hover over it, and to drop into it bombs
      which burst in the air, and discharged a rain of heavy poisonous vapour, destructive of human life.
      Allusions to these may be found in the conflicts related in the great epics and Puranas of the
      Hindus. They had also weapons which projected sheaves of fire-tipped arrows, which scattered far
      and wide as they hurtled through the air like deadly rockets, and many others of similar kinds, all
      constructed by men well-versed in the higher branches of scientific knowledge. Many of these are
      described in the very ancient books above referred to, and they are mentioned as being given by
      some superior Being. The knowledge required for their construction was never made common.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Другие большие города, построенные на равнинах, были защищены огромными земляными валами, пологими
      в сторону города, и иногда спускающимися к нему террасами, тогда как внешняя крутая сторона была
      облицована склёпанными между собой толстыми металлическими пластинами, которые поддерживались
      деревянными балками. Столбы вкапывались глубоко в землю и соединялись тяжёлыми поперечными балками;
      к ним и крепились пластины, перекрываясь подобно чешуйкам. Затем пространство между валом и этим
      барьером также засыпалось землёй, плотно утрамбовывавшейся. Всё это образовывало практически
      неприступный барьер против копий, мечей и стрел, которые были обычным оружием того времени. Но
      такой город неизбежно оказывался открыт для нападений с воздуха, а атланты довели изготовление
      воздушных кораблей, или, как бы мы назвали их, самолётов, до высокой степени совершенства. И если
      нужно было атаковать такой город, то туда посылались эти птицы войны, сбрасывавшие на него бомбы,
      взрывавшиеся в воздухе и обрушивавшие дождь тяжёлого ядовитого пара, смертельно опасного. Намёки на
      это можно найти в описаниях столкновений, описанных в великих эпосах индусов и Пуранах. У них также
      было оружие, исторгавшее снопы стрел с огненными наконечниками, которые разлетались повсюду,
      проносясь по воздуху, как смертоносные ракеты, и много другого подобного оружия, сконструированного
      людьми, весьма сведущими в сложнейших областях научных знаний. Многие из них тоже описаны в
      упомянутых древних книгах как дары того или иного высшего существа. Знания, необходимые для их
      создания, никогда не делались общим достоянием.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The land system of the Toltecs will be described in the chapters on Peru, and the absence of
      poverty and the general well-being of the population were largely due to the provision therein made
      for universal primary education. The whole scheme of government was planned out by the Wise for the
      benefit of all, and not by special classes for their own advantage. Hence the general comfort was
      immensely higher than in modern civilisations.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Земельная система толтеков описана нами в главе о Перу, и отсутствие бедности и всеобщее
      благосостояние народа достигалось в основном благодаря всеобщему начальному образованию. Вся
      система правления была разработана мудрыми на благо всех, а не только для выгоды избранных классов.
      Потому общий комфорт был несравнимо выше, чем современных цивилизациях.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Science was carried far; for, the use of clairvoyance being habitual, the processes of nature, now
      invisible to most, were readily observed. Its applications to arts and crafts were also numerous
      and useful. The rays of sunshine, sent through coloured glass, were used for promoting the growth
      of plants and animals; scientific breeding was carefully carried out for the improvement of
      promising species; experiments were tried in crossing -- e.g., the crossing of wheat with various
      grasses produced different kinds of grain; less satisfactory were the attempts which produced wasps
      from bees; and white ants from ants.1 (¹ Wheat, bees and ants were brought from Venus by the Lords
      of the Flame, and the crossing of these with species already existing on the earth brought about
      the results named. The nature-spirits in charge of some departments of animal and vegetable
      evolution also attempted on their own account to imitate, with the purely terrestrial resources at
      their disposal, these importations from another planet. Their efforts, which were only partially
      successful, are responsible for some of the more unpleasant results above-mentioned.) The seedless
      banana was evolved from a melon-like ancestor, containing, like the melon, large quantities of
      seeds. Forces, the knowledge of which has been lost, were known to the science of the day; one of
      these was used for the propulsion of both air-- and water-ships; another for so changing the
      relation of heavy bodies to the earth that the earth repelled instead of attracting them, so making
      the raising of gigantic stones to a lofty height a matter of the greatest ease. The subtler of
      these were not applied by machinery, but were controlled by will-power, using the thoroughly
      understood and developed mechanism of the human body, “the vina of a thousand strings”.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Наука продвинулась далеко, ведь благодаря тому, что применение ясновидения было обычным делом,
      природные процессы, теперь невидимые для большинства, могли легко наблюдаться. Её применение к
      искусствам и ремёслам также было широким и полезным. Солнечные лучи, пропущенные через цветные
      стёкла, применялись для улучшения роста растений и животных,* тщательно проводилось научное
      совершенствование многообещающих видов. Проводились и эксперименты по скрещиванию пшеницы с
      различными травами для получения разных видов зерна. Менее удовлетворительными были другие попытки,
      в результате которых из пчёл получились осы, а из муравьёв — термиты.** Банан без семян был получен
      из предшественника, подобного дыне, который, как и она, имел в себе большое количество семян. Науке
      того времени были известны силы, знание которых теперь утеряно. Одна из них использовалась для
      передвижения как воздушных, так и водных судов, а другая позволяла так изменить взаимодействие
      тяжёлых тел и Земли, что вместо того, чтобы притягиваться, они отталкивались, что делало подъём
      гигантских камней на большую высоту весьма лёгким делом. Более тонкими из этих сил управляли не при
      помощи технических устройств, а силой воли, используя досконально понятый и развитый механизм
      человеческого тела, "тысячеструнную вину".
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="ru">
      * Этот эффект в XIX веке был повторно открыт в Америке и описан Э. Бэббитом в книге "Принципы света
      и цвета" — прим. пер. ** Пшеница, пчёлы и муравьи были принесены с Венеры Владыками Пламени, и их
      скрещивание с видами, уже существовавшими на Земле, дало упомянутые результаты. Природные духи, в
      ведении которых были некоторые отделы животной и растительной эволюции, тоже со своей стороны
      пытались имитировать с помощью чисто земных ресурсов, имеющихся в их распоряжении, эти
      нововведения, занесённые с другой планеты. Их попытки, которые были успешными лишь отчасти,
      ответственны за некоторые из самых неприятных вышеупомянутых результатов. — Прим. авт. (Конечно же,
      принесены были не физические виды, а те линии эволюции, для которых на Земле были образованы
      соответствующие тела — прим. пер).
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Metals were much used and admirably wrought, gold, silver and aurichalcum being those most employed
      in decoration and in domestic utensils. They were more often alchemically produced than sought for
      in the crust of the earth, and were often very artistically introduced to add richness to schemes
      of decoration, carried out in brilliant colours. Armour was gorgeously inlaid with them, and that
      used merely for show in pageants and ceremonies was often entirely made of the precious metals;
      golden helmets, breast-plates and greaves being worn on such occasions over tunics and stockings of
      the most brilliant colours-- scarlet, orange, and a very exquisite purple.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Металлы использовались широко и их обработка была достойна восхищения. Для украшения и изготовления
      домашней утвари больше всего использовались золото, серебро и орихалк. Гораздо чаще они получались
      алхимически, чем добывались в недрах Земли, и очень часто с большим искусством вводились в схемы
      украшения, добавляя богатство к их ярким цветам. Оружие богато инкрустировалось ими, и то, которое
      использовалось только для шествий и церемоний, часто целиком делалось из драгоценных металлов.
      Золотые шлемы, доспехи и наголенники надевались по таким случаям поверх туник и чулок самых ярких
      цветов — алого, оранжевого и очень изысканного пурпурного.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Food differed in different classes. The masses of the people ate meat, fish, and even reptiles--
      perhaps one should not say ` even,' remembering the turtle of our City Fathers. The carcase of an
      animal, with all its contents, was slit down the breast and stomach, and hung up over a large fire;
      when it was thoroughly cooked through it was removed from the fire, the contents were scooped out
      and, among the more refined, placed on dishes, while the rougher people gathered round the carcase
      itself; and plunged their hands into its interior, selecting toothsome dainties-- a plan which
      sometimes led to quarrels; the rest was thrown away or given to domestic animals, the flesh itself
      being considered as offal. The higher classes partook of similar food, but those belonging
      immediately to the Court made rather a secret of such banquets. The Divine King, of course, and
      those closely connected with Him, ate only food composed of grains cooked in various ways,
      vegetables, fruits, and milk, the latter being drunk as a liquid, or made into many sweet
      preparations. Fruit-juices were also largely used as drinks. Some of the courtiers and dignitaries,
      while partaking of these milder comestibles publicly, were observed quietly stealing away to their
      private chambers and feasting on more toothsome viands, among which fish, as ` high' as modern
      game, played a not inconspicuous part.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Еда подразделялась на разные классы. Народные массы ели мясо, рыбу и даже рептилий — впрочем, можно
      и не говорить "даже", если вспомнить, что и у нас отцы города лакомятся черепахой. Целая туша
      животного, со всем её содержимым, разрезалась по груди и животу и подвешивалась над большим
      костром. Когда она была полностью готова, её снимали с огня, содержимое вычерпывалось и
      раскладывалось по тарелкам — у людей более утончённых, тогда как более грубые люди собирались
      вокруг самой туши, запуская в неё руки, и вырывали кусочки повкуснее, что иногда приводило к
      ссорам. Остальное выбрасывали или бросали домашних животным — к самому мясу относились, как у нас к
      потрохам. Высшие классы употребляли подобную же пищу, но те, кто принадлежал непосредственно ко
      двору, старались держать подобные пиршества в секрете. Конечно же, божественный царь и его
      приближённые питались лишь пищей из разнообразно приготовленных зёрен, овощами, фруктами и молоком;
      последнее и пили, и готовили из него многие сладкие блюда. Фруктовые соки также в значительной мере
      использовались в качестве напитков. Можно было наблюдать, как некоторые из придворных и сановников,
      публично принимавших эту более лёгкую пищу, потом тихо пробирались в свои личные покои и лакомились
      более скоромной пищей, среди которой не последнюю роль играла рыба "с душком".
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Government was autocratic, and in the palmy days of Toltec civilisation under the Divine Kings, no
      system could have been happier for the people; but as the unchecked powers They wielded passed into
      the hands of younger souls, abuses crept in and troubles arose; for here, as everywhere, decay
      began in the corruption of the highest. The system was that Governors were held accountable for the
      welfare and happiness of their provinces, and crime or famine was regarded as due to their
      negligence or incapacity. They were drawn chiefly from the upper classes, but specially promising
      children were drafted out into the higher schools to be trained for the service of the State,
      whenever they were found. Sex was no disqualification, as it is now, for any office in the State.1
      (¹ The exclusion of women from political power in England only came, it should be remembered, with
      the growth of democracy, and the consequent idea that physical force, not intelligence or
      character, should be the basis of Government. This is the nadir of political life, as the occult
      system is its zenith.)
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Правление было самодержавным, и в дни расцвета толтекской цивилизации это правление божественных
      царей было для народа самой счастливой системой. Когда же неограниченная власть, которой они
      обладали, перешла к более молодым душам, начались злоупотребления и бедствия увеличивались, ибо
      здесь, как и везде, рыба гнила с головы. Система заключалась в том, что губернаторы отвечали за
      благоденствие и счастье своих провинций, и преступность или голод считались результатом их
      небрежности или непригодности. В основном они назначались из высших классов, но особо
      многообещающие дети, где бы они ни обнаруживались, набирались в высшие школы для подготовки к
      государственной службе. Дискриминации по половому признаку, подобной существовавшей в XIX веке, не
      было, и для женщин была доступна любая должность в государстве.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The immense growth of wealth and of luxury gradually undermined the most splendid civilisation that
      the world has yet seen. Knowledge was prostituted to individual gain, and control over the powers
      of nature was turned from service to oppression. Hence Atlantis fell, despite the glory of its
      achievements and the might of its Empires; and the leading of the world passed into the hands of a
      daughter Race, the Aryan, which, though it has to its credit many magnificent achievements in the
      past, has not yet reached the zenith of its glory and its power, and will, some centuries hence,
      rise even higher than Atlantis rose in its palmiest days.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Огромный рост богатства и роскоши постепенно подорвал самую великолепную из цивилизаций, которую
      только видел мир. Знание проституировалось для целей личной корысти, и контроль над силами природы
      вместо служения был обращён на подавление. Потому Атлантида пала, несмотря на все свои достижения и
      мощь её империй, и мировое лидерство перешло в руки дочерней, арийской расы, которая, хотя в
      прошлом и имела на своём счету множество великолепных достижений, ещё не достигла зенита своей
      славы и своего могущества, и через несколько столетий поднимется даже выше, чем возвышалась
      Атлантида в свои лучшие дни.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      We have chosen two daughter civilisations which grew up in later days, far from the great centre of
      the fourth Root Race-- one descended from the third sub-race, the Toltec, the other from the fourth
      sub-race, the Turanian-- in order to give a more vivid and detailed picture of the level reached by
      the Atlanteans. These did not form part of the investigations made in the summer of 1910, and
      chronicled in the present book; they were done during the last decade of the nineteenth century by
      the present writers, working with some other members of the T.S., whose names we are not at liberty
      to give. One of the present writers put them into the form of articles for The Theosophical Review,
      and these articles are here reprinted. in their proper place, as part of a much larger work.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Чтобы дать более яркое и детальное представление об уровне достигнутом атлантами мы выбрали две
      дочерние цивилизации которые развились позднее вдали от великого центра четвёртой коренной расы -
      одна из них произошла от третьей подрасы, от тольтеков, а другая произошла от четвёртой подрасы, от
      туранцев. Они не являются частью исследований проведённых летом 1910-го года; они были исследованы
      в течении последнего десятилетия 19-го века настоящими писателями вместе с некоторыми членами Т.О.,
      чьи имена у нас нет свободы разглашать. Один из них изложил их в виде статей для Теософического
      Обзора и здесь эти статьи перепечатаны в нужном месте в рамках гораздо более обширной работы.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
