<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Early stages of the fourth round</view>
<view lang="ru">Начало Четвёртого Раунда</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
IN taking a preliminary bird' s-eye view of the fourth Round, one important and far-reaching change is apparent in the surroundings amid which human evolution is to proceed. In the three preceding Rounds the elemental essence was practically untouched by man, and was affected only by the Devas, or Angels, by whose influences it evolved. Man was not sufficiently developed to affect it to any serious extent. But in this Round man' s influence plays a very important part, and his self-centred thoughts create swirls in the elemental essence surrounding him. The elementals, also, begin to show more hostility to him, as he emerges from the animal state into the dominating human, for he is, from their standpoint, no longer an animal among animals, but an independent and domineering entity, likely to be hostile and aggressive.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Поверхностный обзор четвёртого Раунда выявляет одно важное изменение с далеко идущими последствиями которое выделяется среди окружения человеческой эволюции. В трёх предыдущих Раундах человек практически не трогал элементальную эссенцию, которая подвергалась исключительному влиянию Дэв или Ангелов и эволюционировала под их присмотром. Человек ещё не был развит в той мере, чтобы заметно повлиять на неё. Однако уже в этом Раунде человеческое влияние играет очень важную роль, его мысли о самом себе создают вихри в элементальной эссенции которые кружат вокруг создателя. Элементалы также начинают проявлять враждебность к человеку, потому что он превратился из животного в доминирущего человека и с их точки зрения он перестал быть животным среди животных, а стал независимым и господствующим видом, к тому же весьма агрессивным и враждебным.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Another most important characteristic of the fourth Round, the midmost of the seven, is that, in it, the door was shut against the animal kingdom, and the door was opened to the Path. Both statements are general; here and there an animal, by very special help, may still be evolved to a point where a human incarnation is possible for it, but in almost all cases no human body can now be found of sufficiently low development for its embodiment; so also might a man who had attained Arhatship or more on the Moon Chain climb yet higher, but all below that rank who had complete causal bodies did not enter into evolution on the Earth Chain until the later third and early fourth Root Races.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Другая наиболее важная характеристика четвёртого Раунда, центрального среди семи, состоит в том, что дверь перед животным царством закрылась, а дверь в Путь открылась. Оба утверждения носят общий характер; любое животное, получив достаточно содействия, всё ещё может развиться так, что человеческая инкарнация станет для него возможной, но в большинстве случаев для такого животного не найдётся человеческого тела, развитого достаточно слабо, чтобы бывшее животное смогло его одушевить. Тоже самое верно и для людей: любой кто достиг Архатсва или ещё более высокой ступени на Лунной Цепи может взобраться ещё выше, но все те, кто ниже этого уровня, хотя и завершили построение каузального тела, не смогут войти в Земную Цепь до тех пор, пока на Земле не появится поздняя третяя или ранняя четвёртая коренные расы.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
On Mars in the fourth Round we find a number of savages who had not been sufficiently advanced to leave that globe for the Earth when the mass of the egos went on in the preceding Round. On each globe some fail to go on, and remain behind as the globe begins its period of obscuration; and they return to this same globe when again it recommences full activity, and form a very backward class; these were Basket-works of a very poor kind, and were savages of the brutal and cruel type, some of those who had individualised through fear and anger.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
На Марсе в этом Раунде мы нашли некоторое число дикарей, всё ещё недостаточно развитых, чтобы покинуть эту планету и перейти на Землю в основном потоке эго. На каждой планете были те, кто не смогли пройти дальше и остались позади на то время пока эта планета находилась в тени, и вернулись на неё же вновь, когда она в очередной раз вышла на свет; они образовали самый нижний класс. Среди них были "корзины" самого бедного типа и дикари, самые лютые и жестокие, те которые индивидуализировались черех страх и злость.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Mars, in the fourth Round, felt the stress of scarcity of water, and it was the Lords of the Moon-- Arhats who had attained on Globe E-- who planned out the system of canals, and the Basket-works who executed them under Their direction. The Martian seas are not salt, and the polar snowcaps, as they melt, supply the water necessary for irrigation, and thus enable the ground to be cultivated, and crops to be raised.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В этот период Марс испытывал нехватку воды и Лорды Луны — архаты, которые достигли этого уровня на планете E — спланировали систему каналов, а "корзины" её построили под их руководством. Марсианские моря были пресными, а полярные шапки, постепенно тая, обеспечивали необходимую воду для ирригации, позволяя возделывать землю и собирать урожай.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The fifth Martian Root Race was white, and made considerable progress, and the Basket-work developed into a complete causal body. They were good, well-meaning, and kindly, though not capable of any large ideas, of widely spread feelings of affection, or of self-sacrifice. At a quite early stage, they began to divide food instead of fighting over it, developing the social feeling to some extent.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Пятая Марсианская Коренная Раса была белой; она сделала большой шаг вперёд и "корзины" превратились в полноценные каузальные тела. Они были добрыми и хорошими, хотя и не способными к восприятию какой-либо сложной идеи или к самопожертвованию. На весьма раннем этапе они научились делить пищу, а не биться за неё, и развили некоторое подобие социального строя.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The first and second Root Races on the Earth were going on before Mars was deserted, some entities being available for these primitive conditions whom Mars in its later stages was too advanced to accommodate, and the full attention of the LOGOS not being turned on to the Earth in these early times. The Lords of the Moon-- Arhats who had achieved on globe D of the lunar Chain-- brought into these early Races a number of backward entities, so that these served as special coaches for the laggards, many of whom repaid the care bestowed upon them, and entered the first sub-race of the third Root Race, as its lowest types; they were egg-headed, with an eye at the top of their heads, a roll like a sausage representing a forehead, and prognathous jaws. The egg-headed type persisted for a very long time, but became much modified in the later sub-races of this third Root Race, and specimens of them are found in later Lemurian times, The blue people who formed the powerful sixth sub-race, and the white who composed the seventh sub-race, were finer types, but were still Lemurian, and showed a trace of egg-headedness, due to the retreating foreheads.1 (¹ While this is going through the press a report has appeared in the newspapers of the discovery of some skulls of this type, but no particulars are yet available. See The Theosophist for August, 1912, in ` On the Watch-Tower,' p.631.) The population of the Earth during the first and second Root Races was very limited, and this special help appears to have been given because in the fourth globe of the fourth Chain “the door is shut”. Furthermore, everything possible was done to bring forward all of whom anything could be made, before the coming of the Lords of the Flame, in the middle of the third Root Race, should make the gulf well-nigh impassable between the human and animal kingdoms.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Первая и вторая Коренные Расы покинули Землю до того как Марс опустел, было некоторое число существ для этих примитивных условий, для которых Марс, в свои поздние года, был слишком развит; в те времена Земля ещё не привлекала всё внимание Логоса. Лорды Луны — те, которые достигли архатства на планете D лунной Цепи — принесли в эти ранние Расы некоторое количество backward entities, чтобы те выполняли роль особых тренеров для отстающих, многие из которых были благодарны за проявленную помощь и вошли в первую подрасу третьей Коренной Расы в качестве самых примитивных членов. У них была голова похожая на яйцо с одним глазом наверху, лоб в виде округлости напоминающей колбасу и выступающие челюсти. Яйцеголовые сохранялись на протяжении большого периода, хотя значительно изменились в поздних подрасах третьей Коренной Расы, а его представители были найдены в поздние лемурийские времена. Синие люди, которые образовали могущественную шестую подрасу и белые, которые образовали седьмую, были лучше, но всё ещё оставались лемурийскими, с признаками яйцеголовости и покатым лбом. Население Земли в течении первой и второй Коренных Рас было очень ограничено и на четвёртой планете четвёртой Цепи "дверь" была закрыта, поэтому понадобилась такая особая помощь. Более того, делалось всё возможное для того, чтобы протащить вперёд любого из кого мог выйти хоть какой-то толк, перед прибытием Лордов Огня в середине третьей Коренной Расы, которые сделают проход между животным и человеческим царствами почти непроходимым.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Mars, at the end of its seventh Root Race, had a very considerable population to pour into the Earth, and these came streaming in for the third Root Race, to head it until the more advanced egos from the Moon Chain should come in to take over the leadership. These Basket-works, whose causal bodies were now completed, had made considerable progress on Mars, and they now prepared the way for the more advanced people who were soon to arrive. It was they who fought with the savage reptilian creatures, slimy and backboneless, who were the “water-men terrible and bad” of the Stanzas of Dzyan, the re-embodied remnants of the previous Rounds, who had been ` water-men,' i.e., amphibious, scaly, half-human animals, on Mars.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Марс, в конце своей седьмой Расы, имел значительное население которое влилось в третью земную Расу чтобы возглавить её до тех пор, пока не придут более развитые эго из лунной Цепи чтобы повести всех за собой. Эти "корзины", чьи каузальные тела уже были завершены, показали заметный прогресс на Марсе и теперь готовили путь для более продвинутых людей которые должны были скоро прибыть. Это были те, кто сражался с дикими рептилеобразными созданиями, скользкие и безпозвоночные, вновь воплощённые остатки предыдущих Раундов, амфибии, полулюди-полуживотные.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The many schemes of reproduction characteristic of the third Round reappear in this third Root Race, and run simultaneously in various parts of the Earth. The bulk of the population passed on through the successive stages and became mostly oviparous, but there were various little side-shows in which earlier methods persisted. It seems as though the various schemes of reproduction were suitable to egos at different stages of evolution, and were kept going for laggards after the bulk of the people had passed beyond them. The egg-scheme was dropped very slowly; the shell became thinner and thinner, the human being within developing into a hermaphrodite; then he became a hermaphrodite with one sex predominant; and then a unisexual being. These changes began some sixteen and a half million years ago, and occupied some five and a half to six million years, physical bodies changing very slowly and reversion frequently occurring. Moreover the original number was small, and needed time for multiplication. When this last type became quite stable, then the egg was preserved within the feminine body, and reproduction assumed the form which still persists.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Различные способы размножения которые имели место в третьем Раунде начали встречаться в третьей Коренной Расе четвёртого Раунда; эти способы были распространены по всей планете не мешая друг другу. Большая часть населения прошла несколько последовательных стадий развития и пришла к размножению с помощью откладывания яиц, хотя ещё оставались существа размножавшиеся другими методами, заимствованными из более ранних времён. Казалось, что разные методы размножения выбирались так, чтобы соответсвовать развитию каждого отдельного эго; необычные методы всё ещё были распространены среди отстающих. Очень медленно уходили яйцекладущие существа, им на смену приходили люди-гермафродиты которых сменяли гермафродиты с одним доминирующим полом и лишь затем пришли однополые люди. Эти изменения начались примерно 16,5 миллионов лет назад и длились 5,5-6 миллионов лет; тела эволюционировали медленно, часто делая шаг назад в развитии. Когда последний вид размножения стал стабилен, яйца остались только внутри женских тел и размножение приняло ту форму которую она имеет по сей день.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
To sum up: we have the first Root Race, repeating the first Round, etheric clouds drifting about in a hot heavy atmosphere, which enclosed a world rent by recurrent cataclysms; these multiplied by fission. The second Root Race, repeating the second Round, was of the ` pudding-bag' type, described under the second Round; these multiplied by budding. The early third Root Race, repeating the third Round, was human-gorilla in form, and reproduction was at first by extrusion of cells, the ` sweat-born' of The Secret Doctrine . Then comes the oviparous stage, and finally the unisexual.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Подведём итог. Первая Коренная Раса повторяет первый Раунд: эфирные облака дрейфуют в раскалённой атмосфере планеты раздираемой катаклизмами; они размножаются делением. Вторая Коренная Раса повторяет второй Раунд: люди-мешки размножаются почкованием. Ранная третья Коренная Раса повторяет третий Раунд: гориллоподобные люди размножаются отделенем органов. В конце приходят яйцекладующие, которых сменяют однополые существа.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Some very special treatment was applied to some of the eggs; they were taken away by the Lords of the Moon, and were carefully magnetised and kept at an equable temperature, until the human form, at this stage a hermaphrodite, broke out; it was then specially fed and carefully developed, and when ready, was taken possession of by one of the Lords of the Moon, many of whom became incarnate in order to work on the physical plane, and they used these carefully prepared bodies for a long period of time; some Devas also took some of these prepared bodies. This seems to have been only a few centuries before the separation of the sexes.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Некоторые яйца получили особое внимание: их забрали Лорды Луны, магнетизировали своим влиянием и выдержали в идеальной температуре; когда человеческое тело-гермафродит выросло внутри яйца и сломало оболочку, оно было особым образом выращено, чтобы быть в идеальном состоянии к тому моменту, когда один из Лордов одушевит его для выполнения определённой работы на физическом плане. Некоторые из Дэв также одушевляли такие человеческие тела. Всё это происходило всего лишь за несколько столетий до разделения полов.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
While the later Egg-borns were in possession, the very best of the Basket-works came in, straight from the Inter-Chain Nirvana, and these were quickly followed by the lowest of those who had gained complete causal bodies on the Moon. Between the highest of the first and the lowest of the second there was but little difference. The first boat-load of the latter consisted of those who had responded but little to the influence of the Seed-Manu, from globes G, F, and E of the lunar Chain, the majority being from G, the stupidest of those who had gained complete causal bodies. The second boat-load had a large number from globe G, a low section from globe F, and a still lower from globe E. The third contained the best from globe G, with some fairly good from globe F, and good from globe E. The fourth boat-load had the best from globe F, and all but the very best of globe E. The fifth boat-load brought the best from globe E, with a few from globe D. These all seemed to be sorted out by ` age' rather than by ` type,' and were, in fact, of all types. One individual was noticed who was a chief in the savage mainland tribe which took Mars prisoner on the Moon, one who had individualised through fear. All these incarnated among the Egg-borns, some hundreds of thousands of them.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Пока последние "рождённые в яйце" были одушевлены, лучшие из "корзин" пришли прямо из промежуточной Нирваны, и сразу за ними — худшие из тех, кто завершил построение каузального тела на Луне. Между лучшими из первой категории и худшими из второй есть небольшая разница. Первая группа прибывших второй категории состояла из тех, что откликнулся, но крайне слабо, на влияние Seed Ману; они пришли с планет G, F и E лунной Цепи (большая часть пришла с G) — самые глупые из всех, кто имел завершённой каузальное тело. Вторая группа содержала большое число людей с планеты G, худших с планеты F и ещё более невосприимчивых с планеты E. Третья группа состояла из лучших с планеты G, очень хороших с планеты F и хороших с E. Четвёртая группа была набрана из лучших с F и всех, кроме самых восприимчивых, с планеты E. Наконец пятая группа вобрала в себя лучших с планеты E и некоторых с D. Кажется, что их сортировали скорее по возрасту, чем по типу, потому-что среди них были люди всех типов. Один из них был когда-то лидером банды дикарей которые взяли Марса в плен на Луне, другой индивидуализировался при помощи страха. Все они — сотни тысяч — получили инкарнацию среди "рождённых в яйце".
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then came, from ten to eleven million years ago, when separation of the sexes was fully established, the important stage when some of these incarnated Lords of the Moon descended on the seven-pointed Lemurian Polar Star, and formed etheric images of themselves, which were then materialised into greater density, multiplying these for the use of the incoming egos; the Lords were of different types, the “seven men each on his lot,” and gave bodies suited to the seven Rays, or temperamental types of humanity, making the forms on the points of the Star.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Затем пришёл, 10-11 миллионов лет назад, когда разделение полов у людей было завершено, важный этап в эволюции; некоторые из Лордов Луны вернувшихся на физический план спустились по лучам семиконечной Лемурийской Полярной Звезды и создали свои образы из эфирной материи, чтобы те материализовались на физическом плане и размножились, дав подходящие тела прибывающим эго. Лорды Луны принадлежали к разным типам людей и создали тела разных типов — семь тел соответствующих семи Лучам, семи темпераментам человечества.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At this stage there were four human classes, pressing on each other to obtain better human forms. These were: (1) the set of the best Basket-works above-named, with the five boat-loads from globes G, F, and E, possessing complete causal bodies; then (2) the Basket-works from Mars; then (3) the Lines, who had been here all the time; then (4) the last, composed of those who were only now coming up out of the animals. Below these were the animals, plants, and minerals, with which we need not concern ourselves.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
На этом этапе было четыре класса людей, конкурирующих друг с другом для получения лучших человеческих форм: <ol><li>Лучшие из "корзин" упоминавшихся ранее и пять групп с планет G, F и E, обладающие полными каузальными телами.</li><li>"Корзины" с Марса.</li><li>"Линии" которые были здесь всё время.</li><li>Только что индивидуализировавшиеся из животных. Ниже них находятся животные, растения и минералы которых мы сейчас не рассматриваем.</li></ol>
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The coming of these into the etheric forms provided by the Lords of the Moon was something of a struggle, for there were often many claimants for a single form, and the one who succeeded in gaining it could not always hold it for more than a few moments; the scene recalls the Greek idea that the Gods made the world amid shouts of laughter, for it decidedly had its comic element, as the egos struggled for the forms and could not manage them when they had obtained them. It is one of the descents into matter, the final materialisation of the body of man, the completion of ` the fall of man' . Gradually they became accustomed to the new ` coats of skin,' and settled down to reproduce the seven great temperamental types. In various parts of the world other ways of reproduction continued for long periods of time; the successive stages over-lapped very much, owing to the great differences in evolution, and the classes that came in from other Rounds had not been in the two early Root Races on Earth; the tribes following the early methods gradually became sterile, while the true men and women multiplied greatly, until humanity, as we know it now, was definitely established all over the world.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Вселение в эти эфирные формы созданные Лордами Луны было похоже на битву: несколько желающих претендовало на одну форму и тот, кому удавалось захватить её не мог оставаться в ней вечно; эта сцена напоминала греческую легенду о Богах которые создали мир посреди криков и смеха, потому что дерущиеся эго выглядели очень забавно. Лишь один спускался в материю в виде человека. Постепенно они привыкли к "костюму из кожи" и породили семь великих типов темперамента. В разных частях мира всё ещё оставались разнообразные способы размножения; последовательные стадии эволюции заметно пересекались из-за больших различий в путях развития; так, например, группы эго которые пришли из других Раундов не были в двух ранних Коренных Расах; те племена которые следовали устаревшим методам размножения со временем становились бесплодными и вымирами; мужчины и женщины быстро размножались сделав человечество таким, каким мы его знаем сейчас — доминирующим видом на планете.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The forms as thrown off by the Lords of the Moon were fairly good-looking, but being etheric they were very readily modifiable, and the incoming egos much distorted them; the children born of them were distinctly ugly; probably those using them were accustomed to think of the egg-shaped head and sausage-roll forehead, and hence these reappeared.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Лорды Луны создали очень эстетичные эфирные формы, но эфирная материя легко поддаётся изменениям и те эго, которые вселились в них сильно исказили первоначальный вид — новорождённые дети были определённо безобразны. Возможно новые владельцы форм привыкли к яйцеголовым людям с выпирающим лбом и дали потомство сообразно их представлениям о красоте.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After many generations of well-established human beings, descended from the etheric materialised forms, had been evolved, the Arhats urged on those who had left globes A, B, and C of the lunar Chain-- because they could make no further progress on it-- that they should descend and take incarnation in the bodies now ready for their indwelling. There were three boat-loads of these; more than two million orange people from globe A, rather less than three million golden-yellow from globe B, and rather more than three million pink from globe C-- about nine millions in all; they were guided to different areas of the world' s surface, with the view that they should form tribes. The orange, on seeing the bodies offered to them, refused to enter, not out of any wickedness but from pride, disdaining the unattractive forms, and perhaps also from their ancient hatred of sexual unions; but the yellow and pink were docile and obeyed, gradually improving the bodies they inhabited. These made the fourth Lemurian sub-race, the first which was in any sense, except the embryonic, human; and it may be dated from the giving of the forms. It is interesting to notice that H. P. Blavatsky in The Secret Doctrine speaks of this fourth sub-race as ` yellow,' apparently noting the incoming of the golden-yellow people from B of the Moon Chain; she can hardly have been referring to the established colour of the fourth sub-race, as that was black, and the black continued even in the lower classes of the sixth sub-race, in which the higher classes were of a quite respectable blue. Yet even in those there was an underlying tinge of black.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Многие поколения спустя, когда люди, когда-то материализовавшиеся из эфирных форм, немного эволюционировали, Архаты подтолкнули тех, кто покинули планеты A, B и C лунной Цепи — поскольку те не могли больше развиваться на них — чтобы они приняли инкарнацию в телах уже готовых для них. Три группы, общей численностью девять миллионов человек — два миллиона оранжевых с планеты A, чуть менее трёх миллионов золотисто-жёлтых с B и более трёх миллионов розовых с планеты C — были распределны по разным ареалам нового для них мира где они должны были создать племена. Оранжевые, посмотрев на тела предложенные им, отказались войти в новый мир, исключительно из гордости и презрения к несимпатичным формам, а также, возможно, из-за древней ненависти к брачным союзам. Жёлтые и розовые были более послушны и подчинились, постепенно улучшая тела которыми овладели. Они образовали четвёртую Лемурийскую подрасу, первую, во всех смыслах, не считая её эмбриональности, человеческую расу. Интересно заметить, что Е.П.Блаватская в "Тайная Доктрина" пишет об этой четвёртой подрасе как о "жёлтой", несомненно указывая на прибывающих золотисто-жёлтых эго с планеты B лунной Цепи; она едва ли могла указывать на установившийся цвет этой подрасы, ибо он был чёрным и не изменился даже в шестой расе у низших классов, в которой, правда, высшие классы имели несомненно более приемлимый синий цвет, хотя даже они имели проблески чёрного.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The area allotted to the orange tribe was thus left open, and the bodies they should have used were gladly seized upon by the entities just emerging from the animal kingdom, the lowest of the classes before mentioned, the very poorest human type; these, not unnaturally, felt little difference between themselves and the ranks from which they had just emerged, and hence arose the “sin of the mindless”.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Ареал отведённый для оранжевого племени оставлася открытым и тела, которыми они должны были овладеть, с удовольствием оказались захвачены эго только что вышедшими из животного царства — низший из всех упоминавшихся классов людей. Они чувствовали, небезосновательно, малую разницу между собой и новым видом который они вдруг обнаружили.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It is interesting to note the karma of this refusal of the orange people to take their due place in the work of peopling the world. Later, the law of evolution forced them into incarnation, and they had to take lower and coarser bodies, the Lords of the Moon having gone on into other work; they thus became a backward race, cunning but not good, and passed through many unpleasant experiences; they diminished in number by constantly coming into collision with the common order, and being hammered, largely by suffering, into ordinary folk. A few-- strong, remorseless and unscrupulous-- became Lords of the Dark Face in Atlantis; some were seen among the North American Indians with refined but hard faces; some few still persist, even down to our own day-- the unscrupulous among the kings of finance, statesmen like Bismarck, conquerors like Napoleon; but they are gradually disappearing, for they have learned many bitter lessons. Those who are wanting in heart, who are always fighting, always opposing everything everywhere, on general principles, must ultimately, in a realm of law, be beaten into shape; a very few may end in black magic, but the steady pressure is too great for the majority. It is a hard road to choose for progress!
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Интересно посмотреть на карму оранжевых которую они создали своим отказом занять полагающееся место в очеловечивании мира. Позже, Лорды Луны занялись другой работой, а закон эволюции заставил их принять инкарнацию и они заняли ещё более грубые тела; они образовали отстающую расу, хитрую и нехорошую, которая прошла через многие неприятные испытания; раса постоянно уменьшалась в размерах в столкновениях с обычными препятствиями и её члены со временем преобразились, часто через страдания, в обычных людей. Очень немногие — сильные, беcпощадные и беспринципные — стали Тёмными Лордами в Атлантисе; некоторые были замечены среди серевоамериканских индейцев с изящными, но жёсткими лицами; некоторые существуют даже в наши дни — беспринципные короли финансов, управленцы вроде Бисмарка, завоеватели вроде Наполеона; но и они постепенно исчезают, усвоив много горьких уроков. Те кто желают всем сердцем, кто всегда сражаются против всего на свете из принципа, обязательно потерпят полное поражение; очень немногие могут закончить чёрной магией, но огромное давление закона эволюции слишком велико даже для них. Это трудная дорога чтобы выбирать её вместо прогресса!
</view>
</text>

<text class="subtitle">
<view lang="en">The coming of the lords of the flame</view>
<view lang="ru">Пришествие Лордов Огня</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The great Lemurian Polar Star was still perfect, and the huge Crescent still stretched along the equator, including Madagascar. The sea which occupied what is now the Gobi Desert still broke against the rocky barriers of the northern Himalayan slopes, and all was being prepared for the most dramatic moment in the history of the Earth-- the Coming of the LORDS OF THE FLAME.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Великая Лемурийская Полярная Звезда была по прежнему совершенна, а огромный Полумесяц всё также тянулся через экватор, захватывая Мадагаскар. На том месте где сейчас располагается пустыня Гоби было море, а его волны бились о северные склоны Гималайских гор. Всё готовилось к самому грандиозному моменту в истории Земли — пришествию Лордов Огня.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Lords of the Moon and the Manu of the third Root Race had done all that was possible to bring men up to the point at which the germ of mind could be quickened, and the descent of the ego could be made. All the laggards had been pushed on; there were no more in the animal ranks capable of rising into man. The door against further immigrants into the human kingdom from the animal was only shut when no more were in sight, nor would be capable of reaching it without a repetition of the tremendous impulse only given once in the evolution of a Scheme, at its midmost point.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Лорды Луны и Ману третьей Коренной Расы сделали всё возможное, чтобы привести человека к той ступени с которой можно было оживить зачатки разума и позволить спуститься в них эго. Все отстающиме получили толчок и ни одно животное больше не было способно вырасти до человека. Дверь перед иммигрантами из животного царства в человеческое была закрыта, ибо для её достижения нужен сильнейший импульс помощи который даётся лишь однажды в эволюции Схемы — в её средней точке.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A great astrological event, when a very special collocation of planets occurred and the magnetic condition of the Earth was the most favourable possible, was chosen as the time. It was about six and a half million years ago. Nothing more remained to be done, save what only They could do.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Моментом пришествия было выбрано грандиозное астрологическое событие, когда планеты выстроились в очень редком положении и Земля оказалась в наиболее благоприятных магнетических условиях. Не осталось ничего, что не было бы сделано и следующий ход сделали Они.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then, with the mighty roar of swift descent from incalculable heights, surrounded by blazing masses of fire which filled the sky with shooting tongues of flame, flashed through the aerial spaces the chariot of the Sons of the Fire, the Lords of the Flame from Venus; it halted, hovering over the ` White Island,' which lay smiling in the bosom of the Gobi Sea; green was it, and radiant with masses of fragrant many-coloured blossoms, Earth offering her best and fairest to welcome her coming King. There He stood, “the Youth of sixteen summers,” Sanat Kumara, the “Eternal Virgin-Youth,” the new Ruler of Earth, come to His kingdom, His Pupils, the three Kumaras, with Him, His Helpers around Him; thirty mighty Beings were there, great beyond Earth' s reckoning, though in graded order, clothed in the glorious bodies They had created by Kriyashakti, the first Occult Hierarchy, branches of the one spreading Banyan-Tree, the nursery of future Adepts, the centre of all occult life. Their dwelling-place was and is the Imperishable Sacred Land, on which ever shines down the Blazing Star, the symbol of Earth' s Monarch, the changeless Pole round which the life of our Earth is ever spinning.¹
</view>
<view lang="ru">
И тогда, с грандиозным рёвом в стремительном спуске с необозримых высот, окружённая массами слепящего огня который осветил небо сполохами пламени, сквозь плотные облака прорвалась колесница Сынов Огня, Лордов Пламени с Венеры; она остановилась и нависла над Белым Островом который лежал посреди моря Гоби, утопающий в зелени и светящийся красотой благоухающих цветков всех цветов; Земля предстала во всём великолепии перед свои Королём. Он ступил на землю, вечномолодой шестнадцатилетний юноша, Санат Кумара, новый правитель Земли. Его Ученики, три Кумары, стояли посреди своих Помошников. Тридцать могущественных существ которых не знала Земля были одеты в восхитительные тела созданные силой Крияшакти. Это была первая Оккультная Иерархия, колыбель будущих Адептов и центр всей оккультной жизни. Их обителью была выбрана и является до сих пор Неизменная Священная Земля на которую сияет Пылающая Звезда, символ Земного Монарха или Полюс, вокруг которого всегда вращалась земная жизнь.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
¹ The use of these occult symbols misled the readers of The Secret Doctrine, (perhaps even its writer) into the mistake that the ` Pole' and ` Star' mentioned in the Occult Commentary were the physical North Pole and North Star. I followed this mistaken idea in my Pedigree of Man. -- A.B.
</view>
<view lang="ru">

</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A Catechism says: “Out of the seven Kumaras, four sacrificed themselves for the sins of the world, and the instruction of the ignorant, to remain till the end of the present Manvantara. . . . These are the Head, the Heart, the Soul and the Seed of undying knowledge.” H. P. Blavatsky adds: “Higher than the ` Four' is only ONE on Earth as in Heaven-- that still more mysterious and solitary Being”-- the Silent Watcher.1 (¹ The Secret Doctrine, (1897 Edition) ii, 294, 295; (Adyar Edition) iii, 282, 283.)
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Катехизм говорит: "Из семи Кумар четыре пожертвовали собой за грехи мира, а оставшиеся обучали невежд до конца настоящей Манвантары... Это были Голова, Сердце, Душа и Семя бессмертного знания". Е.П.Блаватская добавляет: "Выше Четырёх есть лишь Один на Земле и на Небесах — ещё более таинственное и одинокое существо — Безмолвный Наблюдатель".
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Until the Coming of the Lords the shiploads from the Inter-Chain Nirvana had arrived separately, but now, with the tremendous stimulus given, fecundity increased rapidly like everything else, and perfect fleets were wanted to bring in egos to inhabit the bodies; these came pouring in, while others of lower types took possession of all the animals with the germs of mind who were individualised at the Coming, the Lords of the Flame doing in a moment for millions what we now do by long care for units.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
До пришествия Лордов группы с Нирваны Внутренней Цепи прибывали раздельно, но после него — грандиозного импульса — изобилие быстро и повсеместно росло и потребовались целые флотилии развитых эго готовых одушевить новые тела; они продолжали вливаться, пока другие, менее продвинувшиеся, становились владельцами животных с зачатками разума которые были индивидуализированы Пришествием. Лорды Пламени в каждое мгновение помогали миллионам, в то время как нам сейчас нужны долгие годы для помощи немногим.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
And now the Arhats from globes A, B, and C came into incarnation, to help the Manu in founding and civilising the fifth, sixth and seventh sub-races of the Lemurians. The fourth sub-race continued, the very egg-headed one, with a stature of from twenty-four to twenty-seven feet in height, loosely and clumsily built, and black in colour; one whom we measured was twenty-five feet in height.² Their buildings were proportionate to their size, cyclopean in structure, made of enormous stones.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Теперь Архаты с планет A, B и C приняли инкарнацию, чтобы помочь Ману основать и цивилизовать пятую, шестую и седьмую подрасы лемурийцев. Четвёртая подраса продолжалась; один был очень яйцеголовым с ростом 24-27 футов (пересчёт в метры на wolframalpha.com — прим. перев.), неуклюже и грубо построенный, чёрного цвета; другой которого мы измерили был 25-футов в высоту. Их строения были им под стать, такие же циклопические, сделанные из громадных камней. Вам, возможно, интересно узнать как мы их измерили. Для начала мы подошли к нему и оказались на уровне его колена, затем мы поставили его напротив балкона первого этажа штаб-квартиры где он мог положить свои руки и подбородок на перила, позже мы измерили высоту балкона. Непредвиденное появление его головы не вызвало чувства радости у владельца балкона: "Уберите его отсюда", сказал владелец, "он очень безобразен и способен напугать кого угодно своим видом!". Возможно, наша идея была не самой удачной.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
² Some curiosity may arise as to how we measured him: first by standing by him, when we came, respectively, a little below and level with his knee; then by setting him against a first-floor balcony at Headquarters, where he could rest his raised hands on the parapet and put his chin on them. We later measured the height of the parapet. The poor image was not made welcome when he put his head over the balcony: “Take him away,” said the owner of the balcony; “he is very ugly and enough to frighten anybody.” Perhaps he was, poor thing.
</view>
<view lang="ru">

</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Arhats became Kings in the later sub-races, the King-Initiates of the myths which are truer than history.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Архаты стали Королями-Посвящёнными в поздних подрасах. Они породили мифы которые оказались правдивее истории.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A King-Initiate would gather a number of persons round Him, forming a clan, and then would teach this clan some of the arts of civilisation, and direct and help them in the building of a city. One large city was erected under such instruction on what is now the island of Madagascar, and many others were similarly built, over the great Crescent. The style of architecture was, as said above, cyclopean, impressive from its hugeness.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Король-Посвящённый собирал несколько людей вокруг себя и создавал из них клан который обучался у него искусствам цивилизации, а также помогал строить город. Один такой город был возведён под его контролем и сейчас мы его знаем как Мадагаскар. Многие другие города были построены таким же образом. Архитектурный стиль был, как уже говорилось, циклопический, впечатляющий своим размахом.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
During the long period thus occupied, the physical appearance of the Lemurians was changing. The central eye at the top of the head was retreating, as it ceased to function, from the surface to the interior of the head, to form the pineal gland, while the two eyes-- at first one on each side of it-- were becoming active. The Greek legend of Cyclops is evidently a tradition from the early Lemurian age.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В течении многих лет физический облик лемурийцев менялся. Центральный глаз на макушке скрылся внутрь головы, перестал действовать и сформировал шишковидную железу, в то время как два глаза по его сторонам начали видеть. Греческие легенды о циклопах, очевидно, передавались с ранних лемурийских времён.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
There was some domestication of animals; one egg-headed Lemurian was seen leading about a scaly monster, almost as unattractive as his master. Animals of all sorts were eaten raw-- among some tribes human flesh was not despised-- and creatures of the grade of our slugs, snails and worms, much larger than their degenerate descendants, were regarded with peculiar favour as toothsome morsels.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Некоторые животные приручались; один яйцеголовый лемуриец был замечен на природе, ведя за собой чешуйчатого монстра, почти такого же непривлекательного как и его хозяин. Животные всех видов пожирались без разбору, а в некоторых племенах не отказывались даже от человеческого мяса. Создания похожие на наших слизняков, червей и улиток, только большие в размерах чем их существенно деградировавшие потомки, считались особым деликатесом.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
While the sixth sub-race was developing, a large number of Initiates and their disciples were sent off from the Inter-Chain Nirvana to the Earth,1 (¹It may be noted that while the general rule was that the less evolved should be sent first to the Earth. exceptions were made where help was wanted, as in this case with this special boatload.) to help the Manu of the fourth Root Race by incarnating in the best bodies He had so far evolved. The very best bodies being given to those who had exhausted their karma, their occupants were able to improve them, and to get out of them everything which they were capable of yielding. These Arhats and their pupils worked under the Lords of the Moon and the Manus of the third and fourth Root Races; the seventh sub-race, the bluish-white, was evolved by their help, and furnished men and women of a better type for further moulding by the Manu of the fourth.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Пока шестая подраса развивалась, большоё число Посвящённых и их последователей были отправлены с Внутренней Нирваны (Нирваны Внутренней Цепи) на Землю. В этом особом случае были сделаны исключения из общего правила, согласно которому наименее развитые отправляются на Землю самыми первыми. Они должны были помогать Ману четвёртой Коренной Расы в самых совершенных телах которые были в его распоряжении на тот момент. Лучшие тела из лучших были даны тем, кто исчерпал свою карму и владельцы этих тел могли улучшать их, получая от них максимум того, на что они были способны. Архаты и их ученики работали под руководством Лордов Луны и Ману третьей и четвёртой Коренных Рас. Седьмая подраса была светло-голубого оттенка; она эволюционировала под их контролем дала мужчин и женщин лучшего типа для дальнейшего совершенствования под присмотром Ману четвёртой Коренной Расы.
</view>
</text>
</body>