<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      The root-stock and its descent into india
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Исток и Его Зарождение в Индии
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      WE have traced, roughly and in broad outlines, the migration out of Central Asia of the second,
      third, fourth and fifth sub-races of the Aryan Root-stock. We have seen its magnificent
      civilisation, and the vast extent of its Empire, and that from 40,000 B.C. onwards it had been
      slowly declining. From 40,000 B.C. to 20,000 B.C. the chief work of Vaivasvata Manu lay with His
      sub-races, and He and His immediate group, during these twenty thousand years, had been incarnating
      in the special districts set apart for the preparation of those sub-races. The original Empire,
      having long passed its prime, had been wearing away, as do all human institutions, while its
      sub-races were going out to play their appointed parts, and the process of disintegration had
      already gone far. The Mongolian and Turanian races, over whom it had so long ruled, had asserted
      their independence, and the Kingdom centring round the City of the Bridge was now but a small one.
      The people built no more-- they lived in the ruins of the great work of their forefathers. The egos
      showing genius and straining after high education were incarnating in the great daughter
      civilisations, so in the Mother State the level of learning steadily sank. Trade had fallen almost
      to zero, and the people were becoming agricultural and pastoral only. The central Kingdom still
      held together, but outlying districts had broken off and become independent.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Мы проследили в общих чертах за миграцией из Центральной Азии второй, третьей, четвёртой и пятой
      подрас Арийской Расы. Мы видели выдающиеся цивилизации и широкое распространение их Империй,
      которые после 40,000 лет до н.э. начали медленно угасать. В период с 40,000-20,000 лет до н.э.
      основная работа Вайвасваты Ману велась в Его подрасах и Он со Своей группой в течении этих двадцати
      тысяч лет рождался в выбранных районах для подготовки этих подрас. Первоначальная Империя прошла
      свой пик славы и уходила со сцены, подобно всем человеческим институтам, а её подрасы выходили на
      свет и играли назначенные роли, хотя процесс разрушения зашёл уже слишком далеко. Монгольская и
      Туранская расы которыми она так долго правила, заявили о независимости и Королевство вокруг Города
      Моста стало совсем маленьким. Люди больше ничего не строили, они жили в руинах большой работы
      сделанной их праотцами. Гениальные эго теперь рождались в больших дочерних цивилизациях и потому
      уровень образования в материнсокм государстве неуклонно падал. Торговля почти пропала из вида и
      люди вели всё больше земледельческий и пастушеский образ жизни. Центральное Королевство всё ещё
      держалось в целости, но внешние районы отделились и стали независимыми.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      But now, 18,800 B.C., the toilsome work of building up and sending out the sub-races was, for the
      time, over. The Manu had managed all His migrations, and seen His sub-races definitely established,
      and He now turned His attention once more to the Root Race, because He wished to get it away by
      degrees from its ancestral home, and to establish it in India, the land chosen for its further
      evolution. In India the splendid Atlantean civilisation had developed from the time that huge
      Atlantean hosts, pouring through the Himalayan passes, after the land was sufficiently dry for
      settlement, had occupied the country; before that, a vast Atlantean Kingdom had existed in the far
      south, and had spread to the ocean which, before the catastrophe of 75,025 B.C., bounded it on the
      north. This civilisation, over-luxurious, had now become effete, and the higher classes, belonging
      to the Toltec sub-race, were indolent and self-seeking; much, however, remained of a noble
      literature, and there was a great tradition of occult knowledge, both of which were needed for the
      work of the future and therefore had to be preserved. The warrior spirit had largely died out, and
      the wealth of the country, enormously and lavishly displayed, invited conquest from a more virile
      people, who should inherit and carry on all that deserved perpetuation.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Но теперь, 18,800 лет до н.э. утомительная работа построения и распределения по миру подрас, на
      некоторое время, закончена. Ману разобрался со всеми миграциями и увидел, что Его подрасы стали
      определённо развитыми, и теперь Он вновь обратил внимание на Коренную Расу, ибо хотел переместить
      её от своего дома и поселить в Индии, на земле выбранной для её эволюции. В Индии великолепная
      Атлантическая цивилизация развилась с тех пор как огромные дома Атлантов, проникая через
      Гималайские ущелья, после того как земли стали достаточно сухими для поселения, заняли страну. До
      того времени огромная цивилизация Атлантов занимала далёкие южные земли и распространялась на океан
      который до катастрофы 75,025 лет до н.э. ограничивал их с севера. Цивилизация когда-то чрезмерно
      роскошная, стала истощённой и высшие классы принадлежащие Толтекской подрасе превратились в ленивых
      и самолюбивых людей. Тем не менее сохранялась традиция благородной литературы и великого
      оккультного знания, ибо обе были нужны для дальнейшей работы. Воинственный дух давно умер и на его
      место пришла демонстрация чрезмерного богатства, которое привлекло людей более сильных, способных
      унаследовать и сохранить всё, что было достойно сохранения.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The entire removal of the Race from its Central Asian Home was necessary so that (1) Shamballa
      should be left in the required solitude; the work carried on in close contact with the outer world
      was finished for the time, and the Race must be left to grow without external supervision; (2)
      India should be Aryanised; (3) the Race should be out of the way before the coming cataclysm, as
      the Central Asian region would be much altered.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Полное удаление Расы из Центральной Азии было необходимо, потому что: Шамбала должна быть оставлена
      в необходимой изоляции, ибо работа с внешним миром подошла к концу на некоторое время и Раса должна
      остаться и расти без вреншнего присмотра.Индия должна быть Арианизирована.Раса должна уйти с пути
      надвигающегося катаклизма, который серьёзно изменит облик Центральной Азии.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The Manu had not incarnated in the Root Race since He led away the fourth and fifth sub-races, that
      is for about one thousand two hundred years; for, as said above, we are now at 18,800 B.C. He had
      therefore become rather a myth in Central Asia, and there had been differences of opinion, a few
      centuries earlier, as to whether His rules as to intermarriage. still held good. Some held that
      they were obsolete, their object having been obtained, and some families had married into those of
      some of the Tartar rulers. A schism had thus occurred, and those who favoured the new departure had
      left the Kingdom and set themselves up as a separate community. They went no further, however,
      along the road of intermarriage, and it may be opined that the few outside marriages which had
      occurred had been brought about in order to gain a slight, but necessary, infusion of other blood,
      and perhaps also to cause the desired separation. The disappearance of the original cause of
      disunion did not draw the communities nearer together, and, indeed, they became more hostile as
      centuries went by, and the increasing numbers in the Central Kingdom pressed the seceders further
      and further back into the valleys of the northern hills. Mars, at the date mentioned above, was
      King of one of the tribes of the seceders, who were suffering much from the incursions of the
      larger nation; continual fighting barely enabled his tribe to hold its own, and its eventual
      destruction was certain; his teacher, Jupiter, advised him not to fight, but this did not help him,
      and he thought and prayed desperately to find a way of safety for his people, so brave, so loyal,
      but so hopelessly overmatched.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Ману не рождался в Коренной Расе с тех пор как увёл четвёртую и пятую подрасы примерно 2,200 лет
      назад; как мы уже говорили, сейчас мы находимся в 18,800 году до н.э. К тому времени Он стал уже
      мифом в Центральной Азии и люди расходились во мнениях несколько столетий раньше, говорил ли Он о
      допустимости браков с другими расами или не говорил. Некоторые люди решили, что те правила
      устарели, ибо выполнили свою цель и потому несколько семей заключили союзы с Татарскими
      правителями. Это привело к расколу и те, кто склонялись к последнему мнению покинули Королевство и
      создали отдельную общину. Как бы то ни было, они зашли не так далеко и ограничились лишь браками с
      другими расами и можно сказать, что те несколько внешних союзов были предусмотрены для получения
      небольшой примеси другой крови и, возможно, желаемого разделения народа. Исчезновение причины
      разногласия не сблизило общины. Проходили века и они становились всё враждебнее друг к другу, а
      возрастающее население Центрального Королевства отталкивало несогласных всё дальше и дальше в
      долины возле северных холмов. В то время Марс был Королём одного из племён несогласных, которые
      сильно страдали от нападок большой нации. Постоянные сражения едва позволяли его племени удерживать
      город, но его окончательное разрушение было лишь делом времени. Его учитель, Юпитер, советовал ему
      не вступать в битву, но это не помогло ему. Он отчаянно искал путь к спасению своего народа, так
      храбро, так благородно и так безнадёжно.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Then, in the crisis of his perplexity, the Manu appeared to him in a dream, and bade him lead his
      tribe westward and southward-- the vanguard of the greatest migration that had ever occurred-- into
      the sacred land of India, which was assigned to the Race as dwelling. He was told to fight as
      little as he could on his way to his future home, to attack none who would let him pass in peace,
      and to press on to the southern extremity of India. In the future all the Race would follow, and in
      the coming migrations he would frequently take part; and at a future time he and his wife Mercury
      would do such work as He, the Manu, was then doing.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      И тогда, в момент окончательной растерянности Марса ему во сне явился Ману и указал вести народ на
      запад и на юг — это был авангард величайшей миграции которую видел мир — на священные земли Индии
      давно уготованные для этой Расы. Ману говорил Марсу сражаться как можно меньше на пути к будущему
      дому, не атаковать тех кто пропускает его с миром и идти как можно дальше на юг Индии. В будущем
      вся Раса пойдёт следом и в этих миграциях он будет часто играть свою роль. В будущем он и его жена
      Меркурий будут делать ту же работу которую Он, Ману, делает сейчас.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Thus encouraged, and full of joy, Mars set to work to prepare, telling his people of his dream, and
      bidding them get ready fir the march. Nearly all believed him, but our old Arabian friend, Alastor,
      had turned up again, and he headed a small party who refused to follow Mars, saying that he was not
      going to leave the old land and the old teachings because of the hysterical dream of an overwrought
      and despairing man. So he stayed behind, betrayed the route of his people to their enemies and was
      put to death after the failure of the pursuing expedition.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Приободрённый, Марс начал подготовку, рассказывая своим людям обо сне и раздавая указания
      готовиться к маршу. Почти все поверили ему, но наш старый друг Аластор вновь оказался рядом и
      возглавил небольшую группу отказавшихся следовать за Марсом, мотивируя это тем, что они не покинут
      старый дом и привычные учения из-за истеричного сна усталого человека. Так он остался позади,
      запутав маршрут своих людей и, попав в руки врага, был предан смерти, так и не сумев догнать
      экспедицию.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Mars started in 18,875 B.C.,1 (¹ See Appendix X.) and followed the appointed road, and after many
      hardships and not a little fighting-- for though he never attacked, he was frequently assailed-- he
      reached the great plains of India, and for a while enjoyed the hospitality of his comrade in many
      lives, Viraj, who was ruling as King Podishpar over the greater part of northern India. The
      alliance was cemented by the marriage of Corona, the son of Podishpar, to Brihaspati, a daughter of
      Mars and the widow of Vulcan, who had been killed in a battle during the journey. Southern India
      was then a large Kingdom under King Huyaranda, or Lahira-- our Saturn-- the High Priest of the
      Kingdom being our Surya, under the name Byarsha, and the Deputy High Priest being Osiris. Surya had
      told Saturn that the strangers were coming at the command of the Gods, some years before their
      arrival, so that the King sent the Crown Prince, Crux, to meet them, and gave them welcome,
      settling them in his land. Later, Surya declared that “the high-nosed strangers from the north”
      were fitted to be priests, and that they should hold the priestly office hereditarily; those who
      agreed to this became priests, and were the ancestors of the Brahmanas of Southern India,
      abstaining from intermarriage with the earlier inhabitants, and living as a separate class.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Марс начал 18,875 лет до н.э. (см. приложение 10) и последовал по указанному пути и после многих
      трудностей и непростой битвы — он никогда не нападал, но сам часто подвергался атакам — он достиг
      великих равнин Индии и с удовольствием встретил гостеприимного старого друга, знакомого с ним во
      многих жизнях, Viraj, который был Королём Podishpar — правителем огромной северной части Индии.
      Альянс был скреплён свадьбой Corona — сына Podishpar — и Brihaspati — дочери Марса и вдовы Вулкана,
      который был убит в битве случившейся в пути. Южная Индия была большим королевством Короля
      Huyaranda, или Lahira — наш Сатурн. Surya занимал пост Высшего Жреца королевства и звался Byarsha,
      а Осирис был его заместителем. Surya рассказал Сатурну, что странники пришли по указанию Богов,
      данному за несколько лет до их прибытия, поэтому король отправил им коронованного принца Crux и тот
      приветствовал их и разместил на своей территории. Позже Surya заявил, что "высоконосые странники с
      севера" подходят на роль жрецов и они должны занять и передавать свой статус по наследству. Те кто
      согласился с этим, стали жрецами и предками брахманов южной Индии. Они воздерживались от браков с
      первыми жителями Индии и жили как отдельный класс.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Others intermarried with the Toltec aristocracy, thus gradually Aryanising the whole upper classes
      of the country, and the south of India passed peacefully under Aryan rule; for Crux, who succeeded
      Saturn, died without issue, and Herakles, the second son of Mars, was elected by the people to the
      vacant throne, establishing an Aryan dynasty. From this migration forward, all the immigrants into
      India are spoken of as the ` first sub-race,' since the whole Root Race, the ancient stock, passed
      over into India. Births into this are reckoned as births into the first sub-race, whether taking
      place in India itself or in the countries colonised and Aryanised by it.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Другие женились на аристократии Толтеков, тем самым постепенно Арианизовывая весь высший класс
      страны, а юг Индии мирно жил под Арийским правлением. Что до Crux, последовавшего за Сатурном, то
      он умер не оставив наследников, а Геракл, второй сын Марса, был избран народом на вакантный трон,
      чем создал Арийскую династию. С этого началась миграция и все иммигранты прибывшие в Индию
      назывались "первой подрасой", так как вся Коренная Раса, древний род, пришёл в Индию. Рождения в
      ней рассматривались как рождения в первой подрасе, случались они в Индии или в странах
      колонизированных Арийцами.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      We find a number of old friends in this migration, in addition to those already named; Mars' eldest
      son was Uranus, who became a hermit in the Nilgiris, and his third son was Alcyone, who became
      Deputy High Priest on the resignation-- due to old age-- of Osiris. His second daughter was
      Demeter.1 (¹ See Appendix X.) A curious instance of bringing friends in from abroad was the arrival
      of a young Mongolian chieftain, Taurus, who fled from his elder brother' s anger, and took refuge
      with Mars in his Central Asian Kingdom; he brought Procyon with him as his wife, and Cygnus, whom
      he married to Aries, was one of his daughters.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Мы нашли многих старых друзей в этой миграции, вдобавок к уже названным. Старшим сыном Марса был
      Уран, который стал отшельником в Nilgiris, в его третим сыном был Алкион, который стал заместителем
      высшего жреца Осириса, ушедшего с поста из за большого возраста. Его второй дочерью была Деметра
      (см. приложение 10). Любопытным примером встречи друзей служит прибытие молодого монгольского вождя
      Тауруса, который избежал гнева своего старшего брата и нашёл убежище у Марса в его
      центрально-азиатском королевстве. Он привёл с собой жену Procyon и Cygnus, женатого на одной из его
      дочерей Aries.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      From the South Indian Aryan Kingdom went out about 13,500 B.C. an important mission to Egypt; the
      order came from the Head of the Hierarchy through the Manu, and the expedition travelled via
      Ceylon, by water up the Red Sea, then hardly more than an inlet. It was not intended to colonise,
      since Egypt was already a mighty Empire, but rather to settle there under the Egyptian Government,
      a great and beneficent, as well as highly civilised, power.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Примерно 13,500 лет до н.э. с юга Арийского Индийского Королевства отправилась важная миссия в
      Египет. Указ шёл от Главы Иерархии через Ману. Экспедиция отправилась через Цейлон, Красное Море и
      узкий пролив. Она не предполагала колонизацию, ибо Египет уже был могущественной империей. Её целью
      было создание под Египестким Правительством великой, благодетельной и не менее высокоразвитой силы.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Mars was at the head of the expedition, and Surya was a High Priest in Egypt as he had been in
      southern India nearly three thousand years before; as then, he smoothed the way for the coming
      Aryans, and he told the Pharaoh of their approach, and advised him to welcome them. His advice was
      taken, and a little later he counselled the Pharaoh to marry his daughter to Mars, and to name the
      latter his successor. This was duly done, and thus peaceably but effectively was an Aryan dynasty
      established in Egypt at the death of the ruling Pharaoh. It reigned gloriously for many thousand
      years, until the sinking of Poseidonis, when it, with the Egyptian people, was driven to the hills
      by the flooding of Egypt. The flood, however, retreated comparatively soon, and the country
      recovered ere long. Manetho' s history apparently deals with this Aryan dynasty; he makes Unas--
      whose date is given as 3900 B.C., while we make it 4030 B.C.-- the last King of the Fifth dynasty.
      The Arab Hyksos Kings are put at 1500 B.C. Under the Aryan Pharaohs the great Schools of Egypt
      became even more famous, and for long it led the learning of the western world.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Марс был во главе экспедиции, а Surya был Высшим Жрецом в Египте как и три тысячи лет назад на юге
      Индии. Как и тогда он сгладил путь Арийцев, рассказав Фараону об их намерениях и посоветовав
      принять их с добром. Его совет был принят и немного позже он обсудил с Фараоном предложение выдать
      его дочь замуж за Марса и именовать последнего его наследником. Это было сделано и после смерти
      Фараона мирно установилась династия Арийцев. Правление было великолепным многие тысячи лет, вплоть
      до катастрофы с Посейдонисом, которая выгнала Египтян на холмы. Потоп, тем не менее, отступил
      сравнительно быстро и страна восстановилась на долгое время. История Manetho несомненно
      рассказывает об Арийской династии. Унас произошёл от этой династии — считается, что он жил 3,000
      лет до н.э. но мы скажем, что настоящая дата 4,300 лет до н.э. — и он был последним королём Пятой
      династии. Арабские короли Хиксос жили 1,500 лет до н.э. Во время Арийских Фараонов великая школа
      Египта стала ещё более знаменитой и долгое время она вела за собой просвещение западного мира.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It was the second mighty Empire of the first sub-race, if we count the Empire of the Root Race as
      the first. From Egypt was introduced Aryan blood into several East African tribes; it would seem as
      though a low type of body were sometimes required for little-advanced egos, who had gone through
      many previous sub-races without making much progress, and were thrown into contact with a higher
      race in order to force them forward. Some of the lowest types of dwellers in the slums of civilised
      fourth and fifth Aryan sub-races are obviously less advanced than Zulus. On the other hand, a touch
      of Aryan blood in an uncivilised tribe would give certain characteristics required for its
      improvement.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Это была вторая могущественная империя первой подрасы, если считать империю Коренной Расы первой.
      Из Египта пришла Арийская кровь в некоторые восточные африканские племена. Казалось, будто низкий
      тип тел иногда требовался для малоразвитых эго которые прошли через многие предыдущие подрасы без
      особого прогресса, чтобы столкнуть их с высокоразвитой расой и заставить двигаться вперёд.
      Некоторые особо неразвитые обитатели трущоб цивилизованных четвёртой и пятой Арийских подрас были,
      очевидно, менее развиты чем Зулу. С другой стороны, касание Арийской крови нецивилизованных племён
      дало им характеристики необходимые для прогресса.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The South Indian Kingdom was used by the Manu as a subsidiary centre of radiation on other
      occasions than this of the Aryanising of Egypt. He sent out from it colonists to Java, to Australia
      and to the islands of Polynesia, which accounts for the Aryan strain to be observed even to-day in
      what are called the brown Polynesians, in contradistinction to the Melanesians.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Южное Индийское Королевство использовалось Ману как второстепенный центр влияния, помимо
      Арианизации Египта. Он отправил оттуда колонистов на Яву, Австралию и Полинезийские острова,
      которые сделали Арийский след заметным даже сейчас в тех, кого мы называем коричневыми
      Полинезийцами.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      While these arrangements were being carried out in the south of India, the Manu still worked at the
      gradual transportation of His Race from Central Asia into the northern parts of India. One of the
      early immigrations settled itself in the Panjab, and after much fighting made terms of peace with
      the inhabitants, partly plundering and partly defending them. Another, turning eastwards, had
      established itself in Assam and northern Bengal. The expedition immediately preceding one on which
      we may pause for a few minutes had taken place about 17,520 B.C.; part of it reached its
      destination safely by the route followed by Mars, more than a thousand years before, while a
      smaller division, seeking to penetrate through what is now called the Khyber Pass, was annihilated.
      In 17,455 B.C. a third¹ (¹ See Appendix XI.) was sent out, led by Mars, the eldest son of the
      reigning Monarch of the central Kingdom, Jupiter: Jupiter had Saturn as his wife, and Mercury as
      his sister. Mars had chosen the members of his expedition with great care, selecting the strongest
      and most vigorous men and women whom he could find; among them were Psyche and his wife Arcturus,
      with three sons, Alcyone, Albireo and Leto. Capella and his wife Judex were chosen. Vulcan, a great
      captain, was the warrior most relied on by Mars, and he, with Vajra as a subordinate, led one wing
      of the expedition, while Mars headed the other.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Пока эти приготовления шли своим ходом в южной Индии, Ману всё ещё работал над постепенным
      перемещением Его Расы из Центральной Азии в северные части Индии. Одна из первых миграций
      обосновалась в Пенджабе и после длительных битв они достигли мира с жителями, частично разграбляя
      их, частично защищая. Другая отправилась на восток и поселилась в Ассаме и северном Бенгале.
      Экспедиция предшествовала другой, на которой мы можем остановиться на несколько минут, случившейся
      17,520 лет до н.э. Часть её достигла цели в безопасности по пути за Марсом более тысячи лет назад,
      а часть искала путь через то, что мы сейчас называем Khyber Pass, и погибла. 17,455 лет до н.э.
      третья (см. приложение 11) была отправлена за Марсом, старшим сыном правящего Монарха центрального
      Королевства, Юпитера. Женой Юпитера была Сатурн, а сестрой — Меркурий. Марс выбирал членов
      экспедиции с большим вниманием, отбирая лучших и сильнейших среди мужчин и женщин которых он мог
      найти. Среди них был Psyche и его жена Arcturus с трём сыновьями: Alcyone, Albireo и Leto. Capella
      и его жена Judex были также выбраны. Вулкан, великий капитан, был воином очень полагавшимся на
      Марса и он, с подчинённым Vajra, вёл одно крыло экспедиции, тогда как Марс — другое.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The two wings of the expedition met, as was planned, and they settled the women and children in a
      strongly entrenched camp, between what are now Jammu and Gujranwala, themselves pressing on to the
      place where Delhi now stands, where they built the first city on that imperial site, and named it
      Ravipur, City of the Sun. On their way they had a skirmish with a powerful Chief, Castor, but
      succeeded in passing on, and when the new city was ready the women and children and their guards
      were brought to it, and the first life of Delhi, as a capital, began. Mars left his Kingdom to his
      eldest son Herakles, who was much aided by Alcyone, nine years his senior and his dearest friend.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Два крыла экспедиции встретились, как и планировалось, и они поселили женщин и детей в хорошо
      укреплённом сооружении, между сегодняшними Jammu и Gujranwala, а сами отправились туда, где сейчас
      стоит Delhi и построили первый город на этом имперском месте и назвали его Ravipur — Город Солнца.
      На своём пути они столкнулись с могущественным вождём Кастором, но смогли пройти и когда город был
      готов, женщины и дети весте с защитниками переместились в него и первая жизнь столицы Delhi
      началась. Марс оставил своё королевство старшему сыну Гераклу, которому во многом помогам Алкион —
      его наставник на протяжении девяти лет и его ближайщий друг.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      One of the hugest emigrations from the central Kingdom took place 15,950 B.C., three great armies
      being formed with Mars as Commander-in-Chief; the command of the right wing was given to Corona,
      who was to pass through Kashmir, the Panjab, and the provinces now called the United, to Bengal;
      left wing was to cross Tibet to Bhutan and thence to Bengal; the centre under Mars, with Mercury as
      second in command, was to cross Tibet to Nepal, and so onwards to the general meeting-place,
      Bengal-- which was to be their home. Corona, however, spent his time for forty years in making a
      Kingdom for himself, and did not reach Bengal till Mars, long ruling there, was an old man. Vulcan
      had joined Mars, and finally had established himself in Assam. Mars himself, with the help of
      Vulcan, had subdued Bengal, and, after desperate fighting, Orissa, and had finally fixed his
      capital in Central Bengal; when an old man, he placed his eldest son, Jupiter, on his throne and
      retired from the world.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Одна из величайших эмиграций из центрального Королевства случилась 15,950 лет до н.э. и состояла из
      трёх огромных армий под командованием Марса. Командование правым флангом было отдано Corona задача
      которого была пройти через Кашмир, Панджаб и объединённые провинции в Бенгал. Левое крыло должно
      было пересечь Тибет и Бутан и попасть в Бенгал. Центром командовал Марс, со своим помощником
      Меркурием, и его задача была перейти Тибет, добраться до Непала и оттуда идти в Бенгал — главное
      место встречи и их будущий дом. Corona, правда, провёл 40 лет создавая государство для себя и не
      добрался до Бенгала, когда Марс, долго там правящий, уже был стариком. Вулкан присоединился к Марсу
      и расположился в Ассаме. Сам Марс, с помощью Вулкана, подчинил Бенгал и после отчаянной битвы
      Ориссу, и окончательно сделал своей столиценй Центральный Бенгал. Будучу совсем старым он посадил
      своего старшего сына Юпитера на трон и ушёл из мира.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The great importance of this far-reaching immigration is marked by the fact that ten who are now
      Masters took part in it: Mars, Mercury, Vulcan, Jupiter, Brihaspati, Osiris, Uranus, Saturn,
      Neptune, Viraj. Of others, bearing familiar names, the gathering was also large.¹ (¹ See Appendix
      XII. For a graphic account of it, see the tenth life in The Lives of Alcyone .)
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Важность этой далёкой миграции подчеркивается тем фактом, что в её организации приняли участие
      десятеро, ставших в наши дни Мастерами: Марс, Меркурий, Вулкан, Юпитер, Brihaspati, Осирис, Уран,
      Сатурн, Нептун, Viraj. Смотрите приложение 12 и десятую жизнь в книге "Жизни Алкиона".
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      From this time onwards there were constant descents into India from Central Asia, sometimes mere
      bands, sometimes considerable armies, the older settlers often resisting the new, the new
      plundering the old. Wave after wave rolled in during thousands of years, and some of the more
      thoughtful of the Aryans studied the philosophy of the Toltecs, whom they sometimes called the
      Nagas. The lower classes of the Atlantean population, mostly the brown Tlavatli, they termed
      Dasyas, while the black people of Lemurian descent whom they regarded with horror, they called
      Daityas and Takshaks.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      С того времени начались постоянные перемещения в Индию из Центральной Азии: иногда шли простые
      банды, иногда целые армии. Старые поселенцы часто теснили новых, а новые грабили старых. Одна волна
      за другой приходили новые народы на протяжении тысяч лет и некоторые из наиболее умных Арийцев
      поняли философию Толтеков, которых они часто называли Нагами. Низшие классы Атлантов — в
      большинстве своём коричневые Тлавати — они нарекли Dasyas; чёрных Лемурийцев, которых они боялись,
      назвали Daityas и Takshaks.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      There were some intermarriages between the more liberal Aryans and the Toltecs, and we found
      Alcyone, about 12,850 B.C., much attached to Psyche, the son of Orpheus, an Atlantean dignitary,
      and marrying the latter' s daughter, Mizar, though his own father, Algol, was a fanatical Aryan,
      hating the Atlanteans and their civilisation. While, under these circumstances, he and his young
      wife became fugitives, yet an Aryan leader, Vesta, head of an invading band, gave them shelter, and
      a relative of his, Draco, with his wife Cassiopeia, members of a band settled longer in India,
      helped them to the possession of an estate, where he was on very friendly terms with Aletheia, a
      rich Atlantean. It was evident, therefore, that in some cases, at least, friendly relations existed
      between the races, and these were not disturbed by the irruption of a large host of Aryans, once
      more under Mars, who passed through the neighbourhood on his way to carve himself out an Empire in
      Central India.¹ (¹ See Appendix XIII.)
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Между наиболее либеральными Арийцами и Толтеками заключались браки. Мы нашли Алкиона около 12,850
      лет до н.э. сильно привязанной к Psyche, сына Орфея, сановника Атлантов, женящегося на дочери
      последнего — Мицар — хотя его отец, Алгол, был фанатичным Арийцем ненавидевшим цивилизацию Атлантов
      и её жителей. Эти обстоятельства вынудили его со своей женой бежать. Арийский лидер — Vesta — глава
      банды, дал приют беглецам, а его родственник Draco с женой Cassiopeia — члены банды долго жившей в
      Индии — помогли им в обустройстве дома, где они завели очень дружественные отношения с Aletheia —
      богатым Атлантом. Было очевидно, таким образом, что в некоторых случаях возникали по меньшей мере
      дружественные отношения между расами и им не мешало большое вторжение Арийцев, вновь под
      командованием Марса, которое прошло по соседству на пути к империи которую Марс вырезал из
      Центральной Индии (см. приложение 13).
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      By these constant migrations the Central Asian Kingdom was drained of its inhabitants by about 9700
      B.C. The convulsions attending the catastrophe of 9564 B.C. , shattered the City of the Bridge into
      ruins, and wrought the destruction of most of the great Temples on the White Island. The latest
      bands did not reach India easily; they were delayed in Afghanistan and Baluchistan for some two
      thousand years, and many were massacred by Mongol raiders; the rest slowly found their way down to
      the plains, already thickly populated.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Эти постоянные миграции из Центральной Азии опустошили её к 9,700 лет до н.э. Сотрясения великой
      катастрофы 9,564 лет до н.э. разрушили Город Моста и величайшие храмы Белого Острова. Последние
      банды с трудом проложили свой путь в Индию. Они задержались в Афганистане и Балучистане на две
      тысячи лет и многие из них были вырезаны монгольскими рейдерами. Оставшиеся медленно добрались до
      равнин, уже плотно заселённые.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      When His people were thus finally conveyed into India, a danger arose that the Aryan blood might
      become a mere trace amidst the enormous majority of the Atlanteans and Atlanto-Lemurians, so the
      Manu again forbade intermarriage, and about 8000 B.C. , ordained the caste system, in order that no
      further admixture might be made, and that those already made might be perpetuated. He founded at
      first only three castes-- Brahmana, Rajan and Vish. The first were pure Aryans, the second Aryan
      and Toltec, the third Aryan and Mongolian.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Когда Его люди окончательно оказались в Индии, возникла опасность, что Арийская кровь затеряется
      посреди подавляющего большинства Атлантов и Атланто-Лемурийцев. Поэтому Ману вновь запретил
      смешанные браки и около 8,000 лет до н.э. создал кастовую систему, чтобы предотвратить дальнейшие
      смешения, а те что уже произошли, увековечить. Он построил только три касты — Brahmana, Rajan и
      Vish. Первые были чистыми Арийцами, вторые — Арийцами и Толтеками, третьи — Арийцами и Монголами.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The castes were hence called the Varnas, or colours, the pure Aryans white, the Aryan and Toltec
      intermixture red, and the Aryan and Mongolian yellow. The castes were allowed to intermarry among
      themselves, but a feeling quickly grew up that marriages should be restricted within the caste.
      Later, those who were not Aryan at all were included under the general appellation of Shudras, but
      even here in many cases a certain small amount of Aryan blood may appear. Many of the hill tribes
      are partly Aryan-- some few are wholly so, like the Siaposh people and the Gipsy tribes.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Касты стали называть Варнами или цветами: чистые Арийцы были белыми, смесь Арийцев и Толтеков —
      красная, Арийцев и Монголов — желтая. Касты могли заключать браки внутри себя: было быстро привито
      чувство того, что браки не могли быть смешанными. Позже, те кто не имел Арийской крови вообще,
      попали в касту Shudras, но даже здесь во многих случаях можно было найти небольшое количество
      Арийской крови. Многие племена с холмов были частично Арийскими — но немногие были такими
      полностью, как народ Siaposh и племена Gipsy.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      During the emigrations into India, one tribe had gone off in a direction different from that of the
      others, and had contrived to establish itself in a valley in the Susamir district. There, forgotten
      by the rest of the world, it enjoyed its primitive pastoral life for many centuries. About 2200
      B.C. , there arose a great military leader amongst the Mongol tribes, and they devastated all of
      Asia that they could reach, utterly destroying, among others, the remnants of the Persian Empire.
      The Tartar leader was finally overthrown, and his hordes scattered, but he had left utter
      desolation behind him. Somehow in a hundred years or so, news of a fertile but unoccupied land
      reached our Aryans in their valley; they sent out spies to report, and when the story was
      confirmed, they migrated bodily into Persia. These were the speakers of Zend, and their late
      arrival accounts for the curiously unsettled state of the country even in the time of the last
      Zoroaster. Such remnants of the third sub-race as had been only driven from their homes, and had
      escaped the general massacre, came back and made common cause with our tribe, and from these
      beginnings gradually developed the latest Persian Empire.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Во время эмиграций в Индию одно племя ушло в направлении отличном от выбранных другими и решило
      поселиться в долине Susamir. Там, забытые остальным миром, они наслаждались примитивной
      пастушесткой жизнью несколько столетий. Примерно 2,200 лет до н.э. там появился великий военный
      лидер среди Монгольских племён и они опустошили всю Азию до которой смогли дотянуться, тщательно
      разрушив остатки Империи Персов. Татарский лидер был окончательно опрокинут, а его орды разбросаны,
      но он оставил после себя полную разруху. Каким то образом через сто лет новости о плодородной, но
      пустой земле добрались до наших Арийцев в долине и они послали шпионов туда. Когда история
      подтвердилась, они целиком мигрировали в Персию. Это были те, кто говорил на Zend и их поздние
      записи говорят о странном безлюдном государстве времён последнего Зороастра. Такие остатки третьей
      подрасы, покинувшие свои дома и избежавшие общей резни, вернулись и основали то, что постепенно
      развилось в последнюю Персидскую Империю.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
