<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">The fourth root race</view>
<view lang="ru">Четвёртая Коренная Раса</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
THE Head of the Hierarchy began, almost immediately after His coming, to make arrangements for the founding of the fourth Root Race, employing the future Manu to pick out the smallest, densest and best of the Lemurian types available; and while the founding and growth of civilisation under the King-Initiates were going forward among the Lemurians, the Manu of the coming Race was diligently seeking for the egos suitable for His purpose, and selecting for them appropriate incarnations. He gathered together, in one case, thousands of people, and finally selected one, after tests that lasted over many years, evidently experiencing much difficulty in finding desirable ancestors for His Race. Tribes were set apart, their members inter-marrying for long periods, and the Manu chose promising specimens and transplanted them; He and His disciples incarnated in the progeny of these to raise the physical level. He carried on various experiments simultaneously on the points of the Star, utilising the differences of climate. It looked at first a hopeless task, as though negroes and mulattoes should inter-marry to made a white race; but after generations of selection within a tribe, He would take away one or two, and pair them off with another one or two, similarly selected from another tribe. The third Race Manu had evolved a blue type for His sixth sub-race, and a bluish-white for His seventh, though the masses of the Lemurians remained black; some of the fourth sub-race also mixed in with the blue, and slowly, very slowly, the general Lemurian type improved. It is noticeable also that when, in other parts of the world a lighter-coloured or better type appeared, it was sent off to the Manu, and He tried to find for it a suitable husband or wife; we observed one that was thus sent in from the Madagascan city, and others similarly came in from elsewhere.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Почти сразу после Его пришествия, глава Иерархии начал отдавать распоряжения для основания четвёртой Коренной Расы, а будущий Ману получил задание выбрать лучших из всех лемурийцев; пока цивилизация создавалась и росла под руководством Королей-Посвящённых, Ману наступающей Расы усердно искал эго подходящие для Его целей и выбирал для них соответствующие инкарнации. Он собрал тысячи людей вместе и окончательно выбрал одного после проверок длившихся годами, очевидно испытывая большие трудности в поиске желаемых родителей Его расы. Племена были разнесены по разным ареалам, а их члены долгое время вступали в брак между собой; Ману выбрал многообещающих представителей и переселил их. Он и Его ученики воплощались в их потомстве, чтобы улучшить тела. Он провёл множество экспериментов на концах Звезды, используя различия в климате. Это была, на первый взгляд, безнадёжная задача получить белую расу из негров и мулатов, но после поколений селекции Он выбрал два представителя из одного племени и скрестил их с двумя представителями из другого. Третий Коренной Ману вывел синих представителей для Его шестой подрасы и светло-голубых для седьмой, хотя основная масса лемурийцев оставалась чёрной. Некоторые из четвёртой подрасы размножались совместно с синими и медленно, очень медленно, основной тип лемурийцев улучшался. Мы заметили, что как только в любой части мира появлялся лемуриец светлого окраса, а значит лучшего типа, он отсылался к Ману и тот пытался найти ему подходящую жену или мужа.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
More rapid progress was made after the arrival of the Initiates, mentioned at the close of the last chapter, the best of the bodies improved by their indwelling being taken by the Manu for the shaping of His first sub-race; the fourth Race had thus, ultimately, a very fine founding and nursing, thanks to the large number of developed people who took the lead and pressed things forward. The Manu was able, finally, to take the bodies of the seventh sub-race, improved by the Initiates using them, as the nucleus of His first sub-race, the Rmoahal, of the fourth Root Race. All who were taken on into the fourth Root Race were the Initiates and their disciples in these bodies, and none at this stage were taken from those who had previously been evolving on the Earth Chain.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
После прибытия Посвящённых, упомянутых в конце предыдущей главы, прогресс стал намного быстрее; лучшие из тел были улучшены усилиями Ману и Его четвёртая Раса стала, наконец, основательно и бережно подготовлена благодаря многим людям собравшим свою волю и устремившимся вперёд. Ману, наконец, смог выбрать тела, улучшенные Посвящёнными которые их использовали, для седьмой подрасы, чтобы те образовали ядро Его первой подрасы — Рмоашал — четвёртой Коренной Расы. Все кто был выбран для основания четвёртой Коренной Расы были Посвящёнными и их учениками в этих телах; среди них не было никого, кто раньше эволюционировал на Земной Цепи.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Subba Rao distinguished the Lemurians as blue-black, the Atlanteans as red-yellow, and the Aryans as brown-white. We find the fourth Race Manu eliminating the blue from the colour of His people, passing through purple into the red of the Rmoahal sub-race, and then, by mixing in the blue-white of the seventh Lemurian sub-race, He obtained the first sub-race which seemed to be fully human, and that we could imagine as living among ourselves. After the race-type was fully established, He thus had the materials for the rich red-brown of the Toltec, the third subrace, the most splendid and imperial of the Atlantean peoples, which ruled the world for tens of thousands of years. After a long period of patient working, about a million years having been spent in taking stupendous trouble and care, He reached a fair resemblance to the type given to Him to produce; then He definitely founded the Race, He Himself taking incarnation, and calling His disciples to take bodies in His own family, His posterity thus forming the Race. In the most literal sense the Manu of a Race is its Progenitor, for the whole Race has its Manu as its physical ancestor.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Субба Рао отметила лемурийцев как тёмно-синих, атлантов как красно-жёлтых, арийцев как светло-коричневых. Ману четвёртой Расы отбирал синих среди своих людей, преобразовывал пурпурный в красный в подрасе Рмоашала и, наконец, смешивая светло-голубых седьмой лемурийской подрасы Он получил первую подрасу которая была, судя по всему, полностью человеческой и, как мы подозреваем, её представители живут среди нас. После того как был получен новый тип расы, Он имел в распоряжении материал для создания красно-коричневых толтеков — третьей подрасы — наиболее величественных среди атлантов, которые правили миром в течении 10,000 лет. После долгого периода спокойной работы, после миллиона лет невероятных усилий, Он получил полное сходство с типом, который Ему был даy для воспроизводства; Он основал новую расу и сам принял в ней инкарнацию, призвал своих учеников взять тела в своей семье, чтобы его потомство сформировало расу. В буквальном смысле слова, Ману Расы — прародитель своей расы, ибо для всех людей расы Он — физический отец.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Even the Manu' s immediate descendants, however, were not a very attractive-looking crowd, judging by our present standard, although a vast improvement on the surrounding population. They were smaller, but had no nervous organisation worth speaking of, and their astral bodies were shapeless. It is extraordinary what he made of such a body for Himself, moulding and shaping it after His own astral and mental bodies and modifying the pigment in the skin, till He worked it into more of the colour that He wished for His Race.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Даже прямые наследники Ману были не очень привлекательными если судить по нашим современным стандартам, хотя они были значительно лучше по сравнению с остальным населением. Они были меньше и не имели нервной системы, по крайне мере такой какой мы её себе представляем сейчас, а их астральные тела были бесформенны. Он выполнил экстраординарную работу по изменению ментального, астрального и физического тел, изменяя пигмент кожи и делая внешность более похожей на ту, которую он бы хотел видеть у представителей своей расы.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After this many generations passed before the young Race took possession of its continent, Atlantis, but from this point onwards ship-loads of egos began to come in from the Inter-Chain Nirvana, to inhabit the fourth Race bodies. The Manu arranged with the Root-Manu to send Him large numbers of egos ready for incarnation-- those from globe D of the Moon Chain who had complete causal bodies, and who had individualised in the lunar fourth and fifth Rounds. Some of these came into the Tlavatli sub-race, and some later into the Toltec, when it was evolved; and then He again incarnated in the latter, and founded the City of the Golden Gates, the first of many successive Cities of that name. The founding was about one million years ago, one hundred and fifty thousand years before the first great catastrophe which rent the continent of Atlantis.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
После многих поколений молодой расы которые потребовались для освоения своего континента — Атлантиды — начали приходить группы эго с промежуточной Нирваны для одушевления тел четвёртой Расы. Ману договорился с Коренным Ману и отправил Ему большое число эго готовых принять инкарнацию; эти эго пришли с планеты D лунной Цепи и они имели завершённые каузальные тела, а также среди них были бывшие животные индивидуализировавшиеся в четвёртом и пятом Раундах. Некоторые из них пришли в подрасу Тлаватей, другие позже пришли в расу Толтеков когда она стала достаточно развитой; Он вновь взял инкарнацию в последней и основал Город Золотых Ворот — первый среди городов с таким именем. Это произошло примерно один миллион лет назад, за 150,000 лет до первой великой катастрофы которая опрокинула Атлантов.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Toltec was at this time the ruling Race, by virtue of its great superiority. It was a warrior race, going all over the world and subduing its inhabitants, but its pure types never formed the lower classes anywhere. Even in the City of the Golden Gates, only the aristocracy and the middle class were Toltec; the lower classes were of mixed blood, and were largely composed of men and women taken captive in wars with other sub-races, and reduced to servitude by their conquerors.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В те времена Толтеки были правящей расой благодаря своему значительному превосходству. Это была раса воинов идущих по всему миру и покоряющих всех людей. Чистые Толтеки никогда не занимали низших классов, даже в Городе Золотых Ворот аристократия и средний класс были Толтеками, в то время как низший класс был сформирован из порабощённых в войнах мужчин и женщин из разных подрас.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At this time arrived on Earth a ship-load of egos, in a group of whom-- which kept much together-- we are specially interested, as it contained many old friends, Sirius, Orion, Leo and others; some of these were ear-marked on their arrival by Vaivasvata Manu-- the Manu of the fifth Race-- as part of His future materials. Hence H. P. Blavatsky speaks of the founding of the fifth Race as occurring one million years ago, though it was only led out from Atlantis in 79,997 B.C. These, later, formed the group with an average 1,200 to 1,000 years' interval between death and re-birth.1 (¹ These intervals must be taken provisionally; the intervals between death and re-birth in this group and in the one mentioned below were relatively about as these lengths.)
</view>
<view lang="ru">
На Землю прибыла группа эго к которой мы имеем особый интерес: в ней были Сириус, Орион, Лео и другие; некоторые из них получили отметку на ухе от Вайваствата Ману — Ману пятой Расы — в знак того, что они будут частью Его расы в будущем. Хотя Е.П. Блаватская говорит об основании пятой Расы как созданной миллион лет назад, она начинает свой путь из Атлантиса лишь 79,997 bc. Они позже образовали группу с интервалом между смертью и рождением в 1,000-1,200 лет.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The interval between death and re-birth was at this time naturally somewhat shorter, for the material gathered in these primitive lives was not enough to make a long interval, however thinly spread out. The people were not yet capable of deep feeling, though making something out of the heaven-life. In the heaven-world these egos kept together, and the filmy beings connected with them in the intuitional sphere showed a strong affinity for each other. In the lower spheres there was apparently a dull, groping, sense of ` want,' as though they were very dimly sensing the absence of the old friends of former lives and of the Inter-Chain interval, who were still sleeping away in the Inter-Chain Nirvana, not to arrive on Earth for another 400,000 years. In the intuitional sphere, these 700-year people were in touch with the 1,200-year group, but it was only when the former arrived on the Earth that there was a time of general rejoicing among the egos in the higher mental sphere, due chiefly to the arrival of those who were the most deeply loved and revered-- the future Masters. Those immediately connected with some of the earlier group were still in that Nirvana, although others had come to earth with the 1,200-year set, among them the two future Masters who now wear English bodies.1 (¹ They were once Sir Thomas More and ` Philalethes' Thomas Vaughan.) A good deal of slight retarding or hastening of re-birth was resorted to, in order to keep the group together in incarnation.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Интервал между смертью и перерождением был в те времена немного короче, так как материал собранный в этих примитивных телах был недостаточно хорош для большего, он будто был тонко размазан. Люди всё ещё не были способны к проявлению глубоких чувств, хотя и проявляли некоторую активность в небесной жизни. Эти эго в небесном мире держались вместе; тонкие существа соединялись с ними в интуитивной сфере проявляя сильную привязанность друг к другу. В нижних сферах было похожее слепое чувство одиночества, будто они смутно ощущали отсутствие своих старых друзей из прошлых жизней и периода сна в Внутренней Нирване, которые не придут на Землю ещё долгих 400,000 лет. В интуитивной сфере 700-летние люди были близки к 1,200-летним. Когда первые прибывали на Землю, среди всех эго на высшем ментальном плане распространялось чувство ликования, в осном потому что прибывающие — будущие Мастера — были наиболее любимы и уважаемы. Те кто непосредственно связаны с некоторыми из ранней группы всё езё были в Нирване, хотя другие прибыли на Землю с 1,200 летней группой, среди них были два будущих Мастера которые сейчас носят английские тела: сэр Томас Мур и "Филателист" Томас Воган. Для некоторых людей интервал между инкарнациями был немного увеличен, чтобы сохранить ранее сформированные группы эго вместе.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In one of these early lives, Corona ² (² Known in later history as Julius Caesar.) -- a very fine fighter-- came from the City of the Golden Gates, and conquered the Tlavatli tribe in which our friends had incarnated. Unconscious as he was of the tie between them, he was yet influenced by it, and treated the tribe kindly: instead of carrying them off as slaves, he introduced various improvements, and incorporated the tribe into the Toltec Empire. Sirius took several births in the Tlavatli sub-race, and then passed into the Toltec. Glancing forward, we saw him once incarnated among the Rmoahals, in order to be with Ursa and others, then several lives were passed in the Turanian, the fourth sub-race-- a Chinese stage-- and a number in the Akkadian, the sixth; he was observed trading among a people who resembled the Phoenicians of later times. He did not take the sub-races in any special order, and it is difficult, at present, to generalise on this question.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В одной из этих ранних жизней Corona — очень хороший боец известный в поздней истории как Юлий Цезарь — пришёл из Города Золотых Врат и покорил племя Тлавати в котором однажды жили наши друзья. Неосознавая наличие уз между собой и завоёванными он, тем не менее, поступил с ними мягко: вместо того, чтобы превратить их в рабов, он интегрировал племя в Толтекскую Империю. Сириус несколько раз родился в подрасе Тлавати и затем перешёл в расу Толтеков. Глядя в будущее мы замечаем его рождение среди Рмоашалов для того, чтобы быть вместе с Урсой и другими, затем несколько жизней он проводит Туранцем — четвёртой китайской подрасы — и несколько раз Аккадцем в шестой подрасе; он был торговцем среди людей напоминающих поздних финикийцев. Он не рождался в подрасах в каком-то особенном порядке.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Ship-loads of egos continued to arrive, and the main cause of separation seemed to be the method of individualisation. Egos of all Rays, or temperaments, of similar general development were mixed up, but those of different intervals between re-births were not. Nor was there any mingling of the large classes of the Moon-Men and Animal-Men. Unless an individual had been taken through the Inner Round, and had undergone its special forcing, when he passed into the class ahead of him, the broad lines of distinction remained, and one class did not overtake another. Even when the Basket-works had completed their causal bodies, the basket origin remained discernible.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Группы эго продолжали прибывать. Основным методом индивидуализации, кажется, оставалась причина разделения. Эго всех Лучей или темпераментов одного уровня развития были перемешаны. Эго с разными интервалами между инкарнациями были разделены, также были разделены лунные люди и люди-животные. Иногда человек проходил через внутренний круг и подвергался его особому воздействию: тогда он переходил в класс который раньше был выше него. Общая схема разделения классов оставлась прежней: один класс не мог обогнать другой; даже Когда "корзины" завершили свои тела, их относительное положение осталось прежним.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The first ship-load containing the 700-year group arrived on Earth about 600,000 B.C. , some 250,000 years after the first great cataclysm which rent the continent of Atlantis. With it came the future Masters, Mars and Mercury and others, and Mars was born in the north in the Tlavatli sub-race, with Surya and Mercury for his father and mother. Herakles was also in the family, as an elder sister. Surya was the Chief of the tribe, and Mars, his eldest son, soon became its foremost warrior.1 (¹ See the Proem for these and other names.) At the age of fifteen, he was left for dead on a battle-field, but was searched for and found by his sister, who was passionately devoted to him, and who nursed him back to health. He succeeded his father as Chief, and had his first experience of earthly rule.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Первая группа эго с 700-летними людьми прибыла на Землю примерно 600,000 bc, около 250,000 лет спустя случился первый великий катаклизм который уничтожил Атлантиду. Среди них были будущие Мастера — Марс, Меркурий и другие — Марс родился на севере подрасы Тлавати в семье, где родителями были Меркурий и Surya. Геракл был в этой семье старшей сестрой. Surya был главой племени, а его старший сын Марс вскоре стал лучшим воином. В пятнадцать лет он был оставлен на поле боя умирать, но старшая сестра которая его сильно любила, искала его на поле, нашла и своей заботой смогла вернуть ему здоровье. Он пошёл по стопам отца и стал Главой, получив первый опыт управления людьми.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
There was one quite small but interesting group, only 105 in number who arrived about the same period, 600,000 B.C. , but who did not come from the Moon. It was a contingent arranged for specially by the Head of the Hierarchy, and seemed to consist of some who in Venus had been pet animals of the Lords of the Flame, and were so strongly linked to Them by affection, that without Them they would not have evolved. They had individualised on Venus, and were brought over here, and He placed them all in the first and second Rays. There were other small groups, abnormal in evolution. Thus one little group, belonging to the third Round, was sent over to Mercury, for the special treatment possible under Mercury conditions, and was then brought back here. Some underwent treatment of this kind in preparation for the fifth Root Race. It may be noted that H. P. Blavatsky speaks of some who came to the Earth from Mercury.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Мы заметили одну очень небольшую, но очень интересную группу в которой было всего 105 человек; они прибыли в то же время — около 600,000 bc. Они пришли не с Луны, а были направлены Главой Иерархии и, кажется, что они были домашними животными Лордов Огня ещё на Венере и так сильно привязались к ним, что не могли развиваться сами по себе. Они индивидуализировались на Венере и были перенесены на Землю в первый и второй Лучи. Кроме них были другие странные группы с необычной эволюцией. Одна такая группа из третьего Раунда была отправлена на Меркурий в особые условия, после чего была возвращена назад. Такая тренировка была необходима для подготовки к пятому Раунду. Вы, возможно, помните, что Е.П.Блаватская говорит о некоторых людях которые пришли на Землю с Меркурия.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Herakles' third birth on earth was in the same tribe, in which many members of the group were re-united. They had a certain amount of civilisation, but the houses were mere huts, and-- the climate being warm-- the clothing was scanty. The life was marked by the re-knitting of the undesirable link with Scorpio, and has therefore a certain importance for those concerned. The tribe in which Herakles was a warrior was attacked by a very savage tribe to which Scorpio belonged; the plan of the latter was to surprise the other tribe and slaughter it as a sacrifice to their deity, or, failing that, to commit suicide, and thereby gain power to torment their enemies from the other world. They performed magical rites of an Obeah-like nature, which, though done in secret, seemed to have become known to Herakles. The final suicide was essential to the success of the whole plan of after-death activity , and the weird spells, with many tremendous ` curses and swears,' became then effective: the result of these was apparently as much dreaded by their foes as it was valued by themselves. The attack failed, and they proceeded to carry out the alternative to victory, a general suicide with gruesome rites. Herakles, partly because his religion did not permit suicide, partly moved by superstitious fears, and partly by the thought that the savages would make nice brawny slaves, interfered and saved a number of them whom he captured and bound. Later on these folk plotted to assassinate him, and he had them executed; thus began again, this time on earth, a long series of antagonisms not yet exhausted.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Третее рождение Геракла на Земле произошло в том же племени к которому ранее присоединились многие члены группы. У них было некоторое представление о цивилизации, хотя их дома были простыми хижинами, а их одежда — из за тёплого климата — была крайне простой. Начало этой жизни было отмечено вновь появившейся нежелательной связью с Скорпио. Племя в котором Геракл был воином было атаковано крайне диким племенем к которому принадлежал Скорпио; план последних заключался в том, чтобы неожиданно напасть на врага и принести его в жертву своим божествам или, в случае неудачи, убить самих себя тем самым получив силу для причинения боли врагам. Они произвели магические действия чем-то похожие на ритуалы Обеах, однако это стало, судя по всему, известно Гераклу, несмотря на то, что обряды проводились в тайне. Массовый суицид в финале был существенной частью плана который предполагал активность после смерти. Многочисленные запутанные заклинания и проклятия возымели эффект: результат был определённо настолько ужасен для врагов, насколько они сами того ожидали. Атака провалилась и они перешли ко второй части плана — массовому самоубийству и отвратительным обрядам. Геракл, в свою очередь, отчасти потому что его религия не допускала суицида, отчасти из за суеверных страхов, а также благодаря здравой идее о том, что дикари могут стать неплохими выносливыми рабами, вмешался и захватил нескольких врагов. Позже, когда эта группа дикарей собралась тайно убить его, он их казнил. Таким образом на Земле продолжилось их противостояние.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It may be noted, as bearing on the closeness of ties set up between individuals and enduring for hundreds of lives, that from this time forward a set of persons within the large groups of 1,200- and 700-years' people-- a set which we may, for the sake of distinction, dub ` the Clan' -- while visiting almost every country in the world, kept generally together, and Sirius, especially, was rarely found to marry outside this little group. Taking a bird' s-eye view, we notice that there were occasional gatherings of the whole big Clan, as in the City of the Golden Gates when Mars was King, in Peru when he was Emperor, in the mainland near the White Island under the Manu, and in the second and third sub-races at their beginnings and their migrations-- to take a few instances out of many. Herakles turned out to be a fighting sort of person, clinging closely to Mars; Sirius a more peaceful one, following Mercury continually; Alcyone is also of that ilk, with Mizar. A good many belonging to the larger groups with whom we were very familiar in those early days, however, seem to have dropped out by the way, and we have not met them in this life; some may be just now in the heaven-world. The Theosophical Society is another instance of the gathering of this same Clan, and people are coming into it all the time, who turn out to be old friends. Some again, like Corona, are just now awaiting a favourable opportunity for incarnation.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Можно заметить, что близость определённой группы людей сохраняется на протяжении сотен жизней и группа с периодом 1,200 и 700 лет, которую для отличия от других мы назовём "Клан", перемещается по всему миру посещая почти каждую страну и при этом держится вместе, поэтому Сириус крайне редко вступал в брак за пределами этой маленькой группы. Бросив поверхностный взгляд мы заметили, что большой Клан редко собирался в полном составе; так было в Городе Золотых Врат где Марс был королём, в Перу где он был императором, на континенте рядом с Белым Островом Ману, а также в начале второй и третьей подрасах. Геракл оказался воинственной персоной и тяготел к Марсу, Сириус оказался более мирным и следовал за Меркурием, Алкион и Мицар были также этого типа. Многие из тех с кем мы были хорошо знакомы в те давние дни кажется пропали где-то по пути и мы не смогли их найти в нашей жизни; возможно, некоторые из них сейчас находятся в небесном мире. Теософическое Сообщество — один из примеров собрания всех членов Клана; новые люди постоянно приходят в него и оказывается, что они — наши давние друзья. Один из таких людей — Corona — сейчас ждёт благоприятной возможности для инкарнации.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The ship-loads continued to come in for a long time, only ceasing with the catastrophe of 75,000 B.C., so the phrase as to shutting the door evidently applies only to the animals coming up into humanity, and not to those whose causal bodies were already developed. The anthropoid apes, of whom H. P. Blavatsky spoke as still admissible to human bodies, would belong to the animal kingdom of the Moon, not to that of the Earth; they took up bodies produced by the “sin of the mindless,” and are the gorillas, chimpanzees, orang-utangs, baboons, and gibbons. They might be looked for in Africa, and might incarnate there in the still existing very low human races of Lemurian type.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Группы эго продолжали прибывать ещё в течении долгого периода, прервавшись на время катастрофы случившейся 75,000 bc, поэтому фраза о закрывшейся двери приложима только к животным которые ещё становятся людьми, а не к людям чьи каузальные уже полностью завершены. Человекоподобные обезьяны принадлежали к животному царству на Луне, но на Земле они возьмут тела произведённые "греха безумия" и станут гориллами, шимпанзе, орангутангами, бабонами и гиббонами. Их можно найти в Африке; они могут принять инкарнацию в ещё существующих сильно отстающих расах Лемурийского типа.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Coming down to 220,000 B.C. , to the City of the Golden Gates, we find Mars there ruling as Emperor, and bearing by inheritance the title of ` Divine Ruler,' transmitted from Those who had ruled in the past, the great Initiates of earlier days. Mercury was the chief Hierophant, the head of the State religion. It is remarkable how these two come down together through the ages, one always the Ruler, the Warrior, the other always the Teacher, the Priest. Noteworthy also is the fact that we never saw Mars in a woman' s body, whereas Mercury did take one from time to time.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Приближаясь к 220,000 лет до н.э. в Город Золотых Врат, мы находим Марса правящего там как Император и носящего звание "Божественного Правителя" унаследованного ещё с тех времён когда великие Посвящённые правили городом. Меркурий был главным жрецом — главой государственной религии. Интересно заметить, что эти два человека, проходя через эпохи, всегда оказываются вместе: один из них всегда Правитель и Воин, другой — Учитель и Священник. Также интересно заметить, что Марс никогда не принимал инкарнацию в женском теле, а Меркурий бывал в разных телах в зависимости от ситуации.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
There was quite a gathering of the Clan at this time. The Crown Prince was then Vajra, and Ulysses, who had been a successful leader on the frontier, was Captain of the Imperial Guard. This Guard formed a picked body of men, even the privates being of the upper classes, and they had charge of the Palace; they were not supposed to go out to war, but rather to strut about in gorgeous uniforms, to attend on the person of the Monarch during ceremonials, and increase his splendour. Later, however, after the death of Ulysses, Vajra became Captain of the Guard, and he persuaded his father to allow him to take his troop off into a campaign; being always a turbulent and restless person, he was not content to lead a life of show and luxury, and his soldiers, who adored him for his dash and courage, were willing enough to exchange their golden breastplates for the severer armament of war. Among them we find a number of our Clan: Herakles was there, with Pindar, Beatrix, Gemini, Capella, Lutetia, Bellona, Apis, Arcor, Capricorn, Theodoros, Scotus and Sappho. Herakles had as servant-boys three Tlavatli youths, captured in battle by his father and given to him-- Hygeia, Bootes, and Alcmene. The soldiers were distinctly rowdy, indulging in orgies of eating and drinking, and then rioting about the city; but they had the merit of respecting learning, paid reverence to the priests, and attended religious ceremonies as part of their Palace duty. They had a certain code of honour among themselves and kept it very rigidly, and in this was included the protection of the weak. Their homes were not unrefined, after a fashion, though not squaring with modern ideas.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В это время Клан собрался почти в полном составе. Vajra был коронованным принцом, а Ulysses был успешным лидером на фронте и Капитаном Имперской Гвардии. Эта Гвардия была сформирована из специально отобранных людей и даже её рядовые принадлежали к высшему классу и заседали в Дворце. Они не обязаны были участвовать в войнах; их обязанностью было важно ходить в эффектной одежде, внимательно слушать Монарха во время церемоний и делать церемонии более яркими. После смерти Ulysses, Vajra стал Капитаном Гвардии и убедил своего отца позволить участвовать в кампании. Vajra был очень бурной и свободолюбивой персоной и он не хотел посвятить всю свою жизнь роскоши; его солдаты обожали своего капитана за резкость и смелость и были готовы поменять свои нагрудные золотые эмблемы на простое обмундирование солдата. Среди них мы нашли многих из нашего Клана: Геракл, Пиндар, Беатрикс, Гемини, Капелла, Лютеция, Белонна, Апис, Аркор, Каприкорн, Теодорос, Скотус и Сапхо. Геракл имел трёх слуг — трёх Тлаватей захваченных в битве его отцом и подаренных ему — Хигея, Бутс и Алкмен. Солдаты были очень вульгарными, забывались в оргиях еды и питья, устраивали буйные гульбища по городу, но они также имели представление о послушании, уважали священников и внимали религиозным церемониям потому что это было частью из обязанностей во Дворце. У них был определённые кодекс чести и они следовали ему очень строго; защита слабых была частью этого кодекса. Их дома не были совсем неопрятными, хотя и были далеки от современных представлений о хорошем доме.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The death of Ulysses, the Captain of the Guard, must not be passed by unnoticed, for it linked in indissoluble bonds the three persons chiefly concerned. The Emperor Mars had placed in the Captain' s hands the care of his son Vajra, a daring, reckless lad; for the times were dangerous, conspiracies were rife in the Golden City, and the capture of the person of the Crown Prince would have been a great triumph for the conspirators. Hence Ulysses would not allow the Prince to leave the Palace grounds, much to that young man' s disgust. One day the Captain and the Prince were sitting at some little distance from the Palace, and a band of conspirators, greatly daring, crept up under the shelter of some bushes, and suddenly pounced upon the two. The Prince was struck down senseless, but Ulysses, bestriding his body, fought fiercely against the assailants, shouting for help. His cries were heard, and as he fell bleeding across the body of his young master, pierced by many wounds, some soldiers of the Guard came rushing up, and the conspirators took to their heels. The two unconscious bodies were lifted on to stretchers, carried to the Throne-room of the Palace, where the Emperor was sitting, and there laid at his feet. The dying Captain raised his eyes to his Emperor: “Sire, forgive; I did my best.”
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Смерть Ulysses, капитана Гвардии, не могла пройти незамеченной, ибо он был связан сильными узами с трёмя особо отмеченными людьми. Император Марс когда-то доверил Вайре заботу о своём беспечном сыне. Времена были опасные и заговорщики были обычным делом в Золотом Городе, поэтому захват Принца Corona был бы большим триумфом для них. Ulysses не позволял Принцу покидать пределы земель Дворца к большому неудовольствию последнего. Однажды Капитан и Принц сидели неподалёку от Дворца; банда очень смелых заговорщиков подползла к ним под кустами и внезапно набросилась на них. Принц был сражён на месте и упал без чувств, но Ulysses смог отбить первую атаку и яростно бился с нападающими, зовя на помощь. Его крик был услышал и когда он израненный упал поверх тела своего молодого хозяина сражённый многими ударами, показались солдаты Гвардии и заговорщики были вынуждены бежать. Два бесчувственных тела положили на носилки, отнесли в Тронный Зал Дворца где сидел Император и положили их у его ног. Умирающий Капитан поднял глаза на Императора и сказал: "Господин, прости, я сделал всё что мог".
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Emperor stooped down, and dipped his finger in the blood welling up from the Captain' s breast; he touched with it the forehead of the dying man, his own forehead and his feet, and musically his voice fell upon the silence. “By the blood that was shed for me and mine, the bond between us shall never be broken. Depart in peace, faithful servant and friend.” The words reached the ears already becoming dull; Ulysses smiled, and died. The young Prince, who was only stunned, revived. And the bond lasted on, millennium after millennium, and became the bond between Master and disciples, for ever unbreakable.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Император спустился с трона и коснулся пальцем крови текущей из груди Капитана, затем он коснулся пальцем лба умирающего человека, своего лба и стоп и напевно произнёс в безмолвном зале: "Пусть узы между кровью пролитой ради меня и моей кровью будут вечны. Иди с миром, преданный слуга и друг". Слова достигли ушей Ulysses; он улыбнулся и умер. Молодой Принц который был всего лишь оглушён, зашевелился. Узы связывающие Мастера и Ученика на протяжении миллионов лет стали навсегда нерушимыми.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The lives of Herakles were not remarkable in any way for a long time. They were spent in fighting, when the body was that of a man, in having very numerous babies when it was that of a woman.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Жизни Геракла были непримечательны во всех смыслах на протяжении долгого времени. Он прошёл через много сражений когда его тело было мужским и оставил многочисленных детей когда тело было женским.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The spread of black magic in Atlantis led up to the second great catastrophe of 200,000 B.C. , which left as remnants of the great continent which had joined Europe and Africa to America the huge islands of Ruta and Daitya. They endured until the catastrophe of 75,025 B.C. ¹ (¹ Usually given roughly as the 80,000 B.C. catastrophe.) overwhelmed them beneath the waters of the ocean we now call the Atlantic.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Распространение чёрной магии в Атлантисе привело ко второй великой катастрофе случившейся 200,000 bc, которая оставила от огромного континента соединявшего Африку с Америкой всего два больших острова: Рута и Дайта. Следующая катастрофа случилась 75,025 лет до н.э. и остатки Атлантиды скрылись под волнами океана который сейчас называется Атлантический.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
During the next hundred thousand years, the people of Atlantis flourished abundantly, and built up a mighty, but over-luxurious, civilisation. Its centre was in the City of the Golden Gates-- the name was preserved-- but it spread far and wide over the world, both over Africa and the West. Unhappily with the civilisation spread again also the knowledge giving control over nature which, used for selfish purposes, becomes black magic.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В течении следующей сотни тысяч лет люди Атлантиса построили могущественную, но чрезмерно пышную цивилизацию. Её центром был Город Золотых Врат — название осталось прежним — а влияние достигало всего мира, в том числе Африки и Америки. К несчастью с цивилизацией опять пришло знание как управлять природой и используемое для личных целей это знание превратилось в чёрную магию.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Members of the Clan came into it, more or less, sometimes being born into families immersed in it, and breaking away; sometimes dallying with it and being a little tarred therewith. Some experiences of Alcyone' s that often tormented him in the form of dreams in a later life may here be put on record.2 (² See ` Rents in the Veil of Time,' The Theosophist, May, 1910.) They happened in a life that occurred about 100,000 B.C. Corona was then the White Emperor at the City of the Golden Gates; Mars was a general under him, and Herakles was the wife of Mars. A great rebellion was being plotted, and a man of strange and evil knowledge,-- a ` Lord of the Dark Face,' leagued with the dark Earth-Spirits who form the ` Kingdom of Pan,' the semi-human, semi-animal creatures who are the originals of the Greek satyrs-- was gradually gathering round himself a huge army which followed him as Emperor, the Emperor of the Midnight Sun, the Dark Emperor, set over against the White. The worship he established, with himself as central idol-- huge images of himself being placed in the temples-- was sensual and riotous, holding men through the gratification of their animal passions. Against the White Cave of Initiation in the City of the Golden Gates was set up the Dark Cave in which the mysteries of Pan, the Earth-God, were celebrated. All was working up toward another great catastrophe.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Члены Клана иногда рождались в семьях чёрных магов и вырывались на свободу; иногда они игрались с чёрной магией чем себя несомненно позорили. Жизненный опыт Алкиона полученный в это время часто преследовал его в форме мучительных снов в следующих жизнях. 100,000 лет до н.э. Corona стал Белым Императором в Городе Золотых Врат, Марс был его генералом, а Геракл — его женой. Массовое восстание явило миру человека странного и злого — Тёмного Лорда — который заключил союз с тёмными Духами Земли и создал "Царство Мёртвых", царство получеловеческих существ фигурирующих в греческих мифах. Они постепенно собирались вокруг него в огромную армию, которая следовала за ним как за Тёмным Императором — противника Белого Императора. Он установил культ с собой в качестве центрального идола. Его огромные статуи и изображения были в тёмных храмах — изображения человека наслаждающегося своими животными страстями. Против Белого Храма Посвящённых в Городе Золотых Ворот был построен Тёмный Храм в котором проводились Мистерии Мёртвых и ритуалы поклонения Земному Богу. Всё шло к ещё одной великой катастрофе.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone, some one hundred and twenty lives back, was the son of a man who followed the hideous rites of this dark cult, but he held himself much aloof, shrinking from the wild orgies of animalism that enchained the bulk of the worshippers. But, as is too often the case, he fell into the trap baited by a woman' s beauty, and met a grievous fate. The story may be told, as it throws light on the conditions which brought down later upon Atlantis the heavy doom pronounced by the Occult Hierarchy.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Алкион, 120 своих жизней назад, родился сыном человека который следовал отвратительным обрядам этого тёмного культа. Однако он сторонился безумных оргий анимализма которые поработили массу фанатиков. К сожалению, как это часто бывает, Алкион попался в ловушку — пал перед женской красотой — и встретил печальную судьбу. Эту историю уместно рассказать, ибо она проливает свет на причины падения Атлантиса.
</view>
</text>
</body>