<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">The fifth sub-race, the teutonic</view>
<view lang="ru">Пятая Подраса: Тевтонская</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
WE must now turn back again to 20,000 B.C., in order to trace from its cradle the fifth sub-race, for it was prepared simultaneously with the fourth, although in a different way. For it the Manu had set apart a valley far from His capital, away on the northern side of the Gobi Sea, and into it He had sparingly introduced factors which had not appeared in the fourth. He brought back to it a few of the best specimens of His third sub-race from Persia, where it was by that time thoroughly specialised, and He called also for a few Semites from Arabia. He chose for it especially men who were tall and fair, and when He Himself was born in it He always used a body showing markedly those characteristics. It must be remembered that the Manu starts each sub-race just as he does the Root-Race-- by incarnating in it Himself; and the form which He chooses to take largely determines what the appearance of the sub-race shall be. This fifth sub-race was of a very strong and vigorous type, much larger than the preceding one, and was tall and fair, long-headed, with light hair and blue eyes. The character was also very different from that of the Keltic sub-race; it was dogged and persevering, with little of the dash of the fourth; its virtues were not of the artistic type, but rather of the business and common-sense practical sort, blunt and truthful, plain-spoken and straightforward, caring for the concrete rather than for the poetic.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Мы должны вновь вернуться к 20,000 лет до н.э. чтобы проследить за пятой подрасой от её колыбели, так как она создавалась одновременно с четвёртой, хотя и другим способом. Для неё Ману выделил долину вдали от столицы и от северного берега моря Гоби и внёс факторы которых не было в четвёртой подрасе. Он взял нескольких лучших представителей третьей подрасы из Персии, а также позвал нескольких Семитов из Аравии. Он выбрал исключительно высоких и светлых людей и когда он рождался среди них, то всегда проявлял в теле эти черты. Нужно помнить, что Ману начинал каждую подрасу также как и Коренную расу — Своим рождением в ней; и то тело которое Он выбирал значительно влияло на весь облик подрасы. Пятая подраса была сильной и стойкой, в гораздо большей степени чем предыдущая, и её люди были высокими, светлыми, длинноголовыми, светловолосыми и голубоглазыми. Характер был также непохож на Кельтский; они были упрямыми и настойчивыми, с небольшой напористостью от четвёртой подрасы; их достоинствами были не столько способность к искусствам, сколько умение вести бизнес и другие практические дела; они были простоваты и правдивы, с прямой незамысловатой речью приспособленной больше для конкретных тем чем для поэзии.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
While the fourth was developing its beautiful and artistic type in its own valley, the sterner fifth was also building up its type in its appointed abiding-place, the two different evolutions being thus carried on simultaneously. By the time that they were both ready to start on their migration, the difference between them was clearly marked; and though they left Central Asia together, 20,000 B.C., and passed together through Persia, their eventual destinies were quite different.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Пока четвёртая подраса развивала свои прекрасные способности к искусствам в своей собственной долине, суровая пятая подраса строила свой дом в назначенном месте: две эволюции шли рядом. К тому времени когда они были готовы для эмиграции, различия между ними стали очевидны и хотя они покинули Малую Азию вместе 20,000 лет до н.э. и вместе прошли через Персию, их конечные цели были совсем разными.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The fifth sub-race, small in number, was directed to move further along the shores of the Caspian Sea, and it settled itself in the Territory of Daghestan. There it slowly grew for thousands of years, gradually extending itself along the northern slopes of the Caucasian Range, and occupying the Terek and Kuban districts. There its people remained until after the great cataclysm of 9564 B.C.; indeed, it was nearly a thousand years after that before they began their great march to world-dominion. They had not been idle during this long time of waiting, for they had already differentiated themselves into several distinct types.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Пятая подраса с небольшим населением направила свой путь вдоль берегов Каспийского моря и обосновалась на территории Дагестана. Там она медленно росла тысячи лет, постепенно расширяя свои владения вдоль северных склонов Кавказкой цепи, захватывая земли Терека и Кубани. Там они оставались вплоть до великого катаклизма 9,564 лет до н.э. Спустя тысячу лет с того момента они начали великий поход для завоевания мира. Они не спали всё это время, так как уже разделились на несколько различных типов.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then, as with one accord, now that the swamps of the great Central European plain were becoming habitable, they moved north-westward in one mighty army as far as what is now Cracow in Poland. There they rested for some centuries, for the marshes were not yet dry enough for safe habitation, and disease fell upon them and thinned their ranks. It was chiefly from this secondary centre that the final radiations took place. The first of them was the Slavonic, and it branched off into two main directions. One party turned east and north, and from it come largely the modern Russians; the other took a more southerly direction, and is now represented by the Croatians, Servians, and Bosnians. The second wave was the Lettish, though its members did not travel far; it gives us the Letts, the Lithuanians and the Prussians. The third was the Germanic, and part at least of that went further afield, for if those called especially the Teutons, spread themselves over Southern Germany, the other branches, called the Goths and Scandinavians, swept to the northern point of Europe. The later descent of the Scandinavians upon Normandy, and of the Goths upon Southern Europe, the spreading of this fifth sub-race over Australia, North America and South Africa, and its dominance in India, where the Root-stock of its people is settled, belong to modern history.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Когда топи стали более пригодны для жизни, они отправились на северо-запад одной могущественной армией и достигли земли на которой сейчас стоит Краков в Польше. Там они оставались несколько столетий, ибо болота всё ещё не были вполне безопасны для проживания. Болезнь напала на них и изрядно проредила их народ. Эта земля стала центром распространения этой подрасы. Первыми стали Славяне которые позже разделились на две ветви. Первая частично направилась на северо-восток и из неё вышли современные Русские; вторая пошла южнее и из неё вышли современные Хорваты, Сербы и Боснийцы. Вторая волна была Латышской, хотя она далеко не ушла; она дала нам Латышей, Литовцев, Прусов. Третья волна была Германской и по крайней мере часть её ушла далеко от дома; эту волну часто называют Тевтонской. Они поселились на юге Германии. Другие её ветви называемые Готами и Скандинавами расположились на севере Европы. Позже Скандинавы заняли Нормандию, Готы — север Европы. Пятая подраса накрыла Австралию, Северную Америку и Южную Африку, а её представители в Ииндии принадлежат уже современной истории.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It has yet to build, like its predecessors, its World-Empire, though the beginnings of it are before our eyes. The terrible blunder of the eighteenth century, which rent away from Great Britain its North American Colonies, may be remedied by an offensive and defensive alliance between the severed halves, and a similar alliance with Germany, the remaining great section of the Teutonic sub-race, would weld the whole sufficiently into one to make a federated Empire. Late events show the rising of India into her proper place in this extending Empire, destined to be mighty in the East as well as in the West.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Они как и их предшественники должны были построить Мировую Державу, и её истоки лежат перед нашими глазами. Ужасная ошибка восемнадцатого века отделившая от Великобритании её Северо-Американские колонии может быть сглажена военным или мирным союзом между разделёнными половинами и похожим союзом с Германией, оставшейся частью Тевтонской подрасы, который бы скрепил части в целое создав федеративную Империю. Последние события показали как Индия взбирается на положенное место в расширяющейся Империи, которой предначертано стать могущественной как на Востоке так и на Западе.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
As this World-Empire rises to its zenith during the coming centuries, the group composed of men of the mightiest genius, spoken of on p. 69 , will be sent to take incarnation in it, to lift it to the highest pinnacle of literary and scientific glory, till it overtops the vanished Empires of the Arabians, the Persians, the Romans, those of the second, third, and fourth sub-races of the Aryan stock. For the resistless course of ages, unrolling the Divine Plan, must accomplish its purpose, until the fifth Race shall have played its part, and the sixth and the seventh shall have followed it, shaping such human perfection as belongs to the story of our earth in this fourth Round of our terrene Chain. What heights of unimaginable splendour lie hidden in the further future, no tongue of half-evolved man may tell.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Мировая Империя будет взбираться к своему зениту в течении грядущих столетий и группа собранная из могущественных гениев примет инкарнацию, чтобы поднять её на вершину литературной и научной славы, пока она не возвысится над сгинувшей Империей Арабов, Персов, Римлян и второй, третьей и четвёртой подрас Арийцев. Под непродолимым напором веков разворачивается Божественный План. Пятая Раса сыграет свою роль и шестая и седьмая последуют за ней, создавая совершенных людей в четвёртом Раунде нашей Земной Цепи. Какие высоты невообразимой славы лежат скрытыми далёким будущим не может передать язык на половину эволюционировавшего человека.
</view>
</text>
</body>