<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Man: Whither. Foreword.</view>
<view lang="ru">Человек: Куда. Предисловие.</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The following pages are an attempt to sketch the early beginnings of the sixth Root Race, comparable to the early stage of the fifth Root Race in Arabia. Ere the sixth Race comes to its own, and takes possession of its continent, now rising slowly, fragment after fragment, in the Pacific, many, many thousands of years will have rolled away. North America will have been shattered into pieces, and the western strip on which the first Colony will be settled will have become an easternmost strip of the new continent.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Последующие страницы — попытка сделать набросок ранних начал шестой Коренной Расы, сравнивая её с ранним этапом жизни пятой Коренной Расы в Аравии. До того как шестая Раса медленно возьмёт своё и захватит свой континент, сейчас медленно поднимающийся, часть за частью, в Тихом Океане, пройдёт много много тысяч лет. Северная Америка будет разбита на части и её западная полоса на которой поселится Колония, станет восточным краем нового континента.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
While this little Colony is working at the embryonic stage, the fifth Race will be at its zenith, and all the pomp and glory of the world will be concentrated therein. The colony will be a very poor thing in the eyes of the world, a gathering of cranks, slavishly devoted to their Leader.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Пока эта маленькая Колония работает в эмбриональной стадии, пятая Раса будет в своём зените и вся роскошь и богатство будет сконцентрировано в ней. Колония будет выглядеть очень малозначимой вещью в глазах мира — кучка причудливых людей подобострастно преданных своему Лидеру.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This sketch is reprinted from The Theosophist, and is wholly the work of my colleague.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Этот набросок переписан из журнала Теософист и полностью является работой моего коллеги.
</view>
</text>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">A.B.</view>
<view lang="ru">А.Б.</view>
</text>
</body>