<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">The second sub-race, the arabian</view>
<view lang="ru">Вторая Подраса: Арабская</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
IT will be remembered that when the Manu went to Shamballa-- after leading His little flock from Arabia to their temporary northern resting-place, and, after the great catastrophe of 75,025 B.C., bringing them to the White Island-- He was shown by the Head of the Hierarchy the plan which was to be followed in the shaping of His Race.1 (¹ See Chapter XIV.) Four long valleys-- running back through the mountain range which lay twenty miles from the shore of the Gobi Sea, separated from each other by intervening hills-- were to be used by Him for the segregation and training of four distinct sub-races. This work was now to begin.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Вы наверное помните, что когда Ману отправился в Шамбалу — после того, как провёл свой маленький народ из Аравии во временное поселение на севере и после великой катастрофы 75,025 лет до н.э. когда он отвёл их на Белый Остров — Ему был показан план Главой Иерархии которому нужно было следовать при формировании Его Расы. Четыре больших долины, лежащие за горами в двадцати милях от моря Гоби отделялись друг от друга холмами, должны были использоваться для образования и тренировки четырёх подрас. Эта работа должна была начаться сейчас.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Manu started by picking out from the great band of Servers-- who had been developing in the noble Aryan civilisation-- a few families, willing to act as pioneers, and, leaving the glorious City of the Bridge, to go out into the wilderness and found His new colony. A large group of people who, for the most part, are or have been in the Theosophical Society of our own times, were selected by Him for this pioneer work,¹ and of these a few families were sent out to lead the way. In the third generation Mars and Mercury took birth among the descendants of these, and then the Manu and some of the great people incarnated there to specialise the type, the Manu preparing a special body of the type at which He was aiming, and incarnating in it, when He had brought it to the desired point.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Ману начал выбирать из большой группы Служителей — которые развивались в благородной Арийской цивилизации — несколько семей желающих стать первопроходцами, покинуть великолепный Город Моста и отправиться в дикие земли, чтобы создать Его колонию. Большая группа людей, основная масса которой была или оказалась в Теософическом сообществе нашего времени, была выбрана Им для пионерской работы и из этих семей были выбраны несколько, чтобы те вели за собой остальных. Они делали, как и всегда, свою работу, открывали путь для новых типов человечества и цивилизации. Они были первопроходцами огромной надвигающейся армии, они очищали путь от джунглей, создавали дороги, перекидывали мосты через реки. Быть может эта работа неблагодарная, но необходимая и многим родственная по духу. Марс и Меркурий приняли воплощение в третьем поколении этой колонии. Ману и некоторые из великих людей также приняли воплощения, чтобы формировать тип. Ману подготовил особое тело к типу которого Он стремился и принял воплощение в нём.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
¹ They are doing, over again, what they have done so often before, breaking open the way for a new type of humanity and of civilisation. They are the pioneers, the sappers and miners, of a great advancing army, for which they are clearing away jungles, making roads, bridging rivers. The work may be thankless, but it is necessary, and to many congenial.
</view>
<view lang="ru">

</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This latter group of highly developed Personages set the type whenever a new sub-race is founded, and the type is then seen at its best: it is the Golden Age to which each nation looks back in later days. Then the younger egos come in and carry it on, unable, of course, to keep at the level set. There is in each case, a group of younger egos sent to prepare the way; then some older ones come, of the rank which now includes Masters; from these the greater people take bodies and set the new type. The juniors then flock in and do the best they can with it, at first led by some of their seniors, and then later left to themselves to learn their lessons by experience.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Последняя группа выдающихся личностей устанавливала тип людей каждый раз когда формировалась новая подраса и этот тип был лучшим среди её представителей: это был Золотой Век на который все нации оглядывались позже. Затем пришли более молодые эго, неспособные, конечно, держать столь высокую планку. В каждом случае группа молодых эго подготаливала путь, за ними шли эго постарше среди которых сейчас есть Мастера, и наконец приходили ещё более великие эго создававшие новый тип людей. Начинающие вливались в поток и делали всё, что было в их силах, по началу ведомые более продвинувшимися эго и позже оставленные учиться на своих ошибках.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Among the juniors chosen to form the first pioneer families, we noticed Herakles-- a son of Corona and Theodoros-- with Sirius as wife, Sirius a tall, rather muscular woman, a notable housewife, and very kind to her rather large family, among whom we observed Alcyone, Mizar, Uranus, Selene and Neptune.¹ (¹ See Appendix vii, for the complete lists.) Herakles had brought some Tlavatli nobles as captives from a foray, and the son of one of these, Apis, married his niece Gemini, much to the anger of the proud Aryan family, that looked on this marriage as a mésalliance -- an unworthy mixing of their pure blood; but doubtless it was quietly arranged by the Manu, in order that a Tlavatli intermixture might be brought in! They had Spica and Fides as twins, a quaint little pair. Hector and Aurora were another married pair of the emigrant families, and their daughter Albireo married Selene; they had Mercury as child. Uranus married Andromeda, and Mars and Venus were born to them, and Vulcan appeared as a son of Alcyone.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Среди пионеров выбранных для создания новой подрасы мы заметили Геракла — сына Corona и Теодоруса — со своей женой Сириусом, которая тогда была высокой и довольно мускулистой женщиной, хорошей хозяйкой и очень заботливой мамой в семье в которой мы заметили Алкиона, Мицара, Урана, Селену и Нептуна (см. приложение 7). Геракл привёл с собой несколько благородных Тлаватей в качестве пленных после набега и их сын, Апис, женился на его племяннице Gemini, к большому негодованию гордой Арийской семьи, которые смотрели на этот брак как на мезальянс — нежелательное смешение их чистой крови; но, несомненно, этот брак был полностью рассчитан Ману который решил, что примесь крови Тлаватей не помешает. У них родились близнецы Спика и Файдс — необычная маленькая пара. Гектор и Аврора были другой парой из эмигрантов и их дочь Альбирео вышла замуж за Селену; у них родился сын Меркурий. Уран женился на Андромеде и у них родились Марс и Венера, а Вулкан родился сыном Алкиона.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It will be noticed here that two who are now Masters, Uranus and Neptune, were born in the second generation; Mars and Venus, both now Masters, were born in the family of these in the third; Mercury, now a Master, was also born in the third, a child of Selene; and Vulcan, also now a Master, in the third, a child of Alcyone. In the fourth generation the Manu appeared, as a son of Mars and Mercury.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Можно заметить, что те двое, которые сейчас Мастера — Уран и Нептун — родились во втором поколении; Марс и Венера, которые сейчас также мастера, родились в третьем поколении; Меркурий, также сейчас Мастер, родился тоже в третьем, как сын Селены; Вулкан, также Мастер, оказался сыном Алкиона. В четвёртом поколнее родился Ману, как сын Марса и Меркурия.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At this time some of our friends were living in the City of the Bridge-- Castor among them, married to Rhea. They thought the people who went to the valley were behaving very foolishly, for the existing civilisation was a very fine one, and there was no sense in going off to make a new one, and to plant turnips in an unreclaimed valley, instead of living in the culture and order of the City. Besides the new religion followed by the valley-dwellers was quite unnecessary, the old one being much better. Another of the friends who accompany Castor through the ages, Lachesis, was a ponderous merchant, with Velleda as a hasty short-tempered son, who was impolite to customers, much to the displeasure of his courteous father. Lachesis had married Amalthea, and she ran away with Calypso, a proceeding which was considered to be most improper. As she and her lover were not received in the City, they went to the valley, but met there with no warmer welcome.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В это время некоторые из наших друзей жили в Городе Моста — среди них был Кастор женатый на Рее. Они думали, что люди отправляющиеся в долину ведут себя очень глупо, ибо существующая цивилизация была очень хорошей и не было никакой необходимости уходить и создавать новую, сажать репу в ещё непаханной земле и жить за пределами культуры Города. Кроме того, новая религия которой следовали обитатели долины была вовсе излишней, ибо старая была намного лучше. Ещё один друг сопровождающий Кастора на протяжении веков был Лачесис — грузный купец со своим сыном, который был невежлив с покупателями к большому неудовольствию всегда тактичного отца. Лачесис женился на Амальтее и та убежала с Калипсо. Поскольку она и её возлюбленный не были приняты в Городе, они отправилисьв долину, но встретили не намного более тёплый приём.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The visit of a Toltec Prince from Poseidonis to the City showed an old friend, Crux, in his person, and among his suite was another old friend, Phocea.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Визит Принца Толтеков из Посейдониса в Город явил нам старого друга в его лице — Crux — а среди его свиты мы нашли другого старого знакомого — Фоцию.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
For some centuries the people in the valley increased and multiplied, the careful specialisation going on, until in 40,000 B.C., the Manu thought them sufficiently numerous and sufficiently prepared to be sent out into the world. He sent them out under the leadership of Mars, supported by Corona and Theodoros, to retrace the way by which so many thousands of years ago they had come, to try to Aryanise the descendants of the Arabs whom they had left behind, for these, of all the Atlanteans, were the nearest to the possession of the new characteristics. These Arabs were still where He had settled them-- a number of half-civilised tribes occupying the whole of the Arabian peninsula, and with a few settlements on the Somali coast. A strong and friendly power existed at that time in the region now called Persia and Mesopotamia, and the Manu-- who had later joined the emigrants and headed His forces-- had no difficulty in obtaining permission to march His host through it along a carefully indicated and guarded route. It is noteworthy that this migration differs in character from those of later years. In those which descended into India the entire tribe moved, from the old men and women to the babies; but in this case the old and those with many young children were advised to stay behind, and the migration was confined to men of fighting age, with their wives and a comparatively small number of children. Many also were young unmarried men. The number of fighters was about 150,000 and the women and children may have added another 100,000 to the party.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Несколько столетий люди в долине размножались под тщательным присмотром и 40,000 лет до н.э. Ману решил, что они достаточно многочисленны и подготовлены и их можно отправить в большой мир. Они пошли за Марс которому помогали Corona и Теодорус по пути, который они проложили много тысяч лет назад, чтобы попробовать распространить Арийскую расу среди потомков Арабов оставленных когда-то позади. Эти Арабы всё ещё оставались там, где их оставили — немногочисленные полуцивилизованные племена занимающие весь Аравийский полуостров и частично побережье Сомали. В те времена на землях Персии и Месопотамии жил многочисленный и сильный народ, дружественный к Ману и тот без проблем договорился о перемещении своего народа через их земли по размеченному и хорошо охраняемому маршруту. Нужно заметить, что эта миграция отличалась по характеру от тех, что происходили в более поздние года. Среди тех кто отправился в Индию были все, от мужчин до женщин и детей; в этом случае старики и дети были оставлены позади и лишь мужчины способные сражаться составили основу переселения, вместе со своими женами и сравнительно небольшим числом детей. Многие из них были молодыми неженатыми мужчинами. Число бойцов составило 100,000, а женщины и дети добавили ещё примерно 100,000 человек.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Manu had sent messengers two years before to prepare the Arab tribes for His coming, but the news had not been altogether favourably received, and He was by no means sure of a welcome. When He had crossed the belt of desert which then, as now, separated Arabia from the rest of the world, and came in sight of the first of the Arab settlements, a body of armed horsemen appeared in front of Him and incontinently attacked the van of His army. He easily repulsed them, and, capturing some of them, endeavoured to make them understand that His mission was peaceful. The language had changed so much that they had great difficulty in understanding one another at all, but He contrived to reassure His captives and sent them to arrange an interview with their Chief. After some trouble and the interchange of more messages, the Chief came, suspicious and unconciliatory; but a long conversation and full explanations somewhat changed his attitude, and it occurred to him that he might use this unusual sort of invasion for his own purposes. He was at deadly feud with a neighbouring tribe, and while he had no force fit to cope with the Manu' s capable-looking army, he felt that if he could enlist these strangers on his side he could make short work of his ancient enemies. So he temporised, and agreed to allow the visitors to establish themselves in a great desolate valley on the borders of his territory.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Ману отправил посланцев к Арабам за два года до своего прибытия, чтобы подготовить тех к своему визиту, но эти новости были несомненно не по душе принимающей стороне и Ману ни в коем случае не рассчитывал на тёплый приём. Когда Он пересек песчаный пояс отделяющий в наши дни Аравию от остального мира и попал в поле зрения первого поселения Арабов, группа экипированных всадников тотчас атаковала его фургоны. Он легко отбил атаку и захватил нескольких с тем, чтобы попытаться убедить их в своих мирных намерениях. Язык изменился столь сильно, что они с трудом понимали друг друга и Ману отправил захваченных за своим главарём, чтобы говорить с ним. После некоторых проблем с обменом сообщениями, прибыл главарь — настроенный с подозрением к Ману. После длительной беседы и полного разъяснения миссии, в его взгляде что-то изменилось и он решил, что этот необычный вид вторжения можно использовать для своих личных целей. Он был в длительной войне со своими соседями и не имея достаточных сил которые можно было бы противопоставить хорошо экипированной армии Ману, он решил, что если сумеет заманить эту армию на свою сторону, то сможет быстро решить свои проблемы с соседями. Он подумал и дал согласие на то, чтобы необычные гости разместились на большой одинокой долине на окраине его земель.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
They thankfully accepted this offer, and very soon changed the whole aspect of that valley. Coming as they did from a highly-civilised nation, they knew all about the science of well-boring, and they presently had the entire valley efficiently irrigated, and a great stream flowing down the middle of it. Within a year the whole of their tract of country was thoroughly cultivated and some good crops had already been obtained; in three years they were fully established as a prosperous and self-supporting community.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Они с благодарностью приняли это предложение и очень скоро полностью изменили облик той долины. Они имели опыт высокоцивилизованной жизни и знали многое о бурении колодцев, вскоре вся долина была обильно орошаема из огромного потока бьющего из середины долины. В течении года та часть страны которая им досталась полностью культивировалась и некоторый урожай уже был собран. В течении трёх лет они создали процветающее и самодостаточное общество.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Chieftain who had received them, however, was by no means satisfied; he cast a jealous eye upon the improvements they had made, and felt that, as this was part of his territory, his own people and not strangers ought to reap the advantages of it. Also, when asked to join in predatory expeditions, the Manu had said quite plainly that although He was grateful to His host and ready at any time to defend him from aggression, He would be no party to an unprovoked attack upon peaceable people. This made the Chief very angry-- the more so as he did not see his way to enforcing his commands. At last he patched up a peace with his hereditary enemy, and induced him to join him in an endeavour to exterminate the new-comers.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Однако тот Вождь, который принял их, был ни в коей мере удовлетворён происходящим и с жадностью смотрел на успехи небольшого народа. Он считал, что раз уж эти люди живут на его территории, то его подданые, а не гости должны получать плоды работы. Когда Ману попросили присоединиться к хищному набегу, он ответил спокойно, что хотя он очень благодарен Вождю за его гостеприимство и готов в любое время защитить его землю от агрессии, он не составит ему компанию в неспровоцированной атаке на мирных людей. Вождь пришёл в ярость — большее что он мог сделать, так как не видел способа заставить Ману подчиниться. Вождь заключил мир со своим давним врагом и предложил совместными усилиями искоренить своих гостей.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This little scheme, however, came hopelessly to grief; the Manu defeated and killed both the Chiefs, and made Himself Ruler over their combined States. Their subjects, when once the battle was over, philosophically accepted a new Ruler, and soon found that they were much more prosperous and happy under the improved regime, though it involved less fighting and more regular work. Thus the Manu made secure his footing in Arabia, and promptly proceeded to Aryanise his new subjects as rapidly as possible. Other tribes attacked Him now and then, but were so invariably defeated with heavy loss that they presently came to recognise the wisdom of letting Him alone. As years rolled on His kingdom prospered mightily, and grew ever stronger, while constant internecine struggles enfeebled and impoverished the other tribes. The natural result followed: by degrees, by taking opportunities as they offered, He absorbed tribe after tribe, usually without bloodshed and with the full consent of the majority. Before His death, forty years later, the upper half of Arabia owned His sway, and might be regarded as definitely Aryan. He might have acquired sovereignty over the south as well, but for the advent of a religious fanatic, who reminded his people that they were a chosen race; this man-- whom, as he will reappear later, and therefore needs a distinguishing name, we will call Alastor-- took his stand on the directions of their Manu, given in ancient days, forbidding them to intermarry with aliens. They must therefore on no account intermingle their blood with that of these Gentiles, who came no one knew whence, with their pretended civilisation and their odious tyranny, which denied to man even his inalienable right to kill his fellow-man freely, whenever he pleased. This appealed to the fierce impatience of control which is a prominent feature of the Arab character, and the southern tribes, who had for centuries squabbled viciously among themselves, actually united now to oppose their re-incarnated Leader. And they opposed Him in His own name, making His original order as to purity of race their rallying cry against Him.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Эта несложная схема, однако, была обречена на неудачу и Ману убил обоих Вождей и сам стал Правителем их объединённых государств. Когда битва подошла к концу, подданные приняли нового Правителя и вскоре обнаружили, что стали гораздо счастливее в государстве с новым режимом, так как он предполагал меньше войн и больше работы. Таким образом Ману сделал путь к Аравии безопасным и немедленно продолжил распространять Арийскую расу на новых землях. Разные племена предпринимали попытки напасть на Него, но были легко отброшены и пришли к мудрому решению оставить Его в покое. Годы шли и Его страна процветала, становилась ещё могущественнее чем раньше, в то время как другие племена истощали себя постоянными междуусобными войнами. Постепенно, используя возможности которые они предоставляли, Он поглощал одно племя за другим, обычно без кровопролития и с согласия большинства. Перед Его смертью, сорок лет спустя, верхняя половина Аравии была под Его контролем и была в полной мере Арийская. Он мог бы также захватить юг, если бы не религиозный фанатик который напоминал своим людям, что они избранная раса. Этот человек — который ещё встретится нам в истории и потому должен иметь отличительное имя, например Аластор — запретил людям вступать в браки с чужаками. Они не имели никакого желания смешивать свою кровь с язычниками, которые пришли неизвестно откуда, с их притворной цивилизацией и одиозной тиранией которая даже забирала у мужчины его неотъемлемое право убивать себе подобных по своему желанию. Яростное сопротивление внешнему контролю было заметной чертой характера Арабов и южных племён, столетиями враждовавших друг с другом; они даже объединились для сопротивления своему вновь воплотившемуся Лидеру.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It was quaint that Vaivasvata Manu should thus be used against Himself, but Alastor was really only an anachronism, set in a groove from which he could not be moved. When the Manu had needed a separate people He had forbidden intermarriage with outsiders; when He wished to Aryanise the descendants of His old followers, intermarriage became essential. But to Alastor-- as to many of his ilk-- growth and adaptation were heresy, and he played on the fanaticism of his followers.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Причудливость ситуации была в том, что Вайвасвата Ману должен был выступить против самого себя. Когда Ману нуждался в новом народе, Он запрещал заключать браки с чужаками; когда Он хотел распространить Арийскую расу, смешанные браки были необходимы. Но для Аластора, как и для многих его последователей, рост и развитие были чуждыми целями.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
While this long struggle was going on, the Manu had the joy, in one of the intervals of comparative peace, of receiving a visit from His mighty Brother, the Mahaguru-- the Buddha-to-be-- who came to the second sub-race ere it began its long career of conquest-- to indoctrinate it with the new religion which He had been teaching in Egypt as a reform of the ancient faith there prevailing.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Пока эта долгая битва шла своим чередом, Ману имел удовольствие принять в один из периодов мира визит своего могущественного брата Махагуру, который пришёл во вторую подрасу и начал долгое обучение новой религии которую Он преподал Египту вместо популярной тогда древней веры.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The great Atlantean Empire in Egypt-- which had quarrelled with Vaivasvata Manu when He was leading His people away from the catastrophe of 75,025 B.C., to settle in Arabia-- had perished in that cataclysm, when Egypt went under water. When the swamps later became inhabitable, a negroid people possessed the land for a while, and left behind them incongruous flints and other such barbarous remains to mark their occupation. After these, came the second Atlantean Empire with a great dynasty of Divine Kings, and with many of the heroes whom Greece later regarded as demi-gods, such as Herakles of the twelve labours, whose tradition was handed on to Greece. This Atlantean Empire lasted until about 13,500 B.C., when the Aryans came from southern India and made there an Empire of the Aryan root-stock. This Atlantean Empire was therefore ruling in 40,000 B.C., when the Manu was again in Arabia, and had attained to a very high state of civilisation, stately and splendid; it had immense Temples, such as that of Karnac, with long and very gloomy passages, and a very ornate ritual, with elaborate religious teaching.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Великая Египетская Империя Атлантов — мешавшая Ману уводить своих людей от катастрофы 75,025 лет до н.э. в Аравию — затонула вместе с Египтом после того катаклизма. Когда болота стали позже более пригодными для жизни, пришла негроидная раса и заняла землю на некоторое время, оставив после себя варварские следы. После них пришла вторая Империя Атлантов с великой династией Божественных Королей и многими героями которых позже в Греции вспоминали как Демиургов, вроде Геракла с его двенадцатью подвигами. Эта Империя существовала до 13,500 лет до н.э. когда Арийцы пришли с юга Индии и основали свою Империю — начало Арийской расы. Таким образом, Империя Атлантов правила 40,000 лет до н.э. когда Ману был в Аравии и добился к тому времени высокого развития в цивилизации; она имела огромные Храмы, вроде того, что был в Карнаке, с длинными тёмными коридорами; ритуалы были красивы, а религиозное обучение — тщательно выверенным.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Egyptians were a profoundly religious race, and they lived through the stories belonging to their faith with an intensity of reality of which only a faint reflection is now seen among Roman and Anglican Catholics on such days as Good Friday. They were psychic, and felt the play of super-physical influences, and hence were without scepticism as to the existence of higher beings and higher worlds; their religion was their very life. They built their huge Temples to produce the impression of vastness and greatness, to instil reverence into the minds of the lower-class people. All the colour and splendour of life circled round their religion. The people normally wore white, but the religious processions were gorgeous rivers of splendid colour, glittering with gold and gems. The ceremonies accompanying the celebration of the death of Osiris palpitated with reality; the mourning for the murdered God was real mourning; the people wept and wailed aloud, the whole multitude being carried away with passionate emotion and calling on Osiris to return.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Египтяне были глубоко религиозны и их жизнь столько тесно переплеталась с религиозными ритуалами, что в наши дни можно найти лишь слабое отражение это глубокой связи среди Романских и Англиканских Католиков во время церемонии Страстной Пятницы. Они имели развитую психику и чувствовали влияния сверхфизического мира и потому относились без скептицизма к существованию высших существ и высших миров; их религия была их жизнью. Они строили огромные Храмы производящее впечатление широты и величия с тем, чтобы внушить почтение в разумы людей низшего класса. Весь цвет и великолепие их жизни кружились вокруг религии. Обычно люди носили белое, но религиозные процессии облачались в восхитительные реки переливающихся цветов блистающих золотом и драгоценными камнями. Церемонии посвящённые смерти Осириса были вполне настоящими; скорбь по убитому Богу была истинной скорбью; люди искренне рыдали и причитали и вся толпа покидала церемонию с сильным желанием вернуть Осириса.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It was to this people that the Mahaguru came as Tehuti or Thoth, called later by the Greeks Hermes. He came to teach the great doctrine of the ` Inner Light' to the priests of the Temples, to the powerful sacerdotal hierarchy of Egypt, headed by its Pharaoh. In the inner court of the chief Temple He taught them of “the light that lighteth every man that cometh into the World”-- a phrase of His that was handed down through the ages, and was echoed in the fourth Gospel in its early Egyptian-coloured words. He taught them that the Light was universal, and that Light, which was God, dwelt in the heart of every man: “I am that Light,” He bade them repeat, “that Light am I.” “That Light,” He said, “is the true man, although men may not recognise it, although they neglect it. Osiris is Light; He came forth from the Light; He dwells in the Light; He is the Light. The Light is hidden everywhere; it is in every rock and in every stone. When a man becomes one with Osiris the Light, then he becomes one with the whole of which he was part, and then he can see the Light in everyone, however thickly veiled, pressed down, and shut away. All the rest is not; but the Light is. The Light is the life of men. To every man-- though there are glorious ceremonies, though there are many duties for the priest to do, and many ways in which he should help men-- that Light is nearer than aught else, within his very heart. For every man the Reality is nearer than any ceremony, for he has only to turn inwards, and then will he see the Light. That is the object of every ceremony, and ceremonies should not be done away with, for I come not to destroy but to fulfil. When a man knows, he goes beyond the ceremony, he goes to Osiris, he goes to the Light, the Light Amun-Ra, from which all came forth, to which all shall return.”
</view>
<view lang="ru">
К этим людям пришёл Махагуру в качестве Техути или Тота, позже названного Греками Гермесом. Он пришёл, чтобы учить великой доктрине "Внутреннего Света" жрецов Храмов — могущественной иерархии возглавляемой Фараоном. Во внутреннем дворе главного Храма Он сказал им: "свет освещает каждого человека пришедшего в этот мир". Эта фраза передавалась через эпохи и отразилась в четвёртом Евангелии. Он учил их, что этот Свет всеобщий и он есть Бог живущий в сердце каждого человека. "Я этот Свет" говорил Он и сказал повторить за Ним: "тот Свет есть я". "Этот Свет", говорил Он, "есть истинный человек, хотя тот может не узнавать его и даже отрицать его. Осирис есть Свет. Он пришёл прямо от Света. Он живёт в Свете. Он есть Свет. Свет скрыт везде. Он есть в каждой скале и каждом камне. Когда человек становится един с Осирисом, он становится един с целым частью которого он был и тогда он сможет видеть Свет в каждом, пусть тот плотно завуалирован, вдавлен внутрь и скрыт. Всего остального нет, но Свет есть. Свет это жизнь человека. Для любого человека — пусть он вовлечён в роскошные церемонии, пусть он жрец со множеством обязанностей и множеством возможностей помогать людям — Свет ближе к нему чем что-либо ещё, Свет внутри его сердца. Для каждого человека Реальность ближе любой церемонии, ибо ему достаточно повернуться внутрь и увидеть Свет. Это есть предмет любой церемении и ни одна церемония не должна происходить без этого. Когда человек знает, он идёт дальше церемонии, он идёт к Осирису, он идёт к Свету Амона-Ра из которого всё исходит и куда всё уйдёт."
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
And again: “Osiris is in the heavens, but Osiris is also in the very heart of men. When Osiris in the heart knows Osiris in the heavens, then man becomes God, and Osiris, once rent into fragments, again becomes one. But see! Osiris the Divine Spirit, Isis, the Eternal Mother, give life to Horus, who is Man, Man born of both, yet one with Osiris. Horus is merged in Osiris, and Isis, who had been Matter, becomes through him the Queen of Life and Wisdom. And Osiris, Isis, and Horus are all born of the Light.”
</view>
<view lang="ru">
И снова: "Осирис живёт на небесах, но Осирис также живёт в самом сердце человека. Когда Осирис в сердце узнает Осириса на небесах, тогда человек становится Богом и Осирис однажды разбитый на части вновь становится единым. Но посмотрите! Осирис Божественный Дух, Исис, Вечная Мать дают жизнь Хорусу который человек и человек рождается от обоих и в то же время только от одного Осириса. Хорус соединяется с Осирисом и Исис, которая была Материей и становится через него Королевой Жизни и Мудрости. Осирис, Исис и Хорус — все рождены от Света."
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
“Two are the births of Horns. He is born of Isis, the God born into Humanity, taking flesh of the Mother Eternal, Matter, the Ever-Virgin. He is born again into Osiris, redeeming his Mother from her long search for the fragments of her husband scattered over the earth. He is born into Osiris when Osiris in the heart sees Osiris in the heavens, and knows that the twain are one.”
</view>
<view lang="ru">
"Два есть рождения Хорнов. Он рождён от Исис, Бог рождён в Человечестве, взяв плоть Вечной Матери, Материи, Вечной Девственницы. Он вновь рождён в Осирисе, освобождая свою Мать от долгих поисков частей своего мужа разбросанного по всей Земле. Он рождается в Осирисе когда Осирис в сердце видит Осириса на небесах и узнает, что двое едины."
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So taught He, and the wise among the priests were glad.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Так учил Он и мудрые среди жрецов были довольны.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
To Pharaoh, the Monarch, He gave the motto: “Look for the Light,” for He said that only as a King saw the Light in the heart of each could he rule well. And to the people He gave as motto: “Thou art the Light. Let that Light shine.” And He set that motto round the pylon in a great Temple, running up one pillar, and across the bar, and down the other pillar. And this was inscribed over the doors of houses, and little models were made of the pylon on which He had inscribed it, models in precious metals, and also in baked clay, so that the poorest could buy little blue clay models, with brown veins running through them, and glazed. Another favourite motto was: “Follow the Light,” and this became later: “Follow the King,” and this spread westward and became the motto of the Round Table. And the people learned to say of their dead: “He has gone to the Light.”
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Фараону, Монарху, Он дал напутствие: "Ищите Свет", ибо лишь тот Король который может видеть Свет в сердцах других сможет хорошо править. Народу он дал напутствие: "Вы есть Свет. Пусть Свет сияет." Это напутствие Он оставил вокруг пилона в великом Храме на колонне, перекладине и другой колонне. Эта надпись была написана на дверях домов и маленьких моделях пилона на которых Он написал её, моделях из металла и моделях из обожённой глины, чтобы даже беднейшие могли купить маленькие синие глинянные пилоны с коричневой надписью. Другими любимыми лозунгами были "Следуй за Светом" и "Следуй за Королём" которые распространились на запад и стали девизом Круглого Стола. Люди научились говорить перед смертью: "Он ушёл к Свету".
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
And the joyous civilisation of Egypt grew yet more joyous, because He had dwelt among them, the embodied Light. The priests whom He had taught handed on His teachings and His secret instructions which they embodied in their Mysteries, and students came from all nations to learn the ` Wisdom of the Egyptians,' and the fame of the Schools of Egypt went abroad to all lands.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Счастливая Египетская цивилизация стала ещё счастливее, потому-что Он жил среди них — воплощённый Свет. Жрецы которым Он передал Свои учения и Свои тайные инструкции, воплотили это в Мистериях и студенты приходили из всех наций, чтобы учиться Мудрости Египтян и слава Египестких Школ распространилась далеко за пределы страны.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At this time He went over to Arabia, to teach the leaders of the sub-race settled there. Deep was the joy in each as the mighty Brothers clasped hands and smiled into each other' s eyes, and thought, in Their exile, of Their far-off home, of the City of the Bridge and of white Shamballa. For even the Great Ones must be sometimes weary, when They are living in the midst of the littleness of ignorant men.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Он отправился в Аравию, учить лидеров подрасы живущей там. Глубоко было счастье в каждом из могущественных Братьев, когда они пожали руки и улыбнулись в глаза друг другу и подумали о том, как далеко они от своего дома, Города Моста и Белой Шамбалы. Даже Великие могут уставать пока живут среди невежественных людей.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Thus to the second sub-race came the Supreme Teacher, and gave to them the doctrine of the Inner Light.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Таким образом ко второй подрасе пришёл Верховный Учитель и дал им учение о Внутреннем Свете.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
To return to the history of the growth of this people in Arabia. In consequence of the opposition raised against the Manu by Alastor in the south, the peninsula of Arabia was divided into two parts, and the Manu' s successors, for many generations, were satisfied to maintain their kingdom without seeking to increase its borders. After some centuries, a more ambitious Ruler succeeded to the throne, and, taking advantage of local dissensions in the south, marched his armies clear down to the ocean, and proclaimed himself Emperor of Arabia. He allowed his new subjects to retain their own religious ideas, and as the new Government was in many ways an improvement over the old, there was no lasting opposition to the conqueror.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Вернёмся к истории развития народа в Аравии. В дальнейшем, оппозиция против Ману выращенная Аластором на юге разделила полуостров Аравии на две части и последователи Ману на протяжении многих поколений согласились не искать путей расширения своих королевств через границы. Спустя несколько столетий к трону пришёл более абициозный Правитель и заметив разногласия на юге отправил свои армии к океану и провозгласил себя Императором Аравии. Он позволил свои новым подданым сохранить прежнюю религию и поскольку новое Правительство были во многих отношениях лучше старого, сопротивления завоевателю не оказывали.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A certain fanatical section of the southerners, however, felt it their duty to protest against what they considered the triumph of evil; and under a prophet of rude and fiery eloquence, they abandoned their conquered fatherland and settled as a community on the opposite Somali coast.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Одна секта фанатиков среди южан считала своим долгом идти против того, что они считали триумфом зла и под влиянием безумных ораторов они покинули земли и поселились на побережье Сомали.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
There, under the rule of the prophet and his successors, they lived for some centuries, greatly increasing in numbers, until an event occurred which caused a serious rupture. It was discovered that the ruling prophet of the period, while proclaiming fanatical purity of race, had himself formed an attachment to a young Negress from the interior. When this came to light there was a great uproar, but the prophet was equal to the occasion, and promulgated as a new revelation the idea that the stern prohibition against intermarriage was intended only to prevent them from mingling with the new-comers from the north, and did not at all apply to the Negroes, who indeed were to be regarded as slaves, as goods and chattels rather than as wives. This bold pronouncement divided the community; the majority accepted it, at first hesitatingly and then with enthusiasm, and black ` slaves' were purchased with avidity. But a fairly large minority rebelled against the revelation, and denounced it as merely a clumsy artifice to shield a licentious priest (as indeed it was); and when they saw themselves outvoted they drew apart in horror, and declared that they could no longer dwell amongst heretics who had abandoned all principle. An ambitious preacher, who had always yearned to be a leader, put himself at their head, and they made themselves into a huge caravan and departed in virtuous indignation. They wandered round the shore of the Gulf of Aden and up the coast of the Red Sea, eventually finding their way into Egyptian territory. Their curious story happened to take the fancy of the Pharaoh of the period, and he offered them an outlying district of his kingdom if they chose to settle there. They accepted, and lived there peacefully enough for centuries, flourishing under the beneficent Egyptian Government, but never in any way intermingling with its people.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Под правлением пророка и его последователей они жили там несколько веков, заметно увеличив численность, пока не случилось одно событие серьёзно им навредившее. Было раскрыто, что сам пророк фанатично вещавший о чистоте расы успел привязаться к одной молодой негритянке. Когда это вышло на свет, поднялся шум, но пророк ловко выкрутился из сложной ситуации сказав, что строгий запрет против смешанных браков придуман лишь для того, чтобы не смешивать свою кровь с чужаками с севера и этот запроет вовсе не распространяется на расу негров которых можно рассматривать как рабов, а не как жён. Столь сильное заявление разделило сообщество; большинство согласилось с ним, по началу нерешительно, но затем с энтузиазмом и алчностью начало покупать чёрных рабов. Но незаметное меньшинство выступило против нового откровения и заявило, что это простая и неуклюжая попытка защитить безнравственного жреца (каким он на самом деле был) и когда они увидели, что в меньшинстве, то в страхе отступили и сказали, что не могут больше оставаться среди еретиков поправших все принципы. Амбициозный проповедник который всегда желал быть лидером, поставил себя во главе протестующих и отбыл в огромном караване с чувством благородного негодования. Они обогнули побережье Аденского Залива и прошли к Красному Морю, случайно обнаружив путь на территорию Египта. Их любопытная история заинтересовала Фараона правящего в то время и он предложил им землю на границе Египетского Государства. Они приняли предложение и жили там в мире на протяжении столетий, расцветая под покровительством Египта, но никогда не вступали в брак с его людьми.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Eventually some Pharaoh made a demand upon them for additional taxation and forced work, which they considered an infringement of their privileges; so once more they undertook a wholesale migration, and this time settled in Palestine, where we know them as the Jews, still maintaining as strongly as ever the theory that they are a chosen people.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Однажды один Фараон наложил на них обязательства отдавать дань и делать принудительные работы. Они решили, что это нарушение их привелегий и снова были вынуждены отправиться в путь, на этот раз остановившись в Палестине. Сейчас мы их знаем как Евреев и они до сих пор поддерживают идею о своей избранности.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
But the majority, left behind in Somaliland, had their adventures also. Now that, owing to the slave-traffic, they became better known to the tribes of the interior, whom they had always previously kept rigidly outside their bounds, the savages realised the wealth to be obtained from robbing the semi-civilised, and the tribes began a series of descents upon the colony, which so harassed its members that, after fighting them for many years, losing thousands of lives, and finding their territory more and more circumscribed every decade, they too decided to abandon their homes, and migrate once more across the Gulf to the land of their fore-fathers. They were received in a friendly manner, and were soon absorbed into the general mass of the population. They had called themselves ` the true Arabs,' though they deserved that title less than any; and even to-day there is a tradition that the true Arabs landed at Aden, and slowly spread northwards; even to-day may be seen among the Hamyaritic Arabs of the southern part of the country the indelible traces of that admixture of negroid blood so many thousands of years ago; even to-day we may hear a legend that the Mostareb or adscititious Arabs of the northern half went away somehow for a long time into Asia, far away beyond Persia, and then returned, bearing with them many marks of their stay in foreign lands.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Но большинство осталось в Сомали со своими приключениями. Занявшись работорговлей они стали больше известны для племён внутренней части острова. Дикари обнаружили, что можно получить богатство совершая набеги на полуцивилизованных людей и они начали серию набегов на колонию, которая столь сильно истощилась от этого, что после многих лет сражений, потеряв тысячи людей и теряя всё больше территории, они также ришили покинуть дома и мигрировать через пролив на землю своих праотцов. Они были приняты дружелюбно и вскоре влились в основную массу населения. Они назвали себя "истинными Арабами", хотя заслужили это звание меньше чем кто-либо другой; даже в наши дни бытует мнение, что истинные Арабы живут на земле Аден и медленно перемещаются на север; даже сегодня среди Хамиарити Арабов в южной части страны можно заметить несмываемые следы негроидной крови; даже сейча слышна легенда об Арабах северной половины которые отправились на долгое время в Азию, далеко за пределы Персии и затем вернулись, принеся с собой множественные следы пребывания в иностранных землях.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The second sub-race grew and increased, flourishing exceedingly for many thousands of years, and extending its dominion over nearly the whole of Africa, except that part which was in the hands of Egypt. Once, very much later, they invaded Egypt, and for a short time ruled as the Hyksos Kings, but their palmy days were when they ruled the great Algerian island, pushed their way down the east coast to the very Cape of Good Hope itself, and founded a kingdom which included all Matabeleland and the Transvaal and the Lorenzo Marques district.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Вторая подраса росла и развивалась, стремительно расцветая в течении многих тысяч лет и расширяя свои владения до границ почти всей Африки, за исключением той территории, что была в руках Египта. Однажды, значительно позднее, они вторглись в Египет и некоторое время правили под именем Королей Хиксоса, но их солнечными днями было то время, когда они правили Алжирским островом. Они отправились на восточное побережье мыса Доброй Надежды и основали королевство которое включало в себя землю Матабеле и Трансвааль с районом Лоренца Маркуса.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Our band of pioneers, after several births in Arabia, took part in the building of this South African Empire, and we found Mars there as Monarch, with His faithful Herakles as ruler of a province under him. Sirius was also born in Mashonaland, where he married Alcyone, and among their negro servants we find the faithful hand-maiden of many lives, Boreas. The scenery in Matabeleland was beautiful, and there were valleys full of fine trees, and studded with herds of antelopes. Great cities were made of the favourite massive type, and huge Temples, and the civilisation gradually built up was by no means an unworthy one. But the gulf between the two peoples, the native Africans and the Arab conquerors, was too wide to be spanned, and the Africans remained labourers and domestic servants, kept entirely in subjection.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Наша группа пионеров после нескольких рождений в Аравии приняла участие в строительстве Южной Африканской Империи и мы нашли Марса исполняющего там роль Монарха, а Геракла — в качестве его верного правителя провинции. Сириус был также найден в Машоналенде где женился на Алкионе. Среди их слуг-негров мы нашли преданную девушку Бореас сопровождающую их на протяжении нескольких жизней. Пейзаж Матабеленда был великолепен: долины полные прекрасных деревьев вытаптывались стадами не менее прекрасных антилоп. Огромные города возводились в любимом массивном стиле с огромными Храмами. Цивилизация постепенно росла и определённа стала неплохим образчиком. Но пролив разделяющий коренных Африканцев и завоевателей-Арабов был слишком широк и Африканцы оставались домашними служащими в полном подчинении.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Arabs made settlements also on the West Coast of Africa, but there they came into collision with men from Poseidonis, and were in the end entirely driven back. Madagascar was invaded, the southern Empire trying to occupy it, but it succeeded only in maintaining for a time settlements on different parts of the coast.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Арарбы сделали поселения также на западном побережье Африки, но столкнулись с людьми из Посейдониса и были окончательно отброшены назад. Южная Империя попыталась захватить Мадагаскар, но ей удалось лишь оккупировать некоторые часть поборежья.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When the great Sumero-Akkad Empire of Persia, Mesopotamia and Turkestan finally broke up into small States and disorder, an Arab monarch conceived the bold idea of reuniting it under his own leadership. He led his armies against it, and, after twenty years of strenuous fighting, made himself master of the plains of Mesopotamia and of almost the whole of Persia, up to the great salt lake of Khorasan, where the desert now is. But he could not conquer Kurdistan, nor could he subdue the mountain tribes who harassed his armies on their way. Then he died, and his son wisely set himself to consolidate rather than to extend his Empire. It held together well for some centuries, and might have endured much longer, but for the fact that dynastic troubles broke out in Arabia itself, and the governor of Persia, a cousin of the Arab King, seized the opportunity to proclaim himself independent. The Arab dynasty which he thus founded lasted two hundred years, but amidst incessant warfare; then again came a period of upheaval and of small tribes, and frequent raids from the savage Central Asian nomads, who play so prominent a part in the history of that region. One Arab King was tempted by reports which reached him of the fabulous wealth of India to send a fleet across to attack it; but that was a failure, for his fleet was promptly destroyed and his men killed or taken prisoners.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Когда великая Шумеро-Аккадская Империя Персии, Месопотамия и Туркестан окончательно рассыпались в маленькие провинции, Арабский монарх здраво решил, что их можно объединить под своим началом. Он повёл свои армии против них и после двадцати лет трудной борьбы сделал себя хозяином равнин Месопотамии и почти всей Персии, вплоть до солёного озера Хоразана, где сейчас находится пустыня. Но он не смог покорить Курдистан и не смог подчинить горные племена, которые потрепали его войско в пути. Он умер и его сын мудро решил укрепить Империю, а не расширять её. Она держалась вместе веками и могла бы продержаться дольше, если бы не внутридинастические ссоры разрушившие Аравию изнутри: управляющий Персией — кузен Короля Аравии — поймал шанс и провозгласил себя независимым. Арабская династия продержалась две сотни лет посреди непрекращающихся войн; затем опять пришёл период подъёма и частые набеги дикарей из Центральной Азии, которые сыграли значительную роль в истории того региона. Один Арабский Король был соблазнён рассказами о сказочном богастве Индии и отправил туда свою флотилию, чтобы атаковать, но это было ошибкой — флотилия была немедленно уничтожена, а люди убиты илм взяты в плен.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After the final collapse of the Arabian Empire of Persia and Chaldaea, there were centuries of anarchy and bloodshed, and the countries were becoming almost depopulated; so the Manu at last determined to come to their rescue, and sent forth to them His third sub-race, which established the great Persian Empire of the Iranians.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
После окончательного коллапса Арабской Империи Персии и Халдеи пришли века анархии и кровопролития которые почти опустошили страну. Ману наконец решил прийти на помощь и отправил туда свою третью подрасу которая воздвигла великую Персидскую Империю Иранцев.
</view>
</text>
</body>