<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Black magic in atlantis: an episode</view>
<view lang="ru">Чёрная Магия Атлантиса</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
ALCYONE is lying half asleep, half awake, on a grassy bank sloping down to a rippling brooklet. His face is perplexed, even anxious, the reflex of his troubled mind. He is the son of a wealthy and powerful family, belonging to the priesthood, the ` Priesthood of the Midnight Sun,' vowed to the service of the Gods of the Nether World, whom the priests sought in the gloom of night, in dark earth-caverns opening into passages that led down, down, into unknown depths.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Алкион лежал полусонный на берегу ручья. На его лице было озадаченное выражение, даже тревожное, отражающее состояние его задумчивых мыслей. Он был сыном в богатой и могущественной семье принадлежащей к касте жрецов, "Жрецов Полуночного Солнца", вовлечённую в служение Богам Низшего Мира, которых жрецы искали во тьме ночи, в тёмных земных пещерах открывающих пути в неизведанные подземелья.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At this time, the great civilised nations of Atlantis had drawn into two opposed camps: the one, looking to the ancient City of the Golden Gates as their sacred metropolis, maintained the traditional worship of their race, the worship of the Sun-- the Sun in the beauty of his rising, clad in the bright colours of the dawning, encircled with the radiant youths and maidens of his court; the Sun in the zenith of his glory, the blazing strength of his mid-heaven, scattering abroad his brilliant rays of life and heat; the Sun in the splendid couch of his setting, touching into rarest softest hues the clouds he left as promise of his return. The people worshipped him with choral dances, with incense and with flowers, with joyous songs, and with offerings of gold and gems, with laughter and with minstrelsy, with joyous games and sports . Over these children of the Blazing Sun the White Emperor bore rule, and his race had for long millennia held unchallenged sway. But gradually the outlying kingdoms, ruled by his lieutenants, had become independent, and they were beginning to join together into a Federation, rallying round a man who had appeared among them, a remarkable but sinister figure.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
К этому времени высокоцивлизованные нации Атлантиса распались на два противостоящих лагеря. Один из них смотрел на Город Золотых Врат как на свою священную столицу, воплощающую в себе традиционный культ расы, культ Солнца. Среди детей сияющего Солнца правил Белый Император. Постепенно среди далёких королевств в которых правили его наместники появились независимые и они начали объединяться в Федерацию, сплачиваясь вокруг одного человека, появившегося среди них — человека необычного и злого.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This man, Oduarpa by name, ambitious and crafty by nature, had realised that, in order to give stability to the Federation and to make head against the White Emperor, it was necessary to call to his aid the resources of the darker magic, to make compact with the denizens of the Nether World, and to establish a worship which would attract the people by its sensuous pleasures, and by the weird unholy powers it placed within the reach of its adepts. He had himself, by such compact, extended his life over an abnormal period, and, when going into battle, rendered himself impervious to spear or sword-thrust by materialising a metallic coating over his body, which turned weapons aside as would a shirt of mail. He aimed at supreme power, and was in a fair way to reach it, and he dreamed of himself as sitting crowned in the Palace of the City of the Golden Gates.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Этого человека звали Одуарпа. Он был амбициозен и целеустремлён. Однажды он решил, что для достижения стабильности Федерации и для противостояния Белому Императору необходимо привлечь возможности чёрной магии, установить связи с обитателями Нижнего Мира и создать культ который привлечёт людей с низменными страстями. Он обучил своих ближайших адептов нечистой силе и сделал свою жизнь гораздо дольше обычной. Когда он участввовал в битве, он делал себя непроницаемым для удара меча материализуя металлическую защиту вокруг тела, которая отклоняла оружие как панцирь. Он намеревался получить огромную силу и был на пути к этому; он мечтал о том, как однажды сядет на трон во Дворце Города Золотых Врат.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The father of our youth was among the most intimate of his friends, and privy to his most secret designs, and both hoped that the lad would devote himself to the forwarding of their ambitions. But the youth had dreams and hopes of his own, nourished silently within his own heart; he had seen in the visions of the night the stately figure of Mars, a general of the White Emperor, Corona, had gazed into his deep compelling eyes, had heard, as from afar, his words: “Alcyone, thou art mine, of my people, and surely thou shalt come to me, and know thyself as mine. Pledge not thyself to mine enemies, thou who art mine.” And he had vowed himself his subject, as vassal to his lord.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Отец нашего подопечного был одним наиболее близких друзей Одуарпы и был посвящён в самые тайные планы. Они оба рассчитывали на то, что Алкион посвятит себя их идеям. Однако Алкион имел свои собственные мечты и надежды, спрятанные в его сердце. В своих ночных видениях он наблюдал статную фигуру Марса, генерала Белого Императора и Corona, который сказал: "Алкион, ты мой, ты из моих людей, ты знаешь себя как меня и должен прийти ко мне. Не отдавай себя в руки моих врагов", and he had vowed himself his subject, as vassal to his lord.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Of this was Alcyone thinking, as he lay musing by the stream. For another influence was playing upon him, and his blood ran hotly in his veins. Ill-pleased at his indifference to their worship-- nay, at his shrinking from it, even in its outward rites of animal sacrifice and poured out oblations of strong drink-- his father and Oduarpa had conceived the plan of drawing him into the secret mysteries by the allurements of a maiden, Cygnus, dark and beauteous as the midnight sky star-studded, who loved him deeply, but had so far failed to win his young heart with her charms. Between her dusky brilliant eyes and his half-fascinated gaze would float the splendid face of his vision, and he would hear again the thrilling whisper: “Thou art mine.”
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Это занимало мысли Алкион задумчиво лежащего у ручья. Было ещё кое-что, что заставляло его кровь в венах бежать быстрее. Недовольный его безразличием к культу — его отталкивал как сам культ, так и ритуалы жертвоприношений животных завершающихся всеобщим пьянством — его отец и Одуарпа придумали план вовлекающий его в тайные мистерии при помощи девушки Сигнус — мрачная и красивая, как ночное небо — которая глубоко его любила, но до сих пор не смогла проникнуть своими чарами в его сердце. Между её тёмными глазами и его полу-очарованным взглядом всплыло лицо из его видения, которое опять прошептало "Ты мой (thou art mine)".
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At length, however, she had so far won him-- persuaded to the task by her mother, a veritable witch-hag, who had told her that thus alone might she gain his love-- as to obtain from him a promise that he would accompany her to the underground caves in which the magical rites were performed, which drew the denizens of the Nether World from their retreats, and gained from them the forbidden knowledge which changed the human into the animal form, thus giving opportunity for free play to the passions of the brute hidden in man, passions of lust and slaughter. Cygnus had played upon his heart with skill taught by her own passion, and had fanned his indifference into fire, not enduring, indeed, but warm while it lasted. And to-day the passion was hot upon him, and the power of her allurement swayed him. For she had just left him, after coaxing him to promise to meet her after sunset near the caverns where the mysteries were performed, and he was struggling between his longing to follow her, and his repulsion from the guessed-at scenes in which he would be expected to take part. The sun sank below the horizon and the sky darkened while still Alcyone lay musing; with a shudder he started to his feet, but now his mind was made up, and he turned his steps towards the rendezvous.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В конце концов она его одолела — подстрекаемая своей матерью, настоящей каргой и ведьмой — и получила его обещание сопроводить её в подземелья где проведут магический ритуал который вызовет жителей Нижнего Мира из своих убежищ, чтобы те дали им запретное знание о том, как превратить человека в животное тем самым позволив безопасно играть с тёмными желаниями спрятанными в человеке — желаниями разврата и жестокого убийства. Сигнус смогла разжечь его безразличие в огонь и её красота подчинила его. Как только она его оставила, предварительно взяв обещание встретиться после заката возле пещер где проводят обряды, он разрывался между желанием последовать за ней и неприятием тех сцен в которых он должен был принять участие. Солнце ушло за горизонт и небо потемнело: Алкион всё ещё лежал в раздумьях. С некоторой дрожью он поднялся на ноги и направился к месту встречи.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
To his surprise a considerable company was gathered at the spot; his father was there with his priestly friends, and Cygnus with a crescent moon on her head, the sign of the bride, and a band of maidens round her, all clad in gauzy star-spangled raiment, through which the brown lithe limbs gleamed duskily; a band of youths of his own age, among whom he recognised his nearest friends, were also waiting, with spotted skins of animals for raiment, and light cymbals which they clashed as they danced round him like fauns.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
К его удивлению, его встретила большая компания. Его отец был со своими друзьями-жрецами, Сигнус с полумесяцем на голове — символ невесты — и группой девушек вокруг неё, облачённых в тонкие одежды через которые тускло просвечивались тела. Кучка парней его возраста среди которых он узнал своих ближайших друзей были в шкурах животных и держали тарелки, которые они разбили в танцах вокруг него.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
“Hail, Alcyone!” they cried, “favourite of the Dark Sun, child of the Night! See where thy Moon and her Stars await thee. But first thou must win her from us, her defenders.”
</view>
<view lang="ru">
"Привет, Алкион!", кричали они, "фаворит Тёмного Солнца, дитя Ночи! Посмотри на свою Луну и Звёзды которые ждут тебя. Но сперва тебе придётся забрать её у нас — её защитников".
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Suddenly she was whirled away in the midst of the dancers, and vanished in the darkness of the cavern yawning wide in front, and Alcyone was seized, stripped of his garments, a skin like that of the rest thrown over him, and intoxicated, maddened, he fled in her pursuit, amid laughter and cheers: “Hey! young hunter, be swift, lest the hounds pull down thy deer!”
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Внезапно она закружилась посреди танцующих и пропала в темном входе в пещеру. Алкиона схватили, сорвали одежду и накинули такую же шкуру как на остальных. Обезумевший, он бросился за ней в погоню, под смех и крик: "Эй, охотник, быстрее! Иначе собаки загонят твою лань!".
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After a few minutes Alcyone, with the shouting crowd at his heels, had raced through the outer caverns, and had reached a vast hall, blazing with crimson light. In the midst rose a huge canopy, red in colour and studded with great carbuncles, that tossed back the light like splashes of fiery blood; beneath the canopy was a copper throne, inlaid with gold, and before it a yawning gulf, out of which flashed tongues of flame, lurid and roaring. Heavy clouds of strange incense filled the air, intoxicating, maddening. The rush swept him onwards, and he was caught up into a wild tumultuous whirl of dancers, who shouted, yelled, sprang into the air in wild bounds, circling round the canopied throne, and crying: “Oduarpa! Oduarpa! Come, we are craving for thee!”
</view>
<view lang="ru">
После нескольких минут погони, Алкион прорвался через внешние пещеры и попал в огромный холл освещённый красноватым пламенем. Посреди него возвышался огромный красный шатёр с какими-то наростами; он отбрасывал блики света похожие на брызги крови. Под шатром стоял медный трон инкрустированный золотом, а перед ним была дыра из которой вырывались зловещие языки пламени. Тяжёлые опьяняющие облака ладана заполняли воздух. Толпа обезумевших людей танцевала, дико подпрыгивая, вокруг трона и кричала: "Одуарпа! Одуарпа! Приди, мы умоляем тебя!".
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A low roll of thunder crept muttering round the cavern, growing louder and louder, and ending in a tremendous clap just overhead; the flames leapt up, and amid them rose the mighty form of Oduarpa, steel-grey in his magic sheathing, stern, majestic, with his face grave, even sad, as that of a fallen Archangel, but strong with unbending pride and iron resolution. He took his seat on the throne, where he sat throughout all that followed, silent and sombre, taking no part in the riot; he waved his hand, and the mad orgy recommenced, the wildest dancers bathing in the flames which lapped over the edges of the gulf and tossed themselves high in the air. Alcyone had caught sight of Cygnus in the midst of the youths and the girls, and he raced, mad with excitement, in her direction; she eluded him, her escort baffled him, he touched her only to see her whirled out of his reach. At last, panting, wild, he made a desperate rush, and the escort fled with screams of laughter, each youth with a girl, and he leapt on Cygnus and clasped her in his arms.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Низкий рокот шёпота разползался по пещере, становясь всё громче и громче, и завершился бурными овациями. Прямо посреди них вырвались языки пламени и появилась могущественная фигура Одуарпы — облачённая в магическую оболочку стального серого цвета, с тяжёлым и печальным выражением на лице как у падшего Архангела, но вместе с тем непоколебимо гордым и крайне решительным. Он занял своё место на троне где оставался на протяжении всего, что последовало, безмолвный и мрачный, безучастно смотрящий на действо. Он взмахнул рукой и безумная оргия возобновилась, дикие танцоры кружились в языках пламени переплетающихся между собой. Алкион нашёл взглядом Сигнус в толпе юношей и девушек и рванул к ней, обезумевший от возбуждения. Она уклонилась от него, а её эскорт встал между ними. Наконец, тяжело дыша, он сделал отчаянный рывок и эскорт разбежался в стороны с криками и смехом, и он схватил Сигнус.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Wilder and wilder grew the revel; slaves bearing huge pitchers of strong drink appeared, accompanied by others with goblets. Madness of drink was added to madness of motion, and the lurid lights sank low into twilight of redness. The orgy which followed is better hidden than described.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Пир становился всё безумнее, одни рабы разносили огромные кувшины крепкого питья, когда другие — чаши для него. Безумие опьянения добавилось к безумию движения и тусклые огни света превратились в красные сумерки. То что последовало дальше лучше скрыть, чем описать.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
But see! out of the passage whence had emerged Oduarpa, comes a wild procession; hairy bipeds, long-armed and claw-footed, with animals' heads and manes streaming over shoulders, horrent, appalling, non-human, yet horribly human. They hold in their claw-like hands phials and boxes, and as they mingle with the wildest dancers they give these to the revellers most mad with drink and lust. These smear over their limbs the ointment in the boxes, drink the contents of the phials, and lo! they drop senseless, huddled on the ground, but from each huddled heap there springs an animal form, snarling, ravening, and vanishes from the cavern into the darkness of the outside night.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Прямо из того входа откуда явился Одуарпа, начала выходить странная процессия. Волосатые двуногие, длиннорукие и когтистые, с головами животных и гривами спадающими на плечи, безобразные, отталкивающие, нечеловеческие, но вместе с тем в них было что-то от человека. Они несли в когтистых руках какие-то флаконы и коробки и после того как они смешались с толпой они дали это наиболее обезумевшим от питья и похоти. Они намазали их конечности содержимым коробок, напоили содержимым флаконов и те упали без чувств в кучи на земле. Из каждой такой кучи лежащих людей вырвалось животное и рыча убежало из пещеры на ночную поверхность.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The bright Gods help the wayfarers who meet these bedevilled astral materialisations, fierce and conscienceless as animals, cruel and crafty as men! But the bright Gods are sleeping, and only the hosts of the Midnight Sun, ghosts, goblins and all evil things, are abroad. The creatures return, their jaws dripping with blood, their hides draggled with filth, ere morning dawns, and, crouching on the huddled forms on the floor of the cavern, sink into them and disappear.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Светлые Боги помогают путникам которые встречают эти колдовские астральные сущности — яростные и беспринципные как животные, и жестокие и изощрённые как люди. Но светлые Боги спали, и здесь были только последователи Полуночного Солнца, призраки, гоблины и другие злые существа. Создания вернулись до рассвета — у них изо рта капала кровь, а конечности были в грязи — склонились над кучами лежащих тел на полу пещеры и скрылись в них.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Such orgies as these were held from time to time, Oduarpa using them to increase his hold upon the people, and he established similar rites at many places, making himself the central figure in all, becoming a veritable object of worship, and gradually welding the people together in allegiance to himself, until he became the acknowledged Emperor. His relations with the inhabitants of the Nether. World-- called in latter days, as said above, the ` Kingdom of Pan' -- gave him much additional power, and he had trusted lieutenants-- bound to him by their common knowledge of; and participation in, the ghastly abominations of that realm-- ever prompt to carry out his commands.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Такие оргии повторялись время от времени. Одуарпа использовал их, чтобы увеличить контроль над людьми. Он проводил похожие ритуалы в разных местах, делая себя центральной фигурой в них, становясь остинным объектом поклонения. Постепенно люди объедилялись в лояльности к нему и он стал признанным Императором. Его отношения с обитателями Нижнего Мира дали ему много доволнительной силы и он завёл заместителей — связанных с ним общим знанием — которые всегда рьяно выполняли его приказы.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He finally succeeded in assembling a very large army and began his march against the White Emperor, directing his course towards the City of the Golden Gates. He hoped to overawe and conquer, not only by fair assault of arms, but by the terror that would be spread by his hellish allies, and the ghastly transformations of the black wizards into animal forms. He himself had a body-guard of magic animals round him, powerful desire-forms materialised into physical bodies, who guarded him and devoured any who approached him with hostile intent. When a battle was raging, and the issue doubtful, Oduarpa would suddenly loose against his foes his horde of demoniacal allies, who would rush into the fray, tearing with teeth and claws, and spread panic among the startled hosts. When his enemies broke into flight, he would send these swift demons in pursuit, and the troops of wizards would likewise take animal forms, gorging themselves on the bodies of the slain.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В конце концов он собрал огромную армию и начал свой поход против Белого Императора, направлясь в Город Золотых Врат. Он надеялся запугать и сломить не только усилиями рук воинов, но и страхом который наведут его адские союзники и чёрные маги которые умели делать ужасающие превращения в животные формы. Он сам был окружён телохранителями из магических существ — могущественные астральные формы облачённые в физическую материю, которые защищали его и поглощали всякого, кто приближался с вражескими намерениями. Когда битва была в самом разгаре, Одуарпа внезапно вступил в бой и его демонические союзники ворвались в битву, разрывая всё клыками и когтями, сея панику среди поражённых людей. Когда его враги обращались в бегство, он отправлял демонов и чёрных магов обращающихся в животные формы в погоню.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Thus he fought his way onwards, northward ever, till he came near the City of the Golden Gates, where the last army of the White Emperor lay embattled. Alcyone had fought as a soldier in the army, partly under a spell, and yet awake enough to be sick at heart at his surroundings, and Cygnus, with other ladies, had accompanied the camp. The day of the decisive battle dawned; the imperial army was led by the White Emperor himself; Corona, and the right wing of the army was under the command of his most trusted general, Mars. During the preceding night, Alcyone had been visited once more by his early vision, and had heard the well-loved voice: “Alcyone, thou art fighting against thy true lord, and to-morrow wilt thou meet me, face to face. Break thou then thy rebel sword and yield thee to me; thou shalt die by my side, and it shall yet be well.”
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Так он продвигался вперёд, на север, пока не подошёл к Городу Золотых Врат где оставалась последняя армия Белого Императора. Алкион был в числе солдат тёмной армии, частично под заклятием, но всё же достаточно осознающий происходящее, чтобы чувствовать неприятие всего этого. Сигнус с другими женщинами сопровождала кампанию. В день финальной битвы имперская армия выступила во главе с самим Белым Императором — Corona — а её правый фланг был доверен наиболее уважаемому генералу Марсу. Алкиона ещё раз посетило видение в котором он услышал: "Алкион, ты сражаешься против своего истинного лорда и завтра мы встретимся лицом к лицу. Сложи свой меч и отдай его мне. Ты должен умереть на моей стороне."
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
And so indeed it happed. For in the fierce shock of battle, as the imperial troops were giving way, the Emperor slain, Alcyone saw, struggling gallantly against overwhelming odds, the face of his vision, the general, Mars. With a cry he sprang forward, breaking his sword in two, and catching up a spear, he threw himself at Mars' back, fiercely thrusting through a soldier who struck at Mars from behind. At that moment Oduarpa charged up, mad with fury, and struck Mars down, and with a cry that rang across the field, he summoned Cygnus, by swift spell changing her into a fierce animal, which rushed with bared fangs at Alcyone, fainting from loss of blood. But in the very act, the love which had been her life cried out from Cygnus' soul and wrought her rescue; for its strong flow changed into loving woman the form of ravening hate, and with a dying kiss on Alcyone' s dying face she breathed away her life.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Так и случилось. В яростной битве где имперские солдаты прокладывали себе путь, Алкион увидел лицо из своего видения — лицо Марса, смело сражающегося против превосходящего числа противников. С криком он рванулся вперёд, разбил свой меч надвое, поймал дротик и яростно пробил им солдата который бросил этот дротик в спину Марса. В этот момент появилися Одуарпа, взебешённый от увиденного, и сразил Марса. Криком через всё поле он призвал Сигнус, сложным заклинанием обратив её в яростное животное, которое набросилось на Алкион с обнажёнными клыками. Алкион уже истекал кровью, когда внезапно из души Сигнус вырвался порыв любви и освободил её от животной формы, превратив в красивую женщину. Поцеловав умирающего Алкион она сама сделала последний вздох и умерла.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Herakles, the wife of Mars, was captured by Oduarpa in the assault on the City of the Golden Gates that followed and completed his victory; she indignantly repulsed his advances, and catching up a dagger stabbed at him with all her strength. The dagger slipped aside on his metallic casing, and, laughing, he struck her down, outraging her as she lay half senseless: when she recovered consciousness, he summoned his horrible animals, and they tore her into pieces and devoured her.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Геракл — жена Марса — была захвачена Одуарпой в штурме Города Золотых Врат, который завершился его победой. Она с отвращением отбивалась от него и попыталась ударить его кинжалом изо всех сил. Кинжал выскользнул из её руки и Одуарпа, смеясь, ударил её и она упала без сознания. Когда она пришла в себя, он призвал своих ужасных животных и они разорвали её на части.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Oduarpa, enthroned on a pile of corpses, and surrounded by his animal and half-animal guards, was crowned Emperor of the City of the Golden Gates, assuming the desecrated title of ` Divine Ruler' . But his triumph was not of long duration, for Vaivasvata Manu marched against him with a great army, and His mere presence put to flight the denizens of the Kingdom of Pan, while he destroyed the artificial thought-forms, created by black magic. A crushing victory scattered the army of the Emperor, and he himself was shut up in a tower whither he had fled in the rout. The building was fired, and he perished miserably, literally boiled to death within his materialised metallic shell.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Одуарпа сел на трон из горы трупов, в окружении своих животных и полуживотных охранников. Он короновал себя в Городе Золотых Врат, осквернив звание "Божественного Правителя". Но его триумф был недолгим. Вайвасвата Ману выступил против него с большой армией, а одно его присутствие обращало в бегство обитателей Нижнего Мира, так как он разрушал искуственные мыслеформы созданные чёрной магией. Сокрушительный штурм разбил армию Императора и он сам был заперт в башне куда сбежал во время битвы. Здание подожгли и он буквально сварился в материализованной металической защите.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Vaivasvata Manu purified the City and re-established there the rule of the White Emperor, consecrating to that office a trusted servant of the Hierarchy. For a time things went on well, but slowly the evil again gathered power, and the southern centre once more grew strong; until, at last, the same Lord of the Dark Face, appearing in a new reincarnation, again fought against the White Emperor of the time, and set up his own throne against him. Then the words of doom were spoken by the Head of the Hierarchy, and as the Occult Commentary tells us: the “Great King of the Dazzling Face”-- the White Emperor-- sent to his brother Chiefs: “Prepare. Arise, ye men of the Good Law, and cross the land while yet dry.” The “Rod of the Four”-- the Kumaras-- was raised. “The hour has struck, the black night is ready.” The “servants of the Great Four” warned their people, and many escaped. “Their Kings reached them in their Vimanas¹ (¹ Chariots which moved in the air-- the ancient aeroplanes.) and led them on to the lands of fire and metal [east and north].”² (² The Secret Doctrine (1897 Edition) ii, 445, 446; (Adyar Edition) iii, 424, 425.) Explosions of gas, floods and earthquakes destroyed Ruta and Daitya, the huge islands of Atlantis, left from the catastrophe of 200,000 B.C., and only the island of Poseidonis remained, the last remnant of the once huge continent of the Atlantic. These islands perished in 75,025 B.C., Poseidonis enduring to 9,564 B.C., when it also was whelmed beneath the ocean.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Вайвасвата Ману очистил Город и вернул правление Белому Императору назначив на эту должность одного человека из Иерархии. Некоторое время дела шли хорошо, но постепенно и очень медленно зло опять собралось на юге и тот же Тёмный Лорд вернулся в новой инкарнации и выступил против Белого Императора и установил свой трон против него. Тогда Главой Иерархии были сказаны слова судьбы и как нам говорит Оккультный Комментарий: "Великий Король Сияющей Стороны" — Белый Император — сказал своим друзьям "Готовьтесь. Люди Доброго Закона, уходите пока земля суха. Час пробил." Служители Великих Четырёх предупредили людей и многие ушли. Взрывы газа, наводнения и землетрясения разрушили Руту и Дайту — Два огромных острова Атлантиса которые остались после катастрофы 200,000 лет до н.э. — и только остров Посейдонис ещё оставался над водой. Эти острова разрушились 75,025 лет до н.э. Посейдонис дожил до 9,564 лет до н.э. и также скрылся под волнами океана.
</view>
</text>
</body>