<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">The third sub-race, the iranian</view>
<view lang="ru">Третья Подраса: Иранская</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
AGAIN we return to the City of the Bridge, still great, though decreasing in splendour, for we have come to the year 30,000 B.C. An interval of ten thousand years elapsed after the despatch of the second sub-race before the Manu sent forth the third. The men for this work had been carefully prepared through many centuries, like the others; He had kept them apart in one of His mountain-valleys, and developed them until they showed as quite a distinct type. In His original selection in Atlantis, He had included a small proportion of the best of the sixth Atlantean sub-race, and He now utilised the families which had preserved most of that Akkadian blood, sending into incarnation in them His group of pioneers. One or two of them were sent further afield to bring back a strain of Akkadian blood from its home in more western countries. Thus we observed Herakles, a strong good-looking young man, arriving at the City of the Bridge in a caravan from Mesopotamia, his birthplace; he was dolichocephalous, an Akkadian of pure blood. He had joined the caravan from a mere spirit of adventure, the desire of high-spirited youth to see the world, and certainly had not the faintest idea that he had been sent to Mesopotamia to take birth, and was being drawn back to Central Asia to rejoin his old friends in their accustomed pioneer work. He was immensely attracted by the beauty and splendour of the ancient and ordered civilisation into which he came, and promptly anchored himself therein by falling in love with Orion, a daughter of Sirius.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Мы снова возвращаемся в Город Моста, всё ещё великого, но уже утратившего часть великолепия, так как мы пришли в него 30,000 лет до н.э. Десять тысяч лет прошло с тех пор как вторая подраса ушла и Ману отправил третью. Люди выбранные для этой работы были тщательно отобраны на протяжении сотен лет. Он держал их отдельно от других в горной долине и развивал их пока они не стали определённо новым видом людей. Он взял немного людей среди лучших из шестой подрасы Атлантов и несколько семей сохранивших кровь Аккадцев, отправив в них рождаться свою группу пионеров. Один или два из них отправились вдаль от дома, чтобы принести с собой штамм Аккадской крови из наиболее западных стран. Мы обнаружили Геракла — сильного хорошо-выглядящего юношу — прибывшего в Город Моста в караване из Месопотамии — его родного города. Он был долихоцефалом — чистым Аккадцем. Он присоединился к каравану из чистого желания повидать мир и не имел даже слабого представления о том, что когда-то был послан в Месопотамию, чтобы родиться там и вернуться в Центральную Азию где находились его друзья занятые пионерской работой. Он был сражён красотой и великолепием древней цивилизации в которую пришёл и сразу же привязался к этому месту, влюбившись в Ориону — дочь Сириуса.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This proceeding was frowned upon by Sirius and his wife Mizar, for Sirius was a younger son of Vaivasvata Manu and Mercury, and he disapproved of the introduction of a young Akkadian into his family circle. But a hint from his Father was enough to ensure his compliance, for he was, as ever, promptly obedient to authority, and the Manu was at once his Father and his King. In order to comply with the law which the Manu Himself had established, it was necessary that Herakles should be adopted into an Aryan family, so he was accepted into that of Osiris, an older brother of Sirius.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Сириус, со соей женой Мицар, нахмуренно смотрел на это, так как он был младшим сыном Вайвасваты Ману и Меркурия и неодобрял появление молодого Аккадца в кругу своей семьи. Но намёка со стороны отца было достаточно для его согласия, потому-что он был, как и всегда, внимателен к власти, а Ману был как его отцом так и королём. Чтобы следовать закону который издал сам Ману, Геракла надо было усыновить в какую-либо Арийскую семью, поэтому он был принят в семью Осириса — старшего брата Сириуса.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Manu was very old, and as Sirius was not wanted for the succession, he was packed off to the valley selected for the building up of the third sub-race, with his family, including his son-in-law, Herakles, and his children.1 (¹ See Appendix viii, for complete lists.) Pallas-- the Plato of later history-- was there as a priest, and Helios as a priestess, a tall commanding figure, with dignified gestures.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Ману был очень стар. Сириус вместе со своей семьёй, детьми (см. полный список в приложение 8) и новым законным сыном Геракла отправился в долину оставленную для создания третьей подрасы. Pallas — в более поздней истории Плато — был там жрецом, а Гелиос — жрицей с высокой повелительной фигурой и выразительной мимикой.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The people of this valley, as they multiplied, were more pastoral than agricultural, keeping large herds of sheep and cattle and numbers of horses.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Люди в той долине, после того как достигли определённой численности, вели аграрный образ жизни, держа стада овец и крупнорогатого скота и некоторое количество лошадей.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Manu who, on this occasion, had largely modified His appearance, came into the sub-race in the fifth generation, and He allowed the people to multiply for some two thousand years until there was available an army of three hundred thousand fighting men, fit to undergo hardship and strenuous marching. He then sent into incarnation Mars, Corona, Theodoros, Vulcan and Vajra, fit captains for His host, and He led it forth Himself. This time it was no ordinary migration; it was simply an army on the march. The women and children were left behind in the valley, where Neptune, the wife of Mars, and Osiris, the wife of Corona, strong and noble matrons, took into their hands the direction of affairs, and ruled the community well.1 (¹ See Appendix ix.)
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Ману значительно изменил свой облик и пришёл в подрасу в пятом поколении и позволил людям размножаться примерно две тысячи лет, пока не смог собрать трёхсоттысячную армию из воинственных мужчин способных преодолеть трудности длительного перехода. Затем он отправил в подрасу Марса, Corona, Теодоруса, Вулкана и Vajra воплотиться и стать капитанами армии которую он повёл за собой. В этот раз перемещение людей было не обычной миграцией, а марш броском армии. Женщины и дети остались позади в долине, где Нептун — жена Марса — и Осирис — жена Corona — взяли дела в свои руки и благородно правили обществом (см. приложение 9).
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A fine body-guard of young unmarried men acted as staff to the leaders, ready to be sent off with messages in any direction; they were very proud of themselves and very gay, enthusiastic over the idea that they were going out for a real good fight under the Manu Himself.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Из молодых неженатых мужчин получились хорошие телохранители своих лидеров; они были готовы отправиться в любом направлении в качестве посланников и были очень горды собой и полны энтузиазма от того, что они отправляются в хорошую битву за самим Ману.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
But it was no holiday march, for the route lay through a difficult country; some of the passes across the end of the Tianshan range, where it curves round into the Kashgar district, were nine thousand feet in height; for part of the way they followed the course of a river which passed through ravines and valleys. The Manu poured His great army of three hundred thousand splendid fighting men into Kashgar, defeating easily such of the nomad hordes as ventured to attack Him as He crossed their deserts. These tribes buzzed round the fringe of the army, and there were many skirmishes, but no battles of any account. The weapons used were long and short lances and spears, short strong swords, slings and bows. The horsemen used lances and swords, and had round shields slung across their backs; the footmen carried spears, and there were bodies of archers and slingers, the former marching in the centre, and the archers and slingers on the outside.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Этот марш бросок был отнюдь не отдыхом, потому-что маршрут пролегал через сложные земли; некоторые дороги шли через горы Тянь-Шань высотой 9,000 футов; часть пути пролегала вдоль реки пересекающей равнины и долины. Ману обрушил свою великую армию из трёх сотен тысяч превосходных воинов на Кашгар, легко сразив орды номадов рискнувших напасть на него и пересёк их пустыни. Эти племена кружили вокруг армии и с ними было несколько небольших стычек. В качестве оружия использовали длинные и короткие копья, дротики, короткие и прочные мечи, пращи и луки. Всадники имели копья и мечи, а также кольчугу защищавщую спину; кроме того были пехотинцы с дротиками и лучники, первые шли в центре, а лучники были по сторонам.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Sometimes, as they neared a village, the villagers-- who dreaded and hated the warlike hill tribes-- would meet and welcome them, bringing cattle and food of all sorts. Long harassed by forays, often attacked, robbed and massacred, the people of the plains were inclined to welcome a power which would restore and maintain order.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Иногда они приближались к деревням и их жители — воинственные племена на холмах — приветливо встречали их, приводя скот и неся пищу всех видов. Долгое время подвергавшиеся набегам и атакам, люди равнин приветствовали силу которая могла восстановить и поддерживать порядок.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Persia was overrun without much difficulty in the course of two years, and then Mesopotamia was subdued. The Manu established military posts at frequent intervals, dividing the country among His chiefs. Forts were built, first of earth and later of stones, until a network was made over Persia to prevent raids from the mountains. No attempt was made to conquer the warlike tribes, but they were practically confined within their fastnesses, and were no longer permitted to plunder the peaceable inhabitants of the plains.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В течении двух лет и без особых сложностей была покорена Персия, а за ней и Месопотамия. Через небольшие интервалы Ману расставил военные посты, поделив страну среди своих наместников. Сначала посты строили из земли, а позже из камня; сеть постов покрыла Персию и предотвращала набеги с гор. Не было предпринято ни одной попытки захватить воинственные племена, но те фактически оказались заперты в своих домах и больше не могли совершать набеги на мирных жителей равнин.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The body-guard, now bearded and seasoned warriors, accompanied their Chiefs everywhere, and the land was conquered right down to the desert of the south, and up to the Kurdish mountains on the north. For some years there was occasional fighting, and it was not until the country was quite peaceful and settled that the Manu called to it the vast caravan of the wives and children of the soldiers, left behind in the valley of the third sub-race.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Телохранители, теперь уже бородатые и опытные воины, сопровождали своих лидеров повсюду и вскоре вся земля от южных пустынь до Курдских гор была завоёвана. Ещё несколько лет случались битвы и когда они стихли и земли стали вполне мирными, Ману привёл огромный караван с солдатскими жёнами и детьми когда-то оставлённых позади в долине третьей подрасы.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The arrival of the caravan was a matter of great rejoicing, and marriages became the order of the day. Herakles and Alcyone fell in love with the same young woman, Fides, a handsome girl with a decided nose; she preferred Alcyone, and the disconsolate Herakles decided to commit suicide, life being no longer worth living; his father, Mars, however, came down upon him, bidding him not to be a fool, and sent him off on an expedition against an insurgent chief, Trapezium; under these conditions Herakles recovered, defeated his adversary, came back quite contented, and married Psyche, a niece of Mars, who had been adopted by him after her father was slain in battle.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Прибытие каравана стало большим поводом для веселья и свадьбы стали обычным делом дня. Геракл и Алкион влюбились в одну и ту же девушку Файдс — симпатичную особу с решительным носиком. Она предпочла Алкиона и несчастный Геракл решил совершить самоубийство, т.к. посчитал, что жить больше незачем, но Марс — его отец — объяснил ему, что не стоит быть дураком и отправил его в поход против восставшего властителя Трапезиума. В походе Геракл пришёл в себя, победил врага и вернулся вполне удовлетворённый. Он женился на Психее — племяннице Марса, которую тот усыновил после того как её отец погиб в битве.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
For the next fifty years the Manu kept this new Empire under His direct rule, visiting it several times, and appointing members of His family as its Governors; but just before His death He resigned His own throne in Central Asia to His grandson Mars, appointed Mars' next brother, Corona, as the independent King of Persia, with Theodoros under him as Governor of Mesopotamia. From this time the third sub-race quickly increased in power. In a few centuries it dominated the whole of western Asia from the Mediterranean to the Pamirs, and from the Persian Gulf to the Sea of Aral. With certain changes its Empire lasted until about 2200 B.C.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Следующие 50 лет Ману держал Империю под своим прямым контролем, иногда её объезжая. Он назначал губернаторами членов своей семьи. Перед смертью он ушёл с трона Центральной Азии и назначил внука Марса своим наследником, а брата Марса Corona — независимым королём Персии, в подчинении которого оказался Теодорус в качестве губернатора Месопотамии. Начиная с этого момента третья подраса быстро набирала силу. Спустя несколько столетий она доминировала на всей западной Азии от Средиземноморья до Памиров, от Персидского залива до Аральского моря. С небольшими изменениями эта Империя дожила до 2,200 лет до н.э.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In this long period of twenty-eight thousand years, one event stands out as of supreme importance-- the coming of the Mahaguru as the first Zarathustra, the founding of the Religion of the Fire, in 29,700 B.C.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В течении всего этого огромного периода в 28,000 лет одно событие заслуживает особого внимания — прибытие Махагуру под именем первого Заратуштры который основал Религию Огня 29,700 лет до н.э.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The country had become fairly settled under the reigns of the Kings who had succeeded Corona, of whom Mars, the Ruler of the time-- of course in a new body-- was the tenth. Military rule had passed away, though occasional raids reminded the inhabitants of their turbulent neighbours on the further side of the ring of forts, now well-built and strong. It was in the main an agricultural country, though large numbers of herds and flocks were kept, and it was these which specially tempted descents from the hills.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В стране установился полный порядок под правлением Королей последовавших за Corona, среди которых Марс, Правитель того времени — разумеется в новом теле — был десятым. Военный режим правления ушёл в прошлое, хотя редкие нападения напоминали населению о непоседливых соседях за хорошо укреплённым кольцом фортов. Строй был в основном аграрным, хотя люди держали большие стада скота так соблазнявшие дикарей живущих на холмах.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The second son of Mars was Mercury, and his body was chosen as the vehicle for the Supreme Teacher; Surya was the Chief Priest, the Hierophant, of the time, at the head of the State religion, a mixture of Nature and Star Worship, and he wielded an immense authority, chiefly because of his office, but also partly because he was of the blood royal. The fact that Mercury had been chosen to surrender his body for the use of the Mahaguru had been communicated to his father as well as to the Chief Priest, and from his childhood he had been carefully trained in view of his glorious destiny, Surya taking charge of his education, and the father co-operating in every way in his power.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Вторым сыном Марса был Меркурий, чьё тело было выбрано на роль проводника для Верховного Учителя. Surya был Верховным Жрецом, Иерофантом, главой государственной религии — смеси поклонения звёздам и природе — и он имел огромный авторитет, в основом благодаря своему статусу в обществе, но также из-за принадлежности к королевскому роду. Поскольку Меркурию была уготована выдающаяся роль проводника Махагуру, он с раннего детства был под пристальным присмотром и Surya, как и Марс, посвящали время для его тщательного обучения и подготовки.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The day arrived when the first public appearance of the Mahaguru was to be made; He had come from Shamballa in His subtle body, and had taken possession of the body of Mercury, and a great procession started from the Royal Palace to the chief Temple of the city. In it walked, on the right, under a golden canopy, the stately figure of the King; the jewelled canopy of the High Priest glittered on the left; and between them was carried, shoulder-high so that all might see, a golden chair, in which sat the well-known figure of the King' s second son. But what was there that caused a murmur of surprise, of wonder, as he passed along? Was that really the Prince, whom they had known from childhood? Why was he carried high as the centre of the procession, while King and Hierophant walked humbly beside him? What was this new stateliness, this unknown dignity, this gaze, so piercing yet so tender, that swept across the crowd? Not thus had held himself, not thus had looked at them, the Prince who had grown up among them.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Подошёл день первого публичного появления Махагуру: Он вышел из Шамбалы в тонком теле и овладел телом Меркурия. Огромная процессия отправилась из Королевского Замка в Главный Храм города. С правой стороны под развевающимся золотым балдахином была статная фигура Короля, с левой стороны блестел богато украшенный балдахин Верховного Жреца, а между ними люди несли на уровне плеч золотой трон на котором сидел хорошо видимый и узнаваемый второй сын Короля. Но что вызвало шёпот удивления и изумление когда его проносили мимо? Действительно ли это был тот принц которого они знали с детства? Почему именно его несли выше всех в центре когда Король и Иерофант скромно шли по сторонам? Откуда появилась в нём эта величавость, этот взгляд, столь пронзительный и одновременно мягкий, направленный на толпу? Не так держал себя, не так смотрел на людей тот принц который вырос среди них.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The procession swept on and entered the huge courtyard of the Temple, crowded with people in the many-coloured garments of festival days, when each wore a mantle of the colour of his ruling planet; down the sides of the steps which rose to the platform in front of the great door of the Temple were ranged the priests in long white garments, and rainbow-coloured over-robes of silk; in the midst of the platform an altar had been erected, and on it wood was piled, and fragrant gums, and incense, but no smoke arose-- for the pile, to the people' s surprise, was unlighted.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Процессия вошла в огромный двор перед Храмом. Люди были в разноцветных одеждах как в дни праздников, каждый облачился в мантию цвета своей планеты. Перед огромной дверью в Храм была платформа к которой вели ступени и на платформе стояли жрецы облачённые в длинные белые одежды и шёлковые мантии всех цветов радуги. Посреди платформы стоял алтарь и на нём были собраны ветви деревьев, благоухания и ладан. Однако дым не поднимался, так как к удивлению людей не было огня.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The procession passed on to the foot of the steps, and there all halted, save the three central figures; they ascended the steps, the King and the Hierophant placing themselves to the right and left of the altar and the Prince, who was the Mahaguru, in the centre, behind it.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Процессия подошла к ступеням и остановилась. Три центральные фигуры поднялись по ним. Король и Иерофант стали по сторонам от алтаря, а принц, которым сейчас был Махагуру, стал в центре и немного позади него.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then Surya, the Hierophant, spoke to the priests and to the people, telling them that He who stood there behind the altar was no longer the Prince they had known, but that He was the Messenger from the Most High and from the Sons of the Fire who dwelt in the far East, whence their forefathers had come forth. That He had brought Their word to Their children, to which all should yield reverence and obedience, and he bade them listen while the great Messenger spake in Their Name. As the Head of their faith, he humbly bade Him welcome.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
/Surya, Иерофант, говорил жрецам и остальным людям, что тот кто стоит сейчас за алтарём не принц которого они знали, а посланник от Сынов Огня живущих далеко на Востоке, там откуда пришли их праотцы. Он передал Их слово Их детям, которому все должны выразить почтение и повиновение. Он предложил всем выслушать слова великого посланника который будет говорить от Их имени и как глава их веры, он может лишь скромно приветствовать Его.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then over the listening throng rang the silver voice of the Mahaguru, and none there was who could not hear it as though spoken to him alone. He toll them that He had come from the Sons of the Fire, the Lords of the Flame, who dwelt in the sacred City of the White Island, in far Shamballa. He brought them a revelation from Them, a symbol which should ever keep Them in their minds. He told them how the Fire was the purest of all elements and the purifier of all things, and that thereafter it should be for them the symbol of the Holiest. That the Fire was embodied in the Sun in the heavens, and burned, though hidden, in the heart of man. It was heat, it was light, it was health and strength, and in it and by it all had life and motion. And much He told them of its deep meaning, and how in all things they should see the hidden presence of the Fire.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Затем на всю слушающую толпу прозвучал серебрянный голос Махагуру и не было ни одного человека который не услышал его, ибо звучал он так, будто предназначался каждому в отдельности. Он говорил им, что пришёл от Сынов Огня, Лордов Пламени, живущих в священном Городе на Белом Острове в далёкой Шамбале. Он принёс от Них откровение, символ который каждый должен держать в своём уме. Огонь воплощённый в Сыне на небесах горит, хотя и не видим, в сердце каждого человека. Он есть свет, он есть здоровье и сила, он есть всё чему обязана жизнь и движение каждого. Он много говорил им о его глубоком смысле и о том, что в каждой вещи они должны видеть скрытое присутсвие Огня.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then He lifted up His right hand, and behold! there shone in it a Rod, as of lightning held in bondage, yet shooting out its flashes on every side; and He pointed the Rod to the East of the Heavens, and cried some words aloud in an unknown tongue; and the heavens became one sheet of flame, and Fire fell blazing down upon the altar, and a Star shone out above His Head and seemed to bathe Him in its radiance. And all the priests and the people fell upon their faces, and Surya and the King bowed down in homage at His feet, and the clouds of fragrant smoke from the altar veiled the three for a few moments from sight.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Тогда Он поднял правую руку и в ней появился сияющий Посох — как будто молнию заключили в неволю, но та всё равно искрила во все стороны — и этим Посохом Он указал на Восток на Небеса и прокричал слова на неизвестном языке и небеса превратились в сплошной холст огня и Огонь устремился вниз на алтарь и Звезда сияющая над Его головой залила Его светом. Все жрецы и люди в толпе упали ниц и Surya и Король склонились в почитании к Его ступням и благоухающий дым с алтаря на время окутал трёх и скрыл их от взглядов.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then, with His hand upraised in blessing, the Mahaguru descended the steps, and He, with the King and the Hierophant, returned with the procession to the Palace whence they had come. And the people marvelled greatly and rejoiced, because the Gods of their forefathers had remembered them, and had sent them the Word of Peace. And they carried home the flowers which had rained down upon them from the sky when the Fire had passed, and kept them in their shrines as precious heirlooms for their descendants.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Затем с рукой поднятой в благословении, Махагуру спустился со ступеней и вместе с Королём и Иерофантом возвратился в Замок откуда пришёл. Восхищению людей не было предела, ибо Боги их праотцов вспомнили о них и послали Слово Мира. Люди понесли домой цветы которые посыпались с неба когда Огонь прошёл и сохранили их как прекрасные драгоценности для своих потомков.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Mahaguru remained for a considerable time in the city, going daily to the Temple to instruct the priests; He taught them that Fire and water were the purifiers of all else, and must never be polluted, and that even the water was purified by the Fire; that all fire was the Fire of the Sun, and was in all things and might be released as fire; that out of the Fire and out of the water all things come, for the Fire and the water were the two Spirits, Fire being life and water form.1
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Махагуру оставалася в городе значительное время, ежедневно заходя в Храм, чтобы учить жрецов. Он учил, что Огонь и вода очищают всё остальное и потому никогда не должны загрязняться, а Огонь даже может очистить воду; что весь огонь есть Огонь от Солца и он есть в каждой вещи и может быть освобождён как огонь; что из Огня и из воды пришли все вещи, а Огонь и вода есть два Духа: Огонь — жизни, и вода — формы (Возможно эти слова легли в основу учения об Аримане и Ахура-Мазде и поэтому Ариман в оригинале был не злой силой, а скорее материей, в то время как Ахура-Мазда — Духом).
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
¹ Possibly out of this arose the later teaching of Ormuzd and Ahriman. There are passages which show that the double of Ormuzd was not originally an evil power, but rather matter, while Ormuzd was Spirit.
</view>
<view lang="ru">

</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Mahaguru had round Him a quite august assemblage of Masters, and others less advanced. He left these to carry on His teaching when He departed.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Махагуру окружил себя благородным собранием Мастеров и группой менее продвинувшихся людей. Он оставил их для продвижения Своего учения после того, как Он уйдёт.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
His departure was as dramatic as His first preaching.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Его отбытие было столь же эффектным как и первое появление.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The people were gathered together to hear Him preach, as He was wont to do occasionally, and they knew not that it was for the last time. He stood, as before, on the great platform, but there was no altar. He preached, inculcating the duty of gaining knowledge and of practising love, and bade them follow and obey Surya, whom He left in His place as Teacher. And then He told them that He was going, and He blessed them, and lifting up His arms to the eastern sky He called aloud; and out of the sky came down a whirling cloud of flame, and enwrapped Him as He stood, and then, whirling still, it shot upwards and fled eastwards, and-- He was gone.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Люди собрались вместе, чтобы услышать Его проповедь и, поскольку, Он имел обычкновение это делать, они не догадывались, что эта проповедь последняя. Он стоял как и раньше на большой платформе, но рядом уже не было алтаря. Он проповедовал об обязанности получать знания и необходимости проявления любви, Он говорил людям следовать за Surya который останется на Его месте и станет Учителем. Тогда Он сказал им, что уходит и благословил их. Подняв руки к восточному небу Он позвал и с неба пришёл вихрь огня, охватил Его и не прекращая кружиться исчез на востоке вместе с Ним.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then the people fell on their faces and cried out that He was a God, and they exulted exceedingly that He had lived among them; but the King was very sad, and mourned for His departure many days. And Mercury, who, in his subtle body, had ever remained near Him, at His service, returned with Him to the Holy Ones, and rested for a while in peace.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Тогда люди пали ниц и начали выкрикивать, что Он Бог. Они были счастливы, что Он жил среди них. Но Король был несчастен и скорбел по Его исчезновению много дней. Меркурий, который в тонком теле всегда оставался рядом, возвратился с Ним к Святым и отдыхал некоторое время в мире.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After He had gone, Star-worship did not at once disappear, for the people regarded His teaching as a reform, not as a substitution, and still worshipped the Moon, and Venus, and the constellations, and the planets; but the Fire was held sacred as the image, the emblem, and the being of the Sun, and the new religion rather enfolded the old one than replaced it. Gradually the Faith of the Fire grew stronger and stronger; Star-worship retreated from Persia to Mesopotamia, where it remained the dominant faith, and took a very scientific form. Astrology there reached its zenith, and scientifically guided human affairs, both public and private. Its priests possessed much occult knowledge, and the wisdom of the Magi became famed throughout the East. In Persia, the Religion of the Fire triumphed, and later Prophets carried on the work of the great Zarathustra, and built up the Zoroastrian Faith and its literature; it has endured down to our own day.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
После того как Он ушёл культ Звёзд не исчез сразу, так как люди рассматривали его как реформу, а не замену и продолжали поклоняться Луне, Венера, созвездиям и планетам; но Огонь стал священным, эмблемой и сущностью Солнца и новая религия постепенно раскрылась и заменила старую. Постепенно Вера в Огонь становилась сильнее и сильнее, а культ Звёзд отступил из Персии и ушёл в Месопотамию, где остался главной верой принявшей очень научную форму. Астрология там достигла зенита и учитывалась в людских делах, как общих так и личных. Жрецы получили много оккультных знаний, а мудрость Маджи стала известна на весь Восток. В Персии религия Огня заняла почётное место и позднее провидцы несли знание великого Заратуштры и создали веру Зороастризма в своей литературе, которая дожила до наших дней.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The third sub-race numbered about a million souls when they settled down in Persia and Mesopotamia, and they multiplied rapidly under the favourable conditions of their new home, and also incorporated in their nation the sparse population which existed in the country when they entered it.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Третья подраса насчитывала миллион душ когда они освоились в Персии и Месопотамии. В благодатных условиях нового дома они быстро увеличивали численность населения и включали в свою нацию небольшие поселения стран до которых добирались.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In the twenty-eight thousand years of the Persian Empire there were naturally many fluctuations; most of the time Persia and Mesopotamia were under separate rulers, of whom sometimes the one, sometimes the other, was nominally Overlord; sometimes the two countries were split up into smaller States, owing a kind of loose feudal allegiance to the central King. All through their history they had constantly recurring difficulties with the nomad Mongolians on one hand, and the mountaineers of Kurdistan and the Hindu Kush on the other. Sometimes the Iranians drew back for a time before these tribes; sometimes they pushed the frontier of civilisation further forward, and drove the savages back. At one period they ruled most of Asia Minor, and made temporary settlements in several of the countries bordering the Mediterranean; at one time they held Cyprus, Rhodes and Crete; but on the whole in that part of the world the Atlantean power was too strong for them, and they avoided conflict with it. At this western boundary of their kingdom powerful Scythian and Hittite confederations disputed their dominion at various points of their history; once at least they conquered Syria, but seemed to have found it a useless acquisition and soon abandoned it; and twice they embroiled themselves with Egypt, against which they could do but little. During most of this long period they kept up a high level of civilisation, and many relics of their mighty architecture lie buried beneath desert sands. Various dynasties arose among them, and several different languages prevailed in the course of their chequered history. They avoided hostilities with India, being separated from it by a wild territory-- a sort of no-man' s-land; Arabia troubled them but little, for there again a useful belt of desert intervened. They were great traders, merchants, manufacturers-- a much more settled people than the second sub-race, and with more definite religious ideas. The best specimens of the Parsis of the present day give a fair idea of their appearance. The present inhabitants of Persia have still much of their blood in them, though largely commingled with that of their Arab conquerors. The Kurds, the Afghans, and the Baluchis are also mainly descended from them, though with various admixtures.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
За двадцать восемь столетий Персидская Империя перенесла много естественных трудностей. Большую часть времени Персия и Месопотамия имели разных правителей, из которых иногда один, иногда другой, формально признавался верховным правителем. Были времена когда страны распадались на небольшие города, правители которых теряли лояльность к центральному Королю. На протяжении всей своей истории они постоянно сталкивались с проблемой монгольских номадов с одной стороны и горцев Курдистана и Гиндукуша с другой. Иногда Иранцы оставались позади этих племён, иногда отодвигали фронт цивилизации вперёд, оставляя дикарей позади. Был период когда они правили всей Азией и имели временные поселения в странах граничащих с Средиземноморьем. Однажды они захватили Кипр, Родос и Крит, но в целом в той части мира сила Атлантов была слишком велика для них и они не рисковали вступать в конфликт. На западном крае их королевства могущественные конфедерации Скифов и Хеттов оспаривали права по многим пунктам. Как-то раз они даже захватили Сирию, но позже по видимому нашли её бесполезным приобретением и покинули её. Дважды они впутывались в конфликт с Египтом, против которого они мало что могли поставить. Основную часть этого длительного периода они поддерживали цивилизацию на высоком уровне и многие следы их великой архитектуры лежат погребённые под песками пустынь. Среди них появлялись разные династии и многие языки, которые поочерёдно доминировали в течении их неспокойной истории. Они избегали проблем с Индией, будучи отделённые от неё дикой территорией — неким видом безлюдной земли. Иногда им докучала Аравия, но не сильно, благодаря песчаному поясу удачно разделявшим два королевства. Они были отличными торговцами, купцами и производителями и гораздо более усидчивыми людьми чем население второй подрасы, к тому же они имели более определённые религиозные идеи. Лучшие представители Парсиса в наши дни могут дать хорошее представление о той цивилизации. Настоящие жители Персии всё ещё имеют кровь своих предков, хотя и смешанную с кровью Арабских завоевателей. Курды, Афганцы и Балучи в основном произошли от них.
</view>
</text>
</body>