<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 36
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 36-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Our story now carries us back again to the great Atlantic island of Poseidonis, for this time
      Alcyone took a male birth in the white race which inhabited its northern mountains. He was born in
      the year 9672 B.C., only a little before the final catastrophe which sank the land. The general
      condition of the country was one of great corruption, and the majority of the population, the
      dominant races which inhabited the plains, lived dissolute and selfish lives, which involved the
      practice of a large amount of black magic. In these northern mountains, however, patriarchal
      conditions existed, and life in general was of a much healthier type than that in the plains below.
      The people had much less of the arts and refinements of civilisation,, but were certainly purer and
      nobler than those of the cities.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Some of the tribes inhabiting the various valleys of the great mountain range owed a nominal
      allegiance to the Toltec king below; others had independent rulers of their own. But in either case
      the owner of the valley was usually practically also its undisputed lord; for his allegiance was
      merely nominal, whether it was given to some monarch of his own fifth sub-race or to the Toltec
      sovereign. Quarrels between the Toltec government and the mountaineers as to the payment of the
      amount of tribute were more or less constant. Owing to the extreme difficulty of manoeuvring an
      army in such rugged country it was rarely worth while for the Toltec sovereign to try to enforce
      his claims; but now and then an army was sent out, and usually it succeeded in devastating one or
      two isolated valleys, massacring the male inhabitants and carrying off the women and cattle.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The father of Alcyone was Neptune, and his mother Herakles. His elder sister Mercury became while
      quite young a postulant at a temple in the hills, and later was one of its priestesses; though this
      in no way interfered with her marriage and family life. All the younger children of the family
      adopted her, and she always gently protected, helped and taught them. The religion was a form of
      sun-worship, and all the great festivals were determined by the solistices and equinoxes. On the
      whole the life of these mountaineers seems to have been pure and healthy a striking contrast to the
      utter corruption of the great cities of the plains. Neptune lived on his huge estate in truly
      patriarchal style; he practically owned a whole valley for the land was all valleys divided by
      steep ridges. He had many dependants, but although they were respectful in a certain independent
      sort of way, they were really almost more like friends than servants.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      We have here then a large group of people who lived happily together, and on the whole lived
      practically to themselves. They occasionally visited the men of neighbouring valleys and received
      visits from them, but these were always rather formal affairs, needing a good deal of preparation,
      because of the serious amount of climbing involved in crossing the intervening ridges. The
      character of the country was such that a detour of many miles was frequently necessary in order to
      reach a house which would have been less than a mile off if a tunnel could have been made through
      the hill. On the whole these valleys were fairly secure against attacks from below, unless a great
      force was brought against them and an elaborate plan was made to close beforehand all means of
      escape. They had books, but not many of them; there was much recitation of bardic poems and much
      telling of legends, of which Alcyone's mother, Herakles, had a wonderful collection enough to make
      a modern folk-lorist green with envy. The people believed in nature-spirits, and there were among
      them many who had seen them.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The conditions in some ways rather resembled those of which we hear in mediaeval England; all the
      weaving and spinning were done at home, and there seems to have been an immense amount of house and
      farm work. The housewives kept great stores of linen and herbs. The men seem mostly to have lived
      on horseback, using a kind of surefooted mountain pony, which looked somewhat mule-like. Many of
      these valleys were loosely joined under a chieftain, and some of these chieftains paid, as we have
      said, a nominal tribute to the Toltecs, though most of them were independent, and among these lost
      was the King to which this valley belonged. The Toltecs periodically attacked them, but rarely with
      success, because of the configuration of the country. Apart from the occasional menace of such
      attacks they lived peacefully and happily enough, with their harvest festivals and their festivals
      at the time of sowing the seed, at both of which races and athletic sports were prominent. These
      festivals were the great occasions of meeting between the people of the different valleys; and
      Neptune's men especially exchanged amenities with their nearest neighbours, the vassals of his
      brothers Naga and Yajna, who divided between them the next valley on one side, and those of Ivy,
      who dwelt in a little isolated basin far up the hills on the other. Their society was necessarily
      limited, but harmonious. Education was simply, and was chiefly given at home, for in most of the
      valleys there was nothing in the nature of a school.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone grew up happily, and was a strong and healthy boy. He deeply admired his father and mother,
      but his love for his elder sister, Mercury, was the dominant factor in his early life. As a small
      boy he could not bear to be parted from her, and did nothing without consulting her; and indeed as
      long she lived she was the principal influence over him.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      At a harvest festivity, when he was only ten years old, he first saw Vega, who was to be his future
      wife; he singled her out at once, and would play with no one else, and the small maiden, who was
      about his own age, was flattered by his attentions and reciprocated his affection. He never forgot
      her, though as he grew older he became more shy in expressing his sentiments. When she was sixteen
      she had grown unusually beautiful, and several suitors were already eagerly applying for her hand
      among them Alcyone's elder brother, Albireo, who was the heir to the estate and therefore could
      offer a better position than Alcyone could as a younger son. This troubled Alcyone greatly; he
      loved his brother and did not wish to stand in his way, nor to prevent Vega from becoming mistress
      of the whole valley, as she would eventually be if she married Albireo; and yet he felt that he
      could not give her up.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      As usual he confided in Mercury, who sympathised deeply, and told him that the matter must be left
      to the decision of Vega, who might after all have a personal preference which could take no account
      of wealth in hand or in flocks and herds. Alcyone kept himself in the background, and gave Albireo
      every chance, and only when Vega had definitely refused the latter did he venture to offer himself
      as a substitute. Vega joyously accepted him, and they were married when they were just twenty, and
      lived the happiest of lives together. Albireo loyally accepted Vega's decision, though he suffered
      much at first. After some years, he consoled himself by marrying another lady, Concord, but they
      had no children, and a little later Albireo was killed in resisting one of the Toltec forays, so
      that after all Alcyone became the heir, and stood in the position of which he had feared that he
      was depriving her.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone and Vega had a large family Sirius, the last and youngest of the flock, being born when
      Alcyone was already fifty-four years of age. Just at that time Neptune died, and Alcyone inherited
      the vast estate, which he directed with much wisdom, for while he kept the headship of the valley,
      and decided all cases himself, he yet left the practical management of the land almost entirely in
      the hands of his younger brothers Psyche and Leo, who were in many ways better at details than he
      was himself. For thirty-two years he held his position, hale, active and keen-sighted to the last,
      outliving most of his contemporaries.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The brothers who had assisted him so ably died long before him, but their place was filled by his
      eldest son Ulysses, who proved a most capable manager. Through all this time his life flowed on
      evenly, and on the whole happy, for the only variations were good harvests or bad harvests, fine
      years or stormy ones, with occasional rumours of Toltec raids. His children grew up and married,
      and he saw his grandchildren and even his great-grandchildren around him, and was always the best
      of friends and counsellors to all of them. The great sorrows of his life were the deaths of Mercury
      and of Vega, the latter fortunately taking place only a little before his own.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The long dreaded Toltec invasion, of which they had been hearing for years as harrying distant
      valleys, finally descended upon them in the year 9586. Old as he was, Alcyone gathered his people,
      and rode at their head to meet the enemy. Owing to the superiority of their position, the
      mountaineers were able to hold back the Toltecs for two days, and to slaughter many of them; but
      reinforcements from the plains arrived, and Alcyone and his faithful followers were overwhelmed by
      numbers. He himself was killed, as were all the men and elder women of his tribe, while the younger
      women were carried into captivity down in the plains. Sirius, at that time thirty-two years of age,
      was one of the latter.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      She was assigned to the harem of a rich Toltec, and plunged into a life of servitude of a most
      intolerable character. She suffered much, but tried to bear it philosophically, hoping always for
      some amelioration of her condition. About a month later, Orion, who had lived in an adjoining
      valley, was captured in the same way and was bought by the same man, and so she and Sirius met for
      the first time in that life. Orion was less philosophical; she was filled with indignation, and was
      all the while in a condition of passionate protest against all the outrages offered to her. By the
      end of a week she was half insane with the horror of it all, and in fact had already made two
      attempts at suicide. Sirius was filled with pity for her, and contrived to some extent to protect
      her and to make her lot more bearable. Naturally, all their hopes were centred upon escape, though
      it seemed entirely hopeless. Sirius at last conceived a plan which, though desperate enough, seemed
      not quite absolutely impossible. To get out of the house at all was their first great difficulty,
      but even if that were achieved their white skins would at once betray them as slaves, and they
      could not walk a hundred yards without the certainty of exposure and capture. Obviously, therefore,
      disguise was necessary, and Sirius contrived to obtain possession of some of the complexion paint
      which, being intended for a Toltec woman, gave the darker tint which would make the fugitives
      resemble the conquering race. One day Sirius contrived to purloin a suit of clothes which belonged
      to one of the male visitors. Hurriedly she applied the paint to her face, hands and arms, and also
      carefully painted Orion. Then she put on the male garments, dressed Orion in some clothes of the
      Toltec women, made her veil herself thoroughly, and then took her boldly by the hand and made her
      way into the more public part of the house, mingling easily with the guests and quite naturally
      walking out of the house by the front door amidst bowing servants. This happy audacity carried them
      safely into the street as they were the appearance of a Toltec husband and wife no one interfered
      with them. They had, of course, no money, but Sirius had some trifling jewels, which she had been
      wearing when captured. They had been taken from her, but she thought it no harm to steal them back
      again before she started. Selling these they obtained some money, and later on they gained some by
      selling their fashionable garments and changing into ordinary dress of the respectable working
      people of the country. With all sorts of adventures and difficulties they made their way towards
      the hills where their home had been, and were very thankful when they came once more among people
      of their own race, even though these were only the tribes of the foot-hills, who had long been in
      subjection to the Toltec government. But at least among them they were able to wash off the
      horrible paint which it had cost them such ceaseless trouble to renew. To attain permanent safety
      they must either reach some part of the mountains where the people did not owe allegiance to the
      Toltecs, or they must take refuge in a nunnery; for when the country had yielded itself to the
      Toltec government a special stipulation had been made that there should be no interference with the
      religious institutions of the country, and that the right of sanctuary should still remain to
      these. As Orion was in weak and nervous state they were practically forced to the latter
      alternative, and accordingly they applied to Helios, the abbess of a great monastery which lay near
      their route. To her they revealed their entire history, and she at once took them in and assured
      them of her protection. Here they lived happily for many years, the only incident of adjoining
      monastery, to obtain mesmeric influence over Orion for improper purposes. This attempt was defeated
      by Sirius, and Scorpio's trickery was revealed to Helios, who had him sent away from the monastery.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The sinking of Poseidonis was foretold by the priests of the northern race, and, though many did
      not believe or pay any attention, there were also many who did. As the time approached, the abbess
      called her great army of nuns together, and dramatically described to them what was coming. She
      stated that as money would soon no longer be required, all the great wealth of the convent was at
      the disposal of those who wished to leave the country, and all were left perfectly free to do what
      they chose. For herself she cared little about life, and did not care to begin it all over again in
      a new place as she was too old, and so she intended to stay and perish with her country, upholding
      the flag of her order to the last. Sirius and Orion, full of affection for her, and fixed by her
      enthusiasm, resolved to stay with her, as did a good many of the nuns. More than half, however,
      took advantage of her offer, and eleven large ships were fitted out to convey them to other lands.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      When the final destruction came the abbess called the nuns together and asked Orion, who was a fine
      musician, to play to them, to play as she had never played before. The nervous shrinking woman was
      absolutely transfigured; an ecstasy descended upon her and she swept the strings with a noble
      gesture and called forth such a volume of sound as no harp had ever before given. So tremendous was
      the power of that divine music that when the sea rushed in and swept all the nuns to destruction
      not a single cry was raised, for all were so rapt from the lower world that the passage into the
      next was unnoticed.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Another of our characters, Erato, also born in a female body among the mountains, had precisely the
      same experience of being captured and enslaved in the great city. In this case, however, the son
      Ursa of her owner Alastor fell in love with her and married her. Though a self-indulgent man, no
      better than the rest in that dissolute era, he was good to his young wife in a careless sort of
      way, and she was grateful to him for having saved her from the ordinary lot of the slave. When the
      time of the cataclysm approached, she was warned of it by the priests of her own people, and she
      announced their prophesy to her husband. He ridiculed the idea, but as many others were escaping to
      Africa and Europe he good-naturedly offered to allow her to go with them, telling her that she
      would come back in a year or two and find him living just the same life under the same conditions.
      She thanked him, but declined his offer, saying that if he intended to perish along with his
      country she thought it her duty to remain by his side. He was pleased with her decision, even
      though he had not the slightest expectation that anything would really happen. When the cataclysm
      came he acknowledged that she had been right, and regretted that he had not listened to her; but
      they died together by no means ignobly.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It would seem that with the life we come as far as Erato is concerned to the close of a minor cycle
      of soul-evolution ; in it we see the success of a kind of evolutionary experiment. In his earlier
      life in Chaldea he was thrown into surroundings which made a good life eminently probable for him.
      Born in the priestly caste, he encountered none but virtuous examples; virtue was universally
      expected of him, and in every way made easy for him. To have sinned seriously would have been
      difficult; it would have been to fly in the face of all comfortable conventions; it would have
      needed a determination in the direction of wickedness which our hero happily did not possess. So he
      succumbed to his fate, and was good. In the second life one may see the application of a test to
      the habit of goodness which had been set up in the previous incarnation. Here were circumstances
      distinctly less favourable than the Chaldean; would the ego prove strong enough to rise superior to
      them? He did; he came triumphantly through the ordeal, and thereby strengthened his character. In
      the third life a far harder test was applied, and he was plunged into the midst of a civilisation
      so unsatisfactory in every way that to lead a good life under the conditions would have been more
      difficult than to lead an evil one as a priest in Chaldea. He was not strong enough for this; he
      became the creature of his circumstances, and lived as did others around him. It may have been but
      natural for them, but for him it was a failure, for he had known something far better.
      Consequently, his next life shows a distinct drop. There was here a certain amount of physical
      suffering, which no doubt toughened his fibre even while it discharged some portion s of his heavy
      karmic debt. In the succeeding incarnation he had a great deal of emotional suffering. On the whole
      he bore it well and nobly, and came out of it purified and strengthened. The Peruvian life was
      clearly an opportunity for him to try his newly acquired powers under the most favourable auspices,
      thereby not only increasing them but setting up a habit of using them creating a momentum along the
      line of good. When this had been accomplished, and when he had also achieved whatever result was
      expected from that quaint Chinese incarnation in which he did little more than leave his card on
      the Celestial Empire, back he came again to the very scene of the original failure in Poseidonis to
      try over again to the very scene of the original failure in Poseidonis to try over again that
      terrible test. But the intervening lives had not been spent in vain; they had done their work; this
      time he passed, and passed triumphantly, not only leading a good life in the midst of general
      iniquity, but even nobly sacrificing that life to an almost exaggerated sense of duty. Thus the
      object of the evolutionary forces was achieved and he was at liberty to pass on to the development
      of another side of his character.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Returning now to the valleys in which our story of this life opened, we find that Ulysses, the
      eldest son of Alcyone, though left for dead upon the field of battle, afterwards recovered and,
      gathering together a few men who had contrived to escape to the hills, attempted a partial
      restoration of the ravaged estates. All the cattle had been captured and all the crops destroyed,
      but he made a beginning again in a small way; and though he lived only for a few years, two of his
      children, Cetus and Pyx, whom he had hidden, carried on the work after his death, and had succeeded
      in bringing part of the estate once more under cultivation before the date of the sinking of the
      island. They were, however, among these who accepted the warning of the priests, and made their
      escape from Poseidonis in time to avoid to final catastrophe.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      A considerable number of the children escaped the massacre. Some, like Cetus and Pyx, were hidden
      in caves which the Toltec marauders never discovered; others were sent away when the first rumours
      of the inland valley, the very existence of which was unknown to the soldiers of the plains. It
      happened that some twenty years before. Alcyone had sent his nephew Fides on a mission to chief of
      that inland valley; and that chief, taking a great fancy to Fides, and seeing that he could be of
      great use to him and could teach his people much, had begged him to send for his family and settle
      there. This fides did, after obtaining permission from Alcyone; and so when wars and rumours of
      wars began to fill the air, a refuge among their own relations in that place of safety was ready
      for those children whose parents thought it wise to provide for them. Sirius, for example, made
      this arrangement for her two little daughters Ajax and Elsa, and consequently they grew up under
      the fostering care of Fides and Uranus, and in due course were happily married.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      When the priests and astrologers of the white mountain race issued their warning of the impending
      destruction of the continent, Fides, though by that time an old man, gathered together those among
      his adopted people who wished to leave the country, and acted as leader of a considerable migration
      by sea to Northern Africa. He was hospitably received there, and his followers were encouraged to
      settle among the Atlas Mountains, in a valley by no means unlike the home that they had left. There
      among the Kabyles some of their descendants are still to be found, though naturally there has been
      some of their descendants are still to be found, though naturally there has been some admixture of
      other blood during the millenniums that have passed. One of our characters, Spica, had the honour
      of being the first baby born in the new settlement, the very day after the caravan had ramped
      there; and Fides declared this to be a happy omen, and specially distinguished the newly born
      infant by conferring upon him the title of father of the new land and taking him under his special
      protection.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
