<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 31
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 31-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Our story takes us this time to the southern part of the great island of Poseidonis, in the middle
      of what is now the Atlantic Ocean. Alcyone was born there among a nation of mountaineers of
      Tlavatli race, in the year 13,651 B.C. She was the daughter of Mercury, a priest of the Sun, who
      was of noble birth, being distantly related to the ruler of the country. She had a happy childhood,
      and was utterly devoted to her father, who was especially kindly and helpful towards her, and seems
      to have understood children better than the average parent of that age. The religion of the period
      was primarily Sun-worship, although there was also a good deal of personification of various powers
      of nature; and it would also seem that some great saints of old had been deified. The little girl
      was keenly interested in the temple ceremonies, and much impressed by them, and when she was young
      it was her wish to dedicate her life to the service of the temple. In connection with the temple
      there were two careers open for women one being something along the line of the usual vestal
      virgins, or temple-clairvoyants, and the other a sort of guild of service which consisted of
      married women.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      В этот раз мы отправляемся в южную часть великого острова Посейдонис располагающегося в центре
      современного Атлантического океана. Алкион родилась там среди горцев тлаватской расы в 13,651 г. до
      н.э. Она оказалась дочкой Меркурия, который был жрецом Солнца благородного происхождения и был
      дальним родственником правителя страны. У неё было счастливое детство и она была очень предана
      отцу, который был к ней очень добр и казалось понимал детей лучше чем другие родители того времени.
      Основной религией тогда было поклонение Солнцу, хотя также было достаточно распространено
      олицетворение различных сил природы; кроме того, некоторых святых из далёкого прошлого почитали как
      богов. Будучи ребёнком её очень интересовали и сильно впечатляли церемонии в храмах, и тогда у неё
      было желание посвятить свою жизнь подобной службе. В храме для женщин открывалось два пути: либо
      стать обычной монахиней - ясновидящей при храме, либо присоединиться к чему то вроде гильдии
      замужних женщин.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      As she grew up she prepared herself for the former position, with the approval of her father, and
      entered herself at the age of sixteen. The various practices of meditation enjoined for the girls
      appear to have produced considerable effect upon her, and the father was hopeful about her making
      rapid progress. However, before her first year of definite service in the novitiate was completed,
      the inevitable young man appeared on the scene, and she fell deeply in love with him. The object of
      her affections (Sirius) was something of a mystery; he had only recently appeared in the city, and
      no one seemed to know who he was, nor whence he came, and even in these earlier years that was
      regarded as an objection to a possible suitor, though he was a handsome and well-set-up youth. She
      saw this young man at some of the temple service, and they were strangely attracted towards each
      other at first sight, so that he began to scheme for occasions of meeting her, which were difficult
      to procure, since she was constantly in attendance at the temple. The young suitor, however,
      contrived, by the exercise of great patience and assiduity, to obtain speech with her on a good
      many occasions, and their strange friendship rapidly warmed into a passionate attachment.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      С позволения отца она готовила себя на роль ясновидящей и приступила к подготовке в 16 лет.
      Разнообразные способы медитации предусмотренные для девочек оказали на неё заметный эффект и её
      отец надеялся на то, что она быстро продвинется вперёд. Однако ещё до того как закончился первый
      год её испытания, в её жизни появился неизбежный молодой человек и она в него сильно влюбилась.
      Объект её симпатий (Сириус) был окутан тайной: он лишь недавно появился в городе и кажется никто не
      знал ни кто он такой ни откуда он взялся; даже в те времена это считалось поводом для отказа
      потенциальному ухажёру, несмотря на то, что он хорошо выглядел и был не беден. Она видела этого
      молодого человека на одной церковной службе и при первом взгляде они странным образом ощутили
      притяжение друг к другу, так что он начал искать поводы встретить её, что было непросто, потому что
      она постоянно находилась в храме. Молодой ухажёр однако сумел при помощи большого терпения и рвения
      поговорить с ней много раз и их странная дружба быстро превратилась в страстную привязанность.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      At first, Alcyone said nothing of this to her father, but he half-divined that something was going
      on, and he put some questions to her which presently brought forth a shamefaced confession that the
      temple services were no longer the first thing in life for her. The father was disappointed at
      this, but nevertheless took it both kindly and philosophically, and gave her some sensible advice,
      to the effect that it was useless to devote herself to the special service of the Deity unless she
      was absolutely certain of her vocation, and that after all she could serve the Sun-God, less
      directly perhaps, yet just as truly and nobly, if she followed the dictates of her heart. He
      demanded, however, to see the young man, and the latter's account of himself was by no means
      satisfactory from the point of view of a parent, for he could only say that though he was of noble
      birth and quite equal in rank to her whom he loved, yet there was surrounding his origin a mystery,
      which he was not at liberty to disclose. Also he seemed to have no present connection with his
      family, whatever it might have been, and was obtaining a somewhat precarious livelihood by hunting,
      though he declared that this was in no way the vocation to which he was born. The priest was
      strongly attracted to him, in spite of his obvious undesirability, for he seemed both a handsome
      and a worthy young fellow, though curiously untamed and seemingly ignorant of the ways of ordinary
      life. Mercury frankly told him that he liked what he saw of him, but at the same time it was quite
      impossible that he should give his daughter to a person involved in so much mystery, and with no
      regular means of livelihood, that unless he was prepared fully to confide in him, he felt with
      regret that he could hardly encourage the intimacy of the two young lovers.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Поначалу Алкион ничего не сказала отцу, но он догадался, что то то произошло и задал ей несколько
      вопросов, которые вывели на свет стыдливое признание того, что церковные службы уже не стоят для
      неё на первом месте. Её отец расстроился узнав это, но принял это мягко и философски и дал ей
      разумный совет, что нет смысла посвящать себя особой службе Божеству если она совершенно точно не
      чувствует такого призвания, и что, в конце концов, она может служить Солнечному Богу, возможно не
      так явно, но всё же также искренне и благородно, если она последует указаниям своего сердца. Однако
      он захотел увидеть молодого человека и рассказ последнего о себе несомненно не был
      удовлетворительным с точки зрения родителя, поскольку он мог лишь сказать, что был благородного
      происхождения и вполне равным по рангу той которую он любил, но его рождение было окутано тайной
      которую он не считал возможным раскрыть. Также он потерял связь со своей семьёй, какой бы она ни
      была, и влачил довольно жалкое существование за счёт охоты, но это, как он сказал, ни в коем случае
      не было его призванием ради которого он родился. Священник начал испытывать к нему сильную
      симпатию, несмотря на то, что он не подходил, поскольку он был не только красивым, но и достойным
      парнем, хотя и удивительно невежественен в повседневной жизни. Меркурий прямо сказал, что он ему
      понравился, но он считает невозможным отдать свою дочь человеку окутанному такой тайной и без каких
      либо средств к существованию.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The young man was much cast down by this, though he could not but admit its justice, but he still
      maintained that the secret in which he was involved was not his own, and that he must await the
      proper time before divulging it. Thus the matter was left in suspense for some little time, the
      priest regretfully forbidding the young people to see each other in private, even though he quite
      frankly admitted that he felt strongly drawn towards the mysterious young man. Alcyone's affection
      for him was so strong that she probably might have ignored the mystery and fled with him, but for
      her strong love for and confidence in her father, which persuaded her that he must be right, even
      in what she thought his first cruelty towards her. She was much torn by divided feelings, and
      suffered greatly for a while.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Молодой человек был этим сильно обескуражен, хотя и не мог не согласиться с тем, что это справедливо,

    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      All this time the ruler of the country, Alastor, was at war with the Toltec overlord, Corona, some
      question of an extravagant demand for tribute having brought a long smouldering disaffection to the
      point of open revolt. Owing to the greatly superior discipline and fighting power of the armies of
      the suzerain, it was difficult for these men of the hills to meet them in open fight. The local
      King, however, knew his country very well, and his son Ursa contrived to destroy a large Toltec
      army by inveigling it into a valley which he was then able to flood from a concealed reservoir. In
      honour of this victory there were great public rejoicings and a sort of national festival was held.
      Somehow, in the course of this, strange rumours began to fly about with regard to the young lover,
      Sirius, and he was one day suddenly arrested and carried before old King Alsator. In the course of
      the enquiries then made the whole of the strange life-story of Sirius came out, and proved to be
      romantic though distinctly unconventional.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Всё это время правитель страны, Аластор, воевал с толтекским владыкой, Короной,
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This old Alastor was a precise but incredibly stupid man, and in consequence of his character the
      affairs of his family had gone seriously wrong. His son Ursa was a wild young fellow, accustomed to
      do what he liked, without any consideration for others. He had a younger sister, Orion, who in
      their childhood was entirely devoted to him. They were always together, and he made her fetch and
      carry for him in the usual manner of elder brothers with devoted little sisters. As they grew up,
      the affection between them remained as strong as ever, and in process of time his relations with
      her became more than fraternal. This was discovered, and caused some scandal, for even in those
      more easy-going times such relationship was considered highly improper. When it came to Alastor's
      knowledge he behaved in the most foolish manner, making a great parade of Spartan justice, and,
      instead of treating the young people kindly and sensibly, he banished his son from the country and
      condemned his daughter to death. Ursa, however, had no idea of submitting quietly to such an
      inauspicious ending to his pleasures. He managed to escape from his father's guards, and to rescue
      his sister from the place in which she was confined, and they fled together and concealed
      themselves in a forest on the outskirts of the kingdom, having contrived to divert pursuit by
      allowing it to be understood that they had fled by sea from a certain port in quite another
      direction. In this forest he and his sister lived for some years, and two children were born to
      them, a son, Sirius, and a daughter, Vega. Ursa carefully tattooed round the waist of Sirius the
      red snake which marked him as the heir to the throne, and the brother and sister lived happily
      enough in sylvan solitude; but after a time Ursa began to tire of this life and to yearn for the
      delights of the Court and the position which he had left.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Being in the habit of considering only his own convenience, he had no hesitation in abandoning his
      wife and children; he made his appearance at a port and pretended to have arrived from a foreign
      country. He soon made his way to his father, who forgave him and reinstated him as heir to the
      throne. Being anxious to provide for the succession. Alastor shortly arranged a marriage for Ursa,
      which the latter accepted without saying anything about the wife and the children whom he had left
      behind in the forest. Indeed, on first returning he had allowed it to be understood that he had had
      no part in his sister's escape, and knew nothing about her fate. His new wife, Hesperia, presently
      bore him child, Pollux; and this child was also tattooed with the snake, for if Ursa had not
      permitted this to be done, suspicion would have been at once aroused. The new wife, however, proved
      to be of a trying temper, and he often looked back with regret on his happy free life in the
      forest. On one occasion when he was out hunting in the forest where he had lived so long, he
      contrived to separate himself from his companions and went to look at the hut which he had built
      for his sister-wife, but he found it deserted.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Orion had lived on there for many years and had seen her children grow up healthy and beautiful.
      She had no difficulty with regard to food, for the various traps which Ursa had made were still in
      action and she was able to gather fruit and dig up roots as he had done. When her children grew old
      enough to need clothing she wove it for them from reeds, and they lived a natural and happy life,
      though she sorrowed much because of the desertion of her brother and husband. She always cherished
      the hope that some time of other he would return to her, and that in process of time her son would
      sit upon the throne of his ancestors.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Presently it occurred to her that, if this were to be so, she must manage to bring her children
      somehow into contact with their fellow-creatures, that they might not be entirely strange to them;
      so she dressed herself in what remained of the clothes in which she had originally escaped, and
      made her way to a village where she was able to exchange the skin of the creatures that they had
      killed for some clothing, such as peasants wear, suitable for the children and herself. She was
      then able to take her children once or twice on expeditions to villages in the remote part of the
      country where the forest was situated, but she did not visit the same village twice, lest suspicion
      should be excited, and she always gave out that she and her children were travellers passing
      through the country. As the young man grew up his mother told him the story of his royal birth, and
      they planned how they would reappear in the capital and claim recognition after the death of the
      old king.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Presently, however, Orion fell ill and died. When on her deathbed she made her son solemnly promise
      that he would go to his father and announce himself as the heir to the throne. She warned him
      however that his father was a man of moods, and that he must watch carefully for the right moment
      at which to make such an announcement. The young people mourned deeply the death of their mother.
      They buried her body under the floor of the hut, and then abandoned it for ever, as they could not
      bear to live any longer in a place where every tree and stone reminded them perpetually of their
      loss. They made their way gradually to the capital, Sirius taking the most affectionate care of his
      sister Vega. He contrived to find some employment there, using chiefly his skill in hunting and
      trapping. His intention was in this way to support himself and his sister until the old King died;
      but, as has been described, he was forestalled in this. Among the festivities in connection with
      the great victory previously mentioned were some swimming races in which he took part in which,
      indeed, he out-distanced all competitors but it happened by some accident that the red snake
      tattooed round his waist was seen, and remarks began to fly about which eventually reached the ears
      of old Alastor, and led to his being brought before him. When the truth came out there was an angry
      scene, and Alastor compelled Ursa to issue an order for the execution of Sirius, who was cast into
      prison and closely guarded. To Alastor, however, the shock of the disclosure had been so great that
      it brought on a stroke, from which he never recovered, and he died in few days.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Ursa then became King, and he was resolved that his elder son Sirius should be heir to the throne,
      instead of Pollux, as the latter had even shown a weak and dissipated character. The new King was
      however in difficulties, as he could not well annul the decree which his father had forced him to
      sign, so he determined to manage privately the escape of Sirius from prison. His second wife,
      Hesperia, seems in some way to have got wind of his intention, or perhaps she only suspected him,
      but at any rate she watched him closely and resolved to thwart him in the interest of her own son
      Pollux.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The prison was a curious labyrinth of stone walls, circle within circle, and every opening from one
      circle to another was efficiently guarded. The son, as a prisoner of State, was placed in the
      central cell of all. Ursa disguised himself and left his palace, secretly at night, went to the
      outer guard and bribed him with a curious trinket, in consideration for receiving which he agreed
      to absent himself for a few moments, and allow the disguised King to enter the prison. Meanwhile
      the jealous Hesperia had discovered her husband's absence, and, full of suspicion, immediately
      rushed to the prison gates. Finding the first guard gone her suspicions were confirmed, and she
      entered by the door which Ursa had left open. The latter went on until he met the second guard,
      upon whom he sprang before he could give the alarm, and managed, after a furious struggle, to choke
      the man to death. He succeeded in eluding the third guard, but again had a struggle with the
      fourth, in which he finally conquered, though he himself was wounded. Finally he penetrated to the
      innermost cell and found his son, to whom he offered freedom and safety on condition that he would
      go away (preserving however absolute silence as to his identity and history) and never return. The
      son, not recognising his father in his disguise, refused to give this pledge, as he said that he
      was bound by the promise which he had already made to his mother on her death-bed that he would
      return to the capital and claim his inheritance. Ursa implored him to go, to go under any
      conditions or no conditions, but in any case to escape while still there was time.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Something caused his son to suspect the identity of his visitor, so he tore away the disguise from
      his father's face and recognised him. Just at this moment Hesperia arrived; she had found the
      murdered guard and had possessed herself of his dagger, but had been detained through having to
      parley with third guard, who would not let her pass until she unveiled herself and used her
      authority as Queen. Now she sprang upon her husband like a maniac; and there was a terrible
      struggle, during which both father and son were wounded. Eventually, when she saw that she could
      not prevail against them, she stabbed herself to the heart in her wild passion.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Father and son now held a consultation as to the best course to pursue. At first the father
      suggested that they should escape together and leave the kingdom to take care of itself, but Sirius
      strenuously opposed that idea, offering rather to disappear and disregard his promise to his
      mother. But Ursa would not now consent to that, and they discussed the matter all through the long
      hours of the night. Sirius suggested that at Ursa's death the kingdom should be divided between
      himself and Pollux, or, if that was not feasible, that a high post in the Government should be
      offered to the latter. Ursa did not approve this, and finally decided that honesty was the best
      policy, and that the time had come to undo the wrong of his life so far as was now possible.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      They went back to the palace together, and Ursa sent for Pollux and told him the whole story,
      saying that he must give up all hope of succeeding to the throne. Pollux took the news badly, and
      rushed out of his father's presence in a great rage.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Ursa then called together his chieftains, told them the whole history of his life, and introduced
      to them the true heir to the throne. The majority of them at once agreed to accept Sirius as heir,
      in spite of the irregularity of his birth, and thenceforward he wore the golden collar which marked
      his rank. Pollux, however, left the country and endeavored to get together a foreign army to help
      him to assert what he supposed to be his claim. He was unable to raise this army among small
      neighboring tribes, and so went off to Poseidonis and tried to interest the Toltec ruler in his
      affairs. Corona was quite willing to espouse his cause because of the question of the tribute, and
      also because Ursa had recently defeated his armies, though he was unable to give much active
      assistance in consequence of a considerable rebellion in another part of his dominions.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Meantime Sirius, having been publicly acknowledged, was able to come before Mercury and tell the
      true story of his early life, and demand once more the hand of Alcyone. Under these altered
      circumstances Mercury was quite willing to give it, saying that though the conditions surrounding
      the birth of Sirius had been exceedingly irregular, yet his public acceptance as heir to the throne
      to a large extent wiped out all that and assured his position. There is no doubt the priest had
      taken a liking to the young man, and that it was this and the strong love of Sirius for Alcyone
      that induced him to be ready to overlook the irregularities aforesaid. Alcyone therefore was
      married with considerable pomp and ceremony, and, though still young, took her place among the
      great ladies of the kingdom. She was intensely happy in this beginning of her new life, proud of
      her husband and really exulting in his most remarkable early history instead of being repelled by
      it. this unalloyed happiness lasted for some three years, during which time two beautiful children
      (Uranus, a son, and Herakles, a daughter) were born to her, but after this the war broke out again
      and her husband had to go forth and bear his share in it.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It seemed, however, that the Toltec Emperor was not pursuing this local war with any great vigour,
      so that in spite of the superior discipline of his men, and their far great number, successes were
      fairly evenly divided, and the war dragged on for a long time with no pronounced victory on either
      side. King Ursa was in the habit of consulting Mercury when he required advice, and paid him deep
      reverence. It was about this time that Mercury gave him some information with regard to his
      relations with his son Sirius in a previous life an account which affected him deeply, and caused
      him to have a great scene of explanation with his son, at the end of which he decided to abdicate
      in favour of Sirius, and retired to a kind of hermit life.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Sirius took up the reins of government and, young as he was, acquitted himself creditably, coming
      often to his hermit-father, and still more often to Mercury, for advice as to the way in which he
      should meet the various difficulties which are inseparable from such a position as his. Alcyone was
      thus lifted to the highest position in this small State, and bore her honours well. The new King
      carried on the war with varying success, and at one time had an exceedingly narrow escape of losing
      his life by treachery. There was at his court a certain old woman, Thetis, who pretended great
      loyalty to his cause, but was in reality on the side of his half-brother, on whose behalf the
      Toltec Emperor was waging war. She contrived in some underhand way to learn something of the King's
      plans, and especially of a certain small expedition which he was about to lead in order to obtain
      important information as to the disposition of the Toltec armies. This woman was able to betray
      this little expedition to the Toltecs, in order that they might arrange an ambuscade, and so, as
      she thought, make sure of the death of the King.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Her nefarious project was defeated only by a dream or inspiration which came to the hermit-father,
      in consequence of which he left his cave, and met his son the King while on his way with his
      expedition, and demanded to be allowed to lead thee party himself. His son expostulated, saying
      that it was madness for his father at his age to expose himself to such risks. Ursa however
      insisted, and Sirius was at last compelled to yield. The old royal hermit therefore led the
      expedition, and contrived to obtain the necessary information and send back a messenger with it
      before he fell into the ambuscade which had been prepared for his son, and was killed. In this way
      the life of Sirius was saved, but he mourned greatly for the death of his father, all the more
      since Mercury by some intuition was able to tell him that his father had, through his dream, known
      of the danger, and had therefore voluntarily resigned his own life in order to deliver his son.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This event produced a profound impression upon both Sirius and Alcyone, and the former went to
      consult Mercury as to what line of action he should take. Mercury's advice was that, since not only
      was the country being devastated by this incessant warfare, but also anything like real progress
      for the people was impossible while such conditions persisted, he should make a determined effort
      to come to terms with the Toltec Emperor, even though for that purpose it might be necessary to
      offer some compromise, such as the payment of a largely enhanced tribute. By good fortune, Sirius
      was able shortly afterwards to inflict a crushing defeat upon the Toltec army, and to drive its
      remnants out of his kingdom. As soon as this had been done, he at once sent an embassy to the
      Toltec Emperor announcing that although the victory was at present entirely in his hands, he yet
      desired peace and not further war, and to save bloodshed he desired to come to an amicable
      arrangement. The Emperor, tired of an unprofitable war in a distant part of his kingdom, was more
      reasonable than might have been expected, and so, by the payment of only a slightly enhanced
      tribute from the revenues, Sirius was enabled to disband his armies, and devote them to much needed
      works of peace.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone was a real helpmate to her husband in all this, being full of plans for the amelioration of
      the condition of the people. A time of peace and prosperity now began both for the King and the
      country. Several more children were born to the King and Queen and they were happy in their
      domestic life together. Another of our list of characters appears here Cygnus, who steward of some
      large States belonging to Sirius, whom he served faithfully in that capacity for many years.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The other claimant to the throne, Pollux, the half-brother of the King, though his case was
      abandoned by the Toltec Emperor, did not cease to plot in order to gain the throne. His chief
      endeavor was to assassinate Sirius, and twice he all but succeeded. On the second of these occasion
      it was really Alcyone who saved her husband's life, for she had a vivid dream which induced her to
      send to him with the greatest haste as he sat in judgement, warning him that an attack on him was
      about to be made. Her dream or forecast described the man who was about to make the murderous
      attack with such accuracy that the king was instantly able to recognise him when he came before
      him, and immediately ordered his guards to seize and examine him. The weapon with which it had been
      his intention to murder the King was found upon him, and as he was not able to account for its
      possession his shrift was a short one.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Under the King's intelligence rule, and with the peace which he had procured for it, the kingdom
      rapidly advanced in power and wealth. Again at the suggestion of Mercury, now drawing to extreme
      old age, Sirius sent for his half-brother, and endeavoured to come to some sort of arrangement with
      him. He told him quite plainly that he regarded the kingdom as a charge committed to his care, and
      that he could not therefore yield it to anyone else, but he offered him the governorship of a
      certain division of the country under himself. The claimant, however declined to accept this, and
      said that he would be satisfied with nothing less than the whole. However, in the course of
      interviews which he had had with Sirius, this half-brother had fallen in love with Alcyone, and for
      the purpose of being near her he presently offered to accept the governorship, not of a distant
      province, but of the capital city. This Sirius willingly gave him.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      When Mercury heard of this arrangement he warned Sirius not to place too great a confidence in the
      apparent friendliness of his half-brother. A time came when Pollux took advantage of his new
      position to make improper advanced to Alcyone, which she promptly rejected, yet she doubted whether
      she should expose him to her husband because of the fact that the latter was greatly pleased to
      have (as he thought) thus extinguished the lifelong enmity of his half-brother. As the young man
      promised amendment she hid the matter for a while, but presently his passions once more got the
      better of him and a scene occurred which it was impossible to hide from Sirius, the latter was
      exceedingly angry, and deposed his brother and cast him into prison, where he shortly afterwards
      died.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      At this period a great sorrow came both to Sirius and Alcyone in the death of their revered father
      and teacher, Mercury, at a very advanced age. They mourned sincerely over his loss, and indeed they
      might well do so, for no similarly sage counsellor was forthcoming after he had gone. Meanwhile the
      Toltec Emperor also had died, and his successor, Ulysses, presently determined upon an aggressive
      policy, his idea being definitely to reduce the whole of the island to a direct obedience to
      himself, instead of his being merely the nominal suzerain over a number of Kings of the earlier
      sub-races. After a great deal of effort to make the whole into one kingdom, but the Tlavatli
      mountaineers could not brook the loss of their liberty, and constant outbreaks were the result, and
      plots and counterplots. Sirius was killed in battle in the effort to save the liberty of his
      country, in the year 13,000.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone was filled with deepest sorrow, and allowed herself to harbour bitter thoughts of revenge
      against the new Toltec Emperor. This misfortune seemed for the time quite to change her character,
      and the gentle and loving wife became a determined and relentless avenger, filled entirely with one
      idea. She dressed herself in her husband's armour, put herself at the head of what remained of her
      people and fled to the recesses of the mountains, since the Toltec armies had overrun the whole
      country. Her husband's steward, Cygnus, who had always greatly admired her, became one of the
      foremost of her band of warriors, and distinguished himself greatly. She directed a guerrilla
      warfare for some years, enduring the greatest hardships, but never for a moment swerving from her
      purpose. She was unable, with her handful of mountaineers, to meet the Toltecs in open fight, but
      she constantly harassed them and, owing to the intimate knowledge which she gained of the
      fastnessees of the mountain-chain, she was always able to elude all attempts to capture her.
      Meanwhile, she never wavered in her hatred of the Emperor, whose ambition had caused the death of
      her beloved husband.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      She caused her sons to take an oath never to rest until that Emperor and his power should be
      destroyed, and she sent one of them (Aurora) in disguise to the City of the Golden Gate to
      endeavour to compass this destruction. After many adventures the young man reached that city, and
      soon contrived to attach himself to some of the many disaffected parties, and when the opportunity
      offered he was one of the party who fell upon the Emperor and slew him. He hurried to his mother
      with the news of the downfall of the tyrant, proudly exhibiting to her the dagger with which the
      deed had been done. She welcomed him with praise as the avenger of his father, yet even in the very
      act a doubt for the first time came across her mind as to whether her dead husband and her dead
      father would fully have approved her action.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The doubt grew and increased until it became a nightmare to her, and she commenced a kind of
      invocation to her dead husband, declaring that she would not cease to call for him until he should
      tell her what was his will. For days and nights she continued this strange invocation until at last
      she fell asleep in sheer exhaustion; then in her dream she saw Sirius once more. Sirius and Mercury
      came to her together, and they told her that, while by all the standards of the time her act of
      revenge had been allowable and even laudable, there was yet a higher standpoint from which all
      revenge was not only wrong but presumptuous as an interference with the devine prerogative of the
      Law.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      My daughter, said Mercury, in this you have erred, though well I understand the reason for your
      error. Your excuse seemed to you a sufficient one, yet no excuse can ever make wrong right, nor
      violence justifiable, and this act of yours will bring much suffering in the future, both to you
      and the devoted instrument whom you have employed; but through suffering wisdom shall come to you,
      and in the far future your hand shall lead to the light him whose career of sin you have now cut
      short, and in that future I shall help and direct you both as I have done in this life.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone, though grieved at the disapproval of her father, was yet greatly comforted in many ways by
      this vision, for she had once more met face to face those whom in all the world she had loved most
      deeply. Once more she became herself again. She retained her man's attire only long enough to
      install her eldest son Uranus upon the throne of his father, and then cast it aside for ever, and
      became the gentle and loving Alcyone of earlier days.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Now that the tyrant was dead, his kingdom at once broke up into its original parts, and no further
      attack was made upon the tribes of the southern mountains. The new King Uranus ruled well and
      wisely, for the Queen-mother Alcyone was ever at his back, thinking always what Sirius would have
      done, and what Mercury would have advised. For some considerable time they did still advise her,
      though she was but half conscious of the fact; yet often it was to their influence that she owed
      the wisdom of the decisions which she made, or rather influenced the King to make.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Though she herself had now come to regard the period of her revenge with regret and distaste, and
      indeed to look upon it with wonder as a kind of obsession, the people applauded it, and regarded it
      as the most splendid heroism. She was therefore greatly reverenced and admired, and her influence
      was in many ways even greater than that of the King himself. She survived her husband for some
      thirty years, and eventually passed peacefully away in the year 13,569, at the age of eighty-two,
      deeply loved and mourned by the whole nation and by the many children whom she had reared so well,
      except fot that one dark time when the shock of a great sorrow had led her to deviate from the
      teaching of the law of love. Her son the King survived her for some years and, remembering her
      instruction, ruled well and wisely, and as the Toltec power never regained sufficient strength to
      reassert itself in the southern mountains, the dynasty which was thus founded lasted for centuries,
      and her tribe flourished exceedingly.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This life was on the whole a good one, and in it considerable progress was made, in spite of that
      one lapse, under terrible provocation, into the fault which had been the dominant note of a
      previous life. But at least we may note that this time the feeling of revenge was excited no longer
      on merely personal grounds, but solely by the injury to a loved one. As we shall presently see,
      there are lives lying yet far in the future in which all thought of revenge shall be cast aside
      under the influence of the great Embodiment of Love and Compassion.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Her eldest daughter, Herakles, married Aldeb, and this transferred her interests to another kingdom
      of the same general type and condition, also Tlavatli. In course of time her husband inherited the
      throne of this kingdom, so that she also became a Queen. She had a great reputation for wisdom, and
      was at times under the control of some good influence, for her husband often consulted her on
      points about which he was in doubt, which she certainly answered with more than her own knowledge.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Mizar married Irene an event which took place much later than any of the other marriages. When her
      mother grew old she and her husband came and lived at the old home, and she took charge of the
      household. Vajra left home early, and seemed to have traveled a good deal, and he stayed a long
      time with Aldeb and Herakles. He was decidedly adventurous, and undertook several exploring
      expeditions into the neighbouring mountains. Demeter was rather sensitive, though not distinctly
      psychic. Neptune, a man with a good deal of affection which he always placed wisely, married Bella.
      Selene led a quiet life and studious life.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"/>
  </text>
</body>