<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 42
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 42-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      We come now to a set of four lives, three of which were spent in India, which were devoted entirely
      to the working out of past karma. The Great Ones, though usually in the neighbourhood, took a less
      prominent part in these than in the earlier lives. In a general way I think we may regard these
      four principally as a preparation for the four which followed them.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone was born this time in the year 4970, as the daughter of an old and noble house, in a small
      kingdom called Tirganga, which was under the suzerainty of protection of the Maharaja of much
      larger district called Sravasthi. Alcyone's name was Manidevi. Her horoscope foretold that she
      would suffer much, and also said that she would be the mother of a king. As a child she was boyish
      and impulsive. Her education seems to have been limited in scope, and included little but reading
      and writing and the recitation of innumerable texts; though she also learnt weaving and cooking and
      housewifely duties of various sorts, as well as the science of herbs and of compounding unguents
      and salves for wounds, and indeed medicines generally.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      She did not at all wish to be married, but her desires were little consulted; when her father and
      mother saw in this at least a possible step in the direction of the fulfilment of the prophesy, and
      when a fine son (Helios) was born to her she naturally had her hopes, though it did not seem likely
      that he could come into the line of inheritance.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      After some years a daughter, Rigel, was born, and then a second son Hector; and soon after that her
      husband died, and her hopes therefore much diminished. From the outer-world point of view this
      practically made the fulfilment of the forecast impossible, but she still cherished in her heart
      the feeling that somehow the Gods would carry out their decree, and so she tried to train her
      handsome son in riding and swordsmanship, and everything that would make him a striking and
      suitable figure in the popular eye.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Presently the old Raja, Cetus, who had seemed likely to live on indefinitely died suddenly, and the
      son, Cancer, who succeeded him proved to be weak and inefficient ruler. His wife, Alastor, the new
      Queen, was a scheming and ambitious person, and having no son herself, she looked with an evil eye
      on Alcyone's handsome boy as a possible claimant in the future. Alcyone had to keep very quiet, for
      Alastor was suspicious and unscrupulous, and only sought for some pretext to harm her. Her hopes,
      however, had again risen; for although at any time the present Raja, who was still a young man,
      might have a son, he seemed no stronger in health than he was in will, and neither he nor the Queen
      was popular; so she thought that, in some turn of the strange kaleidoscope of an Indian court, some
      opening for her own boy might presently appear.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      When her son was eighteen, however, all these hopes were dashed to the ground in an entirely
      unexpected manner. She was a religious woman, and when Herakles, a holy man of great reputation in
      the country, was passing through the town, she eagerly offered herself for the privilege of
      entertaining him. He stayed with her for some weeks, and she felt deep affection and reverence for
      him; and the nobility of his life and the beauty of his teaching appealed so strongly to her son
      Helios that he begged the holy man to accept him as a pupil, and his mother to allow him to go.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      A great struggle took place within her; for this would mean the entire sacrifice of the one great
      dream of her life. And yet, on the other hand, she knew well that this was a high honour, for the
      holy man was willing to accept her son, saying that the boy would do well and would go far, and
      that he had links with him from a previous life. The sacrifice of all her affectionate ambitions
      was a great strain, but after many days at last she agreed; and Helios went with the holy man on
      his journey towards the hills. But having parted with him she shut herself up to mourn, and would
      not be comforted.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      After some days of this, the younger brother, Hector, at last resolved to break in upon her
      solitude, telling her that though his brother was gone it was to a higher and grander life, and
      that he himself was still left and would endeavour to take his place. She had never thought of him
      in that way, though always kind and loving towards him; she had been so entirely engrossed in the
      elder brother and the prophesy, that she had thought of Hector only as a little boy.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alastor maliciously rejoiced when she heard that the handsome son had adopted the ascetic life.
      About this period she determined that it was quite imperative that she should have a son, so she
      contrived a plot by which she presented Scorpio, the illegitimate son of Hesperia, one of the
      servants, as her own, bribing the real mother to silence. This required an elaborate and
      complicated plot, and although it was undeservedly successful, she was never free thereafter from
      devouring anxiety and suspicion. Now that she had thus provided a pretended heir for herself, she
      seemed more than ever desirous to remove by any means all possible rivals. Still uneasy about
      Alcyone , she made various plots against her, and especially made an effort to murder her second
      son. Hector, by night by her own hand; but through a mistake she stabbed the daughter Rigel
      instead, and escaped without being recognised. Though Alcyone suspected her.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This attempt having failed, Alastor brought an accusation of plotting against Alcyone, and
      contrived to manufacture sufficient evidence to get her driven away from the city with her son.
      Alcyone knew that not only her present misfortunes, but also the death of her daughter, were
      directly attributable to Alastor , and therefore felt great resentment against her directly
      attributable to Alastor, and therefore felt great resentment against her, and vowed in a moment of
      anger to be revenged upon her some day. Being exiled in this way she lived in great poverty in a
      neighbouring State, earning a living for herself and her son by making and selling sweet-meats.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Some years passed in this way, Alcyone all the while harbouring bitter feelings against Alastor.
      Cancer presently died, and his wife succeeded in getting her pretended son crowned, but he proved
      dissolute and unmanageable. Among other evil deeds he outraged a girl, Thetis, who was his own
      sister, though he did not know it. His real mother, Hesperia, in anger betrayed his origin. The
      queen-dowager, of course, denied it, and had Hesperia poisoned, but the rumour had spread and found
      general acceptance.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      There was much murmuring and rebellion among the people, and the story eventually reached the ears
      of Mars, the Suzerain at Sravasthi, who came down in person to investigate the case and found ample
      proof of the charge, whereupon he deposed the servant's son Scorpio, and caused enquiry to be made
      for Alcyone. After some trouble she was found, and her son Hector placed upon the throne, it became
      her duty to look after and advise him, and she rose nobly to the emergency, making determined
      efforts to check the impulsiveness of her former life, and to be always patient and gentle with
      him. For sometime she practically governed the little State wisely and well, and by admirable
      prudence and restraint she made it happy and flourishing.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      There was, however, a strong party of the supporters of the previous corrupt court who, having been
      dispossessed, were inwardly disloyal to the new regime, and opposed her effort to do justice
      whenever they dared. Presently the young King married Regulus, but his wife did not prove
      satisfactory. She had much personal ambition, and was jealous of the influence of his mother over
      him, so that she worked against Alcyone, and tried to undermine her power and to inveigle the young
      King into taking action which his mother disapproved. For some years this unsatisfactory condition
      of affairs went on, the new Queen trying to make a party of her own.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Eventually she had a long and serious illness, following upon the birth of one of her children.
      Alcyone nursed her through this, and took such unremitting care of her little children that Regulus
      began to see her true character, and came to love her. After her recovery, therefore, she entirely
      withdrew her old opposition, and everything worked much more smoothly. The Queen-dowager, Alastor,
      the supposed mother of the deposed King, who had been sent away into exile, returned secretly and
      stirred up a plot to restore that unworthy pretended son. She was however detected, taken prisoner
      and brought before the Raja, who then sent for his mother, and said:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Here is your ancient enemy, against whom you vowed vengeance for the death of my sister. Now I give
      her to you. What will you do with her?
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      But the defeated plotter looked so abject that Alcyone could not retain her anger against her, so
      she said:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Her misery and failure are punishment enough. I forgive her. Let her go.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      But the woman came immediately afterwards and asked to see her, and threw herself at her feet, and
      wept over all the evil that she had done, saying:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Now I die, for when I heard that I was to be delivered into your hands I at once took poison,
      feeling that you could not forgive me, but would torture me for all that I had done made you suffer.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      No, said Alcyone; since you have thus repented you shall not die, and she sent for her own court
      physician and asked what antidote there was for this poison. They administered it, and though
      Alastor was already deeply under the influence of the drug which she had taken, by long and careful
      nursing they succeeded in saving her life. She afterwards devoted herself to an ascetic existence
      of meditation and works of charity, to atone for her previous evil deeds.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Herakles, now grown rather old and feeble, arrived one day at Tiraganga, and brought terrible news
      to Alcyone, the news of the death of her eldest son the son whom, in her heart, she had always
      loved the best. Herakles told her, with unaffected sorrow, how he had loved the young man, of the
      swift progress the latter had made along the line of inner development, and how at last he had died
      heroically, defending his master from the attack of a party of robbers. Even though Alcyone had
      long ago made up her mind to give up her son, the news of his death was a great shock to her, and
      caused her deep grief, but Herakles comforted her by reciting again and again the praises of his
      nobility of life, his courage and his devotion, and explained the good karma that such a life and
      such a death could not but make for his own future advancement.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Herakles had half-doubted whether the sad news that he brought would not make him an unwelcome
      guest to Alcyone; but instead of that she was more strongly drawn to him than ever, and begged him
      to make his home in Tiraganga, persuading her son the raja to provide for him such modest
      establishment as he was willing to accept though indeed he needed little persuasion, for he himself
      also felt deep reverence for him. Alcyone herself visited him daily and learnt much from him,
      trusting much to his advice in the education of her grandchildren, to whom she principally devoted
      the closing years of her life. The king and Queen fully recognised how much they owed to her loving
      care and prudent management, so that the concluding years of her life were passed in calm
      happiness, and she was regarded by all with great reverence and affectionate gratitude. She finally
      passed away peacefully in the cold weather of the year 4901, at the age of sixty-nine.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
