<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 8
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 8-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone's next birth, which took place more than eight hundred years later, may be regarded as in
      many respects a continuation of the last. The Band of Servers came again into the same valley, to
      carry to on the development of the same rub-race, now thoroughly well settled and become a
      recognised subsidiary nation. This was not one of the occasions on which the Manu Himself thought
      it necessary to be in incarnation, but His pupil Jupiter was ruling the valley on His behalf, and
      Alcyone appears as his eldest son. He was, as usual in these early times, surrounded by some of
      those egos who seem to be most closely related to him, for we find as his brothers Mizar, Herakles,
      Selene and Sirius, as his sisters Neptune and Venus; he marries Electra, his sons are Apollo,
      Fides, Vulcan and Aquila, and his daughters Brihat, Euphora and Quies.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It seems evident that these groupings are not in any way matters of chance, but are carefully
      arranged as part of a definite plan, in which the close physical association of the
      semi-patriarchal family life of those times was utilised to attain the required results, just as in
      the present day of semi-detached families quite other means are used, and advantage is taken of the
      mental association of societies or clubs of various kinds. That the methods employed have been
      effective is shown by the case of Alcyone. Of the group just mentioned only one was in this present
      twentieth-century life into physical relationship with him, yet every member of it, on meeting him
      for what was then supposed to be the first time, instantly recognized the spiritual relationship
      which means so much more than any earthly tie. Many others than these belong to his group, but we
      give these as an example of what is meant. And what is true of Alcyone and his immediate and
      closest circles is also true of other groups or subdivisions of the clan of Servers, and to
      somewhat less extent of the clan as a whole. Forty or fifty lives ago we find Alcyone engaged in
      riveting these special links of which we have just spoken; later we shall find him meeting these
      people frequently, it is true, but still somewhat less closely associated with them, because he is
      then engaged in forming certain other links making efforts the results of which are perhaps still
      in the future.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      As the real object of the incarnations is the formation of these links, so that the members of the
      clan may learn to understand and trust one another, and thus gradually become a pliable, reliable,
      intelligent unit that can be employed by the great ones as an instrument, it is obvious that we
      cannot measure the importance of any life by the superficial incidents which are all that we can
      describe in our series of stories. Picturesque occurrences may sometimes offer opportunity for
      heroical effort, and so may suddenly crystallize into visibility the result of long, slow interior
      growth; but a life barren of adventure may yet be fruitful in quiet development of necessary
      qualities. Of such a nature was this eight life of our series a life happy, industrious,
      unsensational pleasantly, placidly progressive.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In his boyhood he met with a slight accident that might easily have had fatal consequences, but he
      fortunately escaped from it unhurt, though it was not without its effect on the direction of his
      studies and interests in later life. As a boy he was fond of being alone; and he often climbed the
      rocks at the back of his father's house, and wandered off upon solitary expeditions among the
      hills. On one of these when he was about twelve years old he came upon a pretty little dell which
      he did not remember to have seen before, and ran down to explore it. At one place an unusual
      appearance in the rock attracted his attention, and he jumped down into a small hollow to examine
      it more closely. To his great surprise the ground gave way beneath him, and he had the sensation of
      a considerable fall and a shock, and found himself in dark.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He could not imagine what had happened, and he was very much startled and a good deal frightened.
      He was lying upon something soft something which felt like vegetation, which had evidently broken
      his fall and he understood that he must somehow have dropped into a sort of cave; but he could not
      at all comprehend why he could see nothing of the hole through which he must have fallen, and why
      he found himself in utter darkness. The shock had dazed him for a few moments, but as soon as he
      recovered he stood up and stretched his hands all round, but felt nothing. A few cautious steps
      brought him to a smooth wall, along which he felt for some distance, but it seemed to continue in a
      straight line indefinitely. He was completely puzzled as to his situation, and decidedly
      uncomfortable about it; but he reasoned that as he had somehow fallen down into this place, his
      best plan would be to try to climb out of it by the same way, if he could only find it. So he felt
      his way back along the wall until he thought he reached about the place where he originally came
      into touch with it, and after two or three trials he stumbled over the vegetation among which he
      had fallen. Standing there, he looked upwards, but could not see anything; he stretched his hand
      up, but touched nothing. Then he leapt upwards as high as he could, but found only blank space. He
      certainly had somehow fallen in at that point, and he could not understand why there was no trace
      of the hole through which he must have come.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      No theory which he could formulate would explain the facts, and he began to suspect some
      supernatural interference, and to wonder whether he had been entrapped by some weird denizens of
      the underworld, who could see in the dark. An unpleasant suggestion, which he hurriedly rejected;
      and he decided that as it seemed to be impossible to get up he might well move along the wall as
      before, so as at least to discover the dimensions of his prison. He was not sure of his direction,
      and for some time he could not find the wall, and when at last he did touch it he came upon it
      obliquely instead of at right angles as before. He wondered whether it was the same wall, or
      whether he had reached the other side of his dungeon; but as he moved along it he found that it had
      the same characteristic of apparently indefinite extension. He had been in caves before many of
      them; but none in the least like this. The extraordinary smoothness of both the wall and the floor
      impressed him, as well as the amazing size of the place. He walked -------with his hand upon the
      wall cautiously indeed , for he knew that in caves one often came suddenly upon holes, and even
      pits of great deapth but here the floor seemed as smooth as a pavement, and the idea crosses itself
      into his mind that this must be an artificial excavation. But he had never heard of any such thing.
      Besides, he knew that a cave of any size is usually of corresponding height, which this could not
      be because of the small distance that he had fallen; and he knew that he had been walking beside
      that wall long enough to have crossed half of the great city itself; and how could any cave be of
      such dimensions as that ?
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The affair was a hopeless riddle; but at least he could do nothing but keep moving, though he was
      beginning to be oppressed by fears that there was something uncanny in the business, and that this
      nightmare of walking in the darkness would never end. Indeed, at one time he seriously entertained
      the idea that he might have been killed by the fall without knowing it, and was now wandering in
      some strange underworld of the dead ! Still, there were difficulties in the way of that theory, and
      meantime he was growing physically tired, which seemed to show that he was still in the body. On
      and on he went, and his pace grew insensibly faster, for he learnt to trust the unvarying
      smoothness of the floor, and stepped out almost as briskly as if he were in the light, though
      always keeping one hand on the wall beside him, and the other stretched out in front, in case this
      amazing excavation should come to an end at last. But all the while two things daunted him the
      intensity of the darkness and the silence. In a dark room on earth there is generally some ray of
      half light, some diminution of the blackness; but here it was so absolute, so uncompromising that
      it seemed to fold about him like a pall. Then the silence again; it was not the relative silence of
      the upper world, but an absolute silence that seemed unearthly in its finality. And then the utter
      incomprehensibility of the whole business; perhaps it was better not to think; but just
      mechanically to push on.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      A hard trial for a boy of twelve; but fortunately even then he was already determined and
      persevering. So he pushed on steadily and tried to feel his mind a blank, even when he felt as
      though time must have ended and eternity begun. And then suddenly in front of him appeared a point
      of light like a star so suddenly that he uttered an exclamation.He could not tell how far from him
      it was that tiny spot of intense light, but he forgot his fatigue and hurried forward towards it,
      only then realising, by the magnitude of his relief, how near to hopelessness had been before. For
      a long time it seemed no nearer, for all his hurried walk; but at long last he saw that it was
      larger that instead of being a point it was a hole. After yet another spell of walking the darkness
      began to grow less intense, and presently through the gloom he discovered another wall running
      parallel to his, and a little later a roof, perhaps six feet above his head; so that he realized
      that he must have walking for miles along an unquestionably artificial tunnel, and he began to hope
      that the point of light in front might prove to be the mouth of it.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      So, quite simply, it did; and presently he found himself out in the blessed sunlight once more, and
      for a few minutes quite blinded by it. The tunnel debauched into a cuplike hollow on a lonely
      hillside which Alcyone had never seen before, and he had no idea where he was, though that troubled
      him little now he had escaped from the horror of the dark. Before leaving that strange subterranean
      passage, he turned to examine it more carefully, and his eye confirmed what his hands had long ago
      told him the wonderful smoothness of the walls and the floor. But his sense of touch had not been
      able to inform him that the walls of this tunnel were profusely decorated with drawings, by no
      means badly executed in a rough but foreseeable style. These drawings, extended inwards as far as
      the light from the entrance permitted him to see; he promised himself to return and investigate
      more fully later, but at the height of the sun in the sky, he calculated that he could not have
      been more than three hours in the darkness, though it had seemed whole days; and he resolved to
      climb to the top of the hill in the hope of determining his whereabouts, the matter needed some
      consideration, for though he recognized the outline of certain peaks, he was regarding them from
      quite a new point of view; and it was some time before he realized that he had come through the
      heart of a mountain, and that to get back he would have to make his way either over it or round it.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Now that he had time to think of it he found that he was hungry, but unfortunately the mountain
      side provided nothing edible, so he had to push on as well as he could. After some climb he came to
      a stream and drank, which greatly refreshed him, for in the tunnel there had been a fine, almost
      impalpable, dust which made him very thirsty. When he gained the shoulder of the hill, he wanted to
      see his way back to his valley, but he had to walk fully two miles, so that it was late evening
      before he reached home, and his father had begun to feel anxious about him.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      His tale of adventure keenly interested his father, and next day they went together to the scene of
      the accident taking with the several men, with a rope and some torches. Alcyone had little
      difficulty in finding again the valley in which, as he put it, the earth seemed to open and swallow
      him, but the curious appearance in the rock which had originally attracted his attention was no
      longer visible. What he had noticed was a crack about four feet long and a few inches wide, with
      sharply defined edges, and when he had leapt down to examine it more closely he had a vague
      impression that he must have somehow fallen through it, impossible though that seemed. But no such
      crack was now visible, and his father thought that he had not found the right spot, while Alcyone
      felt quite sure that he had, but could not explain the change.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Presently he saw an oddly rectangular depression in the rock, and going to look at it more closely,
      found that the apparently solid rock yielded when he set his foot upon it. For a moment he saw his
      crack of yesterday, and then as he drew back it again disappeared. He was much startled, but a
      shout brought his father to the spot, and they proceeded to make a cautious investigation. They
      soon found that there was a square of rock a sort of flagstone which yielded when pressure was
      brought to bear upon it, and opened downwards like a trap door, swinging back into its place as the
      pressure was withdrawn. Further examination showed that it was worked by a simple but ingenious
      counterweight, and that it closed against a deep overlapping rim which prevented the faintest gleam
      of light from penetrating. It was evident that in some way a fragment of rock had been caught in
      the opening of this trap door, and had prevented it from closing completely. Through the crack thus
      left open who shall say for how many years? light and rain penetrated , and as a result a thin
      cushion of giant moss had grown directly under the trap-door, and had broken Alcyone's fall. As he
      sped upon the slab it had yielded under his weight; the fragment of rock had fallen, and so the
      door swung back perfectly into its place to completely shut out the light.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      But what could have been the purpose of so strange an arrangement, and who could have made it? And
      what prehistoric race could have built a tunnel six miles long through hard rock, and why? To
      answer these natural questions further explorations were necessary; so by the aid of the rope which
      they had brought, Jupiter and Alcyone, with some of their men, descended into the passage and
      lighted their torches. At this point also the walls were found to be covered with drawings, so they
      at first supposed that they were thus ornamented through the whole length of the passage; but it
      was afterwards ascertained that the pictures were in groups, with long blank intervals, rendering
      it probable that they fulfilled a function roughly resembling that of the Stations of the Cross in
      a catholic church. As the tunnel extended in both directions, they might see what was at the other
      end of this extraordinary excavation.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      With their torches they could move forward rapidly, and they soon came to a point where the passage
      divided , or rather where another and much wider passage left it at right angles. Attracted by the
      appearance of this wider passage they turned along it, and found that it led them to a large hall,
      which from its arrangement had obviously been uses as a temple. At the end of it was a roughly-hewn
      statue of colossal size and forbidding appearance, and in front of it a platform which could hardly
      be anything but an alter, though not of the usual shape. The walls of this temple were covered with
      drawings, some of them intended to represent dances and orgies, probably of questionable character.
      Climbing upon the alter, Alcyone narrowly escaped falling thorough another trap-door constructed
      exactly in the same way as that which had introduced him to this subterranean system.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Holding back this trap door and putting their torches through it, they were unable to see a plain
      square room, into which Alcyone of course begged to be allowed to descend. They lowered him into
      it, and Jupiter came after him, to find him examining a kind of stone trough or sarcophagus which
      occupied one side of the chambers empty now, but possibly once the tomb of some high priest of this
      forgotten religion which celebrated its mysteries thus in the bowels of the earth. At the end of
      the chamber were depressions in the wall by which it was possible to climb it, and on mounting
      these Alcyone found himself inside the great stone statue, and able to look out upon the temple
      through certain cunningly contrived holes. Probably this was an arrangement to enable the priest to
      speak oracles through the mouth of the goddess; but it seemed curious that the only discoverable
      entrance should be through a trap- door on the altar itself. Alcyone suggested that perhaps
      offerings placed upon it were made to drop through and disappear in token of their acceptance by
      the goddess; or that if they built a fire on their alter, the priest may have acquired a reputation
      by mysteriously disappearing amidst the smoke.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      As their supply of torches was rapidly diminishing, they judged it prudent to leave the temple, and
      when they regained the narrower passage they continued their walk along it, to see whither it led.
      After a time they came out, as Alcyone had done the day before, into a small cup- shaped
      depression, but in this case rocks and earth had slipped down and almost closed the entrance, so
      that they had some difficulty in pushing their way out. When they were able to look round them,
      they saw that they were quite near home on a sort of ledge in the face of a cliff overlooking their
      own valley. The place was now inaccessible from below, but from the appearance of the spot it
      seemed likely that a land-slip had occurred at some remote period, and that , before that, there
      might well have been an easy path to the mouth of the tunnel. But what race had done this work of
      excavation, and why they had thought it necessary to take such a stupendous amount of trouble these
      facts remained unexplained.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone was much interested in the place, feeling that he had a sort of proprietary right over it,
      because he had discovered it. He used to visit it frequently with his boy friends, one of whom,
      Albireo , made copies of all the drawings. They measured the passages, and made a plan of the whole
      excavation, and put together their drawings, plans and writings into a kind of book, which was
      forwarded to the King at Manoa, and kept in the great museum there. The drawings were evidently
      illustrative of the ceremonies to be performed at certain stages of the journey to the temple, and
      some of them were of a very remarkable character.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This curious accident had a considerable influence over Alcyone, turning his interest strongly in
      the direction of the study of prehistoric peoples and their religions and ceremonies. In connection
      with this he made friends with the curator of the museum at Manoa, and induced him to write to a
      similar official in the city of the Golden Gate at Poseidonis, sending a description of the
      excavation and the statue, and copies of some of the drawings, and asking whether others of the
      same kind were known. In due course came a reply from the chief guardian of the Atlantean museum to
      the effect that there were two places in Poseidonis where excavations of the same nature existed (
      plans and drawings of which were enclosed) and that they were relics of a curious secret cult of
      the Earth Goddess, supposed to have been practiced by one of the later Lemurian sub-races, and
      borrowed from them by the Rmoahal. The cult was credited with obscene rites and even with human
      sacrifice, but the Atlantean curator considered these charges unproved, and begged for a full set
      of copies of all the drawings in the newly-discovered excavations, hoping that they might throw
      some light upon his theories. Alcyone himself, young as he was, started a correspondence with the
      Atlantean scientist, and suggested the various theories which had occurred to him to account for
      what he had observed. Alcyone acquired a great deal of information from these learned letters from
      Atlantis, and he also studied carefully whatever could be learnt along archaeological lines in the
      museum of Manoa, so that while still quite young he was a recognised authority on these subjects.
      The instruction gained from the Poseidonian curator threw much light on the religion and habits of
      the ancient race which had made the excavations, but they never conclusively established the use of
      the trap door through which Alcyone first fell. A similar arrangement had been discovered in one of
      the Atlantean passages, but its opening was in the floor of a small temple built on the surface of
      the earth, whereas if any building had ever surrounded Alcyone's trap door, no traces remained of
      it. It may have been intended to trap the unwary, to get rid secretly of undesirable or unruly
      worshippers, or simply to enable some priest who knew the trick of it to acquire a reputation by
      mysterious disappearances. Nothing remained either in picture or tradition, which definitely
      explained the mystery.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone's close friends gathered round him in serried phalanx in this incarnation, as in so many
      others. Among his brothers were Mizar, Herakles, Sirius and Selene, and when he came of age he
      married Electra, the daughter of Corona and Viraj. His life was happy and useful, for he was
      surrounded by those whom he loved, and was keenly interested in the work which he had to do the
      government and improvement of the valley. He was in sole control of the valley after the passing of
      his father Jupiter, but before that he was incharge of a district which occupied most of his
      energies, and gave him very little time for his archaeological studies.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Among other functions Alcyone had to act as judge, and obtained a certain reputation for the acumen
      which he showed in difficult cases. One curious affair which came under our notice involved sons of
      our characters, and therefore may be of interest. There was in the chief city of the valley a man
      named Homara, who had acquired great wealth by trading and money lending, and had the reputation of
      being grasping and unscrupulous; in fact, though many made use of him in emergencies, few had a
      good word to say for him, and he was strongly suspected of blackmailing, though nothing had ever
      actually was proved against him. One night this man was murdered; his body was found in the road,
      the head being crushed in, as though by a succession of tremendous blows with a heavy cudgel. The
      road where the body lay was one of those running along the side of the valley and just underneath a
      terrace, so that all along one side of it was a high blank wall which was in reality the front of
      the terrace above, with houses and gardens coming to the edge of it; while on the other side of it
      was a row of houses, each standing in its own garden. Though the gates of these gardens opened from
      the road, it was only their backs which were visible from it, as all their principal rooms faced
      downhill across the valley for the sake of the view. Consequently though the street was in a
      populous residential quarter, and really had houses gardens continually on both sides, it was
      nevertheless comparatively lonely and very little overlooked. Thus the murder had not been
      witnessed, though it seemed certain that it had been committed early in the evening.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Homara's wife informed the police that her husband had left home at dark, saying that he had an
      appointment to meet Clio. Now Clio was heavily in debt to Homara, and the latter was pressing him
      for immediate payment which would have meant ruin to Clio; so here seemed a possible motive for the
      murder, and Clio was promptly arrested. He admitted having an appointment with the murdered man in
      the same street where his body was found, but stated that Homara had not kept it, and that after
      waiting for some hours at the rendezvous he had returned home. Various people came forward to bear
      testimony that while passing along the road they had seen Clio lurking about, and that he
      endeavored to avoid them; and two witnesses declared that they had also seen Clio's brother
      Theodorous loitering suspiciously in that same area. An order was therefore issued for his arrest,
      and it was elicited that he had a grudge against Homara on his own account, as the latter was in
      love with Taurus, whom Theodorous desired to marry; but as Homara had some kind of hold over her
      elder brother Stella, he was able to put obstacles in Theodorous' way.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Each of these two brothers , Clio and Theodorous, believed secretly that the other had committed
      the murder, and each credited the other with semi-unselfish motives; for Clio thought that
      Theodorous had done this thing to save the family from ruin, while Theodorous supposed that Clio
      had been principally influenced by a desire to secure the happiness of his younger brother. Thus
      each was animated with the idea of sacrificing himself to save the other, and consequently each
      confessed himself guilty, to the great perplexity of the judge. The natural suggestion was that the
      brothers had conspired together to remove the obstruction from their path, but both of them
      vehemently denied this, and all the testimony of those who had seen them agreed that they had not
      been together. Alcyone leaned to the theory that booth were guilty of the wish and intention to
      murder, but did not see his way to a decision as to which of them struck the fatal blow, especially
      as there was no evidence to show that either of them had been carrying a weapon capable of
      inflicting such injuries.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      At this stage of the proceedings Udor appeared before the judge, and asked to be allowed to depose.
      Permission being given, he said that he had wished to remain silent, but that his conscience would
      no longer allow him to do so; he could not let innocent men suffer for his action, so he felt bound
      to confess that it was he that had killed Homara; though he declared that the blow had been struck
      in self defense. His story was that he was hurrying along that inauspicious road late on the night
      in question, when a man wildly waving some kind of weapon rushed threateningly upon him. Startled
      at this unexpected and menacing apparition, he had struck out sharply with a thick stick which he
      was carrying; his assailant fell heavily, striking his head against the wall, and lay at his feet,
      apparently unconscious. Udor, unnerved by the suddenness of all this, did not stay for his
      recovery, but hastened home, hoping thereby to avoid being involved in any trouble. He declared
      that at the time he had no idea of the identity of the man whom he had struck; but when afterwards
      he heard that the body of Homara had been found, he supposed that this must be his opponent, and
      was horrified beyond words to find himself guilty of homicide, however unintentionally and even
      excusably. Still he had said nothing, hoping that the death of Homara would remain a mystery, but
      when he found that, from some incomprehensible accession of generosity or through some strange
      mistake, other men were taking upon themselves the blame of his action, he felt it his duty to come
      forward. He had not known Homara, and could offer no suggestion as to his reason for attacking him;
      at the time he had thought that the man must be mad. He was uncertain as to the part of the road
      where the incident took place but such impression as he had did not point to the spot where the
      body had been found, nor could he understand how such a blow as he had given could produce the
      results described.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone's curiosity and interest were keenly excited by this extraordinary crime, of which three
      separate persons confessed themselves guilty; he remanded the case, and himself went down to view
      the spot where the body had been found, wishing to form his own conclusions as to some points which
      had arisen. The first thing which he noticed was the existence of a ditch at the bottom of the
      lofty wall before mentioned; and he at once remarked that this disposed of Udor's story, for if a
      man had fallen so as to strike his head against the wall, his body could not have remained in a
      heap upon the pavement as described, but must have collapsed into the ditch. Inspecting that ditch,
      a large fragment of hewn stone attracted his attention, and he demanded that it should be lifted
      out and brought to him. On a closer examination the under side of it was seen to be stained by a
      dark fluid, evidently blood, and hair resembling that of the dead man was found adhering to it.
      Stopping back into the road and looking upward, he saw that there was a corresponding gap in the
      coping of the wall twenty feet above, and he immdiately demanded to know who lived in the house
      whose garden was directly above the spot where they stood. Being told that it was a man of the name
      of Nabha, he ordered that he should be brought before him, and enquired what he knew as to the
      fallen stone. Nabha hesitated for a while and at last seemed to make up his mind to speak out.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      I will tell you the whole truth, my lord, he said; it is I who killed Homara, and I do not regret
      it, for I believe I did well to rid the world of such a ruffian. Yet have I had no peace of mind
      since the deed was done, and perchance if I confess it openly I may find rest. This dead man, my
      lord, was an evil doer, without shame or remorse; because I had borrowed money from him and was in
      his power he had forced me to give up to him my daughter Suadhu, and under promise of a full
      quittance he carried her off to minister to his vile pleasures. Yet after this he made still
      further demands upon me, telling me that he still held documents which enabled him to seize my home
      and land. Hearing this, I became mad against him, and thought to go and slay him with my hands.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      That night as I walked in my garden cursing him and planning how I could be revenged upon him, I
      looked over into the street far below and there I saw the very man. I caught sight of his face as
      he passed close to a lamp, and I knew that the powers of evil had answered my prayer and had
      delivered him into my hand. I went and stood by the loose stone in the coping of my wall; and
      balanced it so that a touch would throw it down. Hurriedly I dropped over a small piece of stick,
      to determine the exact spot where the stone would drop, and when he was just about to step upon it
      I pressed the stone so that it fell. My calculation was correct; I saw him crushed to the earth,
      and I rejoiced, yet in a moment horror fell upon me like a cloak, and I became as one mad. I rushed
      out of the house. I made my way down into the street below, yet I could not look upon my handwork.
      Distraught I ran along the road, not knowing whither I went; I saw a man approaching me, and I
      thought he intended to stop me. I had a stick in my hand, though I did not know I had caught it up;
      I flourished it threateningly, and the stranger struck me down with a heavy blow. I suppose I lay
      unconscious for a time; when I recovered I was alone, and my head ached shrewdly, yet it seemed
      that my madness had left me, so I crept home and went to bed. The deed was a righteous deed and I
      would do it again; yet have I had no peace of mind since its commission.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone felt that in this fourth confession the truth had at last been told, but he sent to the
      house of the deceased Homara for the girl Suadhu, and heard her testimony, which fully confirmed
      what her father had said with regard to her. Then he called all the prisoners before him. Cleo and
      Theodorous he discharged, delivering to them a homily on the virtue of abstract truth, and
      explaining to them that falsehoods, even when unselfish, and dictated by affection, always hindered
      the cause of justice. Udor was also set free, the judge praising him for having come forward
      voluntarily to make in the cause of justice a statement so much against his own interest, in order
      to save others from the blame attached to a crime which they had already confessed, and saying that
      the credit due to him for his bravery was in no wise diminished by the fact that his statement had
      in fact been inaccurate, as the person against whose imagined attack he had defended himself was
      Nabha and not Homara. To Nabha he said:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      You have rid the world of a villain who unquestionably deserved to die, yet I must tell you that
      you were wrong in doing so, for in taking even such a man's life you have broken the beneficent law
      of our father the Manu, which ordains that all life is sacred, and that private revenge is
      inadmissible. You should have come to me and told me all, trusting to the justice and
      discrimination of your ruler, I will not give the ordinary sentence of banishment for life from the
      Empire of Manoa, because I think that in your case there were extenuating circumstances; but you
      must live for two years as a hermit upon the hills, so that you may have time by meditation to
      purge yourself from blood guiltiness and to quiet your perturbed spirit by the healing influences
      of nature."
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      So Alcyone lived his life quietly doing his duty to his people, absorbed always in plans for their
      welfare; and when he passed away, full of years and honor, he was succeeded in the government of
      the valley by his eldest son Aopllo, who endeavored to walk in his steps and to carry on his
      traditions.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
