<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 22
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 22-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Our hero's next life was a life of pilgrimage pilgrimage of an altogether unusual character,
      extending over half a century of time and many thousands of miles in distance. Yet he did not
      commence his wanderings until middle life. One of several remarkable characteristics of this series
      of lives is their abnormal length upon the physical plane. All these people whose incarnations we
      have been examining belong to what are called the upper classes, where the average length of life
      is on the whole greater than in the lower. A list of seventeen lives of Erato, for example, gives
      us an average length upon the physical plane of 48 years; twenty-four lives Orion give us an
      average of 53, and twenty-one of Sirius an average of 63 6/7 this latter already distinctly above
      the normal; but Alcyone's average is no less than 74.35!
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Следующая жизнь нашего героя была посвящена паломничеству, которое заняло более полувека, в течении
      которого он прошёл несколько тысяч миль. Однако начал он это путешествие лишь в середине жизни.
      Одной из примечательных характеристик этих жизней является их необычайная длина на физическом плане.
      Все те, чьи жизни мы подвергли исследованию, были из тех, кого называют представителями высшего класса,
      которые вообще живут дольше чем низший класс. На протяжении 17 жизней Эрато жил в среднем 48 лет,
      Орион в своих 24 жизнях жил в среднем 53 года, 21 жизнь Сириуса имела длительность, в среднем,
      примерно 64 года, что уже заметно дольше среднего, а средняя жизнь Алкиона длилась более 74 лет!
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Indeed when his life is cut short by accident, he rarely stops short of the fourscore years which
      the Psalmist gives as an extreme limit for the men of his day; and furthermore he seems always to
      retain full vigour up to the end of these unusually extended incarnations. Whether this is an
      individual peculiarity, or the characteristic of a certain type, we have yet to learn.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      После того как несчастный случай прервал его жизнь в раннем возрасте, он редко ограничивался 80 годами,
      что в соответствии с Псалмистом, было чрезвычайно большим возрастом для людей того времени. Более того,
      до последних лет он, судя по всему, сохранял энергичность в полной мере. Является ли это его
      личной особенностью или свойством людей определённого типа, мы пока что не знаем.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This new chapter of our story takes us once more to the south of India, but this time to what is
      now the Salem district, where Uranus, the father of Alcyone, was an important land-owner a sort of
      petty chieftain, who could lead a respectable regiment of his retainers to the standard of his
      overlord Mars. Uranus was a man of great courage and justice, and he trained his children in both
      these virtues, telling them that without these qualities a man of the highest birth was lower than
      the commonest person who possessed them. He had a large family, all of them prominent members of
      the band of Servers.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Эта глава нашего рассказа вновь возвращает нас в южную Индию в город Салем, в котором Уран был отцом
      Алкиона и влиятельным землевладельцем, который правил народом живущим в тех краях основываясь на
      правлении своего господина Марса. Уран был очень решителен и справедлив и оба этих качества он старался
      развить в своих детях, говоря им, что без них любой человек даже из благороднейшей семьи менее достоин
      чем простолюдин обладающий ими. У него была большая семья, которая целиком состояла из выдающихся
      членов группы Служителей.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone who was born in 20574 B.C., was a bright, encouraging, unselfish child, intensely devoted
      to his mother Mercury. All through her life his love for her never wavered, and he took no action
      of any importance without first consulting her. Nothing requiring special note for the purpose of
      our story occurred during his childhood and youth. He received what was considered at the time a
      good education, and at the age of twenty he married Percy, by whom he had twelve children. He had a
      beautiful home and all that wealth could give him; but his desire was rather for the life of a
      hermit than for that of the world, and his mother encouraged him in this inclination, advising him
      however to wait until his children were grown up before leaving them.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Алкион родился в 20,574 году до н.э. красивым, многообещающим и самоотверженным ребёнком, сильно
      привязанным к своей маме Меркурии. На протяжении всей её жизни его любовь к ней ни разу не дрогнула и перед
      любым важным решением он советовался с ней. Во время его детства и юности не произошло ничего такого,
      что стоило бы упоминать. Он получил хорошее по тем меркам образование и в 20 лет женился на Перси,
      которая родила ему 12 детей. У него был прекрасный дом и всё то, что может дать богатство, однако его
      больше интересовала жизнь отшельника, а не жизнь мирянина, и его мама поддерживала его в этом, но
      при этом советовала подождать пока его дети подрастут.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      During his life Alcyone took part in three military expeditions. The first was when he was quite a
      young man, and accompanied his father, when the latter led out his contingent of soldiers to fight
      for Mars. On one occasion during that campaign he received some kind of distinction for signal
      service rendered. On the second of these expeditions he was alone, but on the third he was
      accompanied by his sons, and Herakles performed an act of bravery under the eyes of Mars, who was
      now quite old. In consequence of this act Mars took Herakles into his body-guard, where,
      subsequently, the latter was able to render him many little services.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      За свою жизнь Алкион принял участие в трёх военных походах. Во время первого похода он был весьма молод
      и сопровождал отца, который вёл своих солдат в битву за Марса. Второй поход он вёл сам, а во время
      третьего похода его сопровождали сыновья. В том походе Геракл совершил отважный поступок и это заметил Марс,
      который был тогда уже весьма стар. Марс взял Геракла в свою дружину, где тот смог сослужить ему
      хорошую службу.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      When this expedition was over, the King summoned Alcyone to his presence, and requested that
      Herakles should assume his father's duties in the kingdom. Alcyone replied that whatever the King
      wished should be done, but that he believed himself still quite able to continue his services
      towards him. But the King said:
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      После той экспедиции король вызвал Алкиона и потребовал, чтобы Геракл взял обязанности отца по
      управлению королевством. Алкион ответил, что воля короля должна быть выполнена, хотя считал, что
      пока что сам может выполнять эти обязанности. На это король сказал:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      No; it will not be possible, for when you return to your home you will find that you have sustained
      a great bereavement, in consequence of which you will no longer fight for me in this life, and on
      your next visit to this city you will wear the robe of a holy man a pilgrim.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      "Нет, так не получится, ибо по возвращению домой ты обнаружишь большую утрату и не сможешь больше
      сражаться за меня в этой жизни, а во время твоего следующего визита в город ты будешь уже в одеянии
      святого отшельника."
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Be it as the King wills, said Alcyone; but living or dead I shall always be at the King's service.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      "Да будет так, как пожелает король" сказал Алкион, "однако жив или мёртв, я всегда буду на службе короля."
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It is true that you will do the service, replied Mars, not this time only but many times, through
      ages yet to come; yet your greatest service will be not in fighting my enemies, but in helping me
      to build up a kingdom in the future which shall endure for thousands of years, and the results of
      your achievements in that future kingdom will never pass away. The King then thanked him and bade
      him farewell.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      "Ты и вправду будешь на этой службе," ответил Марс, "и не один раз на протяжении грядущих веков,
      однако твоей важнейшей службой будет не битва с моими врагами, а помощь в построении нового королевства
      в будущем, которое будет жить тысячи лет и достижения твои в этом королевстве остануться навечно."
      После чего король его поблагодарил и попрощался.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      When Alcyone reached home he found that the prophecy of Mars had been fulfilled. The bereavement
      which the King had foretold was the death of his mother Mercury. This was so great a sorrow to him
      that he felt unable any longer to engage in the affairs of ordinary life; so, as his children had
      now all attained years of discretion, he determined to carry out his long-cherished intention of
      becoming a hermit or ascetic. He therefore left his eldest son Herakles to represent him at the
      court of the King, and his second son Mizar to carry on his duties as land-owner.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Когда Алкион добрался до дома, он обнаружил, что предсказание Марса было верным, а утрата о которой он
      говорил, была смертью его мамы Меркурии. Для него это было столь большим горем, что он не смог найти
      в себе силы заниматься дальше обычными делами, а поскольку его дети уже достаточно выросли, он решил
      исполнить своё давнее желание стать отшельником и аскетом. Тогда он оставил своего сына Геракла
      представлять его перед королевским двором, а Мицара - выполнять обязанности землевладельца.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Herakles, though still quite a young man, became not only a great captain under Mars, but also a
      highly trusted advisor. He was popular, and greatly beloved by the people. In time he became a
      close friend of Orpheus, the eldest son of Mars, and after the latter had succeeded his father on
      the throne he made Herakles his chief minister, in which capacity he worked faithfully for many
      years. At last some serious difference of opinion arose between the King and his prime minister, on
      some question of policy. Because of this Herakles, who was of a hypersensitive nature, resigned his
      post, and asked to be appointed to the governorship of a distant province. The King granted his
      request with much regret, and Herakles became practically the absolute ruler of that province, as
      the King did not interfere with him in any way.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Геракл хотя и был весьма молод, стал не только выдающимся полководцем Марса, но и высокоуважаемым
      советником. Он был очень популярен у людей. Со временем он стал близким другом Орфея - старшего сына Марса,
      и когда тот сменил своего отца на троне, он сделал Геракла своим главным министром и тот многие годы
      преданно работал на этой должности. Но однажды между королём и его главным министром возникло
      серьёзное разногласие по поводу политики. Геракл был чрезвычайно чувствительной натурой и из за этого
      отказался от своего поста и попросил назначить его губернатором какой нибудь далёкой провинции.
      Король принял прошение с большим сожалением и Геракл стал фактически единоличным правителем той
      провинции, поскольку король никак не вмешивался в его дела.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In due course the King died, and soon after that his successor, Cetus, issued some mandate which
      Herakles considered it would be unwise for his people to obey; by disregarding it he practically
      declared himself independent, and may therefore be said to have founded a small separate kingdom.
      Herakles had married Gemini, a lady who was stormily affectionate, but of an impulsive nature and
      weak character.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Со временем король умер и его наследник - Цетус - вскоре издал указ, который Геракл счёл неразумным
      для своего народа и отказался его выполнять. Таким образом он фактически заявил о независимости
      провинции и основал маленькое королевство. Геракл женился на Гемини - необычайно привлекательной леди
      с импульсивной натурой и слабым характером.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Meanwhile Alcyone's second son, Mizar, managed the vast family estate satisfactorily. He surprised
      everyone by marrying a slave girl (Irene), whose story is as follows. In the second war in which
      Alcyone fought under Mars, a number of prisoners were captured and made slaves. Among them was a
      man whose daughter was so strongly attached to him that when he was carried off as a captive she
      refused to be separated from him. After her father's death the daughter became a slave in Alcyone's
      household, and grew much attached to him, serving him with great faithfulness and assiduity. She
      helped to look after his children, and when Mizar was left practically the head of the family, he
      took the bold step of making her his wife an act which he never had the slightest reason to regret.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Тем временем старший сын Алкиона - Мицар - успешно справлялся с управлением огромного семейного поместья.
      Он удивил всех тем, что женился на рабыне (Ирене), история которой следующая. Во второй войне Алкион
      сражался за Марса и во время неё они захватили много рабов. Среди них был мужчина, чья дочь была
      столь преданна ему, что когда его забирали как пленного, она пошла с ним. После смерти своего отца,
      она стала рабыней в доме Алкиона и успела к нему привязаться, служа ему с большой преданностью и
      прилежанием. Она помогала присматривать за его детьми и когда Мицар фактически стал главой семьи,
      он сделал решительный шаг и женился на ней, о чём у него не было ни малейшего повода сожалеть.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      At the time of Alcyone's inconsolable grief over his mother's death, a revered friend suggested
      that he should accompany him on a pilgrimage to see a holy man who lived at a sacred shrine to the
      south of Alcyone's home. So they arranged to make the pilgrimage together, and Alcyone's youngest
      son Cygnus went with them, to take care of his father. When they reached the shrine, the wise and
      holy Priest Jupiter received them most kindly, and Alcyone was greatly consoled by listening to his
      words. He also permitted Alcyone to witness certain secret ceremonies which much resembled the
      Eleusian Mysteries, and these stimulated his psychic faculties to such an extent that during one of
      them he not only had a vision of his mother, but was able to communicate with her. He was so deeply
      impressed by the beauty of the temple and its ceremonies and the saintliness of the High Priest,
      that when he was told that there were many such shrines in India he then and there made a vow to
      visit them all before he died. This vow seems to have been occasionally taken by ascetics at that
      period, but most of them died before they accomplished it.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Пока Алкион горевал по поводу смерти своей мамы, один его близкий друг предложил составить ему компанию
      в пути к одному святому, который жил в священном храме на юге от дома Алкиона. Так они отправились в
      путешествие вместе, взяв с собой младшего сына Алкиона - Сигнус, чтобы тот помогал своему отцу.
      Добравшись до храма, их встретил мудрый и святой жрец Юпитер, который утешил Алкиона своими словами.
      Он даже позволил Алкиону поприсутствовать на некоторых тайных церемониях, которые сильно напоминали
      Элевсинские таинства, и они столь заметно усилили его психические способности, что во время одной такой
      церемонии он не только мог видеть свою маму, но и общаться с ней. Его столь сильно впечатлила красота
      храма и его церемоний и святость главного жреца, что когда ему сказали о других подобных храмах в Индии,
      он поклялся посетить их все за остаток жизни. Подобные клятвы давали аскеты того времени, но большинство
      из них не смогли выполнить клятву за одну жизнь.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone soon found that he could continue to communicate with his mother Mercury, and this was a
      great joy and comfort to him. She approved greatly of his pilgrimage, and undertook to guide him
      from shrine to shrine on his way. We next see him at a great temple situated where Madura now
      stands; the High Priest in charge of which was Saturn.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Алкион вскоре обнаружил, что может общаться со своей мамой Маркурием и это было для него большой
      радостью и утешением. Она решительно одобрила его паломничество и взяла на себя роль гида, чтобы
      вести его от храма к храму. Следующим местом куда он добрался был большой храм в современной Мадуре
      и главным жрецом в нём был Сатурн.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Some time after he left this place, we find him at a shrine in Central India near the godavari
      river, where Brihat welcomed him with the warmest hospitality and friendship.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Некоторое время спустя он покинул это место и отправился в святилище в центральной Индии возле
      реки Годавари, где его теплейшим образом поприветствовал Брихат.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Soon after this a regrettable incident occurred. It will be remembered that Cygnus accompanied
      Alcyone on his travels. Cygnus was deeply attached to his father, utterly ready to serve him in any
      way, showing wonderful fidelity. This was one side of his character; but on the other hand he was
      always getting himself involved with the opposite sex. On three separate occasions during this
      pilgrimage he got himself into serious trouble, and Alcyone had much difficulty in pacifying the
      people concerned. Each time Cygnus had promised amendment with many protestations and real sorrow;
      yet temptation was often too strong for him. Alcyone again and again threatened to send him home,
      but still this trouble recurred. On the fourth and last occasion the case was a peculiarly bad one,
      and the facts became generally known, giving rise to strong popular indignation, so that Alcyone
      and Cygnus were compelled to make their escape hurriedly in the middle of the night in order to
      avoid being lynched by an angry crowd. They took refuge in a jungle, and were there attacked by a
      tiger. As the tiger was about to spring, Cygnus who was full of remorse and had been bitterly
      reproaching himself for the trouble he had caused threw himself in front of his father so as to
      receive the full weight of the animal. Alcyone at once attacked the beast with his staff, which was
      the only weapon he had, and eventually succeeded in beating it off; but Cygnus was already dead,
      and his father deeply mourned his loss.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Вскоре произошёл печальный инцидент. Напомним, что Сигнус сопровождал Алкиона в его путешествии.
      Он был сильно привязан к своему отцу и искренне желал служить ему всеми силами, демонстрируя
      удивительную верность. Это было одной стороной его характера, а с другой стороны он постоянно
      попадал в разные истории с противоположным полом. Три раза он оказывался в серьёзной беде из за
      этого и Алкиону с большим трудом удавалось успокоить замешанных людей. Каждый раз Сигнус обещал
      исправиться и выражал искреннее сожаление по поводу случившегося, однако соблазн часто был слишком
      велик для него. Каждый раз Алкион грозился отправить сына домой, но история повторялась. В четвёртый
      и последний раз всё оказалось намного хуже; люди обо всём узнали и начали проявлять всеобщее недовольство,
      поэтому Алкион и Сигнус были вынуждены спешно покинуть всех ночью, чтобы избежать самосуда разъярённой
      толпы. Они нашли убежище в джунглях, но там на них напал тигр. В момент когда тигр собирался прыгнуть,
      Сигнус, который был полон печали и бранил себя за созданные проблемы, прыгнул перед отцом и принял на себя
      удар тигра. Алкион тут же ударил тигра своим посохом - единственным оружием которое у него было -
      и сумел его победить. Но Сигнус был уже мёртв и его отец сильно горевал по этому поводу.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone journeyed next towards Burma, and when he reached the neighbourhood of Chandernagar he
      visited a shrine and temple which were in charge of the High Priest Venus. There was much of an
      astrological nature in the worship here, and on the walls of the temple there were planetary
      symbols made of magnetised metal.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Алкион продолжил путь в сторону Бирмы и когда он добрался до окрестностей Чанданнагара, он посетил
      храм которым заведовал Венера. Богослужения в этом храме носили астрологический характер и на
      стенах были символы планет сделанные из магнетизированного металла.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      From thence Alcyone proceeded towards the north-east, and eventually arrived at a shrine in the
      Lakhimpur district near the Brahmputra river. It was in charge of Lyra, a Chinese Priest who had
      come from Tibet to found a new religion under the direct inspiration of the Mahaguru. This Priest
      at a much later period became the philosopher Laotze. He presented to Alcyone a remarkable
      talisman, made of a kind of black stone, inlaid with minute Chinese characters in white. The
      inspiration had been made with such accuracy that it looked as though it were done with some
      chemical which had taken the colour from the stone, so that it resembled white veining in black
      marble. This talisman gave out remarkably powerful vibrations, and the object of this gift was said
      to be to place Alcyone under the protection of certain exalted influences which were directly
      subordinate to the Mahaguru himself. Before Alcyone took leave the High Priest pronounced over him
      a remarkable benediction, prophesying for him a vast sphere of usefulness in the far-distant future.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Оттуда Алкион продолжил идти на северо-восток и со временем добрался до храма в Лакхимпуре возле
      реки Брахмапутра. Храмом заведовал китайский жрец Лира, который пришёл с Тибета основать новую
      религию под руководством Махагуры. Этот жрец много лет спустя стал философом Лао-цзы. Он подарил Алкиону
      примечательный талисман из какого то чёрного камня с тончайшим письмом из белых китайских символов.
      Надпись была сделана столь аккуратно, что казалось, будто её выжгли неким веществом и оно взяло цвет
      от камня, так что надпись будто состояла из белых прожилок в чёрном мраморе. Талисман излучал примечательно
      сильные вибрации, а его целью, как ему сказали, было поместить Алкиона под защиту определённых возвышенных
      влияний исходящих прямо от Махагуру. Перед уходом Алкиона, главный жрец произнёс примечательное
      благословение и предсказал, что в далёком будущем у него будет большая сфера полезной деятельности.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The next temple that Alcyone visited formed part of a small monastery situated on a snowy
      hill-side, near Brahmkund. The sites of many of these shrines appear to have been consecrated by
      the Mahaguru personally, some of them by quite physical-plane methods, in much the same manner as,
      many thousands of years later, magnetised centres were established by Apollonius of Tyana.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Затем Алкион посетил храм, выглядящий как часть маленького монастыря на снежном склоне горы возле
      Брахмакунды. Многие из этих храмов были освящены самим Махагурой, иногда вполне физическими методами,
      примерно также, как много тысяч лет спустя Аполлоний Тианский установил центры магнетизма.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      After leaving Brahmkund, Alcyone spent several years in journeying slowly across the whole north of
      India, during which time he mat with many adventures of various kinds. Perhaps the next point of
      special interest for us is his visit to a shrine at Mount Girnar in Kathiawar, where Alcesist was
      the chief Priest. With this place both he and Orion were closely connected in a subsequent life;
      and there is now a magnificent Jain temple there, one hall of which Alcyone himself built in that
      later time.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      После Брахмакунды Алкион потратил несколько лет неспешно перемещаясь через весь север Индии,
      где ему встретились самые разные приключения. Наверно следующим интересным моментом в его
      путешествии был его визит в храм на горе Гирнар в Катхияваре, в котором главным жрецом был Алцесист.
      С этим местом будет тесно связана следующая жизнь Алкиона и Ориона. Сейчас там стоит впечатляющий
      храм джаинистов, в котором Алкион в те времена построил один из холлов.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      From here Alcyone went to Somnath, a place situated near the sea, with a fine view. The temple here
      was in charge of Viraj, and was built on a most magnificent scale.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Оттуда Алкион отправился в Сомнатх, из которого открывался прекрасный вид на море. Храм был построен с
      впечатляющим размахом и им тогда заведовал Вирэй.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In order to reach the next shrine of importance Alcyone had to return northwards and was compelled
      to cross a long, barren, deserted tract of country, not far from where Ahmedabad is now.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Чтобы добраться до следующего по важности святилища, Алкион вернулся на север и был вынужден перейти через
      большую пустынную территорию неподалёку от современного Ахмедабада.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      We next see our pilgrim in the district of Surat, at a sort of pagoda temple. The shrine here was
      in chare of Pallas, an old Priest with a white beard and an impressive manner; a splendid, majestic
      man, extremely intellectual , though perhaps with too little heart. This Priest was known in a much
      later life as the philosopher Plato. The officials connected with this shrine were rather of the
      nature of statesmen than of ascetics.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Затем мы находим нашего паломника в Сурате, в храме напоминающем пагоду. Этим храмом заведовал Паллас -
      старый жрец с белой бородой и впечатляющими манерами; он был выдающимся и величественным человеком, с
      экстраординарным интеллектом, но, возможно, с не таким уж большим сердцем. Этот жрец в одной из следующих
      жизней стал известен как философ Плато. Чиновники, связанные с этим храмом, были скорее политиками
      чем аскетами.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      After Surat, Alcyone visited a temple a temple in the Vindhya hills, called by an Atlantean name,
      but not of any special interest. It had a talking image which was worked by means of a
      speaking-tube, but the Priests who managed this had no feeling that they were deceiving the people.
      The Priest who spoke really believed that he was inspired by the deity, and in sending his message
      through the mouth of the image, he considered that he was merely putting it in the way most
      calculated to impress his audience. There were some good people among the Priests there, one of
      them being Phocea, who had taken to wife Procyon.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      После Сурата Алкион посетил храм в горах Виндхья, который имел атлантское имя, но не представлял
      особого интереса. В нём было изображение с трубой через которую говорили жрецы, однако они не считали,
      что таким образом вводят людей в заблуждение. Жрец, который говорил, искренне считал, что его вдохновляет
      божество, а посылая своё сообщение через рот картины, он считал, что всего лишь придаёт ему наиболее
      впечатляющею народ форму.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Passing on, the wanderer visited a number of places on the way home, and altogether spent about
      fifty years of his life in fulfilling his vow. He finally took up his abode in the cave which he
      had inhabited before starting on his pilgrimage, where he lived to the unusual age of one hundred
      and nine.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Продолжая поиски, странник посетил ещё много мест на пути домой и потратил в целом около 50 лет своей
      жизни, чтобы выполнить клятву. В конце концов он сделал своим домом пещеру, где он жил ещё до того как
      стал отшельником, где и прожил до 109 лет.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      During his meditations Mercury constantly appeared to him and gave him much advice and instruction.
      She helped him to recover the memory of previous lives and of those who had been in them with him
      so that his cave was peopled with thought-forms of many of the characters who have previously
      appeared in this series of lives.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Во время медитаций ему постоянно являлся Меркурий и давал полезные советы и указания. Он помог
      ему восстановить воспоминания о прошлых жизнях и тех кто был с ним в них, так что его пещера заполнилась
      мыслеформами многих людей, которые встречались ему в прошлых жизнях.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
