<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 47
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 47-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In the forty-sixth life of our list Alcyone had much mental suffering, but yet he had remarkable
      advantages in his close association with Mercury and Zarathushtra. In this forty-seventh life,
      which we have now to consider, his advantages were to be greater even than those; yet his birth was
      by no means a favourable one. It took place in the year 2472 of the Kaliyuga (630 B.C.), the fourth
      year of King Kshattranjas, near the town of Rajgriha.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It is true that his father Jagannadha was a Brahman and a rich man, bur his character left much to
      be desired. He was a grasping man, who had all kinds of ways of making money, some of which came
      perilously near to the verge of dishonesty.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      With some other Brahmans he owned a temple, and the arrangement was that each of these joint owners
      took sole charge of the temple in turn and managed it for a certain specified time, and during that
      time all the offerings made by pilgrims and others came to him, and were his private property. This
      curious system led to a great deal of sharp practice on the part of these Brahmans; for example
      Jagannadha had agents along the main tracks in all parts of India, who were instructed to warn him
      far in advance when any rich pilgrim, or any specially large party of pilgrims, was setting out.
      When he received the news, he tried to arrange it so that such pilgrims should arrive during his
      period in charge of the temple, and he directed his agents to contrive some pretext for hurrying or
      delaying them so that this might be managed. It was in this way that he had succeeded in amassing
      much wealth, though its possession was, strictly speaking, contrary to the rules of his caste. He
      also owned a good deal of land, and stood well in the favour of the King, to whom he now and then
      made politic presents. Jagannadha was by no means unkind, and he gave his children a good
      education; but unfortunately, as soon as they were old enough, he also trained them zealously in
      his own peculiar methods of increasing the family fortunes. The mother was a kindly and gentle
      woman, careful and thorough in fulfillment of her household duties, but with little interest in
      anything beyond them religious as far as the punctual performance of ceremonies went, but not
      capable of comprehending metaphysics or philosophy. She had had several children, but only Alcyone
      (whose name this time was Shivashankara) and his sister Muli survived. Jagannadha had also adopted
      another boy, Mizar, who was the son of a cousin of his, and had been left an orphan at an early
      age. Mizar's name this time was Nirvana, and he was two years younger than Alcyone. The affection
      between the boys could not have been stronger if they had been brothers, though their dispositions
      differed widely. Alcyone was dreamy and romantic, with high ideals, while Mizar was keen and
      practical. But not always scrupulous. While they were still young their mother died, and they were
      left much to their own devices, as Jaganndha was always occupied with his schemes, or at least so
      full of them that he could talk of nothing else, which made Alcyone think him rather an
      uninteresting companion. Mizar entered much more fully into them, and even sometimes made ingenious
      suggestions, whereby the gains could be increased.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      At the age of eighteen Alcyone married Irene, a good and spiritually-minded woman, and in a year's
      time a son was born to them. A year later his father died, and Alcyone consequently became the head
      of the family, and inherited the father's duties and possessions. He had therefore to take his
      place in turn in the administration of the temple and its sacrifices. He strongly disliked the
      sacrificial work, though since the duty came to him he did it for a time as a matter of course, as
      his father had done. It involved a large amount of slaughter, as the offering of animals to the
      deity was supposed to be meritorious. The sacrifice of a horse was thought to be in some way
      especially pleasing; goats were even more frequently offered, but were not considered so acceptable.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      All Alcyone's feelings revolted against this wholesale slaughter and he inwardly doubted whether it
      could be pleasing to any good God. Also, he further disliked intensely his father's methods of
      attracting pilgrims to the temple. He quite understood the advantage of the arrival of large
      parties of rich people during his tenancy of the office; but his father had frequently resorted to
      direct trickery and shameless falsehood in order to produce this result, and Alcyone felt a strong
      repugnance for this; in fact, he absolutely declined to engage in it. He therefore made by no means
      so good a thing out of the temple revenues as his father had done.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      His cousin Mizar did not at all agree with him on these points. The father's teaching had deeply
      impressed him, and he watched all this with a somewhat jealous eye, regarding Alcyone's scruples
      with some contempt, and often telling himself how much better he could manage affairs if he were
      the head of the family. He often urged Alcyone to follow in his father's footsteps, and intimated
      that not to do so amounted to a kind of disrespectful criticism of the father which ought not to be
      possible for a well-regulated Brahman. Alcyone could only reply that Mizar might do what he liked
      in these matters, but that he himself did not feel that he could carry on the old customs. He cared
      little for money or for ostentation, but was much engrossed in domestic affairs, while Mizar on the
      other hand, though equally well intentioned and kindly in disposition, still thought it a duty to
      carry put the plans of Jagannadha, and so set it before himself as a paramount object to have as
      much money as possible in the family.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      About this time Mizar married Thetis, and unfortunately his wife was not at all the right kind of
      woman. She exercised a great fascination over him, and much increased his growing discontent, for
      she was essentially a schemer an ambitious woman, who longed intensely for wealth and power. The
      young couple often discussed these affairs, and they both felt that if only they were at the head
      of the family they could contrive to accumulate wealth much more rapidly. Naturally Alcyone's wife
      Irene always had to take precedence, and Thetis was distinctly envious of this, and as time went on
      felt more and more that she could not bear it, and that she was not finding a opportunity to show
      what she really could do and be, though Irene was always kind and gracious to her.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Another point was that Thetis has a son, and she wanted so to arrange matters that he should in due
      course inherit the temple and its revenues, instead of the son of Alcyone. She brooded over all
      these until at last she began to plot and plan to bring about her wishes. A vast amount of intrigue
      was always going on in the Court, for the King could give or take away property as he chose, and
      everything depended upon his favour. Thetis therefore began cleverly to set afloat rumours of
      different kinds against Alcyone and Irene, her hope being to undermine them in the favour of the
      King. She also caused a great deal of trouble in various ways in the household, managing by various
      ingenious schemes to cause friction between the two cousins, and even sometimes to get them into an
      open quarrel.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The other Brahmans who shared the charge of the temple with Alcyone were not especially
      well-disposed towards him, because of the attitude which he took both to their sacrifices and to
      their methods of squeezing money from the pilgrims; so that they were quite prepared to accept the
      rumours which Thetis set afloat, and when the King, hearing these over and over again, began to
      think there must be something in them to make enquiries, these Brahmans were quite ready to express
      their doubts, and to give Alcyone a somewhat indifferent character. All this plotting was cleverly
      managed by Thetis, and such a net of constant intrigue was woven round Alcyone and his wife that
      finally this led to an open rupture with the king , and Alcyone, Irene and their child were all
      banished from the court and the city. This was in the year 598, when Alcyone was already thirty two
      years old.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Thetis was exceedingly triumphed over this result. Mizar was not in the secret of her plans, and
      was much distressed at his cousin's exile; but he certainly did think that he could manage the
      temple and its revenues much better than Alcyone, so that as far as that went he was half glad of
      the opportunity which was afforded to him by the latter's disgrace. He had to take Alcyone's place
      , and he and his wife thus gained the fulfillment of their long-cherished desires, and were happy
      in the opportunity thus given to them, though Mizar never ceased to regret Alcyone's banishment,
      and presented several petitions to have him recalled.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone felt that he had been badly treated, especially as the country house to which he was
      banished was an unhealthy and malarious place. His son caught a bad fever here and was ill for a
      long time. He finally recovered, but was never really strong again, as the disease had left a
      weakness of the chest. Alcyone and Irene always blamed Mizar and Thetis for this, and Irene at
      least bore a grudge against the latter for it, and never ceased to think of it secretly.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Four years later, in the year 594, King Kshattranjas died, and Bimbisars came to the throne.
      Alcyone, who had known him well when he was a young prince, immediately applied to be restored to
      favour. The new King at once granted this, so Alcyone was once more put in charge of his share of
      the temple, returned to his town house, and took his original position. There was then a great
      scene between the two cousins, and Mizar for the first time came to know some of the things which
      his wife had said and done, and they shocked him terribly. The feeling between families was
      somewhat softened for the time, and Alcyone permitted Mizar and his wife to continue to live with
      them in the town house. Though the ladies were still to some extent distrustful of one another, and
      even Alcyone could not quite forget that Thetis had been instrumental in procuring the banishment
      which led to the ill-health of his son.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Thetis , however, was still dissatisfied, and continued to try secretly all sorts of plans for the
      purpose of securing the succession for her own son in place of Alcyone's. She hoped that the latter
      would die but as he did not oblige her, she formed a scheme to kill him gradually by slow poisoning
      so that she should not be suspected. She therefore, began to introduce the poison very cautiously
      into his food, increasing the dose little by little. Before the nefarious plot had fully succeeded,
      Alcyone one day discovered it, and was violently angry. His first instinct was to expose the whole
      affair, and deliver Thetis to his friend the King for judgement, but Mizar, though much horrified
      at the discovery, begged him earnestly not to do this. Eventually Alcyone consented to say nothing
      about it, but declared that he could never again feel safe in the same house with Thetis, so he
      stipulated that Mizar and his wife and child should retire to their country house, to which he
      himself had previously been banished. Mizar thankfully accepted this as a comparatively
      satisfactory arrangement, and at any rate more than he could have expected after Thetis's
      treachery. Unfortunately the discovery had come too late to save Alcyone's son, who lingered on for
      some time, but could not be cured by such physicians as were then available, and eventually died in
      the year 590. Alcyone was inconsolable, full of despair, and sometimes almost of hatred for Thetis,
      he seemed to lose his hold on life, and no longer cared for anything.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In the first year of the reign of King Bimbisara the Lord Gautama came to Rajgriha and was asked by
      the King to preach; but He would not then do so, and went on His way to attain Enlightenment. After
      He became Buddha the Lord Gautama remembered King Bimbisara's kindly request, and came and preached
      at Rajgriha in the year 588. He was then thirty-five, having been born in the year 623. Alcyone
      went to hear Him, and was immensely impressed, and lifted clear out of his hopelessness and
      depression. The Lord Buddha preached about sorrow and karma, and much of what He said exactly
      fitted Alcyone's case and wonderfully relieved his aching heart.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He went again and again to hear those wonderful sermons, and one day the Lord spoke strongly about
      the necessity of kindness and compassion. The man who wished to enter upon the Path must put away
      from him even the slightest shadow of anger and of hatred, and must show nothing to friend or enemy
      but all-embracing love. Alcyone thought long over this, and the result of it was that he went out
      to the country house to fetch back Mizar and his wife and child. He spoke to Thetis, whom before he
      had refused even to see, and told her that he regretted his hard feelings towards her, for he knew
      that in all that she had done she had been only the instrument of his own karma. She was utterly
      overcome by his unexpected kindness, and thus it happened that both she and Mizar were brought back
      again to share the home which she had desolated.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone on the first opportunity took Mizar to hear a sermon of the Lord Buddha. The scene was one
      never to be forgotten. Perhaps two thousand people were gathered there among the trees, most
      sitting on the ground, some leaning against the trunks, men and women together, and little children
      sitting with them or running about between the outlying groups of people. The Lord sat on a
      slightly raised platform a grassy bank in the midst of the garden, sorrounded by a band of His
      monks in their yellow robes, and with His glorious musical voice made all that crowd hear without
      an effort, and held them entranced day after day as they came to listen to Him. Of Him it was
      indeed emphatically true, as was once said of another prophet, that never man spake like this man .
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The influence of His magnetism upon the people was incalculable. His aura filled the whole garden,
      so that all the vast crowd was directly under its influence actually within Him, so to speak. The
      splendour of the aura attracted vast hosts of the higher devas of all kinds, and they also helped
      to influence the audience, so that we cannot wonder when we read in the sacred books that often at
      the close of a single sermon hundreds or even thousands attained the Arhat level. Many of the
      people then born in that part of India were those who had followed Him in previous incarnations in
      far-away lands, and were especially born in India in order that they might have this inestimable
      advantage of direct contact with Him after His enlightenment had been gained.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Those whose vision was confined to the physical plane saw only a gracious Prince of commanding
      appearance and of winning manner, who spoke to them with a clearness and directness to which they
      were not at all accustomed from their brahman teachers. The latter had for many years taught little
      but the necessity of frequent offerings to Brahmans, and of constant sacrifice to the Gods, which
      of course always involved heavy fees to their priests. But now came this far mightier Teacher, who
      told them in the simplest and most direct language that the only sacrifice pleasing to the Gods was
      that of a pure and gentle life that not animals but vices were to be destroyed and cast out, and
      that the great necessity was not gold for the temples, but purity and kindliness of life among the
      devotees.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      On this occasion when the two cousins went to hear Him, he took for His text the subject of fire.
      He pointed out to a fire which was burning near, and told them how it was no inapt symbol of
      delusion, in that the flame looked like what it was not; it seemed solid while it was not so, and
      it burned the man who touched it. Then He explained how all passion and all desire were like the
      burning flame how with them, as with it, no half-measures were useful, since the fire was never
      safe until it was utterly stamped out---never certain not to reappear and cause devastation until
      there was no single spark of it left. So, He said, must anger, passion, desire, delusion, be
      stamped out of the human heart. Only then could peace be attained, only then could man enter upon
      the Path.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The impression produced upon both the cousins was indescribable. At once Alcyone announced his
      intention of giving up everything in the world, and devoting himself entirely to following the
      Lord. His wife Irene immediately agreed with him, and he proposed to turn over to Mizar his share
      in the temple, the headship of the family, and all his worldly wealth. Mizar, however, refused to
      receive this, and declared that if Alcyone devoted himself to the religious life he would do so
      too, and even Thetis approved of this, though she said that she could not dare to offer herself for
      it, after all that had happened. Alcyone thought that the family should be perpetuated and the
      office of manager of the temple should be carried on, because of their promise to the father
      Jagannadha; and finally they went together to the Lord Buddha, told Him all that had happened from
      the beginning to the end, and put themselves unreservedly in His hands. The Blessed One heard their
      story, and to Alcyone He said:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Are you sure that there remains now no taint of hatred in your heart that you forgive to the
      uttermost, even the death of your son, and that for all created beings you can feel nothing but
      love evermore,, even for those who have injured you ?
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And Alcyone replied: Lord, this indeed is so; if my cousin's wife has injured me, I have forgotten
      it. I give him freely all my wealth, for I need it no longer. I have now in life only one desire,
      and though it take me a thousand lives, I vow here at Thy feet that I will never cease the effort
      until I shall have accomplished it. I vow to follow Thee, to give myself as Thou hast done to help
      the suffering world. Thou hast freed me from my sorrow, and brought me to eternal peace. To that
      peace also will I bring the world, and to this I consecrate my future lives, even until I shall be
      as Thou art, the saviour of the World.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And the Lord Buddha bowed His head and answered: As thou sayest, so shall it be. I the Buddha,
      accept that vow which can never be broken, and in the far distant ages it shall be fulfilled.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And so He stretched out His hand and blessed him, and Alcyone fell prostrate at His feet.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Then turning to Mizar, He said: You also shall follow me, but not yet. There is still much for you
      to do. Take up this charge which my new pupil has laid upon you. Take this which he gives you, for
      he needs it no longer, for the riches of the good Law excel all other wealth. Do justice and be
      merciful, and forget not that your time also shall soon come.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      So He dismissed him with a blessing, but Alcyone remained with Him, and followed Him thereafter in
      all His wanderings up and down that fair northland of India.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Mizar after this returned home to fulfil his duties, as the Lord Buddha told him to do; but because
      of the Buddha's teaching of mercy to all he steadfastly refused ever again to kill any animals for
      sacrifice, or to adopt any of the mean tricks by which. Jagannadha had amassed so much wealth. Thus
      he lost much money, and made himself very unpopular with the other temple Brahmans, especially as
      he several times publicly announced his adhesion to the Buddha's saying that a Brahman, who does
      not live as a Brahman should, is not in reality a Brahman at all, no matter how high his birth may
      be, whereas even a Shudra who lives the life of a true Brahman is worthy of the respect accorded to
      a Brahman. The other Brahmans therefore plotted against him, and reduced his revenues still
      further. Nevertheless, the King being pronouncedly Buddhist, they could not procure his
      depositions, though they often lodged complaints against him.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He had a good reputation among the people for humanity and kindliness, in spite of all the stories
      which the Brahmans were constantly circulating against him, so as years rolled on he grew richer in
      popularity, though poorer in pocket. It was a great triumph for him when King Bimbisara, moved by
      an eloquent sermon from the Lord Buddha, decreed that there should be no more slaughter for the
      sacrifice. The other Brahmans, though greatly incensed by this order, dared not disobey it, and
      because of the determined propagation of these ideas in earlier days Mizar stood well in the King's
      favour. Still there were many who distrusted him, because the hostile Brahmans had somehow come to
      hear a distorted version of the story of the poisoning of Alcyone's son and of course they made the
      most of it.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Mizar still used some part of Jagannadha's organisation to bring large bodies of pilgrims into his
      period of management of the temple, not now in order to make money out of them, but in order to
      save them from the rapacity of his compeers which naturally increased the hatred of the latter for
      him. His position was therefore always a precarious one, for though he had the favour of the King
      and the gratitude of many people, he had to face ceaseless intrigue and scarcely veiled malevolence
      in all sorts of small every-day matters. Still, for more than twenty years he contrived to carry on
      the work, and in that time introduced many useful reforms into the administration of the temple, in
      the teeth of much opposition. He was all the while quite openly and professedly a follower of the
      Buddha, and was living according to His teaching, though still remaining an orthodox Brahman; and
      in this he was by no means singular,, for the Buddha did not take people away from the older
      religion, and no one except those who actually assumed the yellow robe attached themselves
      exclusively to Him.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The end of Mizar's life was from a worldly point of view unfortunate. In 566 Bimbisara was murdered
      by his unnatural son Ajatshatru, who thus seized upon the throne. His plot had been carried out by
      the aid of the Brahmans, and he therefore favoured them and their religion, and was openly opposed
      to Buddhism. So, when the Brahmans of the temple preferred a complaint against Mizar, the new King
      readily gave ear to them and deposed him, and confiscated most of his property. He still had a
      little land, and he retired and lived upon this in comparative poverty and obscurity until his
      death in 562 at the age of sixty-six.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Meanwhile Alcyone had attached himself to the Lord Buddha, and never again left Him until death,
      but travelled with Him up and down the ganges valley for many years, drinking ever more and more
      deeply at the fount of His wisdom, and partaking in the private teaching which He gave only to His
      monks. He formed a close but reverential friendship for an older monk named Dharmajyoti, who was
      very kind to him, and helped him much along the road to perfect peace. This monk Dharmjyoti is
      known to us as Uranus; he was later Aryasanga, and is now the Master Djwal-kul. The name selected
      by Alcyone upon assuming the yellow robe was Maitribaladasa, which means the servant of the power
      of kindness ; and the Lord said to him: You have chosen well; that name is prophetic.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      For Maitreya is the name of the Bodhisattva who succeeded the Lord Buddha in His office the Christ
      who is to come; so the name may also be rendered the servant of the power of Maitrey . Followinng
      thus in the train of the Lord Buddha. Alcyone naturally bore part in many interesting and
      historical scenes; for example, he was present when, in the year 580, Chatta Manavaka (Selene) was
      called up by the Lord and taught the beautiful verses immortalised for us in the sacred books.
      Whenever the great Master's travels took Him to Rajgriha, Mizar invariably came to welcome Alcyone,
      and the affection between the cousins grew ever stronger as the years rolled on. Alcyone died in
      559 at the age of seventy one, sixteen years before the death of the Lord Buddha in 543. The latter
      part of his life was passed in unalloyed peace and happiness.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      A year after Alcyone's death came the great King Mars to hear the preaching of the Lord. With him
      he brought his son Herakles, who listened to the Lord and followed Him thenceforth, and after His
      death became one of His great missionaries, carrying His Law into Burma and the East. Herakles in
      his turn had many enthusiastic disciples his own son the disputatious Capri, and his nephews, the
      eager, earnest Polaris and Capella, the impulsive and blundering Gemini, and the ever smiling
      Adrona. The latter was, however, drawn away from him by the arguments of a wonder-working brahman,
      Cetus, who had been acting as chief-priest at the court of another Raja, Orpheus, whose daughter
      Herakles had married. An entire breaking up of the religious arrangements of that little State
      followed, for, after Adrona had pledged himself irrevocably to Cetus. Herakles succeeded in
      converting King Orpheus and his sons Siwa and Myna. Cetus was very angry about this, and eventually
      he had Adrona left the country with a small band of followers, and took up their abode in a
      neighbouring State, which they tried unsuccessfully to stir up into war against Orpheus. The first
      and closest follower of Herakles was his nephew. Ivy, with whom he had always a peculiarly strong
      sympathy, born of intimate relationship in the far-off past.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      King Orpheus himself would have followed the Lord, but that the latter told him that he had a
      primary duty towards his Kingdom, and that he must hold it on His behalf. The two kings, Mars and
      Orpheus had an agreement between them that their children should intermarry, and they carried this
      out as far as possible, as will be seen from the accompanying chart. In this combined royal family
      it was not only Herakles who was so deeply affected; his brother Rama and his sister Naga were
      moved as profoundly, and both desired to offer to the Lord as followers not only themselves but
      their entire families all their sons and daughters. Rama's wife Diana heartily agreed with him in
      this, but Naga's husband Myna hung back and was unwilling to make so great a sacrifice. Eventually
      the burning love of his wife overbore his scruples, and the two families were left entirely free to
      throw themselves at the feet of the Lord, Mars stipulated only that his grandson Theo should be
      left to succeed to his throne, and the Lord ordered that this should be so.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The effect of this life upon the characters of Alcyone and Mizar was enormous as well it might be
      when they had earned so great a favour as to be born upon earth at the same time as the Buddha, and
      to come under His benign influence. Every vestige of anger and revenge was wiped from the heart of
      Alcyone, and the qualities of compassion, forgiveness and true affection were developed in him to
      the utmost. How deep and essential in its nature was the result produced by this most fortunate of
      lives may be seen by the fact that the average interval between his lives has been entirely altered
      by it. Before this the average was about seven hundred years and since then it has been twelve
      hundred. Mizar too was powerfully affected, for in the beginning he had had some scheming and
      selfishness in his character. Now most of that had disappeared for ever, and much of earnestness
      and love had taken its place, while valuable links had been formed, the result of which lies yet in
      the future. In his case, however, the average interval was not changed, and he therefore does not
      appear in the forty-eight life.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
