<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 39
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 39-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      As our hero had now had seven successive lives in male bodies, a change of sex takes place. We find
      Alcyone born this time in the year 6986 B.C. in the mighty kingdom of Egypt. Her name was
      Sebek-neferu-ra, and her father Sirius was the governor of a province and a man of importance in
      the country; he was of an old family, and stood high at Court and in the confidence of the Pharaoh,
      Mars, whose son Herakles was all his life his closest friend. Indeed, upon the death of Lutea, to
      whom Herakles had been married in his youth, it was Naga, the elder sister of his bosom friend
      Sirius, whom the heir to the throne chose as his second wife. Thus in due course of time Naga
      became Queen of Egypt, and Sirius and Alcyone thus found themselves in very close association with
      the throne. Alcyone's mother, Ursa was a white woman the daughter of a chieftain near the Atlas
      Mountains; but as he had been only a semi-civilised person no reference was usually made to this
      side of her ancestry.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Ursa was only tepidly affectionate to Alcyone, because she had hoped for a son, and was much
      disappointed; but the father loved the child dearly. When a son (Egeria) arrived eighteen months
      later, the mother was entirely wrapped up in him and therefore neglected the daughter somewhat; but
      the father and the daughter were only drawn the closer together by that. Ursa was very imperious
      and impulsive, but was evidently trying hard to control and improve herself. Sirius, on the other
      hand, was quiet and steady-going.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The girl Alcyone was well-educated; she had a keen brain and was affectionate, sensitive and
      observant, but very shy and in certain ways timid. As she grew up the father had her much with him;
      she asked to be used as a secretary, and he found her really valuable in that capacity. When she
      was fifteen he had a tiresome illness, but she carried on most of the work very efficiently,
      deciding wisely, even when he was too ill to be consulted, and acting boldly in his name. She
      declined, however, to use the death-penalty under any circumstances, although she exercised all the
      other powers of jurisdiction which belonged to her father, using his official seal. Sirius, when he
      recovered, confirmed all her decisions where that was necessary, and applauded her actions. Two
      years later, her mother died after a lingering illness and much terrible suffering. Alcyone waited
      upon her and looked after her devotedly, while the son Egeria for whose sake Ursa had neglected her
      daughter, spent most of the time elsewhere and came to see his mother but rarely. During this final
      illness, Ursa recognised that she had not done full justice to Alcyone, and had been somewhat
      blinded by the intensity of her affection for her son.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      A young man of her own rank presently sought Alcyone's hand in marriage; she was not averse to him,
      but she felt that she could not bear to leave her father, and Sirius on his side also felt that
      life would be empty without her. Still he urged her to accept the young man, as he seemed eligible
      and honestly in love. She obediently did so, and on the whole her married life was happy, though
      she always looked back upon her childhood as an ideal time. The religions ceremonies of the period
      impressed her deeply, and seemed absolutely real to her while they lasted. The ornate ritual of
      Egypt, the splendid processions down the Nile, the hymns and dances in honour of the gods and
      goddesses, the magic that was worked by the priests, and the occasional materialisations of the
      deities all these things had a profound effect upon her feelings, and played a large part in her
      life.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      She had eleven children, to whom she was deeply devoted; they were all handsome, and made a
      beautiful picture when they were gathered round her. She lived chiefly for them, and she regarded
      social functions as tiresome because they took her away from children, although she played her part
      as a grand lady when necessary, and was just and generous to those dependent on her. As she was
      beautiful, several lovers made advances of various kinds to her, but she invariably rejected them,
      and remained faithful to her husband.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      One day an old man, Thetis, turned up a travelling merchant, who had known something of her
      mother's early history, which had not been free from blame. Ursa had been an impulsive and
      headstrong girl; she had refused to accept a husband whom her father had designated for her, and
      had run off instead with another man. Her chosen bridegroom, unfortunately, turned out to be a
      worthless fellow who was already married, and he eventually abandoned her. Now this villain Thetis,
      discovering from gossip Alcyone's position, threatened her with the exposure of all this history.
      Alcyone, being proud with regard to this, and not knowing how her husband would take an exposure
      (he being a conventional type of man) in a weak moment agreed to pay money to this blackmailer, and
      therefore fell into his power. He was so mercilessly rapacious that she had to sell jewels to
      satisfy him.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      However, one of her sons, Helios, a boy of fourteen, accidentally overheard one of her
      conversations with this extortioner, and, stung by a rude remark of the blackmailer, sprang out
      upon him and killed him. The mother was much shocked and startled, though of course from one point
      of view relieved also. There was great trouble as to the disposal of the body, and mother and son
      finally conveyed it by night to the river. The dread of discovery weighed heavily for some time
      upon Alcyone's heart, though, apparently, not at all upon her son's. Nothing further was heard of
      the affair, for the blackmailer's body was not found, and he was supposed to have travelled away
      again, as usual.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      When Alcyone was thirty-seven years of age her father, Sirius, died. The loss was a great grief to
      her; indeed, a child about to be born then died in consequence. One of her other children, however,
      proved to be mediumistic, and could see and speak to the dead father, and this brought great
      consolation to Alcyone. Through this child (Demeter) Sirius was able to give her much good advice,
      and to reconcile her to his absence from the physical plane. During physical life he had been much
      interested in the service of the temple and its magic. And he had often conversed with her about
      such matters as he was allowed to share with her. Even after his death they still spoke of these
      things. Her husband, however, did not understand them or care for them, though he was usually kind
      and proud of his wife. He was a successful man, and had considerable influence; his ideas were more
      worldly and less religious than his wife's, though he often deferred to her judgement about certain
      matters, and seemed to think that she might have some sort of inspiration.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      No very conspicuous events were noticed as occurring in this incarnation; she met the ordinary joys
      and sorrows of life, but acted nobly and steadfastly a part which was not without its difficulties.
      She avoided all the little plots and conspiracies, political and social, which were so common at
      the time, and she attained a position of consideration and respect through a straightforward simple
      reliability. She lived to the age of seventy- seven, the head of quite a clan of children,
      grandchildren and great-grandchildren, retaining her faculties and power of affection to the last.
      Her husband had died some years before.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It would seem that, just as the dissatisfaction with life as a Brahman brought Alcyone into a life
      of constant fighting, so his intense disgust with the unreasonableness and uselessness of that
      constant fighting brought him (or rather her) into what was on the whole a placid and comparatively
      eventless home-life. So true is it that strong desires being about their own fulfilment.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It was in this life that Neptune and Athena crossed the sea to Greece in order to attend the
      Mahaguru in His wandering incarnation as Orpheus, in which He preached the Law to the Greeks
      through the medium of his glorious music.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
