<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 26</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 26-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone's birth this time takes us to Central Asia once more, but now in the midst of the huge orthodox majority settled in that cradle-land of the fifth Root-Race. It took place in 17464 B.C., shortly after the other through thousands of years, gradually established the first Aryan sub-race in the possession of the Indian peninsula. One wing of the expedition previous to that now to be described had met with a serious disaster; part of the emigrant body had followed the western route travelled by Mars in the nineteenth century B.C.(18,875), avoiding the great mountain barriers of the Himalayas; but a smaller party, less weighted by women and children, had decided boldly to face the great Range, following a road they had heard of from traders, which led thorough a practicable but gloomy Pass, debouching into the plains near the city now known  as Peshawar. In modern days we know it as the Khybar Pass. They had pressed on, engaging in skirmishes with the hill-tribes from time to time, until near the end of the Pass, when suddenly a host of foes came down upon them like an avalanche, in front, behind, on each side, and, hopelessly outnumbered, they perished almost to a man. A few stragglers from the main body escaped, and, after incredible hardships which left only two survivors, these two starving, miserable fugitives arrived on the frontier of the Aryans, and, after resting for a brief space, were sent on to the King of the central community. Clad in sheep-skins given to them by their first hosts, they appeared before him and told the story of the massacre, and from that time the Pass was known as the Pass of death. Jupiter was then a boy of about ten, and the story made a great impression upon him, and when, as King of the tribe, he decided to send his eldest son Mars, at the head of another great host of emigrants, to penetrate into India, he advised him to avoid the Pass of Death and to seek some other egress.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The preparations for the expeditions lasted for some years, and Mars decided to make careful selection of the families which were to take part in the emigration, choosing only such as appeared likely to be best able to withstand the inevitable hardships of the way, and specially the warriors best trained in the methods of guerrilla fighting for mountains and of set battles on the plains. Among others his choice fell on Psyche, the father of Alcyone (then a boy of nine), whose wife Arthur was a woman of courage and resource. Capella, a neighbour and a close friend of Psyche, whose comrade he had been in several marauding expeditions, was also chosen by Mars. A great captain, Vulcan, was the warrior on whom Mars placed most reliance, and, dividing his host into two, he sent him a little ahead of himself, with instructions to penetrate through the mountains along a route running southwards and bending eastwards; while he would lead his party a little to the west, but not so far west as the Pass of Death. On emerging from the mountains the separated hosts were to rejoin each other, marching respectively eastwards and westwards till they met.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The starting of Mars was a little delayed by the pregnancy of his wife Neptune; soon after his eldest son Herakles was born, he set forward with his huge caravan. The women and children were divided into large parties, with herds of cattle and horses and flocks of sheep and goats; these were placed in the centre of a great number of fighting men, while on the outskirts all round hovered a cloud of well-mounted warriors, accompanied by swift and lightly armed runners, whom they could dispatch to the main body on any alarm, covering them from pursuit, the runners being less distinguishable than mounted messengers would have been, and the roughness of the ground impeding runners less than mounted men.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In the early days Mars and Psyche were often seen riding side by side, discussing the prospects before them, while Alcyone, mounted on a rough, sure-footed pony of the hills, would sometimes ride beside them, listening thoughtfully to their discourses, then dash ahead to take part with the scout in front, and then pass his elders at full gallop, as he rode to find his mother Arthur in the centre of the troop, eagerly attending to her wants and cheering her with gay stories of the troops, or in the sunset hour, nestle by her side, whispering his dreams, his hopes. Albeiro and Leto often accompanied him on his less adventurous and later baby Ajax would sit in front of him and prattle gaily as he rode, held fast by his brother's arm. Capella's sons became members of this young party, and the daughters, riding astride, often accompanied them. Hector, Capella's eldest daughter, became Albeiro's favourite companion while Alcyone found his best loved comrade in Rigel, the daughter of Betel. Ere the plains were reached the two pairs were wed, and the family of Mars had been increased by two sons and three daughters.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After some fifteen years of travelling, the caravan-army of Mars reached the plains, the earlier bodies camping and awaiting the later ones, until all were gathered in one huge camp. From time to time the younger men would make forays into the surrounding country, and on several occasions Mars had reproved Herakles for his somewhat reckless plunges into the unknown; the lad was wilful and impetuous, and inclined to think that his elders overrated the danger of his excursions. However, he received a sharp lesson, when one day he and his troops fell into an ambush and were suddenly attacked by a hostile force, which rose on all sides and pressed them sore. Herakles charged boldly with his men, trying to break through the encompassing ring, but was beaten back every time; his case seemed hopeless, when a band of horsemen came charging up and a rain of arrows, loosed as they galloped, fell on the assailants. The horse of Herakles had fallen with him beneath it wounded and stunned; a sharp melee followed, the enemies were driven off, and Alcyone, recognising his friend's horse, rolled it over with the aid of two of the soldiers, and found the senseless body of Herakles underneath. It seemed that Alcyone had gone eastword, in search of the hoped-for approaching army under Vulcan, and had met a similar scouting troop from it, under Vajra, looking for the western force; they had met with much rejoicing, and were returning to the camp of Mars when a thick cloud of dust was noted by Vajra's keen eyes. Alcyone was impressed with the idea that Herakles was in danger, and urged his companions to speed. They arrived but just in time to save the party from massacre, and Alcyone, tenderly raising his friend's body, supported it against his breast until he laid it at his mother Neptune's feet. She nursed her stalwart son back into health ere long, but Mars improved the occasion by reminding Herakles of his warning, and pointing out to him that Alcyone was no less brave because he was less headstrong.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The two armies having joined, the ablest leader of both decided to march southwards to find a suitable place for permanent settlement. They left the women and children behind in strongly entrenched camp, covering a large tract of land about midway between the modern Jammu and Gujranwallah, with a sufficient body of armed men to hold the camp against attack.  The place soon assumed the aspect of a city, with great areas for grazing around it on all sides, and cultivated fields within the entrenchments.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The invading host moved into a country already inhabited and flourishing. There were great cities, the dwellers in which had reached a high state of civilisation, and had become ever-luxurious and indolent. One of the immigrations of Aryans seemed to have established itself in the large areas which were not cultivated, and after much fighting and parleying, its members had settled themselves beside the civilised town-dwellers, defending them against the attacks of others and more or less plundering them themselves, under guise of tribute and subsidies. The owners of the country despised the northern warriors as less civilised than themselves, but feared their prowess in arms and their arrogance in council, and allowed themselves slowly but surely to be pressed back into their cities, and allowed themselves slowly but surely to be pressed back into their cities, or turned into servants and labourers outside.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Aryans, chanting the hymns of their War-Gods, and haughty in their strength and virility, despised equally the luxurious and decadent population of the land they coveted, and settled themselves down in the territory now known as Punjab, gradually becoming the real masters of the country. Another immigration turned eastwards, settling in what we now call Assam and northern Bengal. When the present immigration arrived, aiming at what is now called the Punjab by the direction of the Manu conveyed to Mars through Jupiter it found the land partly occupied by previous settlers, who eyed the new-comers askance and, while refraining from active hostility, endeavoured by passive resistance and withholding of aid to turn them away from their own neighbourhood.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After a year spent in obtaining information,, and consultation over the reports brought in by bodies of scouts, Mars and his council decided to make their permanent central settlement in the land where Delhi is now situated, despite the fact that the only convenient route was barred by a great city inhabited by the Toltec owners of the soil. Alcyone, though still under thirty years of age, was charged with the duty of leading an embassy to the ruler of the city and surrounding district, praying for free passage past the city and for permission to purchase food and forage. The mission was skillfully discharged, and permission was obtained on condition that the main body of troops should not pass close to the city, but should make a considerable detour in order to avoid it. Mars was invited to visit the Chief, and accepted the offer of hospitality. Like a wise general, however, he took with a strong escort, and left Vulcan in charge of the main body, taking Alcyone, Herakles and Vajra with himself.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The city lay within a huge wall, made of a high embankment, sloping on its inner side, but perpendicular and faced with iron plates, bolted together on the outer side, thus presenting a continuous and unscalable surface. This extraordinary wall made the city practically impregnable to attack by the arms of the time, such as were possessed by the uncivilised nations whose hordes swept now and again over the country; it could only be successfully assaulted from above, and the art of manufacturing airships had been lost by these degenerated Toltecs, and not yet entrusted to the younger race of Aryans. Castor, its chief, hence felt himself secure from attack, but none the less designated in his own mind that when these formidable strangers entered within his gates, he would seize them, hoping that the army, thus deprived of its leaders, might be persuaded to become mercenaries in his own employ. He was disappointed to find that the second in command to Mars was not one of the party, but was none the less determined to carry out his nefarious design.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
On the night preceding the proposed treachery, Neptune visited her husband in his sleep, and told him that she had seen a vision of his seizure at the morrow's feast. Under the flowing festal robes presented by his host, Mars consequently donned his fighting jerkin and concealed his arms, and bade all his escort follow his example; these at the feast were to be ready at his signal to form a compact body and fight their way out of the hall, while the bulk of his escort were to await them outside. He sent some of his men to lounge near the city gate by which he proposed to escape, with orders to seize the guard and hold the gate on arrival of his messengers, and he stationed a few swift runners to carry to them the news, so soon as they should hear the sound of his war-conch.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In the midst of the feast, as Castor was making a stately speech to his chief guest, he signaled to those chosen to seize the visitors, and Mars was suddenly pinioned from behind. With a desperate wrench, the powerful warrior shook himself free as he sprang to his feet, and the rear of his conch crushed through the hall, so startling his assailants that they for a moment fell back, fearstricken. The pause was sufficient. Alcyone, Herakles, Vajra and others rushed towards him and guarded his sides and back, while, striking down Castor with one mighty blow of his clenched fist for he would not slay the man whose bread he was eating he swiftly charged through the crowd to the door of the banqueting hall. In a moment he was among his men, who had sprung to their horses at the sound of his conch and had galloped into the inner courtyard, bringing the horses of Mars and his comrades, and ere the guards of Castor had recovered from their stupor, Mars and his men were away, in headlong flight through the streets to the appointed gate, where the trusted Captain, Capella who, warned by the runners, had meanwhile captured the guards and substituted for them his own men, locked them with the heavy keys, and trotted away with these across his horse's neck, waiting for explanation of the proceedings until a more convenient moment.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Mars had too arduous work in hand to turn his army back to punish the aggressors; moreover he had no time to waste on reducing the city by starvation a work of years and no arms wherewith to take it by assault. So he pressed onward to his determined goal, laid the foundations of the future city, appointed Vulcan as governor, with Alcyone and Herakles under him, and himself, with Vajra and a picked troop, set out for his far off camp, to bring down the women and children. Gathering all together, he started again for his new city, which he named Ravipur, and arrived there after a wearisome journey; encumbered as a camp, he did not succeed in travelling more than seven or eight miles a day.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 It is only fair to mention that Castor on reflection was ashamed of the trick that he had tried to play upon Mars, and had the moral courage to send trick that he had tried to play upon Mars, and had the moral courage to send an embassy to apologise. Mars responded to this by sending Capella back with friendly gifts to conclude a treaty of alliance with Castor, and by way of cementing this, Castor's eldest son Aries was married to Capella's daughter Demeter a union which turned out happily for all concerned.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Beside the large band of our characters who marched into India with Mars, we find a considerable number who were not chosen for the migration, but stayed behind in the Central Asian kingdom with his aunt Mercury. The latter had married Viraj, and from this union, and that of Viraj's sister Viola with Spes, descended several families, among whom are about forty of the people whose fortunes we have been following.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
From this time onward events moved along ordinary courses skirmishes with sorrounding tribes, embassies to neighbouring Chiefs, cultivation of land, and the business of a great settlement. Mars passed away at about the age of sixty-five, leaving Herakles to succeed him, with Alcyone  as his most trusted councillor and dearest friend.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone died at the age of sixty, in 17,404 B.C., his wife preceeding him by a few years. Herakles died soon after Alcyone, never recovering quite from the loss.  The better half of myself is gone,  he said sadly;  why should I remain behind?  Not considering that either of his sons Gem and Arcor was sufficiently steady and reliable to succeed him, he named his brother Siwa as his successor, and sent his sons away, each with a strong troop and caravan, to found cities for themselves. 
</view>
</text>
</body>