<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 14
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 14-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Here we have another of those royal lives lived in Manoa referred to by Surya in his Irish Prophecy
      which played so large a part in the development of our hero. He was not this time directly in the
      line of succession to the throne, for his father was Selene, the brother of the King; but he lived
      in the immediate neighbourhood of the palace, and Herakles, the eldest son of the monarch, was his
      greatest friend. Indeed, we have in this life a triumvirate of boys always together, as in the
      eleventh life; but as this time Alcyone's previous companions, Saturn and Electra, belonged to an
      earlier generation (Saturn being Alcyone's mother and Electra his uncle) the comrades of his
      adventures on this occasion were cousins, Herakles and Naga.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Happening to be of the same age, and being thrown a great deal together, these three very early
      became inseparables, and their friendship was cemented by a curious incident which occurred when
      they were about twelve years old. They were away in one of the outer suburbs of the city, having
      returned from a long ramble towards the mountains, when they came on an unpleasant scene. A number
      of rough boys and hobbledehoys of the lower classes were making fun of one who was obviously a
      foreigner shouting insulting remarks after him, and even pelting him with mud. The victim was an
      old man, somewhat Mongolian in appearance, dressed in a strange foreign garb, and assisting himself
      as he walked by a curious carved ivory staff. He was hobbling along hurriedly, and trying to ignore
      the rudeness of his assailants; but when one of the bigger louts pushed another against him and
      almost threw him down, he turned upon them angrily and struck at them with his ivory staff. At this
      the young ruffians took to throwing stones instead of mud; and one of these, striking the old man
      on the head, felled him to the ground, and the crowd rushed in upon him.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Our boys had realised the condition of affairs when some distance away, and they at once started
      running towards the scene of conflict, and it was just at this crisis that they arrived. Though
      some of the roughs were much bigger and stronger than they, they atonce sprang upon them and tore
      them away from the old man. The whole group was cowed by the suddenness of this unexpected assault,
      but after a few moments seeing only three small boys, they turned upon them savagely and made as if
      to attack them. Our three stood round the old man, who now sat up and looked about him in a dazed
      sort of way; and Herakles seized the ivory staff, and held it out towards the menacing crowd,
      shouting.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      I am the son of the King, and I order you instantly to retire .
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It is probable that some of the ruffians recognised him, for after a few hurried whispers they drew
      back sullenly, and the little crowd gradually melted away, so that our three boys were able to turn
      their attention to the elderly stranger whom they had rescued. He thanked them effusively for their
      aid, saying that but for them he would have been seriously hurt and quite possibly killed, and he
      begged them to believe that he would not show himself ungrateful. Herakles asked him to come at
      once to the palace, saying that he would lay a complaint directly before his father, but the old
      man thanked him and declared that he would rather go to his own home, and leave the punishment of
      his assailants to fate.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      At least, then, said Herakles, let us accompany you to your home, if you will not come with us to
      the palace; for perhaps these rascals may still be lurking in the neighbourhood, and at any rate
      you seem to be weak and tired.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The old man ( who has previously been known to us as Laxa) seemed touched by the kindness offered
      him, and allowed them to accompany him without further protest, Alcyone asking him to rest his hand
      on his shoulder and lean upon him as he walked. In this order, then , they passed through several
      streets, and at last came to a quarter of a city unknown to our three boys, and to a somewhat
      mean-looking house in it which the old man said was his home. He asked them to honour him by coming
      in, and glancing at one another, they accepted his offer, for they all felt considerable curiosity
      with regard to him. Naga, especially, had been examining the curious ivory stick, and had asked him
      a question about it, to which he gave a rather mysterious reply that it was of far greater
      importance than it appeared to be. So they were glad of the opportunity of entering his house, and
      they found that the inside by no means corresponded with the somewhat squalid outer appearance. The
      rooms were much larger than they had expected from so poor an entrance, and it was evident that
      this was by no means the abode of a poverty stricken person. There was not much in the way of
      furniture, but what there was seemed good in quality, though evidently of foreign manufacture;
      there were rich draperies of brilliant colouring, and many curiosities hanging on the walls and
      lying about. The old man noticed their evident curiosity, and seemed gratified by it.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      I suppose, he said, you did not expect such rooms in a house which seem so poor.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      When they assented he continued: I am not quite so poor as I find it advised to appear in a country
      where men of my race are despised and often ill-treated. I can assure you that you will find me not
      ungrateful for the great kindness which you have shown me, and perhaps my gratitude may not be so
      entirely worthless as at first sight it might seem to be.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The boys understood but little of the meaning of his talk, but they saw that he intended to be
      friendly, and their native courtesy induced them to treat so old a man with deference. They were
      much interested in many curiosities in the room, and Laxa seemed pleased to show in many of the
      curiosities in the room, and Laxa seemed pleased to show them to them, and to explain their
      character and use. Presently he struck upon a beautifully-chased gong, and a servant appeared, to
      whom he gave orders to bring refreshment. The boys at first demurred, but the old man pressed food
      upon them so insistently that they were afraid of hurting his feelings by refusing, and
      consequently partook of some curious little sweet cakes with an odd spicy flavour quite new in
      their experience.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      After talking for some time, he said; Now what shall I do for you, to prove my gratitude to you for
      saving my life?
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Herakles protested against this, saying that they desired no reward for doing what any gentleman
      would have done, and other boys expressed full agreement with what he said.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Very well, then, said Laxa, since you put it in that way I will not insult you by the offer of
      presents of any kind. Yet I will confer upon you the greatest benefit which it is in my power to
      give. Poor as I appear, I hold high office in a powerful secret Society in my own land. Young as
      you are, and old as I am, you have yet stood by me and succoured me as if you were of my own race
      and family; therefore, as you will take no other reward from me, I will admit you as brothers of my
      Society; and let me tell you that although you may think that a matter of but little importance
      here in Manoa, you will find that wherever there is a man of my race he will be your servant
      because of what you have done to-day, when you show him the sign that I shall give you.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The boys again glanced at one another, doubting whether these proceedings would meet the approval
      of their parents and leaders; but they were devoured by curiosity to know more about this strange
      old man and the secret Society of which he spoke, and they felt that at any rate they might as well
      see what, if anything, it required of them. So Herakles somewhat hesitatingly signified his
      consent, and the other two boys were quite ready to follow his lead.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Laxa then explained to him that long ago his country had been conquered by a neighbouring race
      conquered finally by an act of treachery so gross that it made all really friendly relation between
      the races impossible for ever. He said that his people had become unwarlike through centuries of
      peace, and that they were unable to resist these foreign rulers; but they had banded themselves
      together in various secret societies, and by means of these they contrived to maintain themselves,
      and to keep the tyranny of the foreigners to some extent in check. Now that foreign dynasty had
      come under the rule of Manoa, and matters were much better than they had been previously; but it
      was the custom of the Empire of Manoa to recognise the ruling classes in the countries which came
      under its control, and as far as possible to continue them in offices which they had previously
      held. Consequently the hated conquering race still held their position as a sort of noble caste,
      and much of the power was even yet in their hands; so there was still much ill feeling, though the
      old hatred was to some extent dying down.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      There were several of these secret societies, he said and they differed much in their aims; that to
      which he himself had the honour to belong was not one of those which resorted to the extreme
      measures of arson and assassination; it was rather a brotherhood all the members of which were
      sworn to help one another in the case of need, and to defend one another against aggression. He
      explained to them that as they were not citizens of his country it would mean to them only that
      they were sure of help from any of his countrymen whenever they might meet them; and that if they
      ever should in later life visit his native land it would at once put them on the footing of friends
      instead of strangers, and enable them to enter into the inner life of the people in a way which
      without such a passport would be entirely impossible. All that he asked of them was a pledge to
      regard and to treat as brothers one who could show them the sign of the brotherhood.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This they readily consented to do, and Laxa then proceeded to teach them a certain sign whereby
      they might recognise other members whenever they encountered them. He told them also that all
      members of this Society bore its seal, indelibly impressed upon the inside of their arm just below
      the armpit, and he asked them whether they were willing to bear this sign. Joyously scenting an
      unusual adventure, the boys eagerly agreed, and Laxa thereupon struck his gong again and when the
      servant appeared, gave him some directions in a strange language. As a result of these the man
      brought a little piece of apparatus which looked not at all unlike an ordinary seal, except that
      the pattern on the seal was marked out by a number of tiny needle like points. He asked them to
      bare their arms, and warned them that the imprint of the seal was for a few moments exceedingly
      painful; but that feeling he said, would soon pass away. He then performed his little operation,
      pressing the seal upon the arms of the boys in the place indicated and in rubbing upon the wound
      which was made a curious kind of paste.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The result of this operation was to impress upon the arm the sign of swastika in a beautiful
      crimson colour; but it naturally made the arm very painful, so the old man tied a small piece of
      wet cloth over the wound, and then sent them away, telling them that its effect would pass off and
      they would be all right in a day or two. He had exacted from them a promise to say nothing of their
      adventure to any one; and this promise they faithfully kept. As Laxa had said, after a day or two
      the inflammation passed away, and the only permanent result was a beautiful little piece of
      tattooing. Before leaving the old man the boys had asked whether they might call upon him again,
      and had been told that he would always be glad to see them ; so after a few weeks they repeated
      their visit, and were welcomed as before, Laxa telling them many exciting stories about his country.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This little adventure produced a considerable impression upon their minds an impression which was
      deepened by the fact that a few weeks later they happened, upon one of their numerous expeditions
      together, to meet two men of Mongolian extraction men who seemed to them to be of the same race as
      the old man whom they had rescued. It immediately occurred to them that here was an opportunity of
      putting his statements to the test; so Herakles made the mystic sign that had been taught to them.
      The men, who had looked stolid before, exhibited the liveliest interest, and instantly drew aside
      their cloaks and raised their arms so as to bring into view the sign of the swastika. As they had
      been instructed by the old man, our boys immediately responded by showing their signs in a similar
      way; and as soon as the Mongolians saw these they instantly knelt before them in the road with
      every appearance of reverence. Laxa had told the boys that the form in which he had impressed the
      sign upon them indicated their admission to the highest order of the society; and this difference
      in rank accounted for the great deference shown by the Mongolians, for on examination they saw that
      the mark borne by those men differed in certain respects from that which had been impressed upon
      them. This little incident, however, reassured them as to the genuineness of Laxa's statements, and
      they began to realize that the reward which he had given them was not so much a mere form as they
      had at first supposed. This fact, and the information which they gained from their old friend, gave
      them strong information which they gained from their old friend, gave them a strong interest in
      Mongolia and its people, and they determined that when they grew up they would contrive to travel
      in that part of the world and put their membership in this strange society to a practical test.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It was however a good many years later when the opportunity to do this actually came their way; but
      the old interest still survived, and they were eagerly desirous to take it. It was the custom of
      the country that scions of the royal house should hold the governorships of the provinces of the
      empire; and the opportunity which offered itself was that a governorship in a remote part of what
      is now the Chinese empire fell vacant when our hero had reached the age of twenty-two. Herakles,
      being the heir to the throne was precluded from taking any appointments of this nature; but Alcyone
      immediately applied for the post, and to the surprise of his father and his other relations, who
      regarded him as too young to undertake such responsibilities so far away from the capital. However
      he insisted upon his desire to take this office, and as there was no competition for it, it was
      eventually assigned to him; and Naga's eager application to go as his assistant was also admitted.
      Thus it happened that these two young princes set off together on a journey which was to have an
      unexpected termination.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      They rode for many months before they reached the province over which Alcyone was to rule. When
      they did reach it their reception was far from satisfactory, for immediately upon crossing its
      borders their little party fell into an ambush, and was attacked from all sides by armed men whom
      they then supposed to be robbers. In the first wild rush Alcyone was struck down, and the Aryan
      soldiers were swept along in confusion for some distance. Then Naga, quickly assuming the command,
      rallied them and by a few quick evolutions enabled them to get room to re-form and to use their
      weapons. When this was done, they soon drove before them the armed mob which had attacked them,
      which seemed in a moment to fall into inextricable confusion and to begin to fight among
      themselves. These men were in full flight, and many of them were killed; but when the bodyguard got
      back to the place where Alcyone had fallen his body was nowhere to be seen. The prisoners whom they
      took were interrogated, but none of them would admit that he knew anything about it. A careful and
      exhaustive search was made of the whole neighbourhood, but no trace of the missing leader could be
      found, and they were at last reluctantly compelled to abandon all hope of recovering his body.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Enquiry showed that the attack had been engineered by one of the secret societies, of which the old
      man had spoken to them the Society of the Blue Spear, which had the reputation of being the most
      extreme and the most anarchistic of all such organisations. Naga, full of grief and rage at the
      loss of his leader, promptly made prisoners of all the men upon whose body the blue spear-head
      could be found, and drove them before him on his march. Presently he was met by a deputation
      representing the ruling classes of the province a deputation which had come out to receive the new
      Governor, and appeared to be overwhelmed with grief and anxiety at the tragedy which had occurred.
      Naga told them shortly that unless and until Alcyone reappeared he himself proposed to take
      command, and while he was Willing to accept their professions of loyalty, it could be
      satisfactorily proved to him only by the discovery of the body of Alcyone, and the punishment of
      those who had slain him. The notables of the country assured him of their profound grief and of
      their thorough co-operation with him in his endeavour to sift the matter to the bottom.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      All members who could be proved to belong to the Blue Spear Society were put under arrest, a
      searching investigation was made, and the existence of a widely extended plot was unearthed. It was
      discovered that the heads of this illicit organisation had concocted a plan to seize upon the
      government of the province and massacre the ruling classes; and as a preliminary they had thought
      it well to remove the new Governor.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      But although the existence of the plot was freely admitted, no information could be obtained as to
      its result; the survivors of the attack declared that they themselves had been mysteriously
      attacked in turn, not only by the handful of Aryan soldiers, but by others whom they did not know.
      So many people separately told this strange story that it seemed as though there must be some
      foundation for it; but Naga could obtain no satisfaction, though he distinctly acquired the
      impression that the people whom he was cross-examining were speaking the truth as far as they knew
      it.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In this extremity it occurred to him to make use of the secret sign of the Society of the Crimson
      Swastika, and although that met with no response among the ruling classes who surrounded him, it
      quickly brought him recognition from others among the people who, as soon as they knew of his rank
      within their Society, immediately put their whole organisation at his command. They were able at
      once to explain the mystery of the failure of the Blue Spear attack. They had themselves received
      information of it, and it was their members who had intervened and come at the critical moment to
      the assistance of the Aryan Guard. They were, however, unable to throw any light upon the
      disappearance of the body of Alcyone.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Profound as was his sorrow for his cousin, Naga felt the business of the state must be carried on.
      He therefore assumed the office of Governor, and despatched an embassy to Mars with a full report
      of all that had happened, and an intimation that he held the province on behalf of the King until
      he should be confirmed or until someone else should be appointed. Then he settled down to the
      business of administration, but he first of all made it a point to stamp out of existence the Blue
      Spear Society, and in this he invoked the services of the Crimson Swastika. He was successful up to
      a certain point; but he had the impression all the while that something was eluding him, for he
      frequently came across traces of some other hidden force of far greater power which he was yet
      unable to identify. He stated this impression quite plainly in the secret meetings of his Society,
      and its local leaders agreed with him, yet they were unable to solve the mystery, although the
      surface administration appeared to be most successful, and the affairs of the province moved
      smoothly and prosperously. This secret uncertainty caused Naga constant inward anxiety; he felt
      keenly the responsibility of his position and often longed to be able to discuss it with his old
      comrades, Herakles and Alcyone, and to advise with them as he would have done in the days gone by.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Matters went on in this way for some months, during which Naga's feeling of irritation increased
      all the while, for he found himself foiled again and again at various points by some intangible
      opposition. Finally this incomprehensible but ever recurring difficulty got upon his nerves to such
      an extent that he called a council of all the heads of the Crimson Swastika of the whole province a
      secret meeting to which only those with the highest credentials were admitted. Before them he laid
      his case and recapitulated his reasons for feeling certain of the existence of some powerful
      organisation which was entirely unknown to them, although they supposed themselves to have spies in
      every part of the country, and to be thoroughly well informed as to what was going on. The heads of
      the organisation maintained that it was quite impossible that such a body could exist without their
      knowledge; yet they were unable to explain satisfactorily the indications which Naga pointed out to
      them. He demanded that a more searching investigation should be made, and blamed the leaders for
      the inefficiency of their arrangements; but they were quite unable to suggest any further steps for
      the elucidation of the mystery.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Just as they had come to this unsatisfactory conclusion the guard of the door of the chamber came
      before them in a condition of manifest perturbation, declaring that there stood one at the door who
      gave the sign of the highest division of their order, although every member of that division in the
      country was already present in the hall. This seemed to imply the serious suggestion that the
      highest of their secrets were somehow in the hands of an outsider something which could have
      happened only by quite incredible treachery. The janitor asked what he should do; but Naga quickly
      decided that a brother who held the supreme secrets must at least be admitted, whatever steps it
      might be necessary to take afterwards. The doors were consequently thrown open, and a cloaked
      stranger came in. As he advanced up the hall he made a sign which all present instantly recognised,
      before which they rose in reverence; and when at last he came before Naga he threw back his hood
      and showed the face of Alcyone. Naga received him with a shout of incredulous surprise, but as soon
      as he realised that his cousin really stood before him, introduced him as the true Governor to the
      rest of the assembly, and then installed him in the President's chair.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone of course had a story to tell a very remarkable story. He had been knocked down and stunned
      in the attack by the Blue Spears but when the members of the Crimson Swastika, who had in turn been
      watching the watchers, poured out upon the Blue Spears and overthrew them, he was just recovering
      sufficiently to make a sign which they instantly recognised. They promptly bore him away from the
      field into a place of concealment, but while they were doing so he again relapsed into
      unconsciousness. When he recovered for the second time he found himself being most carefully and
      respectfully tended, for in the mean time they had discovered his rank in the order from the
      peculiar form of the seal impressed upon his arm.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It was sometime before he recovered perfectly from the blow which he had received and in the course
      of that recovery he learnt much from his temporary host about the condition of affairs in the
      country, and especially about the relations between the various secret societies. He was in the
      house of a high official of his own Society, and that official was in possession of a great deal of
      information about the inner workings of the hostile organisation of the Spear. Alcyone was
      intensely interested by what he heard of this, and he found his host to be in possession of
      knowledge by means of which it might be possible for them to pass themselves off as members of the
      inner circle of the Spear. Alcyone immediately resolved to devote himself to the discovery of the
      truth about this iniquitous organisation, and it occurred to him that he had now an unexampled
      opportunity of following the matter up in person in a way that as governor of the province he could
      not possibly have done. Officially he was supposed to be dead, and consequently he was free to make
      use of his knowledge; whereas as governor his every movement would have been known, and he must
      have made all the most critical investigations by deputy. Though regretting the sorrow that he knew
      this would cause to Naga, he felt that it might well be for the best interests of his province that
      he should take advantage of the opportunity that had thus fallen in his way, and that he and his
      host should disguise themselves thoroughly and endeavour to follow up the clues so providentially
      placed in their hands.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      They carried out this resolve; the succeeded in obtaining possession of the innermost secrets of
      the Spear, and they found that its strength lay in the existence of an inner circle which was
      unknown even to the rank and file of the Society an inner circle which, while it directed that
      outer society, also acted upon its own account and struck with unerring secrecy and dispatch. It
      cost Alcyone a vast amount of time and trouble to trace all the ramifications of this conspiracy,
      but eventually he came to know by sight all of its leaders, and he gathered together against them
      an overwhelming mass of evidence. During all the time that these investigations were in progress he
      remained closely hidden, his identity absolutely unsuspected except by his original host, whom he
      had bound over by his oath of obedience to maintain rigid secrecy. When at last he had all the
      information that he required and his schemes had fully matured, he came to the headquarters of his
      own Society with the intention of getting through it into communication with his cousin without as
      yet revealing himself to the outside public; and, as has been seen, he happened to arrive
      dramatically in the midst of a specially important meeting.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      That same night orders were sent out for the arrest of all the members of that inner circle of the
      Spear, and in the course of a few days Alcyone and Naga had every one of them safely in their
      hands. Only when that result was achieved did Alcyone declare himself to the country and take up
      the reins of government. The accused were brought before the proper courts and the whole story came
      out, and then for the first time the force which had all the time been thwarting Naga's best
      endeavours was discovered and exposed. The prisoners were duly brought before the appointed courts
      and condemned; the tyranny of the evil organisation was broken, and the land had rest from intrigue
      and conspiracy.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone and Naga spent many years in carrying on the administration of their province. Through
      their membership in the Society of the Crimson Swastika they gained the confidence and co-operation
      of the natives of the country, were able to meet them in intimate relations, and learned to
      understand their desires and aspirations. Mars, seeing that he had here enthusiastic subordinates,
      who thoroughly understood their work, wisely left them to do as they would; and the result was
      great contentment and prosperity in that far-distant province.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Both the cousins had been betrothed before they left home, and deep had been the sorrow in Manoa at
      the news of the supposed death of Alcyone; correspondingly great also the rejoicing when it came to
      be known that the report was false. As soon as the great conspiracy was definitely broken up, and
      it became certain that the province had entered upon an era of unexampled peace and prosperity, the
      governor and his assistant arranged that their future wives should journey out to them, and the
      double wedding was celebrated with great pomp and much national rejoicing.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      As the years rolled by large families grew up around them, and life went very well with them.
      Alcyone and Naga endeared themselves to all the people in their great province, travelling
      constantly about it, and obtaining private and detailed information as to the needs of the people
      through the organisation to which they belonged. On several occasions they paid visits to their
      relations at Manoa, Naga remaining in charge of the province when Alcyone was away, and Alcyone
      doing double work during the absence of Naga; but they were never both away simultaneously, until
      at the age of sixty Alcyone obtained from Herakles(who had by that time succeeded his father Mars)
      leave to retire and spend the rest of his days in his own country. Five years after his return
      Alcyone passed peacefully away, leaving behind him a record of efficient and useful work for his
      country.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
