<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 28
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 28-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      There was much movement and excitement in the central city of the Fifth Race settlement in Central
      Asia. Swetdwipa, the White island in the inland sea, whereon stood and stands Shamballa, the Sacred
      City, was indeed, pervaded as ever by the solemn peace which is the benediction of the high
      Presences that dwell there; but the adjoining city on the shore of the sea, taking its name from
      the Manu Manu's City was full of eager turmoil, for preparation were on foot for a great
      emigration, the greatest which we have so far observed. Once more the Manu had spoken and had
      demanded from Surya, the Deputy of the Mahaguru, the gift of His two sons, Mars and Mercury, to
      lead the vast host of emigrants. He had directed that the emigrants should be divided into three
      columns. One, forming the right wing, led by Corona a warrior of iron will and extraordinary
      ability, but also of indomitable pride was to cross the Himalayas through what is now Kashmir, and
      to find its way through the Punjab and the United Provinces to Bengal; the central and principal
      host, commanded by Mars who was the head of the three armies was to penetrate to Nepal through
      Tibet, and march from Nepal to Bengal; the central and principal host, commanded by Mars who was
      the head of the three armies was to penetrate to Nepal through Tibet, and march from Nepal to
      Bengal; the third, the left wing, under Vulcan, was to make its way across Tibet to Bhutan, and
      thence to Bengal. Thus the three armies were to converge on Northern Bengal, and subjugate that
      country, making it their home.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This migration seems to have been one of special importance, and a large number of familiar figures
      were concerned in it. No less than ten who are now Masters are found playing important parts, to
      say nothing of their many disciples who have followed Them through the ages. A great ceremony
      preceded the setting out of the vast hosts. In the temple of the Sacred city on the White Island,
      in the great Hall of Audience with its massive chair hewn out of living rock, covered with golden
      mouldings that scarce allowed the rock to peep through were gathered the most august of Figures. In
      the centre, in front of the chair but at the foot of its seven steps, towered the mighty form of
      Vaivasvata, the Manu, the typical man of the Fifth Root-Race. Clustering hair of dark brown shot
      with gold fell upon His shoulders, and the massive beard of like hue rolled, thick-curling, over
      His breast; eagle-eyed, with brows slightly arched and shadowing the eyes into darkness, save when
      the lids, normally somewhat dropped, were lifted suddenly and the eyes flashed out dazzlingly,
      compelling all who looked on Him to veil their gaze; the nose high and arched, the lips curved and
      set firmly. A King of men, truly; one whose word meant Law, whose lifted hand impelled or
      restrained at will.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Beside Him, on His right, stood the Mahaguru, His priestly Brother, the Head of the Religion of the
      community. Stately and mighty also was He, but while the Manu breathed resistless Will and every
      gesture spoke of Rule, this Blessed One breathed Love most compassionate, and a Wisdom as pure and
      deep as the Manu's Will was mighty. His hair dusky as ebony, His eyes of darkest violet, almost
      black, His mouth tender, easily curving into a gracious smile. Seeking His name, we find many in
      the people's minds as though reverence and love sought varied expression; often Pita, Deospita,
      Vyas, Sarvajnarshi, Sugata, Ravidas, Ushadas, Mahamuni, Jnanraja such are some of the names by
      which the people love Him. On the left side of the Manu stands Surya, with radiant hair and shining
      eyes eyes that dwell with deep affection on His noble sons, the chief figures in the crowd facing
      the alter, which stands between the Heads of the community and Their people.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      They are clad with great magnificence; a long cloak of cloth of gold with heavy jewelled clasps
      falls around Their feet; the Mahaguru and Surya have, beneath this, long white robes of finest
      material; the Manu wears a double-like garment of rich crimson, reaching below His knees, the legs
      and feet bare. They are waiting, expectant, for the overshadowing presence of the Mighty Lords of
      the Flame, who are to appear to bless the departing hosts.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The leaders of the army stand close to the ancient Alter, whereon each has placed his favourite
      weapon, mace, or axe, or sword, facing their Chiefs. Mars is in the centre, with his wife Brihat on
      his left, and Mercury upon his right. Mercury's wife, Saturn, is beside him, and by her, again,
      stands Vulcan. On Brihat's left is Corona, who had once in a previous birth ruled as an Emperor of
      the city of the Golden Gate in far Atlantis. A noble quartet of warriors they looked, with their
      stately wives, full worthy of them.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      A group of children sat beyond the Alter, a little awed by the great Figures on whom their eyes
      were fixed; they were the children of Mars and Mercury; Jupiter, a noble boy of ten years of age,
      the eldest son of Mars, with his sisters Osiris, Uranus and Ulysses, his brother Siwa, a chubby boy
      of two, and in the arms of Osiris, the eight years-old maiden, a baby boy, Viraj, who gazed with
      solemn eyes upon the Three. Mercury's eldest son was Selene, a thoughtful-looking boy, about the
      age of Jupiter, his arm thrown round the youngest girl, Mizar, a restless babe scarce twelve months
      old; his brothers Leo and Vajra sat, with arms round each other's shoulders; the sisters Herakles
      and Alcyone sat nested together, little maids of five and three, for Alcyone had been born in
      15,995, and Herakles was two years her elder and a little inclined to be protective of her junior.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      There is a great hush, for a single note rings through the great Hall, clear as a silver clarion,
      and a brilliant Light blazes out above the rock-hewn chair. The assembly bows down, for in the
      chair is seated a marvellous Figure, dazzling, an emboldened Power, and behind Him are three
      Others, only less great than He. They are the four Kumaras of Indian Scriptures, the Lords of the
      Flame.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Go forth, my children, and do my work; my strength is upon you. Having wrought return.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The accents fall upon the hushed stillness; a hand is raised in blessing, and when the heads bent
      low in reverence are raised, the chair is empty and the Light is gone.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Surya stepped out and blessed his sons, who bent the knee before him and then, stooping, raised the
      little Alcyone, his favorite grand daughter, and drew close to him the sturdier form of Herakles:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      My little ones, he said, and his tender face grew gently solemn, on a far rough way you go. Mothers
      of brave men you shall be, and fair women also shall call each of you mother'. Your race shall
      dwell long in the land and thither also you shall come again many times, to learn and teach. But
      this is the first of the lives of expiation, that old Karma may be outworn, old wrongs made right.
      Death shall come to both of you together, in strange and violent way. In that hour, call on me and
      I will come to you, and the Light you have just now seen shall shine in the darkness then.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Little Alcyone hid her face in his neck and laughed softly; she did not understand, but she loved
      her grandfather; and Herakles looked up boldly, unwitting the gravity of the prophecy; I shall call
      loud, so that you will hear, and Jupiter, who always called Herakles his little wife, said proudly:
      I will take care of you.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Long and arduous was the journey, and many years had passed ere the three commanders met again.
      Corona found his way south fairly easily, as the road through Kashmir was known, and the people of
      the settled portions were not unfriendly. But on reaching the Punjab he fell out with the
      inhabitants almost from the beginning, and presently he had to fight his way through a hostile
      country. He besieged the great Toltec city, now under Aryan rule, where Mars had been betrayed some
      fifteen hundred years before, and at length reduced it by starvation, and made its ruler swear
      fealty to himself; he next subdued Ravipur near the site of the modern Delhi and established there
      one of his own officers as a tributary King; he pressed southwards, ever fighting and reducing his
      enemies to submission, till he had carved himself out an empire, with half a hundred tributary
      chiefs. Forty years had rolled away ere he reached Bengal, an aged warrior of over seventy years of
      age, to find Mars settled in Central Bengal, having founded and established his kingdom.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Vulcan had found his way through Tibet and Bhutan a good sixteen years earlier, had joined his
      forces with those of Mars, and in 15,953 had invaded Assam, and had there established himself in
      fairly peaceful possession by the time Corona arrived, in 15,952 B.C. Much however had happened ere
      that, and our hero, or rather heroine, is with Mars, and to her fortunes we must turn.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The route of Mars, on leaving Central Asia, took him in four years across the great Range into
      Tibet, and he remained there for a full year, to rest the feebler members of his army-caravan, ere
      they began the toilsome road across the mountains to Nepal. During this time Castor was born, and
      much time was given daily to training the boys of the party in athletics of every sort. Jupiter was
      the leader in all manly exercises, and among the boys whom he formed into a troop, which he trained
      in scouting and mimic warfare, we note his cousins Leo, Vajra and Selene, Vajra making up for his
      juvenility by his reckless daring and extreme activity and their friends Albeiro and Arcor.
      Alcyone, a girl between seven and eight, was a somewhat dreamy maiden, quiet and thoughtful, more
      apt to sit at home than to roam abroad. She would sing softly to herself the chants to the angels
      of her people and lose herself in visions as she sang.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      At the end of the fifth year since leaving Manoa, the army started again on its way, and climbed
      slowly over the mountains which lay between Tibet and Nepal. It tried to follow the course of a
      mountains which lay between eastwards and southwards, but was constantly forced to turn aside when
      the river plunged into impassable gorges and foamed through ravines where the cliffs almost closed
      above it. There were many skirmishes with hill-tribes, but no serious fighting until two years
      later they approached Nepal, where Mars found himself obliged to divide his army, leaving half
      under Mercury to guard the huge entrenched camp, and going out himself with remainder of his troops
      to subdue the country sufficiently to make a safe road for his people. He took with him his eldest
      son, Jupiter, and his young troop, Mercury specially bidding his son Vajra learn the soldierly duty
      of obedience. One attempt was made to rush the camp during his absence, but Mercury repelled it
      without great difficulty and with little loss of life. It is a pretty scene to see Mercury seated
      with his wife and sister-in-law, with Alcyone nestling on his breast, and a girl-friend Capri,
      Herakles' special chum, leaning against his knee, as he told them stories of Surya and the
      Mahaguru, and sometimes, speaking softly and low, of the great Kumaras whom they had seen ere
      leaving Manoa. Herakles was a more restless child, and her eyes would rove eagerly over the camp
      outside while her father was speaking, bringing on herself sometimes a solemn reproof from the more
      demure Capri. Osiris and Uranus also, with little Viraj, were interested auditors while Ulysses was
      apt to sympathise with Herakles' wandering gaze.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Two years passed before the waiting camp again welcomed Mars and joyous were the greetings which
      met the returning wanderers. He had secured a passage through Nepal, partly by fighting, partly by
      diplomacy, and the whole caravan set out, a couple of months later, in early summer. That winter
      they camped near the borders of Nepal, resuming their journey the following summer, and thus slowly
      they went forwards, marching during the summer, camping in the winter, and spending weary years on
      the way ere they reached India itself.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Meanwhile the sisters had grown into stately and handsome maidens, inheriting something of the
      beauty and grace of their father and mother. Herakles was now eighteen, and Alcyone sixteen, and
      Mars sought his favourite niece as wife for his eldest son, while the sweet ways and gentle eyes of
      Alcyone had won the heart of Albeiro, Jupiter's brother in arms. Demure Capri had become the ideal
      of Arcor, whose own somewhat stormy nature found rest and refreshment in her gentle household ways,
      and the three pairs were married ere the army left its winter camp in 15,979 B.C.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Mars led his great host peacefully through the extreme north of Bengal that summer, and camped
      along a huge river when marching time was over. Here he determined to wait the arrival of Vulcan
      and Corona, in order that their united forces might take possession of the land, and that he might
      there build up his kingdom. Another two years, however, elapsed before the approach of Vulcan was
      reported to him. Nothing whatever was to be heard of Corona, and after waiting for a third year,
      Mars, Mercury and Vulcan decided to press on without him. They left the women and children in an
      entrenchment camp in northern Bengal (15,975 B.C.) while they marched southwards, taking with them
      Jupiter, Albeiro, Selene and Leo, through a fertile but only thinly settled land, and at intervals
      the army stopped and threw up strong embankments, protected by deep trenches which seem to have
      become easily filled up with water, the water being thus drained away from a considerable
      surrounding area, which was readily cultivable, and afforded splendid grazing grounds for cattle.
      Mars detached at each of these settlements a considerable body of troops, leaving them orders to
      make broad and firm roads between the camps; after five years of this marching and building, he
      placed Vulcan in authority over the whole of the conquered land, directing him to return to the
      northern camp, taking with him all those who wished to settle down there with their wives and
      children, as well as a large force, sufficient to guard the great numbers that were to settle in
      the various camps established in Bengal. He himself determined to continue his march southwards,
      and arranged to return to the place where they parted after another five years.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Vulcan accordingly started visiting all the settlements on his way north; he found them prosperous
      and busy, the scattered inhabitants of the country having entered into friendly relations with
      them, often taking service as cowherds, laborers and so on. He pressed on northwards till he
      reached the original camp (15,967 B.C.) and was joyfully welcomed by its inhabitants. He found a
      few newcomers there; before they had parted Herakles had given birth to a son, Bee, and a daughter,
      Canopus; Alcyone to two sons, Neptune and Psyche, while Capri had borne Arcor a daughter, a pretty
      little girl, Pindar, and a son, Altair. To these had been added Aletheia, son of Herakles, Rigel,
      daughter of Alcyone, and Adrona, son of Arcor. The three older children, Bee, Neptune and Pindar
      were of an age eleven years old, having been born in winter of 15,978 and were as inseparable as
      their mothers, while remaining trio, Canopus, Psyche and Altair were equally fond of each other.
      Each little maiden had her two knights, Pindar being everywhere accompanied by Bee and Neptune,
      Canopus by Psyche and Altair. A happy childhood was theirs, playing on foot and on ponyback, rough
      unkempt ponies, and gathering at eventide with their mothers, to tell of the day's delight, and to
      listen to stories of the land the mothers had left in childhood, above all to the story of the
      great Temple from the lips of Alcyone, and the august Figures their childish eyes had seen.
      Aletheia, Rigel and Adrona were but seven years of age, pretty healthy children, much petted by the
      uncles of the two first-named, Vajra and Castor, the younger sons of Mercury.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Vulcan gathered together all the families whose heads or elder members had followed Mars, and took
      them southwards, leaving each group with their long separated men relatives in the settlement where
      these were dwelling. Joyous were the meetings, saddened here and there by gaps in family circles,
      when death had swept away by disease or violence those who were not to meet again their loved ones
      upon earth.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Meanwhile Mars had gone southwards, and soon found himself engaged in a long series of skirmishes
      and battles, for the country he invaded was thickly populated with people of Atlantean blood, and
      as he approached the sea-board these became more warlike, and offered more resistance to his
      advance. At last he had to fight a serious pitched battle, to which the King of the Orissa country
      had summoned all his hosts: his priests, followers of the Atlantean dark magic, had incited the
      troops to fury by fiery harangues, and had rendered them, as they believed, invincible by human
      sacrifices offered to their gloomy elemental deities in the huge temple near the sea which was the
      most sacred centre of their worship, a temple of unknown antiquity and cyclopean architecture of
      the Lemurian type, standing in what is now the town of Puri. In the dim recesses of that temple, on
      the night before the battle joined, the priests had gathered in unholy conclave, and with ghastly
      rites and furious invocations had summoned their dark deities to give battle to the radiant angels
      of the Aryan invaders.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      At daybreak the decisive battle began, and for five days it raged; Mars and Mercury led their hosts
      with dauntless valour, well seconded by their sons and their faithful friends, among whom Arcor was
      conspicuous for his reckless courage. Great was the slaughter, but, as the fifth day darkened into
      evening, the hosts of Orissa were in headlong fight and the victorious Aryans chased them
      southwards, and encamped for the night in the camp that their enemies had left. Mars appeared to
      have carried a charmed life, but all the other leaders were wounded more or less, and very weary
      were the hosts that slept.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Rising ere daybreak, as was their wont, strange and new was the sight before the eyes of those who,
      all unknowing had camped near the sea-shore. Never had they seen the broad expanse of the ocean,
      and loud cries of wonder and of awe burst from these children of the desert and the mountain as the
      huge plain of heaving waters burst upon their gaze in the dim twilight ere the dawn, and the waves
      rippled to their feet, making them start back in fear. Their leaders came out at the shouts of the
      soldiers, wondering if the enemy had returned in force. Transfixed they also stood, and, as they
      gazed, the eastern sky began to redden towards the dawn; they watched, breathless, and suddenly the
      crimson globe of the Sun flung itself upwards from the waters, as though it leaped from the bosom
      of the deep, and Mars and Mercury threw themselves upon their faces and the red rays blazed across
      the ocean, and the cry: Samudra! Samudra! rang from a thousand throats. The Sun had been Pushan,
      the Nourisher, Pantha, the Path, as he guided them over the deserts; now he was born of the sea, in
      the magical wonder of the dawning.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The neck of the resistance was broken, and Mars established the centre of his kingdom to the north
      of Orissa, in Central Bengal, leaving Jupiter, his eldest son, in charge of Orissa, with Albeiro,
      Leo and Arcor as his lieutenants. He departed to keep his tryst with Vulcan, promising that Mercury
      should return and bring with him the families of all left to settle in that part of his realm.
      Immediately after this Vulcan parted from Mars and invaded and conquered Assam, setting up there
      his kingdom with little difficulty.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In due course Mercury returned, bringing with him his noble wife, Saturn, and his sons Viraj and
      Castor, and his three daughters, Herakles, Alcyone and Mizar. He brought with him also Uranus, to
      be the bride of Leo, and Aurora to wed Selene. Arcor joyfully welcomed his fondly loved Capri and
      his sons Altair and Adrona.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And now came many years of hard work, the building up of a kingdom, interspersed with occasional
      wars of defense skirmishes with predatory bands, endeavours to conciliate the former owners of the
      country, and efforts to put down human sacrifices. Once during these years Mars paid a visit to his
      children, bringing with him his sons Siwa and Viraj, and his daughter Ulysses. Osiris had married
      and could not leave her home. On this occasion Vajra and Ulysses were wed, and after much
      discussion, the parents decided to leave these two as rulers of Orissa, and to return themselves to
      the northern capital, taking with them Jupiter and his family; for Mars was very old, and wished to
      install his eldest son upon the throne and retire from the world with Mercury and their wives. This
      was done, and Vajra and Ulysses were left in charge.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      For a time all went apparently well, but a storm was gathering below the surface. Vajra did not
      show the skill in conciliation characteristic of Jupiter, and his measures, aimed to bring about
      good results, were sometimes harsh. In 15,937 B.C. a great religious festival of the old religion
      was to be held, and Vajra had, the year before, forbidden its celebration, knowing the danger of
      such a concourse, excited by sacrifices and incantations. Herakles had come to spend some months
      with Alcyone, for the twain were not happy when apart, and she having become learned in the deeper
      knowledge of the Atlantean White Magic and having wedded it to the worship of the bright Gods
      worshipped in her ancient home began teaching this mingled philosophy and religion to the younger
      men and women of her brother's kingdom, and she included in her classes some of the younger priests
      of the dark Atlantean faith. This was to strike a deadly blow to the still powerful priesthood, and
      ere long the muttering of hatred grew deep and angry.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      As the months passed, the growlings grew louder, and a conspiracy was formed to attack the house of
      Albeiro, where Herakles and Alcyone were living, while he was away on a projected journey with
      Vajra to a distant part of the country. The priesthood resolved that the forbidden celebration
      should take place, and with victims nobler than the common herd; and they diligently circulated
      rumours that a rising was to take place in the district whither Vajra and Albeiro were going. The
      result of this skillfully planned deception was that Vajra took with him the main part of his army,
      leaving a comparatively small force under Arcor to preserve order and defend his household.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It was 15,937 B.C. and the high day, or rather night, of the forbidden festival was near. The early
      morning dawned clear and cool, but scattered groups might be seen slowly converging to a centre,
      and that centre the house of Albeiro. The groups coalesced into a crowd; the crowd grew in number
      and denseness. Presently a deep clanging note clashed into the quiet: it was the note of the great
      bell of the temple, unheard for long, the bell that no longer might be sounded. The roar of the
      crowd answered the brazen voice of the bell, and in a moment a riot had broken out. The house of
      Albeiro was broken into, the guards slaughtered, and in front of the crowd, as it surged inwards,
      towered the tall gaunt form of the Atlantean High Priest, Scorpio, on whose head a price had long
      been set, and who had lain hidden in the underground vaults of the temple, known to none but the
      initiated priesthood. Ya-uli! Ya-uli!, shrieked the mob, half deeming him risen from the dead, and
      frenzied by religious excitement. A slow stern smile curved his iron lips as he heard his name
      re-echo, and turning, he waved back the yelling mob, and they stopped silent.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Wait, children of the Lord of the Dark Face; your day has come. I go to bring forth the accursed,
      the women of the barbarians of the North, who have crushed your worship and closed the temples of
      your Gods. Aiyo! Aiyo! The Lords have risen; they cry for blood, and blood shall they have. Slay !
      slay all but the two women who are theirs. They are mine, as the priest of the Gods who drink human
      blood and devour human flesh. Tonight shall their thirst be slaked and their hunger appeased, Aiyo!
      Aiyo ! I have said !
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Into the house he stalked, grim as death and stern as an incarnate Hate. At the first alarm Arcor
      had sounded his conch to summon his men, and , as they flung themselves into the passages and held
      the stairways, a fierce but hopeless combat had ended in their extermination. Arcor himself had
      rushed to the private entrance into the ladies' apartment, had struck down the priests who led the
      crowd Ya-uli cautiously withdrawing till the way was clear and had battled desperately, though
      alone, to bar the road. He fell, pierced by a score of wounds, and the Chief Priest stepped over
      his body to his prey.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone and Herakles were at their morning worship when the crash of breaking doors told them of
      danger, and as they rose, two tall and stately women Herakles, now at the age of sixty, crowned
      with silver hair, and Alcyone with dark tresses, silver streaked, falling below her waist the door
      of their worship-chamber burst open, and the tall Priest stood on the threshold. The two women
      faced him, a proud interrogation as to such intrusion spoken by the uplift of the noble heads, the
      gaze of the steady eyes.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Come, ye accursed! The day of your oppression is over; the night of your doom is near. Come, for
      the Dark Lords call. I am their messenger of vengeance.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Herakles threw her arm round her sister's slight form: Priest! You threaten those who know not
      fear. Begone ! invite not death.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      A harsh laugh grated on the air: Death, woman ! I give it, I do not accept it. Come forth: you are
      mine.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He made a gesture to some priests behind him; they came in and seized the women by the arms,
      drawing out cords to bind.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Bind not! said Herakles. We shall not flee. Come, dearest, come. Our father's daughters know how to
      die.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone glanced up at her sister, an angelic smile upon her face: I am ready, sister beloved.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And they moved slowly forward, surrounded by the priests, through the passages strewn with the
      bodies of the dead. Unblenching they went through the seething crowd, which yelled at them, shook
      clenched fists as they passed, and would have torn them in pieces had it not been for the priests
      they feared. Slowly they went onwards through the city to the place where yawned widely the mighty
      open gates of the temple, with long aisles of dark pillars glooming away into darkness.
      White-robed, fair skinned, the two sisters looked like angels of light amid the tossing crowd of
      dark faces and dark bare arms flung high in the air. At the gate the priests turned and Ya-uli
      spake:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      To-night, four hours after the sunset, the gates will be opened; let all children of the Lords of
      the Dark Face come to their festival. The gates clanged together, and Herakles and Alcyone were
      past all earthly help.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      At first, no harm was wrought on them; they were offered rich food and wine, but would not eat.
      Only fruit would they take, and a drink of milk. Then commenced a long persuasive talk; Ya-uli
      strove to win their promise to take part in the worship of the Dark Gods that night, pledging
      himself that they should return home in safety if they would thus purchase life with dishonor. In
      his false heart he meant to slay them after they had worshipped, but he longed to proclaim them
      renegades to their faith and so win credit for his own. Uselessly he strove against their steady
      will, and in wrath at last he bade the priests take them to the gloomy centre of the temple, and
      leave them there awhile.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      A dread and awful place it was in which they were left. Dim shapes, some red, some black, some
      sickly grey, were half visible through the gloom. Low moans, as of something in pain, came, dully
      muffled, to their ears.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Herakles, whispered Alcyone, are these things alive or dead? They make me shudder.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Darling, I know not, but living or dead, they cannot hurt the soul. They whispered to each other in
      the gloomy cavern, spoke of home, of husbands, of children, and then of the days of happy
      childhood, and the glorious vision of the past.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      I think the time has come, said Alcyone, and we shall see our grandfather again.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And the Light! breathed Herakles.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It was ten o'clock, and a dense crowd filled the huge dark building, silent, expectant, awe-struck.
      At a given sign the women were seized, and lifted upon a high altar, in view of all, and a lurid
      light, blood red shone out, none could say whence, and threw the awful figures around into grim
      semblance of life. There was a sound of rending cloth, and the robes of the two women were torn
      from them, and the fair white bodies shone out nude and shrinking. A low cry of horror burst from
      them, and then Herakles threw up her proud head and flung her arms around her sister, striving to
      shield her from the gaze of the rough crowd: You shame your mothers, men, in shaming us, she cried,
      and then stood silent. Look at them, called the Priest, before the Dark Lord feasts upon them. When
      next you see them, he shall have had his fill. And then the light faded, and the crowd filed out,
      to wait for the rites that none save the priests might see and live.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      How tell the horrors that ensued: flames rose from surrounding altars, and shrieking captives were
      led in, and the fire fed with fat skinned from their living bodies till the flames roared high;
      then their blood was set flowing and caught in iron vessels, and set to boil in huge iron pots, and
      poured upon the images set in the circle round; foul creatures of the slime, huge spiders,
      monstrous scorpions, fed on the remnants of the slime, huge spiders, monstrous scorpions, fed on
      the remnants of the mutilated bodies; and presently one after another of the images woke into awful
      life, began to stir, to slip downwards from their pedestals, obscene shapes of unimaginable horror,
      and crawled and writhed towards the centre where Alcyone and Herakles still stood, clasped in each
      other's arms. Fly! Fly! yelled the priests, the Dark Lord is coming, and his hosts are here! and
      they tumbled over each other in a mad rush to escape from the terror they had invoked.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Out of the darkness loomed a gigantic face a face of power majestic, of pain and wrath too deep for
      words, of intolerable weariness and despair. A mighty hand was waved, just visible by its own dull
      glow, as of hot iron half-quenched and the fearful figures rolled up around the alter and reared up
      red gaping mouths and hairy tearing claws. Then rang out the voice of Herakles, loud and clear:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Suryadeva, Suryadeva, Mahapita, come! Oh, come!
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And there, in the midst of all the horrors, there shone out the light on which the children's eyes
      had rested, and beneath it the radiant form of the Surya they knew, with tender eyes and
      outstretched arms; and with a sob of joy Alcyone sprang forward, and her body dropped lifeless on
      the alter. And all the horrid shapes shrivelled into nothingness, and lay about like the cast-off
      skins of snakes, and the pillars broke, and the cavern walls fell in, and the bodies of the sisters
      had for tomb the mighty temple of the Lord of the Dark Face.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And that night in Puri, there was fear and trembling, for earthquake rent the ground, and a huge
      tidal wave came rushing from the sea. But they who cowered in terror, and they who, remembering the
      two sisters, wept for their awful fate, they knew nothing of the outstretched arms that had carried
      them home, cradled on the bosom that is to become the Refuge of the world; they knew nothing of the
      Light that had turned into heaven the darkness of that hell.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Of the vengeance Vajra wrought when he returned, and of the grief of Jupiter and Albeiro, there is
      here no room to tell. And it was all over very long ago.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
