<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 29
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 29-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It may be remembered that in the ninth of this series of lives Surya prophesied the tragic death
      which closed the tenth, and also foretold that great trial and difficulty should characterise that
      which succeeded it. On the other hand he promised that if the trial were nobly borne, the
      difficulty successfully surmounted, definite progress should be the result. Indeed, apart from this
      particular case, we may take it as a general rule that, when a man is approaching the entrance to
      the Path, he is likely to have some lives involving a good deal of suffering and some unpleasant
      conditions.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      There are two reasons for this. First, whatever of evil karma remains to him must be cleared out of
      the way as speedily as possible, in order that it may not hamper him when the time draws near for
      the final effort. Second, any undesirable qualities in him must be quickly conquered, so that the
      necessary qualifications may be acquired, and the way may be clear.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In the lives already described our hero has had the privilege of frequent and close association
      with men women who have since become Masters of the Wisdom, and everything has been done to
      strengthen his character by example and precept. In this life which is now to be chronicled he is
      thrown from birth into gross and evil surroundings and the help of the presence of those Great Ones
      is withdrawn from him the object evidently being to work off some bad karma, and in doing so to
      give him an opportunity of showing whether he has within him sufficient strength and insight to
      break through an evil tradition even though it has behind it all the weight of religious and
      tradition even though it has behind it all the weight of religious and parental authority, of
      immemorial custom and of personal passion.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone, then, was born this time in a female body in the year 15,402 B.C. in Rahana, in the Oudh
      district of India. Her father, Cetus was the priest of a religion about which there seemed to be
      much mystery. Although he himself was unquestionably of Aryan descent, the religion was certainly
      aboriginal, for it was at the same time too elaborate and too barbarous for the joyous-hearted
      Aryans. It may well have been the seed from which Kali worship has since arisen, for it consisted
      mainly of gloomy rites to a bloodthirsty female deity. There was a good deal of reckless gaiety
      about the outer side of this faith, but through it all there always rang a sombre note of gloom and
      fear. Many secret services were held to which only the initiated' were admitted, and at these the
      most horrible rites of the darker magic were freely practiced. Many parts of some of these services
      were held in a language incomprehensible to the people, but at the same time some of the
      recitations were at least partially Sanskrit.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone's father was a fit person for such a faith, a stern, reserved and gloomy man, but
      nevertheless a person of very great influence. He was supposed to have won many powers by
      sacrifices and austerities, and was further credited with readiness to use them for evil in a great
      many ways. Her mother, Cancer, was not unkind, but was always in a condition of anxiety and terror,
      which speedily communicated itself to the child. The latter lived a rather frightened and neglected
      life; she was not actually badly treated, and as she was not admitted to the inner services, she
      saw nothing definite of the more unnecessary horrors of her religion, but the gloom and the fear of
      the inner circles reacted upon her childhood miserable with vague terrors.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      She grew up without much education, and there was no event of special importance in her young life,
      until at the age of about sixteen she met Pollux, a bright handsome careless fellow, whose
      appearance at once attracted her. The attraction seems to have been mutual, so they fell in love in
      the ordinary way. Alcyone was too terrified to find it possible to propound the idea of love in the
      dark, uncertain atmosphere of the family life, so these young people met frequently in secret, and
      in course of time became too intimate. After a while Alcyone pressed her lover to make some
      arrangements as to marriage, but when urged he declared that this was an impossibility, as not only
      did he belong to quite a different religion, but there was also a hereditary feud between his
      family and that of Alcyone.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It took a long time to convince Alcyone that her lover was really heartless and did not intend to
      make any move in the matter; but, when at last she realised the truth, she turned from him with
      disgust and told all to her mother, announcing her condition, and vowing to devote her life being
      revenged upon the man who had brought her into it. Her mother was much shocked and upset, but when
      she learnt who the lover was she said at once that he came of a bad stock, and that his father
      before him had ruined a younger sister of hers, in a similer manner. This story made Alcyone only
      the more fiercely indignant and, as has been said, she resolved to dedicate her whole life to a
      full and carefully-planned revenge. Her mother then unfolded to her the secret that revenge could
      be had through the secret rites of their religion, and she consequently became eager to be
      initiated into it.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The whole story had to be told to her father, who also was furiously angry, for by the customs of
      the time the birth of an illegitimate child doomed her to the life of a widow. He blamed her
      bitterly, but yet commended and encouraged her desire for revenge. He permitted her to learn the
      secrets of the faith, by which she was deeply impressed, but also greatly terrified, for she had to
      pledge herself to a nightmare of horrors which she would have been glad to be able to forget. In
      order to cloak as far as possible the results of the undue intimacy, the father insisted upon her
      immediate marriage to a devil-priest, Scorpio, a man much older than herself and of most
      undesirable type, one who was a medium for the most horrible influences.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Of course she shrank with loathing from all this, but yet accepted it as a necessary part of the
      revenge to which she had resolved to devote her life. The whole affair had become distorted by her
      long brooding over it, and her state of mind was such that she was open to a steady pressure from
      evil astral influences, a condition of practical obsession which was considered a mark of great
      advancement in this peculiarly abominable religion. After extracting from her blood curdling oaths
      of secrecy, her mother unfolded to her a particularly ghoulish scheme of vengeance which she said
      had never been known to fail. Among other repulsive details it involved the crime of murdering her
      own child, and offering it to the deity invoked. In her rage against Pollux she agreed to this,
      because it would be his child; but when it was born her maternal instincts triumphed, and she
      refused to fulfil the agreement or to consummate the sacrifice.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Many of the ceremonies had already been commenced, for it was of the essence of the horrible pact
      that the birth of the child she should already have dedicated both herself and it utterly to the
      service of this loathsome goddess. The culmination was to be the slaughter of the child upon the
      alter of the deity with certain tremendous invocations, in response to which the image was supposed
      to descend from its pedestal and to embrace the suppliant. In this embrace the goddess was to pass
      from the image into the body of the worshipper, who then, as the vehicle of the deity, was herself
      to devour the sacrifice. In the strength of that ghastly meal the obssessing entity was supposed to
      give to the body much the same powers which medieval superstition attributed to the Hand of Glory.
      At the approach of the avenger all doors flew open, and all living creatures became incapable of
      resisting his will, so that he could wreak his vengeance unopposed, and even unrecognised, for the
      goddess threw over him a mantle of invisibility.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Driven by mad rage and by the almost irresistible force of environment, Alcyone had begun the
      earlier stages of this appalling piece of witchcraft. But when the child was actually born she
      experienced a revulsion of feeling, and declined to continue the dedicatory ceremonies. Her father
      was exceedingly angry, and rediculed her as weak and unworthy of the assistance and favour of the
      goddess. He even claimed that the child already belonged not to the mother but to the deity to whom
      it had been dedicated, and demanded that it should be delivered to him on her behalf. Alcyone
      firmly refused this, braving even the anger of her gloomy and terrible father. He insisted
      indignantly for a time, and then suddenly yielded with a sneer, saying that the goddess would
      obtain her rights in another way.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Soon afterwards the baby fell ill, and in spite of all that the mother could do its mysterious
      malady grew rapidly worse. She presently fell ill herself with watching and grieving over it, and
      when she recovered she fell ill herself with watching and grieving over it, and when she recovered
      she was told that early in her illness the baby had died, and its body had been burnt in the usual
      way. But she always had certain lurking suspicions, and ever after this a drawing of hatred mingled
      with her fear of her father. The truth (which, however, she never actually knew, whatever she may
      have suspected) was that her father, really believing in his fanaticism that the child belonged to
      the goddess, and that her anger would descend upon him if he allowed her to be robbed of it, had
      contrived to administer repeated doses of slow poison, first to the child and then to the mother,
      and as soon as the latter was unconscious he had taken the child and sacrificed it himself to his
      bloodthirsty deity.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Human sacrifice formed a regular part of the secret rites of this horrible faith, and yet in the
      midst of all these abominations there were certain gleams of some original better
      influences--certain suggestions which may have been the reflection of a condition in which the
      faith was not so utterly degraded. The very phrase which was solemnly pronounced by the priest at
      the culminating point of a human sacrifice seemed to have in it some faint reflection of a better
      time, for the earlier part of it at least had a tone which reminds one of the Upanishads. It ran
      something like this:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      From the earth is the breath and the blood, but whence is the soul? Who is he who holds the unborn
      in his hands? The watchers of old are dead, and now we watch in turn. By the blood which we offer,
      hear us and save! The breath and the blood we give thee. Save thou the soul and give it to us in
      exchange.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      These last words seemed to point to the idea that the soul, or perhaps more exactly the astral
      body, of the sacrificed was to be given into their power to become one of their horrible band of
      obsessing entities, to be at once an instrument and yet in some strange way one of the objects of
      their degraded worship. As has been said, most of their incantations were entirely
      incomprehensible, and bore a considerable resemblance to those employed in Voodoo or Obeah
      ceremonies by the Negroes. Others, however, contained distinct Sanskrit words, usually buried in
      the midst of a series of uncouth exclamations delivered with a furious energy which certainly made
      them terribly powerful for evil. One of their characteristics was the use of certain cacophonous
      combinations of constants into which all the vowels were inserted in turn. The syllable hrim was
      used in this way, as also the interjection kshrang . In the midst of these uncouth outbursts of
      spite occurred what appears to be an evil wish in unmistakable Sanskrit: Yushmabhih mohanam
      bhavatu, and the whole utterance concluded with some peculiarly explosive curses which it seems
      impossible to express in any ordinary system of letters.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Poor Alcyone led an exceedingly miserable life amidst all the chaos of obscene horrors. Her husband
      was an evil and crafty man, who prayed upon the credulity of the people, and was often in a
      condition of complete intoxication from the use of hemp and some form of opium. Soon Alcyone came
      bitterly to regret the fit of mad revenge which had led her into all this network of evil, but she
      was too firmly entangled in it to be able to make her escape, and indeed there still were times
      when the obsession dominated her and she felt that revenge would be right and sweet. Presently her
      father died, and the family fell back into a position of less influence.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This unnatural parent, however, was more terrible dead than alive, for he concentrated all his
      energies, in the lowest part of the astral plane, and execercised a peculiarly malignant obsession
      over his daughter. She knew the influence well, and earnestly desired to resist it, but could find
      no method of doing so, though her suffering under it was indescribable and her whole soul was
      filled with uttermost loathing. Her mother and all three other female members of her family were
      under the same malign influence to a greater of less degree, but to them the whole thing was a
      matter of course, and they even supposed themselves to be specially favoured and to become in some
      way holy, when they were seized upon even for the most dreadful purposes.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Along with all the psychical influence there was a perfect labyrinth of the most complicated and
      ingenious plotting on the physical plane. Years were spent in the elaboration of a nefarious scheme
      to get Pollux into the power of the family, and at last the plan matured itself and he and his
      child Tiphys were in their hands for he had married in the meantime and had with him a bright
      little boy. Alcyone's mother and other female relatives were filled with fiendish exultation, and
      joined in a strange kind of orgy of hatred, the father impressing himself upon them all more
      strongly than ever. Alcyone felt the tremendous power of this combination, and was often carried
      away by it and unable to resist its action, although even then she was all the time in a condition
      of bitter protest and resentment. Pollux was to be poisoned in a piculiarly horrible way, and it
      was to Alcyone that the task was entrusted of the actual administration of the dissipation, and
      Alcyone felt nothing but repulsion for him; and, as at this critical moment the obsession by the
      father was almost perfect, there is little doubt that the crime would have been committed, but for
      a most fortunate shock which she received at the last moment.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Just as she was handing the cup to her victim, she met the wide gaze of the child. his eyes were
      exactly those of his father, her joyous young lover of so many years ago, who had been the one
      bright spot in her dreary early life. in a flash those eyes brought back the past, and with it a
      realisation of what she was about to do now under the awful compelling power of this ghastly
      religion of hate. The instantaneous revulsion of feeling was complete; she dashed the cup to the
      ground and rushed from the house from the house and from the city, dressed just as she happened to
      be at the moment, so overpowered by the horror of the thing that she never even paused for a
      thought as to what lay before her, or what would come of it, resolved only to have done for ever at
      any cost with all that evil life.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The violence of her feelings broke through the black pall of evil influence which had so long
      dominated her, and for the time she was entirely freed from the maleficent control of her father.
      She rushed out into the country, careless whither she went so long as she escaped for ever from
      that awful life. Unaccustomed to exercise and to the free air of heaven, she was soon sinking from
      fatigue, but still she pressed on, upheld somehow by a kind of frenzy of determination. She had of
      course no money, and only indoor clothing, but she thought nothing of these things until night
      began to fall. Then for the first time she looked about her and became conscious of her
      surroundings. She was already many miles from home, out in the open country, and, becoming
      conscious at last of severe fatigue and hunger, she turned her steps towards a country house of
      some size which she saw at a little distance.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      She knew little what to say or do, but fortunately Achilles, the mistress of this house, was a kind
      motherly woman, who was touched by the exhausted condition of the wanderer and received her with
      open arms, and postponed her questions until she had eaten and rested. Then, little by little, the
      whole story came out, and many were the exclamations of wonder and pity on the part of the good old
      dame, as the horrors of the dark demon-worship were gradually revealed. The old lady made light of
      the fact that in leaving home Alcyone had lost her position in life and all her worldly
      possessions, telling her that all that mattered nothing now that she had escaped from the other
      horrors, and that she must now devote herself to changing radically and entirely her whole attitude
      of mind, and forget all about the past as though it had been a mere hideous dream. She said wisely
      that life began afresh for her from that hour indeed that she had not really lived until now, and
      she promised to do all in her power to help her and make the new life easy for her.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone feared that her husband, the devil-priest, might be incited to assert some kind of legal
      claim over her, for she knew that the worshippers of the dark cult would be fiercely angry that one
      of their initiates should escape from the fold. But the old woman, who was a brave and capable
      person, declared that she did not know exactly how the law might stand, but that, law or no law,
      she was at any rate quite certain as to one fact that she did not intend to give Alcyone up to her
      husband or any of her relations; and she felt quite confident that if the case were carried before
      the King of the country and all the nefarious proceedings of the dark demon-worship exposed, the
      authorities would be certain to take her side and decline to deliver her again into the slavery
      from which she had escaped.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone was most thankful to this kind protectress, and in her condition of utter exhaustion of
      body and mind was glad to adopt the suggestion that at least they might leave all further
      discussion till the morrow, and to sink to rest in the comfortable quarters provided for her. The
      shock to her had been severe, and it would have been only natural if some serious illness had
      supervened; and indeed it seemed as though that would have been the case but for a wonderful vision
      which came to her during the night. A man of commanding appearance and wonderful gentleness of
      mien(Mercury) appeared to her and spoke words of comfort and encouragement, telling her that the
      awful life which she had lived so far had two aspects of which she had been entirely unconscious.
      First, its terrible sufferings had paid off outstanding debts from long past lives and had made the
      way clear for future advancement; and secondly, the whole life had been in the nature of a test, to
      see whether at its present stage her will was strong enough to break through as exceedingly
      powerful surrounding of evil.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He congratulated her upon her success and determination in breaking away, and prophesied for her a
      future of rapid progress and usefulness. He said that the way was long before her, but drew for her
      also by his words a beautiful picture of two paths of progress, the slow and easy road that winds
      round the mountain, and the shorter but steeper and more rugged path that lies before those who for
      love of God and man, are willing to devote themselves to the welfare of their brothers. She had, he
      said, the opportunity to take the latter in the future if she chose, and if she took that path,
      though the work would be arduous, the reward would be glorious beyond all comprehension. This
      vision produced a profound impression upon her, and she never afterwards forgot the words of the
      face of the instructor, not did she ever entirely lose the glow of enthusiasm with which she felt
      herself eagerly accepting the second of these alternatives which he placed before her.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Next morning she related her vision to her kind hostess, who was deeply impressed by it, and said
      it quite confirmed the impression which she herself had received. It had its effect even upon the
      physical plane, for it was largely owing to it that Alcyone was better than might have been
      expected. Her dead father troubled her greatly by constant and determined attempts to reassert his
      old dominion over her. She however, called up all the latent reserves of her will and and set them
      definitely against this influence, rejecting it with all the vigour which she possessed, without
      the slightest hesitation or compromise, with the strong resolution that she might die in resisting
      the obsession, but at least she would never again submit to it. This struggle continued at frequent
      intervals for many months, but whenever it came she always kept before her the face of the
      vulnerable messenger of her vision, and fortified herself by remembering his words.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      All this time she stayed with her kind hostess, who would not hear of her going anywhere else, or
      of her making any effort to support herself in any way. Apart from this constant astral pressure
      she had no trouble, for no attempt to reclaim her was made on the physical plane on behalf of her
      husband. Indeed, it seems that the family somehow acquired the idea that she was dead, some rumours
      reaching them of the discovery of the body of a woman vaguely answering to her description. Her
      hostess always declared that the Gods had guided her footsteps to her, and that she accepted her as
      a charge from them. Alcyone was most grateful for all this kindness, and tried in every possible
      way to make herself of some use to her benefactress in return for it. She now began to learn
      something of the ordinary Aryan religion, which proved attractive to her after all the horrors of
      her early training. She devoted much time to its study, and soon knew much more about it than her
      hostess.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Little seems to have been at this time committed to writing, but she obtained much assistance and
      instruction from Vega, a Brahman, who made her acquaintance on the occasion of a visit which he
      paid to her hostess. He was much interested in her and profoundly touched by the story of her
      previous sufferings. He taught her a number of hymns, some of them of great beauty, and all of high
      moral tone and of beneficent intent. His advice was on the whole good and sensible, though in
      certain directions he was somewhat narrow and fettered. His wife Auriga was also of great help to
      Alcyone, for she was deeply interested in religious matters. At the end of about a year the dead
      father ceased to make any effort to assert his influence, and Alcyone felt at last that all
      connection with the old evil life had been entirely severed. It seemed to her like looking back
      upon some past incarnation, when she tried for a moment to see anything of that earlier time, and
      soon she was able to cut herself off from it so far that some at least of its details began to fade
      from her memory.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      After the influence of the father had entirely departed, she had the unspeakable pleasure and
      encouragement of seeing once more in dream the Hierophant who had shown himself to her on the first
      night of her escape. On this occasion he congratulated her upon her newly won freedom and gave her
      a promise of help and protection. She endeared herself much, not only to her hostess , but also to
      other members of the family and to friends. She became practically a daughter of the house, or
      rather filled the place of one who had married and left the homestead. It seemed in fact as though
      the family had forgotten that she was not one of themselves, for when the old benefactress died an
      equal share of what was left was offered to her as a matter of course, and when she protested
      against this it was pressed upon her with the utmost sincerity. She agreed at last to accept a
      certain small share, and continued for some years longer to live with this same family.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      There came a time when the second generation was growing up and more room seemed desirable, so she
      transferred herself to a smaller house on the estate, to live there with one of the younger
      couples, Cygnus and Iris, to whom she acted as a kind of mother and advisor. Her interest in the
      religion never waned, and presently she had learned all that her Brahman friend, was able to teach
      her, and was passionately desirous of still further information upon many points. The Brahman found
      himself unable to supply all this, but he told her of a holy man who, if he still lived, would be
      able to answer all her questions. He spoke of this man with the greatest reverence, saying that
      from him he had learnt all that he knew, and that he had always felt sadly conscious that he might
      have learnt much more if only he had had the power to grasp fully the words of wisdom which fell
      from the teacher's lips.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He spoke so earnestly and enthusiastically of this teacher, that after much consultation Alcyone
      resolved to make a journey in search of this man a considerable undertaking for one who was now
      becoming an old woman. The distance was great, and as the Brahman had not heard of his teacher for
      a number of years, there was a good deal of uncertainty as to whether he would still be found in
      the same place, but there seems to have been no readily available method of making enquiries.
      However, Alcyone set off on this rather curious pilgrimage, and at the last moment the Brahman Vega
      resolved to throw up his position and his work and accompany her, and thus they journeyed together
      taking with them only a couple of servants as attendants, one of whom was our old acquaintance
      Boreas.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      After various adventures and more than a month's travelling, they reached the temple over which
      Vega's teacher presided, and heard to their great joy that he was still living. They asked for an
      audience and Vega was overjoyed to fall once more at the feet of his ancient instructor. He then
      turned to introduced Alcyone, but saw with amazement that she was regarding the teacher with
      unspeakable wonder and reverence, and yet with an obvious recognition, while he in turn smiled upon
      her as some one with whom he was already familiar. A few words of incoherent explanation soon
      showed that this teacher was Mercury, the person who had twice appeared to her in vision, and of
      course this discovery put an entirely new complexion upon the affair, and linked them all together
      as already old friends.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Now began a happy time for Alcyone, for all her questions were answered and her most earnest
      desires were fulfilled, and the teacher spoke often to her of a far distant future in which she
      should learn far more than she could at present know, and should hand on the knowledge to others
      for the helping of the world. But he told her that for this many qualities were needed which she
      did not yet possess, that there was much karma even yet to be worked out; that to this end she must
      be willing to forget self and to sacrifice herself utterly for the welfare of mankind, but that at
      the end of this effort would come triumph and peace at the last. Vega made up his mind to send for
      his wife and family and to stay for the rest of his life with this teacher, and Alcyone would
      gladly have done the same, for a strong affection sprang up between them; but the teacher told her
      that this was not her destiny, and indeed that he himself would be but a little while longer upon
      the physical plane, while her duty lay with the family who had helped and rescued her.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      So at the end of about a year she took leave of him with many regrets and travelled slowly back
      again to her old friends, who were heartily glad to welcome her. The rest of her old friends, who
      were heartily glad to welcome her. The rest of her life was spent quietly but happily in
      ministering to and helping the children and grand-children of those who had been so kind to her.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone acquired a wide reputation because of her remarkable knowledge on all religious points, and
      she became an authority to be consulted even by the priests and the Brahmans of the neighbourhood.
      So the life which had begun amidst such horrors of storm and strife ended with the calm of a
      peaceful sunset, and she passed away deeply regretted by all those who knew and loved her so well.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
