<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 37
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 37-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Whenever he is not drawn elsewhere by absolute necessities of service or of evolution, our hero
      here seems to gravitate naturally towards the great motherland of India. It is there that we find
      him reborn in 8775 B.C. at a place called Dorasamudra (now Halebida) north of Hassan in Mysore. His
      father was Proteus and his mother Mercury, a most saintly woman, of high reputation for wisdom. He
      received what was considered at the time a good education, which consisted chiefly in memorizing
      immense numbers of verses on any and every subject - religion, legendary history and folklore, law,
      medicine, and even mathematics. His mother had a marvellous knowledge of all these matters, and her
      influence was of the greatest value to him in every way. There was a vast amount of unnecessary
      ceremonial, but the mother took an eminently common-sense view of all this, and constantly
      impressed upon him that a virtuous life was more important than a thousand ceremonies, and that
      truth, honour, and kindliness were the offerings must pleasing to the deity.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      His father taught him a number of priestly invocations, into which he threw himself with great
      vigour, and was able to perform them effectively, really succeeding in obtaining a response from
      the various entities upon whom he called. His will-power as a boy was remarkable, though not always
      wisely exercised; for instance, he was once discovered in the act of tearing off a nail from one of
      his fingers just to see if he could bear it. Once again, as in Peru, he acquired a reputation for
      writing temple manuscripts, and also for the extraordinary number of verses that he knew in
      proportion to his age, the latter being of course due to the influence of his mother.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      When he was about twenty he married Uranus, the daughter of another of the priests. Although there
      was not yet at this period and in this place exactly a Brahman caste, there was a priestly class
      which already tended somewhat to keep apart, so that it was natural that a priest's son should
      marry a priest's daughter, although he was in no way bound to do so. The father of Uranus was a
      priest of considerable position, but not quite equal in rank to Proteus, who was a man of great
      power because he was in charge of the principal temple, a magnificent polished stone building wit
      elaborate sculptures. The local Raja, Castor, attended and supported this temple, so that the
      position of Proteus as his spiritual adviser was one of great importance in the State. Castor owed
      allegiance to an overlord, Mars, who ruled a far larger kingdom, but he was practically
      independent, except as to foreign affairs.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Soon after the marriage of Alcyone a new factor was introduced into the case by the arrival from
      the north of Aries, a man with a great reputation as a magician a reputation which was not
      altogether undeserved, for he really had studied deeply and acquired control over certain astral
      entities, and he also possessed a knowledge of some facts in chemistry and electricity, which
      enabled him to perform what to the men of those days seemed marvellous miracles. He had, too, some
      mesmeric power; and by the display of these various accomplishments he soon acquired complete
      ascendancy over Castor, and so became a formidable opponent to the orthodox Proteus, whose
      influence and prestige declined as that of the new man increased.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Aries did not in any way set himself in open opposition to Proteus, and he was not at heart a bad
      man, though it must be said that he took every opportunity to feather his own nest. Perhaps even
      more than by thought of gain, he was actuated by the love of power and by the pleasure which he
      felt in working his wonderful experiments, and seeing the profound impression which they forced
      upon the people. Proteus was, not unnaturally, a good deal annoyed at the falling off of his
      revenues and the decrease of his influence and he was thoroughly persuaded that the influence of
      Aries was entirely an evil one.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This condition of affairs went on for some years, the friction getting worse as time passed. Castor
      built a great temple for Aries, and the two cults may be said to have been in open rivalry. Proteus
      really believed Aries to be guilty of various objectionable forms of magic, and did not at all
      scruple to say so and this was partly responsible for the fact that Aries acquired a somewhat
      unenviable reputation, and though his undoubted powers were much admired, he was also a good deal
      feared. Castor caused some trouble to Aries by always insisting on partaking in his secret rites,
      trying always to understand the working of the various forces employed, and even to attempt new
      experiments of various kinds with them. As his own knowledge was after all somewhat limited, Aries
      was always distinctly nervous about these experiments, and eventually his fears were realised, as
      Castor contrived to get himself blown up and killed.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Of course Castor's death was supposed to be attributable entirely to magic, and Proteus, not
      unnaturally, made the most of this accident and charged his rival with having intentionally
      compassed the death of the King; indeed, there is no reason to doubt that he really believed this
      to be the case. Aries indignantly repudiated the charge, and declared that Castor had come by his
      end through disregarding his warnings, and provoking the wrath of his attendant spirits. This
      unfortunate occurrence exasperated the feeling between the two rival sects, and the leaders
      actually began to hate one another and to enter into plots against one another, each feeling
      himself inspired by the highest motives and doubtless believing that his rival's success would mean
      disaster of the State.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      As Castor had no heir, the overlord Mars sent his own son Ulysses to fill the vacant throne, and
      the two sects immediately began to scheme for the support of this new King. The showy miracles of
      Aries carried the day, and Ulysses, who was exceedingly eager after phenomena of this kind, became
      a devoted disciple of the magician. The success of the rival galled Proteus greatly, and it was
      chiefly through disappointment and baffled rage that he fell ill and speedily died, though his
      followers with one accord attributed this entirely to the workings of magic by Aries. Whether there
      was any truth in their surmise it is difficult to say. There is no doubt that Aries, firmly
      convinced that Proteus was a dangerous man, employed mesmeric and elemental forces and accelerated
      his death. Alcyone, at any rate, believed this. Young as he was, he succeeded to his father's
      position as chief priest of the great temple, and he undoubtedly felt that in doing this he was
      taking up arms against Aries and his followers.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In the meantime the lot of Aries was by no means a happy one. His own immediate followers naturally
      accepted his statement as to the cause of Castor's death, but there was a good deal of doubt and
      suspicion among the majority of the populace, and people feared and distrusted him more than ever.
      Ulysses also gave him a good deal of trouble, though not quite in the same way as Castor had done
      it was not so much that Ulysses desired to perform all the experiments himself, as that he was
      constantly requiring to be entertained by new marvels, and would not believe when Aries told him
      that he had exhausted his repertoire. By this constant pressure Aries was forced into exhibiting
      experiments with which he was only imperfectly acquainted, gave rise to doubt in the King's mind.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      To retrieve his position Aries employed all the magical arts which he knew, even some which were
      decidedly dark in complexion. By means such as these he wove kind of mesmeric spell round Ulysses,
      so that the latter eventually became a mere tool in his hands, and had scarcely any will of his
      own. But though in this way he had obtained complete ascendancy over the King, he was by no means
      free from trouble; in order to produce some of his effects he had resorted to trickery, and one of
      his subordinates, Scorpio, who knew of this, threatened to expose him to the King and the people,
      and so obtained a powerful influence over Aries, which he exercised mercilessly. Unfortunately his
      designs were more personal and less innocent than those of Aries, and the latter sometimes found
      himself involved in schemes which were intensely hateful to him.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Among these was a plot with many complications, an account of which is not essential to our story.
      One of its chief element however was that Aries (or rather the schemer behind him) was to gain
      possession of Mizar, a young brother of Alcyone, and push him into some of the mysteries of the
      darker cult. The plotters had contrived to obtain a certain hold over Mizar in consequence of some
      small youthful indiscretions of his which they threatened to expose, and he was besides, somewhat
      dazzled by the splendid prospects of success and power which they held out to him. Mercury,
      however, was determined that no son of hers should fall under the their influence, and she strongly
      urged Alcyone to take a determined stand in the matter and to declare open war if necessary.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      An appeal was made to Ulysses about the affair, and the case was so pressed upon him that, even
      though he was sunk into a kind of stupor under the constant obsession of some of the entities
      directed by Aries, he found it difficult not to give ear to Alcyone's representations. Aries,
      however, seeing his plans to be in some danger, appealed to the weak side of Ulysses by proposing a
      spectacular exhibition of magic, in which he undertook finally to overthrow Alcyone and dispose of
      his pretensions to knowledge. Ulysses, who had a great love for theatrical display of any sort,
      immediately consented to this, as it had every appearance of fairness, and yet relieved him from
      the trouble of coming to a decision; so at an appointed time he summoned all the parties before
      him, and contrived what practically amounted to a public contest in magic before his assembled
      court.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It seemed a very unequal contest, for Aries was a man of great reputation, thoroughly well-equipped
      with a certain amount of science on the physical plane and also with capable co-adjucators on the
      astral a man of commanding presence, hardly past the prime of life. Alcyone, on the other hand, was
      young and comparatively untried; he had none of the scientific knowledge, and his mantras, though
      effective in their way, were only of the orthodox kind. His will, however, was strong, and he was
      absolutely determined at all costs to save his brother. He took counsel with Mercury who urged him
      to undertake the struggle and promised him victory in spite of all appearances. The contrast
      between the two opponents was still further emphasised by the splendid robes in which Aries
      appeared, and the fact that he was surrounded by all his temple servants whereas Alcyone had simply
      presented himself unattended, and in the creamy white dress of a priest of his temple.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Ulysses was in his usual condition of partial obsession, and seemed somewhat dazed and hesitating
      in his speech, as he opened the proceedings by calling upon his friend and teacher Aries to state
      his case. Aries had had a tripod brought in, a sort of temporary altar, upon which he burnt great
      quantities of some special kind of incense, upon the stupefying effects of which he evidently
      calculated. He produced a number of his best miracles and worked up his auditors to a condition of
      great excitement and enthusiasm, though it must be admitted that some of them were also badly
      frightened. Finally he ended a long diatribe by calling Mizar out of the crowd of his followers to
      stand by his side, and asking him publicly to swear allegiance to him, which Mizar, being quite
      obviously under hypnotic influence, forthwith proceeded to do. Aries then called upon Ulysses and
      the courtiers present to witness this, and then, turning to where Alcyone was seated alone at the
      opposite side of the dais upon the upper part of which the King's throne was set, he projected all
      his mesmeric and magical force against him, and adjured him also to come over at his bidding and to
      be his slave. The stream of force poured upon him made Alcyone's head swim for a moment, but as his
      sight cleared he saw the face of his mother before him. He rose and said:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      I come, but not as your slave!
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Bowing deeply before Ulysses, he strode across and confronted Aries, standing face to face with
      him, and challenging his mesmeric power. Aries raised his arm as though to curse him, and began
      rapidly uttering spells. Alcyone said nothing more; he spoke not a single word, but kept his
      burning eyes fixed upon those of Aries, and threw all the force of his will into a most determined
      resistance. For some minutes they stood thus facing each other amidst breathless silence. Then
      Alcyone became conscious that the power of Aries was failing, and with one great effort of will he
      raised his arm and, pointing straight at Aries, said with fell intensity:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      May the power that thou hast misused depart from thee!
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Even as he uttered the words Aries, realising his defeat, fell to the ground insensibly. Then
      Alcyone turned his will on Ulysses, and called to him:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      O King, awake! Rise, shake off this evil power and defy the demons who have seized thee! Come forth
      from darkness to light!
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      With a great start the King sprang to his feet and came down the steps until he faced Alcyone, and
      said:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      What is this that you have done to me? A great change has come over me?
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone answered: I have done nothing, O King; but the power of the deity has manifested itself,
      and thou hast been freed from the prison in which this man had immured thee.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And Ulysses replied, speaking to his courtiers: Verily this which he says is true, for I feel as
      though I had escaped from some dark dungeon, and I know that whereas before I was bound, now I am
      free.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Turning to Alcyone he continued: You, who have done this great thing for me I transfer to you by
      this act all the revenues of him whose wiles you have conquered, and I ask you to instruct me
      further in a magic so powerful as to defeat so easily the greatest magician whom I have known.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      There is no magic here, O King, replied Alcyone, but that of a strong will, a pure heart and a
      sense of right; yet I thank thee for thy gift, and if it be thy will I will gladly help thee to
      undo the wrong that has been done. But first let me call my brother.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      With a look he called Mizar to his side. Mizar came willingly enough, for the fall of his quondam
      chief had caused a shock which had enabled him to throw off the hypnotic influence, and now he felt
      not the slightest attraction to the darker magic which before had meant so much to him. Now he too
      saw before, him the face of their mother. And he gladly attached himself to Alcyone, unable to
      comprehend how he could ever have even temporarily left him. Ulysses dismissed the assembly and,
      calling Alcyone to him, began at once to arrange for a series of instructions from him. From that
      moment he transferred all his interest and support to the great temple over which Alcyone presided;
      and; with the advice of his mother, Alcyone was gradually able to lead him from love of magical
      phenomena to a consideration of the mighty truths of life and death and to inspire him with an
      earnest desire to set his feet on the path which leads to perfection. Thus was fulfilled the
      prophecy-made---by Mercury in the thirty first life, five thousand years before.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Ulysses on his part felt strong affection and gratitude towards Alcyone, and conferred him with
      honours. Young as Alcyone was, this triumph made him practically the greatest power in the kingdom,
      for Aries eclipsed entirely and ceased to be a factor in public life. Indeed, it would seem that
      his nerves were shattered, for he was no longer able to command the entities with which he had
      formerly worked and even his chemical and electrical knowledge appears largely to have slipped from
      him. It seems as though, in the tremendous effort of willpower, made on the occasion of the public
      test, something had snapped in his brain, so that ever after that his memory was defective and
      quite unreliable. Most of his fair-weather friends deserted him, and Ulysses, who had now a
      complete revulsion of feeling, did not feel called upon to do anything for him, saying that he had
      already wasted over him a large proportion of his substance. This partial occlusion of memory may
      be regarded as merciful, for his life would have been a miserable one if he had fully realised the
      change which had come over his fortunes; but the weakness in the brain increased as the years
      passed, and he eventually sank into an almost animal condition. Now that Ulysses accepted Alcyone
      as his adviser he also came much into contact with Mercury, and felt the deepest respect for her,
      and it was in reality owing to her intercession that a sort of small pension was eventually
      assigned to Aries, so that he was able to live out what remained of his life without actual anxiety
      as to food and lodging.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Ulysses sent to his father the Maharaja a highly coloured account of all that had occurred, which
      so interested Mars that he promptly ordered Ulysses to send both Alcyone and Mercury to his
      capital. The visit was duly paid, and Mars received them with great pomp, and after a series of
      interviews with them desired that Alcyone should settle in his capital, offering to put him in
      charge of one of the principal temples there. It was difficult to refuse this munificent offer;
      but, after long consultation with his mother, Alcyone respectfully begged to be allowed to return
      to his own temple, representing that he felt the carrying on of its work to be a duty which he owed
      to his dead father, and also urging his earnest desire to help and guide the Maharaja's son
      Ulysses, for whom he felt a serious responsibility. Mars regretted this decision, but yet
      eventually granted the request influenced thereto principally by the strong regard which he had for
      Mercury. The most intimate understanding seemed immediately to spring up between them, and though
      Mars would fain have had them both remain with him permanently, yet he would not oppose the clearly
      stated wish of the lady for whom he felt so deep a respect. In due course Mercury and Alcyone
      returned home, but from that time onward constant correspondence was kept up between the Maharaja
      and Mercury, and the Maharaja more than once visited Dorasamudra in order to see her.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone's influence over Ulysses was emphatically a good one, for without it the young ruler would
      certainly have fallen into dissolute ways. He had distinctly two sides to his character. Both of
      them exceedingly strong. His interest in occult powers and phenomena , and also in the progress of
      his people, was undoubtedly genuine and strong, yet at the same time there was a streak of
      sensuality in him which led him sometimes into reckless disregard of the rights of others and of
      the duties of his position. Alcyone's advice and influence steadied him greatly, and much modified
      the occasional outbursts which occurred, so that on the whole the King was kept within reasonable
      bounds. The character of Ulysses changed greatly for the better under Alcyone's direction, and he
      formed and carried out many schemes for the good of his people, Alcyone and Mercury being always
      the force behind the throne in these matters, so that eventually this little kingdom became one of
      the most flourishing in the whole of the south of India.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Many years passed in this way, and in the fullness of time Mercury died, to the lasting sorrow of
      Alcyone and Ulysses. The Maharaja survived Mercury by a few years only, and then Ulysses was
      compelled to transfer his energies to the management of the larger state. He in his turn repeated
      the offer which his father had made, begging Alcyone to go with him to the capital, and saying that
      as all that he had been able to do in Dorasamudra had been with the advice of and largely under the
      direction of Alcyone, he could not possibly take upon his shoulders the responsibility of this far
      larger work without the same help and guidance. Alcyone resisted this persuasion for a long time,
      but as his eldest son Siwa had now grown up and was not only well able to take charge of his
      temple, but also quite willing to undertake that responsibility. Alcyone at last yielded to the
      urgent solicitations of Ulysses, and they journeyed together to take up the new work. Alcyone was
      at last appointed as chief priest of the principal temple in the capital, a post which he filled
      with dignity and success; and although at every turn both he and the new Maharaja missed the sage
      counsel of Mercury, they were yet able to manage well by constantly applying the maxims which she
      had taught them.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Here then Alcyone remained until his death, in a position of great honour dignity and usefulness,
      in which he was succeeded by his brother Mizar. And yet in spite of all this he quite frequently
      had an irrational longing for the more active life of the world a desire to go out with Ulysses in
      his occasional campaigns, and to live the life of a soldier rather than that of the priest and
      student. Nevertheless his life was on the whole a happy one, and one in which much good karma was
      unquestionably made. Finally he passed peacefully away at the age of eighty three, leaving behind
      him a great reputation for wisdom and sanctity of life.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      After Mizar's death, Alcyone's eldest son Siwa was invited to take charge of the Principal temple
      at the capital. He accepted, and brought with him his eldest son Brihat as assistant, leaving
      Alcyone's original temple in the hands of his second son, Naga, who with the help of his wife
      Herakles had already established for himself a great reputation for administrative ability.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
