<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 32
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 32-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The fanatical majority of the Aryan race in Central Asia continued to increase and multiply, and as
      the cultivable land round the shores of the Gobi Sea was a limited quantity, wave after wave of
      emigrations went forth from it, and the great majority of these waves eventually found their way
      into India. Much later certain bands penetrated Persia, but at this time the empire occupying that
      district was much too strong for them to venture to attack it. One army or tribe of such emigrants
      had, however, worked their way round the north of Persia, and eventually arrived at the Caucasian
      district, from which far later they radiated over Europe. Many minor waves of immigration into
      India seem to have extended over a period of some thousands of years.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Фанатичное большинство арийской расы в центральной азии продолжало расти и поскольку земли пригодной
      для земледелия вокруг моря Гоби на всех не хватало, оттуда одна за другой исходили волны эммигрантов,
      большинство из которых нашли свой дом в Индии. Гораздо позже некоторые группы отправились в Персию,
      но в то время империя владеющая той территорией была слишком сильна, чтоб на неё можно было напасть.
      Однако одна из этих армий, или точнее племён, смогла пройти по северу Персии и добраться до Кавказа,
      откуда этот народ позже распространился по Европе. Множество меньших волн иммигрантов в Индию ещё
      случались на протяжении следующих нескольких тысяч лет.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In a general way the Aryan incursion much resembled the descent of the Goths and Vandals upon the
      Roman Empire. We find the same phenomenon of a high civilisation with all sorts of specialised
      detail, yet somewhat effete. The Aryan invaders, though much less civilised as far as arts and
      sciences went, were a more virile race, far more fanatical and less philosophical. Their leaders
      impressed upon them that their conquest was a religious war. They spoke of the Atlanteans as
      Dasyas, and regarded them as unbelievers, to be exterminated at all costs, despising their higher
      civilisation and their arts, though not apparently their gold and jewels, and their soldiers were
      well-disciplined, yet in most cases they were unable to stand before the wild onrush of the burly
      barbarians from the north, Other races existed in the country, apparently of Lemurian descent;
      there was a large black population quite apart both from the brown Tlavatli majority, and from the
      red Toltec race, in whose hands was usually all the power. The Toltecs were sometimes spoken of as
      Nagas, and some of the darker people were called Takshaks a people who used poisoned arrows with
      iron barbs.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      В целом вторжение арийцев напоминало вторжение готов и вандалов в римскую империю. Здесь мы также
      видим развитую цивилизацию со всеми ей присущими качествами и уже находящуюся в упадке. Арийские
      же варвары были не такими продвинутыми в плане наук и искусств, но зато были намного живучее, фанатичнее
      и менее склонными к размышлениям. Их лидер внушил им, что эта война носит религиозный характер.
      Атлантов они называли "дасьями" и считали их неверными коих следовало уничтожить любой ценой,
      а также терпеть не могли их более развитую цивилизацию и их искусства, хотя и ненависть эта не
      распространялась на золото и драгоценности атлантов. Выучка у солдат атлантов была лучше, но это
      им редко помогало против безумного напора варваров с севера. Там были и другие расы, судя по всему
      потомки лемурийцев. Обычно власть была сосредоточена в руках многочисленного чёрного народа
      держащегося в стороне как от коричневых тлаватей, так и от красных толтеков. В то время толтеков
      называли "нагами", а более тёмных людей "такшаками" - тех, которые применяли ядовитые стрелы с
      железными наконечниками.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The Aryans were physically larger and men, with keen eyes and aquiline noses, not unlike the Afgans
      or Pathans of the present day, and man for man they easily overmatched the more enervated
      Atlanteans, though some of the large fortified towns of the latter held out against their attacks
      for centuries. The Aryans were on the whole a bright and happy people, though by no means ideal in
      the life which they lived. At this period the majority were flesh-eaters; at least it is certain
      that some large tribes did kill and eat cattle. Also there was a good deal of drunkenness among
      them, the chief liquor being the juice of some plant of the asclepiad order, which they mixed with
      milk. Some of the tribes, when they settled down in the conquered countries in the north of India,
      cultivated wheat and barley, and practically became vegetarians. Nothing in the nature of caste is
      observable at this period.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Арийцы были сами по себе больше и своими пронзительными глазами и орлиными носами напоминали
      афганцев или пуштунов наших дней. Их также было намного больше чем более слабых атлантов, хотя
      последние сумели удерживать некоторые укреплённые города столетиями. В целом арийцы были людьми
      хорошими и счастливыми, хотя и ни в коей мере не идеальными судя по тому как они жили. В то время
      большинство были мясоедами; по крайней мере несколько больших племён убивали и ели коров. Также
      было распространено пьянство и их главным напитком был сок некоего растения из семейства аскелепиадов,
      который они смешивали с молоком. Некоторое из племён поселившихся на завоёванных землях на севере
      Индии выращивали пшеницу и ячмень и так практически стали вегетарианцами. Ничего похожего на
      кастовую систему мы не обнаружили в то время.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The parents of Alcyone belonged to one of these wandering bands, and he was born on the march,
      somewhere in the hill country in the neighbourhood of what is now called Afghanistan, in the year
      12,877 B. C. This band made its way slowly down to the Punjab, which was already in the hands of
      the Aryans. These marauding invaders seem always to have been ready to fight, just as much with men
      of their own race as with others, if they could not get exactly what they wanted. In some cases the
      Aryan Kings already in possession were wise enough to claim kinship with these new bands and speed
      them on their way; others, having been settled for centuries, regarded their bretheren as mere
      savages, resisted them vigorously, and were usually defeated by them.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Родители Алкиона были в числе одной из бродячих групп и во время одного из маршей он и родился,
      где то в горном селе неподалеку от того места которое сейчас стало Афганистаном, в 12,877 г. до н.э.
      Эта группа медленно прошла до Пенджаба который у тому времени уже был захвачен арийцами.
      Марадёрствующие варвары казалось всегда были рады схватиться не только с противником, но и с людьми
      своей же расы если им не удавалось получить то что хочется. Уже обосновавшиеся арийские короли
      были достаточно мудры, чтобы заявить о родстве с этими бандами и помочь им пройти, хотя некоторые,
      уже живущие там столетиями, считали тех за дикарей и яростно им сопротивлялись, за что обычно терпели
      поражение.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The family to which Alcyone belonged eventually settled down at a place called Arupalu, not far
      from where Amritsar now is. It must be remembered that while the Aryan invaders usually expelled or
      massacred the Atlanteans, in some places they lived amicably with them; and though the majority of
      the Aryans were fiercely intolerant and fanatical, and objected to anything which even savoured of
      the higher civilisation of Atlantis, there were yet some who were more broad-minded and more
      willing to learn. The religion of the Atlanteans was a form of Sun worship, but it was accompanied
      by a magnificent system of philosophy. Their temples were usually of dazzling white stone, and
      built in the shape of a star.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Со временем семья Алкиона обосновалась в поселении Арупалу, неподалёку от того места где сейчас
      находится Амритсар. Стоит упомянуть, что хотя обычно арийцы прогоняли или убивали атлантов,
      в некоторых случаях они жили с ними мирно: хотя большинство арийцев были яростными фанатиками
      и ненавидели всё, что хоть как то было связано с более развитой культурой атлантов, среди них
      всё же попадались те, кто смотрели на мир шире и стремились узнавать новое. Религией атлантов
      было поклонение Солнцу и у них также была впечатляющая философская система. Их храмы были обычно
      построены в форме звезды из слепяще белого камня.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone's earliest memories were connected with the ceaseless forward movement of the tribe, and
      the first deity to whom he was taught to pray was the Path-finder, to whom the tribe put up their
      petitions that he would find a road for them, and lead them into a pleasant land. They had many
      strange and interesting traditions of the country whence they had come. If these are in any way to
      be trusted, it would seem that they had been a semi-barbarous people, living on the outskirts of
      the territory of some great settled power, whose constant pressure and expansion drove them into
      migration.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Детские воспоминания Алкиона были связаны с непрестанным движением его племени вперёд, а первым
      божеством которому его научили молиться был Путеводитель - к нему обращались соплеменники с просьбами
      указать им дорогу к хорошим землям. В стране из которой они пришли было много странных и любопытных
      обычаев. Если этим обычаям хоть немного верить, то получается, что они вели полудикий образ жизни
      на задворках страны которой правила могучая сила, постоянное распространение которой вынудило
      их уйти.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone's father in this incarnation was Algol, and his mother was Theseus, but she died very
      shortly after his birth. The father was a man of fanatical type, bitterly opposed to everything,
      good and bad alike, which savored of the high Atlantean civilisation, and this feeling was rather
      intensified than modified by the fact that in the district in which they settled the Aryans and
      Atlanteans had arranged to live together in comparative harmony. Alcyone soon doubted the wisdom of
      his father's position for there were many things about the civilisation which attracted him
      strongly, and even as a boy he made friends equally with Atlantean and Aryan children. Indeed, his
      favorite companion , Psyche, was the son of a wealthy Atlantean dignitary, Orpheus, but his
      father's fanaticism was so great that he never dared to invite his friend to his home, or even to
      let his father know of that friend's existence. He contrived incidentally to get a good deal more
      education than his father would have given him, for he learnt at second-hand from his friend a good
      deal of what the latter was taught.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      В этот раз отцом Алкиона оказался Алгол, а Тезеус стала его мамой, которая умерла вскоре после его рождения.
      Алгол был типичным фанатиком, яростно отвергающим всё, хорошее или плохое, что было хоть как то
      связано с цивилизацией атлантов и это чувство лишь усиливалось, а не менялось, от того, что оказались
      они в районе где арийцы и атланты мирно жили вместе. Алкион довольно быстро усомнился в правильности
      отцовских взглядов поскольку было много вещей в атлантской культуре которые сильно привлекали его,
      а ещё ребенком он завводил друзей в равной степени среди арийцев и атлантов. Более того, его лучшим
      другом был Psyche - сын богатого атлантского чиновника Орфеуса - но фанатизм его отца был столь силён,
      что Алкион никогда не решался не просто пригласить того к себе домой, но и даже дать знать отцу, что
      у него есть такой друг. Алкиону удалось получить лучшее образование чем то, что мог бы дать ему его
      отец, за счёт того, что Psyche пересказывал ему то, чему учили его самого.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      All these facts had a serious influence over the direction of his future life, for his visits to
      this boy-friend continued over a period of some years, until they were both young men, when he
      complicated the situation by falling deeply in love with his friend's sister Mizar. The feeling was
      strongly reciprocated, but the prospect before the two young people was not hopeful. It was
      impossible even to think of proposing such an alliance to the father Algol, while the Atlantean
      dignitary on his side was little likely to welcome an arrangement which linked him to one who was
      so fiercely opposed to his race. So the young people found themselves to some extent in a
      dilemma--unable to do anything without taking the parents into their confidence, and yet at the
      same time unable to tell either of the parents, because of the feelings with which they regarded
      each other.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Всё это оказало большое влияние на его дальнейшую жизнь: на протяжении нескольких лет он продолжал
      ходить к своему другу до тех пор пока они не стали старше, после чего он ещё больше усложнил
      ситуацию влюбившись в Мицар - сестру того друга. Чувство это было взаимным, но перспективы
      этого знакомства были неутешительны. Было бы безумием даже рассказать о возможности такого
      альянса отцу Алкиона, а атлантский же чиновник вряд ли был бы рад таким образом связаться с
      Алголом - человеком, столь люто ненавидящим атлантов. Таким образом молодые люди оказались
      перед сложным выбором: они не могли продолжать отношения не вовлекая родителей, но также не могли
      рассказать родителям о своих взаимных чувствах.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The Gordian knot was cut for them, however, for through gossip of some kind the news of Alcyone's
      visits to an Atlantean household reached his father's ears, and called down upon his head an
      outburst of vituperation. When it thus came to the point, Alcyone boldly admitted that his
      friendship was a matter of years, and he furthermore announced his intention of marrying Mizar. His
      father promptly turned him out of the house, but fortunately omitted to notify his Atlantean
      friends. Alcyone at once went to call upon them, took his friend and Mizar into his confidence, and
      took away the breath of the latter by proposing that she should instantly fly with him then and
      there, before the news of his father's proceedings could come to the ears of her family. At first
      there was some natural hesitation, but finally Mizar yielded, and with Psyche's assistance, and a
      large sum of money which he lent them, these two young lovers actually started off together.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Проблема решилась сама собой: слухи о том, что Алкион посещает атлантский дом добрались до Алгола
      и тот вызвал сына и долго его бранил. Тогда Алкион открыто признал, что этой дружбе уже много лет,
      а также то, что он собирается взять Мицар замуж. Алгол тут же выгнал сына из дома, но к счастью
      забыл об этом сообщить его атлантским друзьям. Алкион тут же отправился к ним, нашёл своего друга
      и Мицар и сходу сообщил, что та должна с ним бежать сейчас же, до того как новости доберутся до
      её семьи. Мицар естественно засомневалась, но потом уступила и с помощью Psyche и большой суммы
      денег которую тот им одолжил они отправились в путь.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Their method of escape was to attach themselves to one of the Aryan bands which happened just then
      to be passing through the country, feeling certain that that was the last place in which anyone
      would look for them, and also that a body of Aryan invaders would be unlikely to give them up, even
      if enquiries were made for them. Some sort of excuse about a sudden visit to some friends or
      relations kept the Atlantean father off their track until the band to which they joined themselves
      had passed out of the province, and by the time that he realised the state of affairs it was
      practically impossible to trace the fugitives; that is to say, he was able to discover that they
      had joined the Aryan host, but not to recover them or to obtain any further information about them.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Их план заключался в том, чтобы присоединиться к одной из арийских банд как раз продвигающуюся
      через те земли и считать, что там их вряд ли кто то будет искать, но даже если будут, то арийцы
      вряд ли их выдадут. Они придумали что то про внезапный визит к каким то друзьям или родственникам
      и это первое время держало отца Мицар в неведении вплоть до того момента когда они уже в составе
      той группы покинули страну, а когда тот понял, что случилось - было уже практически невозможно
      найти их след. Стоит сказать, что ему удалось выяснить, что они ушли с арийцами, но ни вернуть их
      ни узнать что либо ещё он уже не смог.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The Aryan bands were moving eastwards, and though there was much about their mode of life which was
      distasteful to the young couple, they were nevertheless kindly treated in a kind of hearty and
      boisterous manner. They moved on with the band for some time, though always fully intending to
      break away from it when they felt themselves sufficiently secure from possible pursuit or
      interference.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Арийцы шли на восток и хотя в их образе жизни было многое, что не нравилось молодой паре, к ним всё
      же хорошо относились. Какое то время они шли с той группой, но всегда помнили, что им надо уйти как
      только это станет безопасно и их никто не станет преследовать.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Having thus sacrificed everything for the sake of love, Alcyone had of course to consider how he
      could make a living for himself and his young wife. As they were of different nations it was
      necessary that they should find something to do, and somewhere to make a home, in one of these
      parts of the country where the two races were living together in amity. Alcyone had the good
      fortune to be able to reduce a personal service to Vesta, one of the leaders of the band, by an act
      of bravery during a night attack which was made upon a part of this very irregular army; but
      although for that once Alcyone had saved his life, his destiny was evidently to leave this plane,
      for he was killed shortly afterwards in some fighting a little further to the east. In return for
      this service Vesta pressed upon Alcyone's acceptance a large chest of gold and jewels which he had
      acquired in the attack upon some Atlantean city in an earlier part of his march.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Пожертвова таким образом всем ради любви, Алкиону пришлось думать над тем, как прожить ему и его жене.
      Поскольку они были разных рас, им нужно было найти работу и дом в таком месте где две расы бы жили
      мирно вместе. Алкиону представилась хорошая возможность вернуть часть долга Весте, который был одним
      из вожаков группы, храбрым поступком одной ночью во время нападения на их весьма разношёрстную банду,
      однако хотя в тот раз Алкиону и удалось спасти его жизнь, судьба Весты очевидно была в том, чтобы покинуть тот
      мир потому что немного позже он таки был убит в одной стычке восточнее того места. В благодарность
      Веста вручил Алкиону большую чашу с золотом и драгоценностями которые он ранее забрал после атаки на
      один город атлантов во время похода.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He also demanded Alcyone's story, and when he heard that it was his desire to abandon the wandering
      life as soon as possible and settle to some occupation, he offered him the choice of coming on with
      them to further conquests in the remote and unknown eastern country (probably Bengal) or of
      establishing himself almost immediately with recommendations to Draco, a certain relative of the
      leader's who had come into the country a few years before with a previous band, and had succeeded
      in establishing himself not far from where they then were. As Mizar was about to become a mother,
      and found the constant travelling and the rough boisterous life of the camp very trying, Alcyone
      accepted the latter alternative, and through the good offices of the leader's relative he presently
      found himself in possession of an estate at a place called Dhramira, not far from where Saharanpur
      now stands. Draco's wife Cassio was particularly kind to Mizar, and nursed her carefully through
      her confinement.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Также он потребовал от Алкиона рассказать о себе и когда услышал, что тот хочет как можно скорее
      прекратить скитания, осесть и найти какую нибудь работу, то предложил ему на выбор либо продолжить
      с ними путь в неизведанные земли на востоке (возможно в Бенгал) или остаться с Драко - родственником
      Весты который добрался туда несколько лет назад и сумел обосноваться неподалёку от того места где они
      сейчас остановились. К тому моменту Мицар была близка к тому, чтобы стать мамой и ей было трудно
      держаться во время этого бесконечного путешествия, Алкион выбрал второе предложение. Благодаря
      знакомству с Вестой он быстро оказался владельцем поместья в Дхрамире неподалёку от современного
      Сахаранпура. Кассио - жена Драко - была особенно добра к Мицар и внимательно о ней заботилась.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      They settled down now into a happy and somewhat uneventful life. Owing to the recommendation which
      they had received from the Aryan leader they were able to make good friends, but they were so much
      devoted to each other that the really important part of their life was the domestic. A son, Fomal,
      was soon born to them, and their pleasure would have been unalloyed but for an unfortunate accident
      which befell Alcyone at this period, and caused him a great deal of suffering-indeed, he never
      entirely recovered from it. He was always of as enquiring and experimental turn of mind, and when a
      rich Atlantean friend, Aletheia, imported one of the strange air-ships from Atlantis, he willingly
      accepted an invitation to make a trial trip in it along with its owner. Some error in the
      management of the power caused one of the directing tubes to catch and become jammed at a critical
      moment so that the machine fell, and its passengers were thrown out with great violence. Both were
      badly injured, and though Alcyone eventually recovered and become as strong as ever, he walked with
      a limp until the day of his death, owing to some injury to the hip which could not be perfectly
      dealt with by the primitive surgery of the time.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Так они начали счастливую и довольно однообразную жизнь. Благодаря рекомендации от арийского вожака
      им удалось завести много хороших друзей, однако самую важную часть своих жизней они провели дома
      потому что были столь сильно привязаны друг к другу. Вскоре у них родился сын (Фомал) и ничто не
      омрачило бы их радость, если бы не одно событие случившиеся с Алкионом в то время которое принесло
      ему много страданий и от которого он так и не оправился. Алкион всегда был очень любопытным и
      стремился узнать что то новое, поэтому когда один его богатый друг (Алетия) привёз необычный
      воздушный корабль из Атлантиса, он решительно принял приглашение на нём прокатиться. Во время полёта
      что то случилось с управлением и одну из направляющих труб заклинило, так что корабль упал,
      а пассажиры разлетелись в стороны. Оба серьёзно пострадали и хотя Алкион со временем восстановил силы,
      он так до конца своих дней продолжал хромать из за ранения в бедре которое нельзя было исправить
      примитивной медициной того времени.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      His estate however prospered, and as the years rolled by he became rich and respected. He took
      considerable interest in the study of Atlantean philosophy, and he and Mizar remained always upon
      the most friendly terms with both the Aryan and the Atlantean priests, though their attachment was
      on the whole greatest to the star-shaped temples of the Sun-God. Aryan migrations continued to pass
      them at intervals, but they were fortunate in being able to deal in a politic manner with these
      wandering bands, and Alcyone, in memory of his friend Vesta, always offered them the freest
      hospitality, and so kept on good terms with them. The largest of all these migrations was under the
      charge of Mars, who led a mighty host of armed men through Amritsar on his way to Central India,
      where he eventually made for himself an empire. His brother Mercury came with him as high priest.
      Alcyone felt an intense admiration for Herakles, the daughter of Mars, and could not bear to part
      from her.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Дела в его поместье шли в гору и с годами он стал богат и уважаем. Он проявлял большой интерес к
      философии атлантов и потому он и Мицар всегда были в самых дружеских отношениях как с арийскими,
      так и с атлантскими священниками, хотя наибольшую привязанность они испытывали к звездообразным
      храмам Бога Солнца. Время от времени мимо них шли волны мигрирующих арийцев с которыми ему к счастью
      всегда удавалось найти общий язык, а в память о Весте, Алкион всегда был гостеприимен к мигрантам и
      так сохранял с ними хорошии отношения. Самую большую из этих волн - могучую вооружённую армию - вёл за
      собой Марс через Амритсар в центральную Индию, где он позже основал империю. Рядом с ним был его брат
      и священник Меркурий. Алкион был поражён красотой Herakles - дочерью Марса - и момент расставания
      был для него очень тяжёл.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Both Alcyone and his wife lived to a good old age, and were much respected, he being especially
      looked up to as an expounder of the philosophy and one who was able to harmonise the conflicting
      tenets of the two religions. Towards the end of her life Mizar suffered much from rheumatism, and
      was practically bed-ridden for some years before her death at the age of seventy-five. Alcyone
      survived her for five years, himself passing away in the year 12,795.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Алкион и Мицар дожили до почтенного возраста и были очень уважаемы; Алкион в особенности за своё
      толкование философии и умение примирять догмы двух религий. К концу жизни Мицар очень страдала от
      ревматизма и была практически прикована к постели в течении нескольких лет вплоть до смерти в 75 лет.
      Алкион пережил её на пять лет и покинул тот мир в 12,795 г. до н.э.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Although there were few striking events in this life, and many years of comparatively quiet
      prosperity, it was not without its effect in developing the character of Alcyone, who gained in
      courage and decision, and showed considerable administrative ability, learning also especially the
      art of dealing wisely with men an acquisition which was of great value to him in his next
      incarnation.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Хотя в этой жизни было немного примечательных событий и много лег довольно спокойного процветания,
      нельзя не отметить её влияние на характер Алкиона который прибавил как в храбрости так и в решительности:
      он продемонстрировал неплохие навыки управления и в особенности научился мудро обращаться с людьми -
      навык, который имел большое значение в его следующей жизни.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
