<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 6</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 6-ая</view>
</title>

<text class="footer">
<view lang="en">
Africa
38,000 B.C.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Африка
38000 лет до н.э.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Two thousand years later Alcyone was still in the same sub race, but this time in a female body and in quite different sorroundings. The Arabian Empire had spread in many directions; indeed, except for a strip of Atlantean territory on the West Coast, Arabia and Egypt practically divided between them the continent of Africa. Mars had pushed his conquests as far south as the Waal River and had built himself an empire there, into which the Arabian population overcrowded at home, flowed down in ever increasing numbers. The work of erecting a new state is quite congenial to our band of Servers and as they always cluster around Mars and Mercury, who are both to be found in incarnation at this time and place, we need not wonder that but few of our characters are missing.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Две тысячи лет спустя Алкион была все еще в той же самой подрасе, но на сей раз в женском теле и в весьма отличающейся среде. Аравийская империя распространилась во многих направлениях; действительно, за исключением полосы территории атлантов на Западном Побережье, Аравия и Египет фактически разделили между собой африканский континент. Марс продвинул свои завоевания далеко на юг до реки Вaaл и утвердил империю там, куда аравийское население, переполнив свои старые земли, устремлялось в непрерывно растущем количестве. Работа построения нового государства была весьма благоприятна для нашей группы Служителей, и так как они всегда собирались вокруг Марса и Меркури, которые были в воплощении в это время и в этом месте, мы не должны задаваться вопросом, почему некоторые из наших персонажей отсутствовали.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Our hero Alcyone was the eldest daughter of Mars and his eldest son Herakles who was even already ruling a province under Him. Mercury was the emperor's sister and was married to Dhruva, who was at that time officiating as Chief priest and minister of education- a position of great power and importance, for the tradition of the occasional overshadowing of Surya by Mahaguru (which was mentioned in our last chapter) still subsisted, and, though the priest took no direct share in the government of the country their authority in certain matters was supreme. For example it was their duty to select the heir to the throne, and their choice by no means always fell upon the eldest son of the last occupants will be seen later.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Наш цeнтральный персонаж Алкион была самой старшей дочерью Марса, а его самый старший сын Геракл уже управлял одной из провинций. Меркури была сестрой короля и была замужем за Друвой, который тогда исполнял обязанности главного священника и министра образования – положение великой силы и важности, определенное Махагуру для Сурьи (который был упомянут в нашей предыдущей главе), все еще существовало, и, хотя священник не выполнял прямых акций в правительстве страны, его власть в определенных делах была высшей. Например, его обязанностью был выбор наследника трона, и этот выбор ни в коем случае не всегда выпадал на самого старшего сына последнего правителя, как будет замечено позже. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
King Mars and his people speedily built cities and temples for themselves and introduced into their new country all the arts of their civilization much as had been done in Arabia two thousand years before; but it was not found possible to Aryanise the population of the country. The inhabitants whom the newcomers had found in occupation were Negro tribes derived from several different stocks. Thousands of years before the population had been purely lemurian but it had considerably intermingled with the Rmohal  sub race and as the country had at one time been conquered by the Tlavatli, there was a small infusion of that blood also among the chieftains. Mars permitted a certain amount of experimental intermarriage indeed, he never at any time actually forbade it but His proud Arabs did not readily mingle with a race in many ways so inferior, and so radically different in color. Some of the lower class whites (for the Aryan Arabs were almost white) boldly took Negro wives, and among those who made this experiments we notice Phocea and Sirona but their mulatto children were practically a race apart. Some of these, if exceptionally pleasing in appearance, became absorbed in the ruling race, and introduced into it some rather curious new characteristics; some of them on the other hand married among the Negro population and eventually sank back into it; but the majority kept to themselves, married among themselves and dwelt to a great extent as a separate community a community which, as centuries passed on, slowly grew into a nation which acquired a territory of its own , and had a long and checkered history with which we are not concerned. It will be seen however, that the Aryanisaiton of the race previously in occupation was not in this case countenanced and recommended as it had been in Arabia; though one mixed marriage, made for political purposes, had an influence upon the lives of some of our principal characters as will presently appear.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Король Марс и его люди быстро построили города и храмы для себя и ввели в новой стране все достижения их цивилизации так же, как это было сделано в Аравии две тысячи лет назад; но не было найдено возможным арианизировать население страны. Жители, с которыми встретились вновь прибывшие, были негритянскими племенами различного происхождения. За тысячи лет до этого население было чистыми лемурианцами, затем оно значительно смешалось с подрасой рмоахалов и, поскольку страна была когда-то завоевана подрасой тлаватлей, там было небольшое вливание их крови среди вождей. Марс разрешил определенное количество экспериментальных смешанных браков – в действительности, он никогда фактически и не запрещал этого, но его гордые арабы не желали смешиваться с расой, в любом отношении столь низшей и так радикально отличающейся по цвету. Некоторые из белых низшего класса (для арийца арабы были почти белыми) смело взяли негритянских жен, и среди тех, кто сделал этот эксперимент, мы замечаем Фоси и Сирону, но их дети-мулаты были фактически обособленной расой. Некоторые из них, внешне исключительно привлекательные, были поглощены правящей расой, принеся в нее довольно любопытную новую особенность; некоторые же с другой стороны заключали браки среди негритянского населения и в конечном счете слились с ним; но большинство, заключая браки между собой, жили в основном как отдельное сообщество, которое с течением времени медленно превращалось в нацию, которая приобретала собственную территорию и имела длинную и изменчивую историю, которая нас не заинтересовала. Следует заметить однако, что арианизация расы, ранее занимавшей эту территорию, не была в этом случае одобрена и рекомендована, как это было в Аравии; хотя один смешанный брак, заключенный в политических целях, имел влияние на жизни некоторых наших основных персонажей, как теперь выяснилось.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The religion of the Negro tribe was unusual, for it consisted in the worship of a mysterious female deity, who was alleged to inhabit a certain towering rock which was visible for many miles, the foot of this rock was surrounded by almost impenetrable forest, in which (naturally enough) all sorts of dreadful daemons were supposed to dwell but no definite information was forthcoming, for no Negro dared to enter the dark and gloomy glades. It was a tradition that on several occasions daring hunters had entered into the outskirts of the woodland in pursuit of game but they had never returned; and it was commonly believed that only the chief priest of the deity could ever reach the rock in safety by means of a hidden path, a knowledge of which was one of the great secrets of his. Even he must go only at stated times to make a special offering; and, it was well understood that if he failed to keep his ghastly appointment or went without the offering, his own life would be forfeit. On the day of the full moon he must appear before his dire deity and he must be accompanied by a young and handsome man, but just come of age, who was destined for the doubtful honour of marriage with the goddess. What occurred none knew but the high priest, and his lips were sealed by awful oath; but every month he returned alone in a condition of panic terror, and nothing more was ever heard of any of the bridegrooms.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Религия негритянского племени была необычна, поскольку оно поклонялось таинственному женскому божеству, населявшему, как предполагалось, одну высокую скалу, которая была видна на много миль вокруг; подножие этой скалы было окружено почти непроходимым лесом, в котором жили (что достаточно естественно) все виды ужасных демонов, но никакой более определенной информации не было, поскольку никто из негров не осмеливался ступить на темные и мрачные поляны. Несколько раз смелые охотники доходили до края лесистой местности, но они никогда не возвращались; предполагалось, что только главный священник божества мог когда-либо достигать скалы в безопасности, следуя по скрытому пути, знание которого было одной из больших тайн его. Даже он должен был приходить только в установленное время, чтобы сделать специальное пожертвование; подразумевалось, что, если бы он был не в состоянии выдержать его ужасную обязанность или пошел бы без подношения, его собственная жизнь была бы штрафом. В ночь полнолуния он должен был появляться перед своим страшным божеством в сопровождении молодого красивого человека, только что достигшего совершеннолетия, который был предназначен для сомнительной чести брака с богиней. Что происходило потом, никто не знал, потому что уста первосвященника были запечатаны ужасной присягой; но каждый месяц он возвращался один в состоянии панического страха, и никто больше никогда не слышал ни об одном из женихов. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Rumor had it that many years before three rash youths of bold and skeptical spirit, friends of the chosen spouse of the occasion, had venturously followed the priest and the victim secretly at a distance. Two of these, it was said, had returned: one, a gibbering lunatic, who lived in that state for many years; the other a broken man, with his nerve utterly gone, so that he never held up his head again, and died a few days afterwards. The story which this same survivor told was a sufficiently horrible one. The three foolhardy youths had followed the priests through the wood, hearing and seeing much that terrified them, but still persistently pursuing until the priest and their friend had gained the foot of the rock. Then, so the trembling narrator declared, those two ascended a few feet to a kind of natural platform, behind which the face of the precipice curved back in the shape of the horse shoe - the watcher, of course staying below in the shade of the tree, because the light of the full moon fell upon the platform, so that every object upon it was clearly visible.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Ходили слухи, что много лет назад трое отважных молодых людей смелого и скептического духа, друзья выбранного в этот раз супруга, бесстрашно последовали за священником и жертвой, тайно на расстоянии. Двое из них, как говорили, возвратились: один – невнятно говорящий сумасшедший, живший еще много лет; другой – немощный человек с больными нервами, который умер через несколько дней. История, которую рассказал этот оставшийся в живых, была достаточно ужасной. Трое безрассудных молодых людей шли за священником и их другом через лес, слыша и видя то, что пугало их, но не отставая, пока священник и их друг не пришли к подножию скалы. Тогда, по словам трясущегося рассказчика, те двое поднялись несколько выше к своего рода естественной платформе, позади которой была пропасть, изогнутая в форме подковы – он же наблюдал снизу, оставаясь в тени дерева, при этом свет полной луны падал на платформу так, что каждый объект на ней был ясно виден. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then the highpriest began a strange wild chant or evocation; and suddenly, as he sang, a great gap opened in the rock, and a horde of demons rushed out - creatures like dwarfed men or huge monkeys, but somehow indescribably distorted and horrible, giving an impression of hellish hate, despair and craving for revenge.  These appalling creatures surrounded the priest and the victim, and seemed to be springing upon them and tearing at them ; but the priest thrust them roughly aside with a gesture of authority, and raised his chant again. Suddenly, in the vast doorway, which had been so mysteriously rent in the face of the cliff, appeared a huge naked female form, at sight of which the priest and his companion fell upon their faces while the demon danced around them with a strange fiendish glee. The awestricken witness described the figure of the goddess as far beyond human stature, yet beautiful with a horrible dark beauty that was not of earth; and he passionately affirmed that of all the horror the worst feature was that while he was more utterly overwhelmed with terror than he had ever been before, he was also at the same time irresistibly attracted, so that, if his limbs had not absolutely refused to obey his will, he must have crept to the feet of that grisly form, even though he knew full well that discovery meant for him something far worse than death.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Священник начал странно, не по-человечески петь или взывать; внезапно после того, как он пропел, в скале открылась большая щель, и выбежала орда демонов – существ, как примитивные люди или огромные обезьяны, но так или иначе, неопределенно искаженных и ужасных, полных адской ненависти, отчаяния и желания мести. Эти ужасные существа окружили священника и жертву, и казалось, были готовы прыгнуть на них и разорвать их; но священник остановил их властным жестом и возобновил свое пение. Внезапно в обширном дверном проеме, который так загадочно возник на поверхности утеса, появилась огромная голая женская форма, при виде которой священник и его компаньон упали ниц, в то время как демоны танцевали вокруг них со странным жестоким ликованием. Свидетель, охваченный благоговейным страхом, описал фигуру богини намного более высокой, чем человеческая, и все же красивой какой-то ужасной темной красотой, которой не могло быть на земле; и он неистово утверждал, что из всего ужаса его худшей особенностью было то, что, в то время как он был крайне поражен страхом, как никогда прежде, он был в то же самое время неодолимо прельщен, так что его члены абсолютно отказались ему повиноваться, он полз к ногам той ужасной формы, очень хорошо зная, что раскрытие себя означало для него кое-что намного худшее, чем смерть.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Presently the priest and the bridegroom rose to their feet, and an awful alluring smile broke forth upon the face of the giant figure, and she held out her arm to the doomed man as he moved slowly towards her walking as though in a trance. As he came within her reach, she stooped forward and lifted him in her arms lifted that big, strong man lightly, as one might lift a kitten, and turned, carrying him, and disappeared into the darkness. The demons rushed tumultuously in after her and suddenly the rock was a blank wall in the bright moonlight, and the priest was staggering down the path from the platform like a drunken man. He was too full of his own mad fear to see the watcher, though he passed closed to them, than, they followed him in his wild flight back through that haunted forest as well as they could. But once they lost sight of him in the darkness, and so lost the path also, and fell into an apparently bottomless mud hole, from, which only two of them escaped, and that with the greatest difficulty and the most exhausting effort. When this happened they were already near the verge of the wood, so somehow the survivors made their way out of it, and somehow they got home again, but the only one who could speak said it would have been better for them if they also had died in the bog. And when the high priest heard the story, he smiled a dreadful smile, and said that those who pried into the mysteries of the goddess could not expect to escape her vengeance.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Теперь священник и жених встали на ноги, и ужасная, но очаровательная улыбка появилась на лице гигантской фигуры, она протягивала свою руку к обреченному человеку, поскольку он медленно двигался к ней, как если бы был в трансе. Как только он оказался в пределах ее досягаемости, она наклонилась вперед и легко подняла его руками, как большой сильный человек мог бы поднять котенка, повернулась, неся его, и исчезла в темноте. Демоны шумно помчались вслед за ней, и внезапно скала снова стала глухой стеной в ярком лунном свете, и священник сошел вниз с платформы, пошатываясь, как пьяный. Он был слишком полон собственным безумным страхом, чтобы заметить наблюдателей, хотя он прошел вблизи от них; и тогда они последовали за ним, в его диком обратном беге через незнакомый лес. Но как только они потеряли его из виду в темноте, так потеряли и путь тоже, и попали, очевидно, в бездонную топь, из которой удалось выбраться только двоим из них, и это оказалось самой большой трудностью и потребовало самых утомительных усилий. Когда они уже были около края леса, таким образом, так или иначе оставшись в живых и так или иначе возвращаясь домой, тогда тот, кто мог говорить, сказал, что было бы лучше для них, если бы они тоже утонули в трясине. А когда первосвященник услышал эту историю, он улыбнулся страшной улыбкой и сказал, что тот, кто сует нос в тайны богини, не может надеяться уйти от ее мести.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This was the tradition  handed down in the tribe, and it may easily be imagined how such a tale would affect the mind of a crowd of superstitious savages. This grim religion was surrounded with such secrecy that it was not for a long time that the new ruling race heard anything definite about it. As the Negroes always bowed towards the rock whenever they caught sight of it, it was at first supposed that they worshipped it, and later that they regarded it as the throne or symbol of some deity. But the existence of the alleged goddess and the sacrifices periodically offered to her remained entirely unsuspected. The way in which it became known, and all that followed upon the discovery, will appear as we unfold our story.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Это было традицией племени, и можно легко предположить, как такой рассказ затронул бы ум толпы суеверных дикарей. Их мрачная религия была окружена такой тайной, которая существовала в течение долгого времени, так что новая правящая раса не узнала чего-либо определенного из этого. Поскольку негры кланялись любой скале всякий раз, когда они замечали ее, сначала предполагалось, что они поклонялись и этой, как трону или символу некоего божества. Но существование предполагаемой богини и жертв, периодически предлагаемых ей, оставалось неизвестным. Путь, через который это стало известно, и все, что последовало за открытием, появятся, поскольку мы разворачиваем нашу историю. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In order that this may be comprehensible, we must first describe the other side of this repulsive religion the benefits which her people were supposed to receive from their promiscuously polyandrous goddess in return for the heavy toll of sacrifices exacted by her. A peculiarly gruesome item in the disagreeable impression which she produced upon the one person outside her priesthood who claimed to have seen her was that baleful power of irresistible attraction apparently magnetic in its character. It was asserted that she was able to confer this power upon her votaries that her priest possessed by virtue of their office, and they could bestow it upon others at will for a consideration, of course! It could be used on a small scale in matters of daily life, or on a large scale in national affairs; by it a young brave could compel the affection of the lady of his choice, a merchant could influence the mind of a customer so that he obtained his own price for his goods, or a man engaged in combat with another could render his enemy harmless. The power may be described as communicable mesmeric control, and by its means there is no doubt that the priests contrived to enrich themselves considerably.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Чтобы все это понять, мы должны сначала описать другую сторону этой отталкивающей религии — льготы, которые ее люди, как предполагалось, получали от их богини беспорядочной полиандрии взамен тяжелых жертвоприношений, подносимых ей. Странным и ужасным пунктом в неприятном впечатлении, которое она произвела на человека вне ее духовенства, который утверждал, что видел ее, была мрачная власть непреодолимой привлекательности, очевидно, магнетическая в ее характере. Утверждалось, что она была в состоянии присудить ее почитателям эту власть, которой священник обладал как ее служитель, а они могли даровать ее другим по желанию – после рассмотрения, конечно! Это могло использоваться в мелком масштабе в делах ежедневной жизни или в крупном масштабе в государственных делах; этим бравый молодой человек мог заставить привязаться к нему леди его выбора, торговец мог влиять на ум клиента так, чтобы он получил свою собственную цену за его товары, или человек, втянутый в бой с другим, мог безопасно направить его на другого врага. Власть может быть описана как гипнотическое управление общением, и ее средствами, без сомнения, священники умудрялись значительно себя обогащать.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Mars and Dhruva had resolved not to interfere in any way with the religion of the Negroes to give them the opportunity of hearing a plain statement of truth, but not to excite opposition by seeming in any way to force it upon their attention. Their general plan was one of conciliation in all directions, and though they insisted upon just and  sufficient government, and held all the real power in   their own hands, they still left the Negro chiefs and the priests as much of the pomp and the outward show as they desired. The chieftain of the  period is not one of our characters, but his two sons appear in our list as Markab and Scorpio; and it was while the second of these was still a boy that the attention of the conquerors was first attracted to this curious religious hypnotism. The old chief intended that his eldest son Markab succeed to such a show of state as was left to him, and with a view to securing his position instructed him to seek for a wife among the ruling race. He even suggested to Mars that it would be a suitable arrangement if Markab could wed Alcyone, who was then a beautiful girl of fourteen; but Mars declined this ingenuous offer, and Markab consoled himself with the affection of Abel, a  pretty girl of much lower class among the Arabs. From this marriage of political expediency was born Pollux, who caused much trouble later on.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Марс и Друва решили в любом случае не вмешиваться в религию негров – чтобы дать им возможность просто услышать правду, не усиливая оппозицию тем, что могло бы каким-либо способом вызвать их внимание. Их общий план исходил из идеи примирения по всем направлениям, и хотя они настояли на своем достаточно сильном правительстве, они сдерживали всю действительную мощь их собственной руки; они оставили негритянских руководителей и священников в большом количестве из-за их показного великолепия, поскольку они того желали. Их вождь в это время не был ни одним из наших персонажей, но его два сына появляются в нашем списке как Маркаб и Скорпион; когда второй из них был еще мальчиком, внимание завоевателей было привлечено к этому любопытному религиозному гипнозу. Старый вождь надеялся, что его самый старший сын Маркаб преуспеет на таком же посту в государстве, какой предоставили ему, и с целью упрочения его положения порекомендовал ему искать жену среди правящей расы. Он даже предложил Марсу, что это была бы подходящая договоренность, если бы Маркаб мог жениться на Алкион, которая была тогда красивой девушкой четырнадцати лет; но Марс отклонил это бесхитростное предложение, и Маркаб утешил себя привязанностью Абель, симпатичной девушки более низкого класса среди арабов. От этого брака политической целесообразности был рожден Поллукс, который позднее создал большую проблему.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
With the laudable view of concentrating in his own family whatever in the way of power lay within his reach, the old chief had bargained with the high priest, who happened to be childless, that his own second son Scorpio should succeed to that important office; and consequently the boy was already undergoing the necessary training. Young Scorpio also, as well as his elder brother, had designs upon the beautiful Alcyone; and though he knew enough that he could never legitimately obtain her hand in marriage, he thought that he might get her into his power by the  peculiar forces which he was learning to use. With this end in view he contrived to put himself in her way,  and practice his unclean arts of fascination upon her not without some effect, for she found herself constantly thinking of him, with an odd mixture of detestation and an incomprehensible sort of attraction. She spoke of him to her cousin and playmate Sirius, who had constituted himself her knight and attendant, while the gentler Alcyone thought there must be something good in him to cause that half sense of attraction.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
С незаурядным представлением о пути его собственной семьи к власти, пролегающем в пределах его досягаемости, старый вождь заключил сделку с первосвященником (у которого, как оказалось, не было детей), что его собственный второй сын Скорпион должен преуспеть в этой важной деятельности; и, следовательно, мальчик уже приступил к необходимому обучению. У молодого Скорпиона так же, как и у его старшего брата, были проекты по поводу прекрасной Алкион; и хотя он прекрасно знал, что он никогда не сможет легитимно добиться ее руки, он думал, что он смог бы получить ее при помощи специфических сил, которыми он учился пользоваться. Придя к такому решению, он умудрился оказаться на ее пути и практиковать свое грязное искусство обаяния в отношении ее — не без некоторого эффекта, поскольку она обнаружила себя постоянно думающей о нем со смешанным чувством отвращения и непостижимого влечения. Алкион рассказала о нем своему кузену и приятелю Сириусу, который держал себя как ее рыцарь и адъютант; в то же время она думала, что должно же быть что-то хорошее в человеке, если эта привлекательность проявляется.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Even her charity was strained, however, by his action a few days later. Meeting her one-day in a lonely part of a great garden near the palace, he turned the full battery of his half acquired hypnotic  power upon her, and tried to compel her to submit to her embraces. Hitherto unknown feelings began to stir within her; though she had a strong sense of anger and outrage, she yet could not move from the spot, and there was somehow half of her that did not want to move. Fortunately the faithful Sirius ( who had been detained by some work which he had to do for his father) was on her track, and came rushing up just as Scorpio, with lust flaming in his eyes, was about  to clasp her unresisting form in his arms. Sirius hurled him to the ground, and turned sharply to Alcyone, asking  how she could let such a creature come near her. She haltingly explained how utterly she had loathed him, and yet had felt powerless to move as long as his eyes were upon hers; how some strange hateful spell had set half of her warring against the other half, and how his burning eyes had somehow soiled her and made her very soul feel unclean. Sirius, hearing and raging, set off again in chase of the culprit, who had limped away cursing; and the latter, seeing him gaining upon him, and realising that his anger was dangerous, leapt over the river that flowed through the garden, and thus escaped for the time by swimming to the other  side; while Sirius, having explained emphatically to the discomfited youth in the water exactly what unpleasant things, he would do to him if he ever caught him thus trespassing again, returned to comfort Alcyone.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Все же ее милосердие было вымученным, что подтвердилось его некоторыми действиями несколько дней спустя. Встретив ее однажды в безлюдной части большого сада около дворца, он полностью развернул свою почти приобретенную гипнотическую силу и попытался заставить ее подчиниться его объятиям. Внутри нее начали шевелиться ранее неизвестные чувства; хотя у нее был сильный повод для гнева и сопротивления, она все же не могла сдвинуться с места, и так или иначе, но была половина ее, которая не хотела уходить. К счастью преданный Сириус (отвлеченный некоторой работой, которую он должен был сделать для своего отца), думая о ней, прибыл, мчась так же, как Скорпион, с жаждой, пылающей в его глазах, и собираясь стиснуть ее в своих объятиях. Сириус, швырнув его на землю, резко повернулся к Алкион, чтобы выяснить, как она могла позволить такому существу подойти к ней. Она сбивчиво объяснила ему, как она сильно ненавидела его и все же чувствовала себя безвольной, чтобы уйти из-под его взгляда; как некое странное и ненавистное колдовство настроило одну ее половину враждебно против другой ее половины, и как его горящие глаза так или иначе пачкали ее и заставили саму ее душу чувствовать себя грязной. Сириус, выслушав и возмутившись, бросился в погоню за злодеем, который с проклятиями убегал прочь; последний, видя, как был опасен гнев, направленный против него, прыгнул в реку, которая текла через сад, и, таким образом, убежал в этот раз, переплыв на другую сторону; тогда как Сириус, объяснив решительно и точно беглецу в воде, какие именно неприятные вещи он сделал бы ему, если бы он когда-либо изловил его за нарушение границы вновь, возвратился, чтобы успокоить Алкиона. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
They talked the matter over exhaustively, and as they knew nothing whatever about hypnotism they came to the conclusion that it must be some horrible aboriginal magic; and Sirius promptly bore off the troubled Alcyone to his mother Mercury, who was wise in such matters. She heard their story , sympathised with their indignation, and reassured them by saying that she had heard of this kind of magic before, and that the power of the eye , as she called it, could be used for good as well as for evil, though the Priests of the light employed it but sparingly, not thinking it well to take a man's will from him even for a noble purpose. And she taught Alcyone a sacred word by the repetition of which such a spell could be averted if ever Scorpio should try it again; but Sirius calmly remarked that he did not think Scorpio would try it again; but that if he did, he, Sirius, would personally attend to him in such a way that he would work no more spells in that incarnation. Mercury smiled enigmatically and sent the children off together, greatly comforted. Sirius was right so far, for Scorpio had learned his lesson, and made no further direct attempts upon Alcyone. A few years later he married Hesper, a girl of his own race, and presently became high priest, as his astute father had intended.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Они исчерпывающе обсудили вопрос, и так как они вообще ничего не знали о гипнозе, они пришли к выводу, что это, должно быть, некая ужасная местная магия; и Сириус быстро рассказал о проблеме Алкион своей матери Меркури, которая была мудра в таких делах. Она слушала их историю, симпатизируя их негодованию, и успокоила их, сказав, что она знала об этом виде магии давно, и что власть глаза, поскольку она так назвала это, может использоваться как для хорошего, так и для плохого; и хотя священники Света используют это, но в меру, не считая хорошим, чтобы лишать человека его воли даже в благородных целях. И она передалаАлкион священное слово, повторением которого можно было предотвратить такое заклинание, если когда-либо Скорпион захочет попробовать его снова; но Сириус спокойно заметил, что он не думает, что Скорпион попробует его снова; но что, если он сделает это, то он, Сириус, лично проявит внимание к нему таким способом, который не позволит ему больше делать эти заклинания в этом воплощении. Меркури загадочно улыбнулась и отослала вполне успокоенных детей. Сириус был пока прав, поскольку Скорпион выучил свой урок и не делал дальнейших прямых попыток в отношении Алкион. Несколько лет спустя он женился на Геспер, девушке его собственной расы, и теперь стал первосвященником, как и предвидел его проницательный отец.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This was the first event which drew the attention of the ruling race to the uncanny powers connected with the Negro religion, but the subject was not seriously persued. Strangely enough it was a similar occurrence in the very same family twenty years later that caused further inquiry, which resulted in a full exposure of the whole iniquitous business, and the downfall of the obscene cult which had cursed the country for so long.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Это был первый случай, который привлек внимание правящей расы к необычным полномочиям, связанным с негритянской религией, но предмет не был серьезно оценен. Достаточно странно, что нечто подобное повторилось в той же самой семье двадцать лет спустя, а это вызвало дальнейшие события, которые привели к полной ликвидации целого неправедного бизнеса и крушению непристойного культа, который надолго проклял страну.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
As might naturally be expected, Sirius and Alcyone married in due course, and it will be seen equally natural to students of reincarnation that Mizar should be their eldest son, and Electra their eldest daughter, and that all these should be linked together by bonds of affection of far more than common strength. Other children followed, all of them characters well known and loved in previous and later lives, all of them, dear now as then, though some have reached the further shore and hold high office among Those who rule the world. It has been mentioned that Markab, the Negro chief, had married  Abel; he had four mulatto children two boys, Pollux and Tripos, brothers again, as they had been two thousands years ago in Arabia, and of much the same respective dispositions; and two girls, Alastor and Cetus, less coarse at any rate than their male relations.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Как и должно было случиться, Сириус и Алкион должным образом поженились, и как будет замечено изучающими перевоплощение, Мицар должен быть их самым старшим сыном, а Электра их самой старшей дочерью, и что все они должны быть соединены силой привязанности намного большей, чем обычно. Другие дети следовали, все они персонажи известные и любимые в их предыдущих и более поздних жизнях, дорогие и теперь, как тогда, хотя некоторые достигли Другого Берега и получили высшие должности среди Тех, кто управляет миром. Было упомянуто, что Маркаб, негритянский вождь женился на Абель; у него было четыре ребенка-мулата два мальчика Поллукс и Трипос, братья снова, как они и были две тысячи лет назад в Аравии, и с почти такими же взаимоотношениями; и две девочки, Аластор и Сетус, менее грубые во всяком случае, чем их мужские воплощения.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Now Electra, even while still a child, was famed throughout the land for her wondrous beauty; and Pollux, being so much what he had been in Arabia, was all aflame with desire to possess her for his own. Being the eldest son of the chief, he was in the habit of seizing what ever he wanted, so he thought that in this case also he had only to ask to have, and was much surprised and annoyed when he found his suit politely but quite definitely rejected. Soon he was more than surprised and annoyed, for he was like a spoilt child, and could not bear to be contradicted or denied, so he sulked and fretted until he grew actually ill with unfulfilled desire. Now Markab really loved his eldest son, and saw nothing but a proper sense of his position in his most flagrant faults of character; also he had never forgiven Mars and Alcyone for rejecting his own offer of marriage to the latter, any more than Scorpio had forgotten his bitter experience at the hands of Sirius as a boy. Therefore these worthies laid their hands together, and resolved that Pollux should not be left to suffer from love-sickness, but that Electra should be abducted for him thus not only relieving his pain, but paying off old scores at the same time, and gratifying a long smoldering hatred.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Электра с детских лет была известна по всей стране из-за ее поразительной красоты; и Поллукс, будучи фактически тем же, чем он был в Аравии, едва сдерживал огонь желания обладать ею для себя. Как самый старший сын вождя, он имел привычку захватывать то, чего когда-либо он хотел, таким образом, он думал, что и в этом случае он должен только пожелать; и был очень удивлен и раздражен, когда нашел свой иск вежливо, но весьма определенно отклоненным. Он был более, чем удивлен, и поскольку он походил на испорченного ребенка, не могущего даже представить, чтобы ему противоречили, он сделался фактически больным из-за невыполненного желания. Маркаб, действительно любивший самого старшего сына и не видевший настоящего смысла его положения в его самых скандальных свойствах характера, никогда не забывал того, что Марс и Алкион отклонили его собственное предложение брака с последней, во всяком случае меньше, чем Скорпион забыл свой горький опыт от кулаков Сириуса. Поэтому эти важные персоны, ударив по рукам, решили, что нельзя оставлять Поллукса страдающим от любви, но для него должна быть похищена Электра, чтобы таким образом не только освободить его от боли, но и окупить одновременно все старое, удовлетворив их так долго тлеющую ненависть. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
They chose for their nefarious plot a time when Sirius and Alcyone were away from home for a day or two, attending to some of his priestly business on another city. By a forged note, purporting to come from a girl friend, they easily lured the unsuspecting Electra from the shelter of her home; then Scorpio met her just as he had once met her, and with the added power conferred by  years of practice, at once determined her will and induced her to accompany him unresistingly to the household of Markab. She had never heard of his attempt to seize her mother, but he was a man whom she instinctively disliked and rather feared; yet she afterwards declared that she had no option but to go with him that (just as her mother had said) half of her wanted to go, while the other half vehemently protested. Go she did, at any rate, and as they walked along Scorpio used all his arts to strengthen  his hold upon her will, taking into his hand a certain talisman which he wore and by its means invoking his dreadful goddess to send her power through him, and receiving in reply a strong outpouring of the smell of musk, which was always a sign of her attention and approval.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Они выбрали для их низкого заговора время, когда Сириус и Алкион были вне дома в течение дня или двух, чтобы устроить часть его священнических дел в другом городе. Подделанным письмом, якобы отправленным подругой, они легко выманили ничего не подозревающую Электру из ее дома; тогда Скорпион встретил ее так же, как он когда-то встретил ее мать, но с использованием силы, умноженной годами практики, и сразу определил ее желание и побудил ее податливо сопровождать его к дому Маркаба. Она никогда не слышала о его попытке схватить ее мать, но он был человеком, которого она инстинктивно не любила и скорее боялась; все же она впоследствии объявила, что у нее не было никакого выбора, кроме как пойти с ним — что (так же, как у ее матери) одна половина ее требовала, чтобы пойти, в то время как другая половина сильно возражала. Идти она согласилась, и когда они шли, Скорпион использовал все свое искусство, чтобы усилить его власть над ее желанием, взяв в руку определенный талисман, который он носил, и посредством его призвал свою ужасную богиню, чтобы она послала ее силу через него, и получил в ответ сильное излияние запаха мускуса, который всегда был признаком ее внимания и одобрения. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Electra followed him docilely to Markab's house, and there, to make more certain of her absolute submission, he administered to her a potion well known to many tribes, a compound of some of their vile secret poisons which has the effect of weakening the will, and of weakening and eventually destroying the memory. Having done this, he locked her safely in one of the rooms while he wet to tell Pollux, who was ill in bed and feverish with his disappointed desires. His uncle's news effected a temporary cure; he hastily rose and began to dress himself elaborately, with the view of making a favourable impression on his victim. But when, having completed his toilet, he hurried down to the reception room where he expected to find his love awaiting him, the door was unfastened and the bird had flown! This was indeed a staggering surprise to all three villains, for they well knew that the drug alone, to say nothing of the hypnotism, made it quite impossible that their victim could have walked away voluntarily; she must have been carried away, but by whom? They began to feel terribly frightened, for to them this savoured of the supernatural; and even if there was some natural explanation, matters were but little improved, for that must involve the discovery villainy, and terrible vengeance from the outraged Arabs.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Электра послушно следовала за ним к дому Маркаба, и там, чтобы сделать более бесспорным ее абсолютное подчинение, он дал ей зелье, известное многим племенам, часть которого составляли мерзкие секретные яды, имеющие эффект ослабления воли и ослабления и в конечном счете разрушения памяти. Сделав это, он благополучно запер ее в одной из комнат и пошел, чтобы сказать Поллуксу, который лежал больным в кровати с лихорадкой от его неисполненных желаний. Новость его дяди произвела временное излечение; он торопливо поднялся и начал продуманно украшать себя с целью произвести благоприятное впечатление на свою жертву. Но когда, закончив свое переодевание, он быстро спустился к комнате приема, где он был готов найти ждущую его любовь, дверь оказалась открытой, а птичка – улетела! Это было действительно потрясающим сюрпризом для всех трех злодеев, поскольку они хорошо знали, что одно только зелье, не говоря уже о гипнозе, лишало жертву любой возможности уйти самостоятельно; она, должно быть, была унесена, но кем? Они начали чувствовать себя ужасно напуганными, для них это отдавало сверхъестественным; и даже если было некоторое разумное объяснение, дела все равно были плохи, поскольку это вело к раскрытию их подлости и к страшной мести со стороны оскорбленных арабов. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Leaving them for the moment to their terrified consultations, let us explain exactly what had happened. One of the servants of the chief, Markab was our old acquaintance Boreas; he had seen Alcyone on several occasions, and felt a strong admiration for her, because of which he had made enquiries into the religion of the light, and had secretly accepted it. He knew a great deal of the  depravity of his master and of the execrable Scorpio; and when he saw the latter bring the young Electra into this infamous house, he at once suspected some unimaginable turpitude. Catching a glimpse of her face, he saw that she was under what he would have called magical influence, and he instantly resolved, for Alcyone's sake, to save her daughter from whatever hellish plot had been woven around her. As soon as Scorpio went away to Pollux's room, Boreas unfastened the door he had just barred, and walked straight in upon Electra, who lifted a wan and uncomprehending face to greet his entrance.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Покинув их на время для их испуганных переговоров, мы сейчас точно объясним, что случилось. Одним из слуг вождя Маркаба был наш старый знакомый Борей; он видел Алкион несколько раз и почувствовал сильное восхищение ею, из-за чего он начал интересоваться религией Света, и тайно принял ее. Он знал многое о развращенности своего хозяина и отвратительного Скорпиона; и когда он увидел, что последний привел молодую Электру в этот позорный дом, он стал подозревать, что готовится некая невообразимая низость. Мельком увидев ее лицо, он понял, что она была под тем, что он назовет магическим влиянием, и он немедленно решил спасти дочь Алкиона от этого адского заговора, который был соткан вокруг нее. Как только Скорпион пошел в комнату Поллукса, Борей открыл дверь, которая только что была заперта, и вошел к Электре, которая повернула к нему бледное и непонимающее лицо, чтобы приветствовать его появление.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Lady  he said earnestly and respectfully,   I am your friend, and I have come to save you from wicked men; I beg you to come back to your home with me at once. But she could not understand him clearly; she only replied: How can I come? He told me to wait here for him. There was no time for argument; begging her to pardon him, he lifted her in his arms and carried her out quickly into the garden, and by a side path and through some outhouses to a gate.  Lady,    he said,   you are in great danger; trust me, come with me, and I will save you. I cannot carry you outside without attracting too much attention; you must walk with me, and I will help you along. 
</view>
<view lang="ru">
"Леди", сказал он искренне и с уважением, “я – Ваш друг, и я пришел, чтобы спасти Вас от злых людей; я прошу Вас немедленно возвратиться в Ваш дом со мной.” 
Но она не могла понять его ясно; она только ответила: “Как я могу пойти? Он сказал мне ждать здесь его.”
Не было никакого времени для аргументации; прося ее простить ему, он поднял ее и на руках быстро перенес в сад и затем окольным путем через какие-то надворные постройки к воротам.
“Леди,” сказал он, “Вы находитесь в большой опасности; доверяйте мне, идите со мной, и я спасу Вас. Я не могу нести Вас снаружи, не привлекая слишком большого внимания; Вы должны идти со мной, а я буду помогать Вам.”
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
She obeyed as if automatically, for the drug had disturbed the effect of hypnotic action; but it had also weakened her physically, and she walked with uncertain steps. He hurried her along as well as he could, half supporting and guiding her, until he felt himself out of immediate  pursuit; and then he allowed her to walk more slowly. His object was to get her home unnoticed, if it might be ; for he realised that her capture by Scorpio and her presence alone in a house of evil reputation should if possible not be generally known until he had explained it to Alcyone, and knew her wishes in the matter. He therefore took an unfrequented way, and was fortunate enough to escape almost entirely unquestioned. Entering the house of Sirius, he demanded at once to see Alcyone, and was sadly disappointed to hear that she and Sirius were away from home; he hesitated for a moment, and then asked to see Mizar. The latter was horrified at the sight of the pale, frightened face of his sister, and still more so to find that she could not speak to him coherently, and seemed not to understand what he said to her. He demanded an explanation from Boreas, who Told all that he knew, and incidentally asked to be taken into the Sirius household as a servant, as he could never now go back to that of Markab. Assuring him of his protection, Mizar made him repeat carefully once more of his account of what had occurred, and by a few gentle and tactful questions to poor Electra elicited enough from her to enable him to grasp the situation. He then sent for his sister Fides and Saturn, placed Electra in their care and told them to get her to bed and if possible to sleep; and then started out in a towering rage for the house of Markab.  
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Она повиновалась, как будто автоматически, от зелья нарушился эффект гипнотического воздействия; но это также ослабило ее физически, и она шла неуверенными шагами. Он помогал ей, как мог, наполовину поддерживая и ведя ее, пока он не почувствовал себя вне опасности непосредственного преследования; и затем он позволил ей идти более медленно. Его цель состояла в том, чтобы привести ее домой по возможности незаметно; поскольку он сознавал, что ее захват Скорпионом и одно только ее присутствие в доме с дурной репутацией не должны стать общеизвестными, пока он не объяснит все Алкион и не узнает ее пожелания по этому вопросу. Поэтому он выбрал нечасто посещаемый путь, и они достаточно успешно прошли почти никем не замеченными. Войдя в дом Сириуса, он сразу потребовал увидеть Алкион, и был сильно разочарован, узнав, что она и Сириус были вне дома; он колебался мгновение и затем попросил встречи с Мицаром. Последний был шокирован при виде бледного, напуганного лица его сестры, а всего более тем, что она не могла говорить с ним адекватно и, казалось, не понимала того, что он говорил ей. Он потребовал объяснения от Борея, который рассказал все, что он знал, и между прочим попросил взять его в домашнее хозяйство Сириуса как слугу, поскольку он теперь не мог возвратиться к Маркабу. Заверив его в его безопасности, Мицар заставил его повторить тщательно еще раз все, что произошло, и после нескольких коротких и тактичных вопросов к бедной Электре получил от нее достаточно информации, чтобы быстро оценить ситуацию. Тогда он послал за своими сестрами Фидес и Сатурн, поручил им ухаживать за Электрой: положить ее в кровать, чтобы она по возможности спала; и затем отправился в гневе к дому Маркаба.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Arrived there, he walked straight in without ceremony or hesitation, and found the three trembling rogues still in fearful consultation. He was as yet scarcely more than a boy,  but he was a son of the dominant race, and he expressed his opinion of that chief and the high priest in rigorous and unflattering terms. He paid not the slightest heed to the boasted mesmeric power of the priest, who indeed was far too disturbed in mind to be able to use it. He concluded the denunciation with these words:
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Прибыв туда, он сразу вошел без церемоний и колебаний и нашел трех испуганных дрожащих жуликов. Он был пока еще почти мальчиком, но он был сыном доминирующей расы, и он выразил свое мнение относительно вождя и первосвященника в строгих и нелестных терминах. Он не обращал ни малейшего внимания на имевшуюся гипнотическую силу священника, который, действительно, был слишком встревожен, чтобы быть в состоянии использовать ее. Он заключил обвинение такими словами:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 You know quite well that I have only to go before my grandfather the King and tell my story, and within the hour you will be in prison, never to leave it alive; and you know that that is the fate that you deserve. But if that were done , your crime and my sister's misfortune would be known to all the kingdom, and I do not choose that it shall be so known. My mother is away from home; if when she returns she finds my sister still in this condition, she will be troubled about it, and I do not intend to have her troubled. Therefore instead of delivering you to justice, I will agree not to denounce you on this one condition ; that you come at once and remove your diabolical spell from my sister's mind, and restore her to normal health. If you don't do this, be sure that you shall both die. 
</view>
<view lang="ru">
“Вы знаете весьма хорошо, что я могу пойти к своему деду королю и рассказать эту историю, и в течение часа вы будете в тюрьме, откуда никогда не выйдете живыми; и вы знаете, что это – судьба, которую вы заслужили. Но если бы это было сделано, то ваше преступление и несчастье моей сестры были бы известны всему королевству, а я не желаю, чтобы это было настолько известно. Моей матери нет дома; если, когда она вернется, она найдет мою сестру все еще в этом состоянии, то она будет обеспокоена, а я не намерен видеть ее обеспокоенной. Поэтому вместо того, чтобы доставить вас правосудию, я соглашусь не делать этого при условии, что вы идете и сразу удаляете свое дьявольское колдовство из ума моей сестры и восстанавливаете ее нормальное здоровье. Если вы не сделаете этого, будьте уверены, что вы оба умрете.” 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Markab at once breathed more freely, and made haste to agree; but Scorpio looked more disturbed than ever and, and said: Young white lord, I would truly do this for you if I could; but what you ask is impossible. If I had cast only my spell upon your sister  I could remove it ; but I have worked upon her the greatest magic at my command. I have cast upon her the spell of the goddess, and the goddess herself has ratified it; only she herself can remove it, if she should choose. But she will never choose to do so. I know nothing of your goddess ,  replied Mizar sternly,  and I do not fear her, because I worship the Light; but if only she can remove the spell, lead me at once to her shrine, and I will speak to her face to face in the power of the Light, and will compel her do undo her foul magic. Master , master,  cried  Scorpio in horrified accents  you know not what you say ; it is death to look upon the face of the goddess, and no man may withstand her power. Perchance that may be so,  replied Mizar;   Yet I shall not shrink from death for the sake of my mother and my sister. But at least I will face this goddess, and the  spell shall be removed. Young sir, you are brave ; though I hate your family, I admire your courage,  said Scorpio;  but I warn you that it is useless. Take me to your goddess, or you shall both die,  was all the reply that Mizar would give. Lead him to her, brother,  said Markab, it is better that he should die than we.   Come then if you must have it so,  said Scorpio;  but your blood be upon your head. I do not even know that the goddess will show herself on any day but her own day of the full moon; and it may be that she will slay us even for disturbing her rest. Yet come, since come you must. For myself, I care not; it can be death either way, and I do not think that she will kill her priest.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Маркаб сразу задышал более свободно, и поторопился согласиться; но Скорпион выглядел более встревоженным, чем его брат, и сказал:  “Молодой белый лорд, я действительно сделал бы это для Вас, если бы я мог; но то, что Вы спрашиваете, невозможно. Если бы я создал только свое заклинание для Вашей сестры, я мог бы удалить его; но я направил на нее величайшую магию по своей команде. Я вызвал на нее заклинание богини, и сама богиня санкционировала его; только сама она может удалить это, если она захочет. Но она никогда не захочет сделать так.” “Я ничего не знаю о вашей богине,” ответил Мицар серьезно,“ и я не боюсь ее, потому что я поклоняюсь Свету; но если только она может удалить заклинание, ведите меня сразу к ее святыне, и я буду говорить с ней один на один в силе Света, и это заставит ее уничтожить ее грязную магию.”  “Господин, господин,” вскричал Скорпион испуганно, “Вы, не знаете, что Вы говорите; это смерть – смотреть в лицо богини, и никакой человек не может противостоять ее силе.” “Возможно это так,” ответил Мицар; “но я не буду уклоняться от смерти ради своей матери и своей сестры. По крайней мере я окажусь перед этой богиней, и заклинание будет удалено.” “Молодой сэр, Вы храбры; хотя я ненавижу Вашу семью, я восхищаюсь Вашей храбростью,” сказал Скорпион; “но я предупреждаю Вас, что это бесполезно.” “Возьмите меня к вашей богине, или вы оба должны умереть,” был ответ, который дал Мицар. “Приведи его к ней, брат,” сказал Маркаб, “пусть лучше он умрет, чем мы.” “Идите тогда, если Вы должны сделать это,” сказал Скорпион; “но Ваша кровь будет на Вашей голове. Я даже не знаю, может ли богиня показаться в любой день, но ее собственный день – полнолуние; вполне возможно, что она убьет нас даже за то, что мы нарушим ее отдых. Все же идите, раз Вы должны. О себе я не забочусь; смерть придет любым путем, и я не думаю, что она убьет своего священника.”
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So Mizar and Scorpio started together for the haunted forest, the priest revolving in his mind the various plans for killing his companions so that he might avoid the risk of angering the goddess. But Mizar was on his guard and contrived always that Scorpio should lead the way and thus the latter had not the opportunity to which he had hoped of pushing him into one of the bottomless mire holes in the swamps. Unknown to the two adventurers, Boreas, who knew Scorpio well enough to be incessantly suspicious of him was following him at a distance, armed with a heavy and murderous looking dagger and fully determined to use it in Mizar's defense if he saw the slightest suggestion of foul play. In course of time he reached the rock platform, and Scorpio once more urged Mizar to abandon his project and return without attempting to see the deity, upon whom it was death for any but his duly appointed priest to look. But Mizar impatiently bade him get on with his conjuration; and so in despair he raised the strange immemorial imploring cry which had never before been used except the night of the full moon.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Так Мицар и Скорпион вошли вместе в часто посещаемый лес; священник, перебирал в уме различные планы относительно убийства его компаньона, чтобы избежать риска возмущения богини. Но Мицар был настороже и всегда делал так, чтобы Скорпион шел впереди, и таким образом у последнего не было возможности, на которую он надеялся – столкнуть его в одну из бездонных топей в болотах. Неизвестный этим двум, Борей, который знал Скорпиона достаточно хорошо, чтобы с подозрением относиться к нему, следовал за ними на расстоянии, вооруженный тяжелым и убийственно выглядящим кинжалом и решительно настроенный использовать его для защиты Мицара, если бы он увидел малейший признак умышленного нарушения правил. Наконец, они дошли до горной платформы, и Скорпион еще раз попытался убедить Мицара оставить его план и возвратиться, не пытаясь увидеть божество, потому что это была смерть для любого человека, не назначенного священником. Но Мицар нетерпеливо предложил ему приступить к вызыванию; и тогда в отчаянии он поднял странный умоляющий крик, который прежде никогда не использовался кроме ночей полнолуния. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It seemed to do its ghastly work as well by sunlight as by moonlight, for the traditional results quickly followed; the rock door rose, the horrid horde of malignant creatures rushed out, and directly afterwards the giant figure showed itself. Scorpio fell upon his face, but Mizar stood gazing in intense surprise, not unmixed with fear, he tried to speak to this appalling being, but his tongue refused its office; he was conscious of a strange whirling sensation in his brain and an irresistible inclination to move forward; he struggled to remember his purpose in coming, and what he had resolved to do; but the power of thought had gone from him, and he felt as though he were in the grasp of some great force of Nature a tornado, an avalanche, a maelstrom. The sword which he had drawn fell from his hand, and  the  hideous rabble seized it with a yell of triumph, and surging round him, bore him on with them like a rolling tide, while a strange, slow, dreadful smile broke out upon the face of the deity. She drew back as the swarming brood apporached, and the door of rock fell once more as soon as the mob had disappeared within it. Then Scorpio rose from the ground, and threw up his arms above his head.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Оказалось, что это делало свою ужасную работу при солнечном свете так же, как и при лунном, и традиционный результат быстро последовал; каменная дверь поднялась, неприятная орда злостных существ выбежала, и затем показалась гигантская фигура. Скорпион упал ниц , но Мицар стоял, пристально вглядываясь с большим удивлением, смешанным со страхом; он попытался говорить с этим ужасным существом, но язык отказался служить ему; он ощущал странное кружение в его мозге и непреодолимое желание продвинуться; он сопротивлялся, чтобы не забыть его цель прибытия сюда и что он должен сделать; но сила мысли ушла от него, и он чувствовал, как если бы он был подхвачен какой-то природной стихией большой силы – торнадо, лавиной, водоворотом. Меч, который он вытащил, выпал из его руки, и отвратительная толпа захватила его с воплем триумфа, как захватывает тонущего человека прибывающий катящийся поток; в то время как странная, медленная, ужасная улыбка появилась на лице божества. Она отодвинулась, поскольку роящийся выводок приблизился, и дверь скалы упала, как только толпа исчезла в ней. Тогда Скорпион встал и поднял руки над головой.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Praise be to the great and ever-victorious goddess,  he cried;  may all her foes be vanquished thus! And he turned and left the platform with exultant mien; but he had scarcely passed the first tree in the forest when Boreas sprang from behind it and buried his great dagger in his heart. So Scorpio fell in the hour of his unholy triumph, and Boreas fled back through the forest as though the hounds of hell had been behind him.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
“ Слава великой и могучей богине,” кричал он; “так будут уничтожены все ее враги!” Он повернулся и покинул платформу с ликующим выражением лица; но как только он приблизился к первому дереву в лесу, Борей прыгнул из-за него и вонзил свой большой кинжал в его сердце. Так в час его безобразного триумфа закончилась жизнь Скорпиона, а Борей побежал назад через лес, как если бы его преследовали собаки ада.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When a few hours later, he reached the house of Sirius and Alcyone, he found that they had just returned from their journey. He introduced himself, and told his weird and harrowing tale. Incredible as it seemed, they could not but believe when they saw the pitiable state to which poor Electra had been reduced, and indeed they obtained some sort of partial confirmation from her, for she was now able to speak somewhat more coherently; for Boreas, who knew much of negro charms and drugs, had instructed her sisters to administer to her an infusion of a certain plant which was an antidote to the poison which had been forced upon her by Scorpio.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Когда несколько часов спустя он достиг дома Сириуса и Алкион, он увидел, что они только что возвратились из их поездки. Он представился и рассказал эту фантастическую и страшную историю. Каким бы невероятным это ни казалось, они не могли не поверить, когда они увидели жалкое состояние, до которого была доведена бедная Электра, и действительно, они получили своего рода частичное подтверждение от нее, поскольку она теперь была в состоянии говорить несколько более вразумительно; Борей, который немало знал о способах негритянского очарования и наркотиках, проинструктировал ее сестер использовать для нее листья определенного растения, которое было противоядием от зелья, примененного Скорпионом.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Her  father and mother saw the advisability of keeping this unsavoury story from the public ear, but at the same time Sirius realised  that they were here in presence of a formidable power of whose resources they were  ignorant. So, although he determined to set off himself without loss of time for the lair of the foul goddess in order to attempt the rescue of his eldest son, he first called his second son Viraj, told him the whole story, and sent him off to repeat it in secret to his father in law the king, asking only that it might not be made  public unless he also fell into the power of this vile gorgon, and it was necessary to invoke military force to destroy her. But he trusted that it might not come to that, for he fully realised that they were treading on delicate ground, and that an open attack upon their sacred shrine might tear the whole Negro race into rebellion, and he knew that Mars wished to conciliate them.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Ее отец и мать понимали, что желательно сохранить в тайне эту сомнительную историю, но в то же самое время Сириус чувствовал, что они столкнулись здесь с огромной силой, о масштабах которой они ничего не знали. Итак, хотя он решил заняться, не теряя времени, логовищем грязной богини, чтобы попытаться спасти первого сына, сначала он, вызвав своего второго сына Вирая, рассказал ему всю историю и поручил повторить это в тайне своему тестю королю, сказав только, что это не может быть обнародовано, даже если он еще не попал во власть этой мерзкой горгоны, и это было необходимо, чтобы мобилизовать военную силу для ее уничтожения. Но он полагал, что сразу этого нельзя делать, вполне понимая, что они ступили на деликатную почву, и что открытое нападение на их сакральное святилище могло бы спровоцировать всю негритянскую расу на восстание, а он знал, что Марс желал примирения.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At this  point Alcyone came forward, and honestly begged her husband to let her accompany him on his perilous quest declaring vehemently that Mizar was her son as much as his, and that she had a right to help in his rescue, and assuring him also that she felt a strong insistent intuition that this was her work, that some emergency would arise in which a women's wit , sharpened by a mother's love, would be worth more than the strength and valor of a mere man. At first Sirius, much surprised at her request, would not hear of such a thing; but she was so persistent and so sure of her ground that at last he, who had in the past had good reason to respect her intuition, yielded half against his will. So she clad herself in the dress of a hunter, the clothes belonging to her son Viraj, and she armed herself with a bow and arrows, in the use of which she was expert as indeed were many ladies of that race. Then they called Boreas to act as guide, and all three set out on horse back pushing on at utmost speed. Soon they reached the border of the forest, and , time their horses to a convenient tree, plunged into its gloomy depths. 
</view>
<view lang="ru">
В этот момент выступила Алкион и попросила у мужа разрешения сопровождать его в его рискованном предприятии поиска, сказав что, поскольку Мицар – ее сын так же, как и его, она имеет право помогать в его спасении, добавив также, что она интуитивно чувствует, что это ее работа, что бывают некоторые чрезвычайные ситуации, в которых женская сообразительность, обостренная материнской любовью, стоят больше, чем сила и доблесть простого человека. Сначала Сириус, очень удивленный ее желанием, не хотел даже слышать о таких вещах; но она была настолько тверда и настолько уверена в обоснованности своего предложения, что, наконец, он, имевший в прошлом серьезные основания уважать ее интуицию, неохотно уступил. Одевшись в платье охотника, принадлежащее ее сыну Вираю, она вооружилась луком и стрелами, в использовании которых она имела большой опыт, как и многие женщины той расы. Затем они определили Борея быть их проводником, и все трое отправились на лошадях на самой большой скорости. Они быстро доехали до границы леса и, привязав лошадей к подходящему дереву, погрузились в его мрачные глубины. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
As they pressed on they discussed their plan of campaign -- though so much had to be left uncertain that they could hardly be said to have one.  They had no means of forcing the rocky door, but Boreas thought that he could imitate successfully the weird cry of the high priest, and hoped that the usual response might follow.  Yet even if it did, they had no conception as to the dangers which that opening door might disclose, nor the strength of the diabolical garrison which might lie behind it.  They knew not even that awful vampire goddess could be wounded by human weapons, whether she was accessible to human appeal, whether she could understand the yearning of a mother's heart, or respond to the conception of love or pity.  During  their walk they extracted from Boreas all that he knew as to this horrible cult, and all that he had heard of its meagre but gruesome traditions; but they found in this little to encourage them.  Boreas could not tell them, with any certainty, of the supposed origin of this is strange deity; one theory allied her with a mysterious race of beings, half men, half animals, who were said to live in vast halls in the bowels of the earth; another regarded her as a princess among a giant race which had occupied the country long ago and had died out or been expelled, she only surviving because she had discovered in secret of eternal life.  It was rumored also that she had a twin sister with whom she had shared the secret; that this sister had at first lived with her, but that they had quelled over some victim whom both desired, and that the other had gone away to the east by sea, to pray upon the inhabitants of some far distant land.  That she possessed real powers, which had frequently been manifested through her priests, was incontestable, but no one knew the exact nature of the powers, nor how far they extended. Boreas, however, firmly  believed that the same great knife which had killed her high-priest would suffice to rid the world of her, and he asked nothing better than to have an opportunity to put his theory to proof.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Поскольку они спешили, понятно, что много было неясного в плане их кампании. У них не было никаких средств для управления дверью в скале, но Борей думал, что он смог бы успешно воспроизвести фантастический крик первосвященника и надеялся, что могла бы последовать обычная реакция. Но даже если бы это было сделало, у них не было никакой концепции ни относительно опасностей, которые эта дверь могла бы раскрыть, ни относительно силы дьявольского гарнизона, который находился за ней. Они даже не знали, могла ли быть ранена человеческим оружием ужасная богиня, была ли она доступна для человеческого обращения и смогла бы она понять тоску сердца матери или ответить на человеческую любовь или жалость. Во время пути они извлекли из Борея все, что он знал об этом ужасном культе, и все, что он слышал об этих примитивных, но отвратительных традициях; но они не нашли в этом ничего, что бы удовлетворило их. Борей ничего не мог сказать им с какой-либо уверенностью о возможном происхождении этого странного божества; одна теория соединяла ее с таинственной расой существ, наполовину людей, наполовину животных, которые, как было сказано, жили в обширных пещерах в недрах земли; другая рассматривала ее, как принцессу гигантской расы, которая занимала страну в древние времена и вымерла или была изгнана, выжила только она, потому что она знала тайну вечной жизни. Было известно по слухам также, что у нее была сестра - близнец, с которой она разделила тайну; что эта сестра сначала жила с нею, но потом ушла на восток морским путем в некую отдаленную страну. То, что она владела реальными силами, которые часто проявлялись через ее священников, было бесспорно, но никто не знал ни точной их природы, ни как далеко они простирались. Борей, однако, твердо верил, что тот же самый большой кинжал, которым он убил ее первосвященника, вполне подойдет, чтобы избавить мир и от нее, и он не желал ничего лучшего, чем иметь возможность претворить свою теорию в реальность.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When they reached the platform they found the corpse of Scorpio lying where Boreas had left it, but it was in process of being tore to pieces by some huge and peculiarly loathsome crabs, which had presumably come up  out of the swamp. Driving these ghoulish creatures away, they examined the body, and found hanging round its neck a curious talisman a disk of gold bearing upon it the image of a woman, evidently intended to represent the deity. From a confession later made by Cancer, who as the eldest daughter  of the magician knew some of the secrets of the prison house, it was established that this highly magnetized disc was a centre of radiation for the power of the goddess, and that when, in mesmerizing any person or thing, the chief priest held that object, in his hand, the person or thing was brought into direct touch with that lurid divinity and could not afterwards be set free without her special intervention. This had been  in the case of Electra, and therefore Scorpio was unable to remove the spell.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Когда они достигли платформы, они нашли труп Скорпиона лежащим там, где Борей оставил его, но его уже рвали на части какие-то огромные и странно отвратительные крабы, которые, по-видимому, приползли из болота. Отогнав этих омерзительных существ, они исследовали тело и нашли висевший на его шее любопытный талисман – диск из золота с изображением женщины, очевидно представляющей божество. Из признания, позже сделанного Канцер, которая как старшая дочь колдуна, знала некоторые тайны тюремного дома, было установлено, что этот высоко магнетизированный диск был центром радиации силы богини, и что, когда при месмеризации любого человека или предмета, главный жрец держал тот объект в руке, человек или предмет вступали в прямой контакт с этим страшным божеством и не могли впоследствии быть освобождены без её специального вмешательства. То же самое было и в случае с Электрой, поэтому Скорпион был не в состоянии удалить заклинание.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The small but intrepid party mounted the platform, and Boreas lifted up his voice in the weird chant that he had heard the dead man sing, hoping that through the rock any trilling difference of intonation  might not be noticed. It would seem that the lady was uncritical, or perhaps she did not care what visitors she received, confident in her power to deal with any who might appear. At any rate, the rock door rose as before, and the swarm of misshapen goblins poured forth. A minute or two later they saw the gruesome entity to meet whom they had undertaken this extraordinary expedition; there stood in the doorway, filling it from ground to lintel, a huge gross female form, fully eight feet in height, and more than broad in proportion, dark-blue distinctly dark-blue in color, and faintly luminous in the gathering dusk. This awesome apparition was absolutely unclothed, except for a necklace of enormous gleaming stones; it emanated a strong and most sickening, yet half-intoxicating musky odour; and in the expression of its face there was ruthlessness and strange inhuman fathomless iniquity, and yet somehow a kind of fearful fascination.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Маленький, но бесстрашный отряд поднялся на платформу, и Борей поднял тональность своего голоса в фантастическом пении, которое он слышал, когда пел убитый жрец, надеясь, что через скалу какое-либо отличие в интонации не будет замечено. Оказалось, что леди была некритично настроена, или возможно, она не заботилась, каких посетителей ей принимать, уверенная в своей власти иметь дело с любым, кто бы ни появился. Во всяком случае дверь в скале поднялась как прежде, излив рой деформированных гоблинов. Минутой или двумя позднее они увидели ужасное существо, для встречи с которым они предприняли эту экстраординарную экспедицию; там в дверном проёме, заполняя его снизу до верху, стояла огромная грубая женская фигура, полных восьми футов в высоту и более, чем широкая в пропорции, тёмно-синяя – отчётливо тёмно-синяя цветом и слабо люминесцирующая в собирающихся сумерках. Это удивительное явление было абсолютно раздето за исключением ожерелья из огромных мерцающих камней; оно выделяло сильный и более всего вызывающий отвращение, но всё же почти опьяняющий мускусный аромат; в выражении этого лица была жестокость и странно непостижимое бесчеловечное зло и своего рода пугающее обаяние.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Sirius who stood in front as champion of the party, experienced just the same sensations as those which had overpowered Mizar earlier in the day; he also tried to speak but could not; he also felt a resistless influence stealing over him from those inexorable unwinking eyes; he also would unquestionably have been subjugated by this preternatural witchery which was being concentrated upon him, if he had been left alone to face it. But a voice rang out from behind him like a clarion: "Husband, Husband, she is overpowering you! Stand firm, and uphold the light!"
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Сириус, который стоял впереди как глава отряда, испытал те же самые эмоции, которые пересилили Мицара ранее днём; он так же попытался говорить, но не смог; он так же чувствовал, что непреодолимое влияние оказывают на него эти непреклонные немигающие глаза; он так же был бы бесспорно порабощён этими сверхъестественными чарами, которые концентрировались на нём, если бы он оставался в том же положении. Но позади него, как из трубы, зазвенел голос: “Сириус! Она пересиливает тебя! Держись! Храни Свет!” 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
And as she spoke, Alcyone drew her bow to  the very head of the arrow, and sped her shaft unerringly to the heart of that unearthly monster; and as it struck, that dread figure crashed to the earth with a blood curdling non-human cry, and lay writhing there with a ghastly contorted visage. In a few minutes it was still in death, and all present were conscious of a curious change in the atmosphere of a sense of intense relief, of the removal of a weight. And as they stood looking at one another and wondering, a loud cry was heard  from within the cave, and Mizar came bounding out, shouting:  I am free; I am free!  He leapt over the prostrate body, and rushed up to his father and mother, asking wonderingly how they came there, and what had happened. But perhaps the strangest change was in the horde of creatures who had always been the first to rush out when the door was opened. They seemed as though thunderstruck; all their impish malignity was gone; they began to speak of one another in hesitating accents; some of them fell down as though from weakness. Alcyone said to Sirius: "See, husband, see! These are not demons, but men, and they have been suffering under some horrible enchantment. Say, brothers, who and what you are, and if we can help you, we will."
</view>
<view lang="ru">
И говоря так, Алкион натянула тетиву своего лука самой мощной из стрел и направила её безошибочно в сердце этого неземного монстра; и когда она ударила, огромное тело обрушилось на землю с нечеловеческим криком и начало корчиться там с ужасно искажённым лицом. Через несколько минут она была уже мёртвой, и все по-настоящему ощутили любопытное изменение в атмосфере — в смысле интенсивного облегчения, удаления чего-то давящего. И пока они стояли, смотря друг на друга и удивляясь, громкий крик послышался изнутри пещеры, и выбежал Мицар, повторяя: “Я свободен; я свободен!” Он перепрыгнул через неподвижное тело и помчался к своим родителям, спрашивая с любопытством, как они попали сюда и что тут случилось. Но, возможно, самое странное изменение произошло с ордой существ, которые всегда были первыми, чтобы выбежать, когда открывалась дверь. Они казались как бы ошеломлёнными; вся их озорная злобность ушла; они начали говорить друг с другом с акцентом неуверенности; некоторые из них падали как бы от слабости. Алкион сказала Сириусу:  “Смотри, смотри! Они не демоны, а люди, и они были под какими-то ужасными чарами. Скажите, братья, кто и что вы, и если нужно, мы поможем вам”.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Then one of these strange beings stepped forward and spoke haltingly, as one to whom speech is unfamiliar: "Princess",  he said,  "not long ago you knew me as a soldier of the palace guard; you have spoken to me many times, yet I cannot wonder that you do not know me now. Three months ago I was young and strong and brave; now my hair is white and I am old and broken, and cannot live; nor indeed do I wish to live, for my soul is utterly polluted and imbrued with deadly sin. For I was chosen, by the high priest of that dread demon there whom you have slain, to be her husband; I was brought her under her awful spell, and all that was unclean and animal within me she stirred into a mad riot such as you could never understand, nor any sane healthy human being; for there are things so hellish that the flesh creeps at the thought of them, and even the telling of them is as a blast of death. For a whole month I ministered to her monstrous lusts, and it seemed to me one long mad whirl of pleasure in which I lost all count of time; but in that time she drew all life from me, and left me what you see. At the next full moon a new victim came, and she cast me aside like a worn out garment.  All these whom you see are like me; each has had his day, and has been drained of his vitality by that awful vampire who lies there; thus has she kept herself alive for untold ages, feeding upon the life of men, for her victims have numbered many thousands, and in the cave is a vast heap of their bones. Yet she does not let us die at once, but keeps us thus unnaturally alive and  without sleep, full of a devilish malice and jealousy, yearning to drag others in to suffer as we have suffered, yet all the time envying and hating them. A hell indeed our dregs of life have been to us, and very day has seemed a thousand years of agony and despair. But now that you have killed her all is changed; the awful nightmare has gone, and I think that we shall die in peace; as you see, some of us are dying even now."
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Тогда одно из этих странных существ вышло вперёд и сказало, запинаясь, как тот, кому речь незнакома: “Принцесса”, – сказал он, – “недавно Вы знали меня как солдата дворцовой стражи; Вы говорили со мной много раз, и я не могу поверить, что Вы не знаете меня теперь. Три месяца назад я был молод, силён и храбр; теперь мои волосы седые, и я стар и немощен, и не могу жить; но в действительности я хочу жить, хотя моя душа и запятнана смертным грехом. Поскольку я был избран главным жрецом того демона страха, который теперь убит, быть её мужем, я был подвергнут её ужасным чарам; и всё, что было грязного и животного во мне, она смешивала в безумный клубок, такой, о каком Вы никогда не имели представления, как любой нормальный здоровый человек, поскольку есть вещи настолько адские, что плоть cползает c костей от одной мысли о них, и разговор о них, как дыхание смерти. Целый месяц я обслуживал её чудовищные вожделения, и это казалось мне одним безумным водоворотом удовольствия, в котором я потерял счёт времени; но за это время она вытянула всю жизнь из меня и оставила то, что Вы видите. В следующее полнолуние поступила новая жертва, и она отвергла меня, как изношенный предмет одежды. Все они, кого Вы видите, походят на меня; у каждого был его день, и было истощение его жизненности этим ужасным вампиром, который лежит здесь; таким образом она поддерживала себя до невероятного возраста, питаясь жизнями мужчин, её жертвы исчисляются многими тысячами, и в пещере находится огромная куча их костей. Всё же она не позволяла нам умирать сразу, но держала нас такими вот противоестественно живыми и без сна, наполненными дьявольским преступным намерением и ревностью, жаждущими столкнуть других в страдание, поскольку мы пострадали, одновременно завидуя им и ненавидя их. Остаток нашей жизни был адом для нас, и каждый день казался тысячей лет муки и отчаяния. Но теперь, когда Вы убили её, всё изменилось; ужасный кошмар ушёл, и я думаю, что мы умрём в мире; как Вы видите, некоторые из нас умирают уже теперь”.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Pity and horror filled the hearts of Alcyone, Sirius and Mizar when they heard these fearful revelations; and Sirius felt his heart burn within him, and he spoke to those doomed wretches such words as were given to him to speak. He told them of the light that dwelt in every one of them, that dwelt there ineradicable still, in spite of all these obscene horrors; that light which was a ray of the Eternal Light, from Whom all had come , into whom all must return. So that for them also there was hope and help, because, though indeed the Divine Spark had burnt low, it should surely one day be fanned again into flame; for them also the darkness should lighten, until they stood for ever in the perfect day. And the poor creatures heard and believed and were comforted; and natural sleep, a stranger to their eyes for many weary months  and years, fell softly upon them, and in that sleep many passed peacefully away. And indeed naught else could be desired for them, for continued life could but have been continued misery; they were wan and shrunken and nerveless, bent so that those who had been tall men were now like deformed and stunted children, warped and gangrenous, rotting in death while still alive.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Жалость и ужас заполнили сердца Алкиона, Сириуса и Мицара, когда они услышали эти страшные откровения; и Сириус почувствовал боль в сердце, и он сказал этим обречённым несчастным людям такие слова, какие были даны ему, чтобы говорить. Он говорил им о свете, который пребывал в каждом из них, который всё ещё пребывает, потому что неискореним даже в злобе всего этого непристойного ужаса; о свете, который был лучом Вечного Света, из которого все вышли и в который все должны возвратиться. Так что для них также есть надежда и помощь, потому что, хотя, действительно, Божественная Искра горит слабо, она должна быть однажды раздута в пламя; для них также должна осветиться темнота, пока они не войдут навсегда в истинный день. И бедные существа услышали и поверили, и успокоились; и естественный сон, незнакомый для их глаз в течение многих утомительных месяцев и лет, мягко упал на них, и в том сне многие мирно отошли. И действительно, что ещё могло быть желательным для них, если продолжение жизни не могло не быть продолженным страданием; они были изнурёнными, сморщенными и бессильными, согнутыми так, что те, кто был высокими мужчинами, теперь походили на деформированных и измождённых детей, исковерканных и омертвелых, гниющих, как мёртвые, но всё ещё остающихся живыми.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
But Sirius and his son went and looked at the body of the dead monster, overcoming their horror in order that they might see what manner of being this was. Human undoubtedly, yet of a race happily long extinct; a ghastly anachronism, perpetuated only by some gruesome secret of wholesale murder verily   a thing to shudder at, not to see.  Sirius conquered his repugnance sufficiently to unclasp the necklace of huge stones; but the very touch of that blue flesh was in itself revolting, for it was suberous, polyp-like, nauseating, unhuman. Mizar overleaped the corpse, and called to them to come to come and look at the cave, so shudderingly they passed into murky depths. Prodigious indeed it was, vast hall extending beyond vast hall far into the heart of the great needle of rock; and whether these halls were natural or artificial none could tell. In one of them was a huge pyramid of human bones the remains of thousands of victims, even as the dying soldier had said. But the whole place reeked like a charnel-house, that seemed more than mere physical.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Сириус и его сын, преодолевая отвращение, пошли осмотреть тело мёртвого монстра, чтобы представить манеры того, кто им был. Несомненно, человек, однако, принадлежащий расе, давно и благополучно угасшей; невообразимый анахронизм, увековеченный только некоей ужасной тайной массового убийства; поистине “вещь для трепета, но не для взора”. Сириус достаточно преодолел своё отвращение, чтобы расстегнуть ожерелье из огромных камней; но в самой точке контакта синяя плоть сопротивлялась, причиной этому была подобная полипу субсерозная фибромиома (cпецифическое женское заболевание – прим. пер.), отвратительная, нечеловеческая. Мицар, перепрыгнув через труп, позвал их подойти, чтобы осмотреть пещеру; брезгливо содрогаясь, они прошли в тёмную глубь. Это, действительно, потрясало: несколько обширных залов, простирающихся до середины большой скалы; были эти залы естественными или искусственными, никто не смог бы сказать. В одном из них возвышалась огромная пирамида человеческих костей — останки тысяч жертв, как раз то, о чём рассказал умирающий солдат. Везде сильно отдавало склепом, что казалось более или менее естественным.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So the exploring party soon came out again into purer air, and as they emerged they were amazed by the sound of a trumpet and by eager voices calling. They shouted in reply, and guided by their cries, king picked men, the very flower of his own special guard. Glad indeed was he t o see his daughter safe and sound, and much he marveled at the astounding story which was told in reply to his enquiries. Incredible it might well have seemed, but for the irrefragable evidence before him the corpse of the Lemurian giantess, and those of the men whom she had vampirised. Appalled at the discovery of the horrors which had been going on close to his very capital without his knowledge, he issued stern sharp orders in truly royal fashion. A huge litter should be made of branches, and the dead body of the monster should be carried through every street of the city, so that all the Negroes might understand that their direful deity was harmless now, and that her sanguinary cult was a thing of the past. The doctrine of the Light was to be preached to them in their own tongue, more fully, more clearly, more widely, than ever, so that none might ever again fall under-the sway of such a strange and loathsome superstition. A camp was to be made then and there, and such help as could be given to the fast dying victims was to be at their disposal. The entrance to the caves was to be at their disposal. The entrance to the caves was to be sealed up and covered deep  under vast  piles of rock, so that no man should ever enter there again; the swamp was to be filled up and drained, and a broad road made through the forest. And furthermore he ordered that the tall black peak that towered above them should be painted white as though crowned with snow, and ever thereafter kept so, as a sign that the reign of darkness was over, and that the Light had triumphed over its enemies. All these decrees were duly carried out, and the peak which had been a symbol of horror and dread became a constant reminder of the inevitable victory of the Light that  lightens every man who cometh into the world.   
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Осмотрев всё, отряд вскоре вышел опять в более чистую атмосферу, и здесь они были остановлены звуком трубы и нетерпеливым окриком. Они прокричали в ответ и пошли навстречу королю, прибывшему в сопровождении людей из его собственной специальной охраны. Он был, действительно, очень рад увидеть живой и здоровой свою дочь и был очень 
поражён удивительной историей, которую ему рассказали в ответ на его вопросы. Каким бы невероятным это ни казалось, но неоспоримые свидетельства лежали перед ними — труп лемурийской великанши и трупы мужчин, умерших от её вампиризма. Потрясённый раскрытием ужаса, который происходил так близко от его столицы без его ведома, он действительно по-королевски выпустил строгие и решительные указы. Нужно было сделать из ветвей огромную надпись, а труп монстра нужно было пронести через каждую улицу города, чтобы все негры смогли понять, что теперь их ужасное божество обезврежено, и что её кровавый культ остался в прошлом. Доктрина Света должна была проповедоваться им на их собственном языке более полно, более ясно, более широко, чем когда-либо, так, чтобы никто никогда не смог бы снова подпасть под влияние какого-либо странного и отвратительного суеверия. Необходимо было безотлагательно устроить лагерь для оказания помощи всё ещё умирающим жертвам. Вход в пещеры отныне должен был находиться под контролем [администрации короля]. Этот вход нужно было запечатать и скрыть глубоко под огромными кучами камней так, чтобы никто никогда не попал туда снова; болото нужно было засыпать и осушить, и сделать широкую дорогу через лес. И кроме того, он приказал, чтобы высокий чёрный пик, который возвышался над скалами, был закрашен белым под вид короны из снега, что для всех должно было означать, что господство Тьмы закончилось, и что Свет одержал победу над своими врагами. Все эти указы были должным образом выполнены, и пик, ранее бывший символом ужаса и страха, стал постоянным напоминанием о неизбежной победе Света, который светит каждому человеку, пришедшему в этот мир.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Our exhausted party returned to its home, and the first inquiry was after the health of Electra. They found her pale and weak indeed, but otherwise entirely herself again, and her sisters related how, all in a moment, her senses had returned and she was free from the strange oppression which had weighed her down so terribly; and none doubted that this relief came to her at the moment of the death of the Lemurian whose spell had been woven around her. The shock of this unparalleled experience had been great to all those who had shared it, and it was some weeks before they entirely recovered from it. Electra's part in what had happened was never made public, but was confided only to Corona, her future husband.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Наш утомлённый отряд возвратился домой, и первый вопрос был о здоровье Электры. Они нашли её бледной и слабой, но всё же в полном сознании; её сестры заметили, как всё изменилось в одно мгновение: её чувства возвратились и она освободилась от странного притеснения, которое так ужасно давило на неё; и никто не сомневался, что это облегчение пришло после смерти лемурийки, чары которой были сотканы вокруг неё. Шок от этого беспрецедентного происшествия был для всех, кто пережил его, настолько большим, что потребовалось несколько недель, чтобы полностью восстановиться. Участие в происшествии Электры никогда не разглашалось, но было доверено лишь Короне, её будущему мужу.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A few days later, Sirius, Alcyone, Mizar and Electra all came together to the wise mother Mercury, and talked long and earnestly with her about these strange occurrences. Mizar asked her: "grandmother, how was it that I, trusting in the Light which we worship, could not resist the spell of that dreadful woman, and that even my father was powerless before her, while my mother unaffected, and she was able to kill her?"
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Несколько дней спустя Сириус, Алкион, Мицар и Электра пришли все вместе к мудрой матери Меркури и разговаривали долго и искренне с нею об этих странных событиях. Мицар спросил её: “Бабушка, как объяснить, что я, доверяя Свету, которому мы поклоняемся, не мог сопротивляться чарам той ужасной женщины, даже мой отец был бессилен перед нею, в то время как на мою мать они не подействовали, и она оказалась в состоянии убить её?”
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
And Mercury replied:   Grandson, the monster's   power of will was greater far than yours, aye, greater even than your father's; not greater than the power of the Light, but greater than its manifestation in you, for a certain reason that I will tell you. The horrible mystery of this creature's strength had its root in that other mystery of sex, and therefore it could be used best, by each person, upon one of the opposite sex. Remember how, long ago, Scorpio even when a boy dominated the girl Alcyone by its means, but was at once overthrown by the boy Sirius, upon whom it had no effect. Again, Scorpio easily influenced Electra, but could do nothing against you, even when you went to his house and openly threatened him. Yet when the operator was a woman when you came face to  face with the prodigy herself- you were overcome, and so was your father, while against Alcyone, because she was a women, her efforts were fruitless. Because your mother was dressed as a man, the monster was probably deceived; the magnetism which she poured out was aimed at men, and so your mother was unaffected. Truly you would have been unharmed also, if through you the Light had shown with perfect purity; because you have not yet attained perfection, because you are still human, there was within you that upon which her terrible forces could play. In the strength of utter purity, even the weakest will may naught that can be stained, naught upon which the can seize; but while there is even a germ of evil there is still danger. Yet though that fiend could neutralize your will, ad could draw you within her unholy cave and hold you there as prisoner, she could not dominate your very soul and bend you to her evil ends as she did those who yielded voluntarily to her. She could perhaps have taken your life; she could not make you her slave. So always there are limits to the power of evil; and only that can come to each man that he has himself deserved.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
И Меркурий ответила: “Внук, сила воли монстра была намного больше, чем твоя, даже больше, чем у твоего отца; но не больше, чем сила Света, хотя больше, чем Его проявление в тебе, по определённой причине, о которой я скажу. Ужасная тайна силы этого существа имела свой корень в тайне пола, поэтому и могла использоваться лучше всего против любого человека противоположного пола. Вспомни, как много лет назад Скорпион, тогда ещё мальчик, доминировал над девочкой Алкион его средствами, но был сразу же повержен мальчиком Сириусом, на которого он не сумел никак повлиять. Опять же, Скорпион легко влиял на Электру, но ничего не мог сделать против тебя, даже когда ты вошёл в его дом и открыто угрожал ему. Но, когда оператором была женщина — когда ты столкнулся лицом к лицу с ней – ты был пересилен, и так же было с твоим отцом, в то время как против Алкион, потому что она была женщиной, её усилия были бесплодны. Поскольку твоя мама была одета как мужчина, колдунья была, вероятно, введена в заблуждение; магнетизм, который она вылила, был нацелен на мужчин, и таким образом, твоя мама оказалась незатронутой. По-настоящему, и ты не был бы затронут, если бы Свет, проходящий через тебя оказался совершенно чистым; но так как ты ещё не достиг совершенства, потому что всё ещё человек, в тебе было то, на чём могли играть её ужасные силы. С силой абсолютной чистоты даже самая слабая воля может превратить в ничто всё, что может запачкать и что может завладеть; в то время как даже микроб зла уже опасен. И хотя та ведьма могла нейтрализовать твою волю, втащить тебя в свою проклятую пещеру и держать там как заключённого, она не могла доминировать над твоей душой и склонить тебя к своему злу окончательно, как она сделала с теми, кто уступил ей добровольно. Она, возможно, смогла бы взять твою жизнь; но не смогла бы сделать тебя своим рабом. Итак, всегда есть пределы власти зла; и только то может прийти к человеку, что он сам заслужил”.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After years had passed, Sirius became High Priest in the place of Dhruva, his father, and with the ever sweet and sagacious help of his wife Alcyone he held that position long and creditably; and when he also died he was succeeded in it by Mizar, his son. Alcyone survived her husband by a year or two only, and died greatly honored at the age of seventy six. On the death of King Mars, Herakles as eldest son was set upon the throne; but when he in turn passed away, the choice fell upon his second son Corona, so that the lovely Electra graced the position of the first lady in the land. At Corona's death the succession passed to his second son Theodorous; but Koli, who was the daughter of Corona and Electra, married Mizar's son Leto, and to them was accorded the honour of giving birth to the Manu Himself, who thus came down to south Africa to confirm the dynasty and emphasize the characteristics of His second sub-race, so naturally the Priesthood placed Him upon the throne at the death of Theodorous.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
После того, как прошли годы, Сириус стал первосвященником вместо Дхрувы, его отца, и с всегда приятной и проницательной помощью жены Алкион служил в этой должности долго и надёжно; а когда умер, на его место пришёл Мицар, сын. Алкион пережила мужа только на год или два и умерла очень уважаемой в возрасте семидесяти шести лет. По смерти короля Марса Геракл, как самый старший сын, занял трон; но когда он в свою очередь скончался, выбор пал на его второго сына Корону, так что прекрасная Электра украшала место первой леди страны. Со смертью Короны преемственность перешла к его второму сыну Теодорусу; а Коли, дочь Короны и Электры, вышла замуж за сына Мицара Лето, и они получили честь рождения непосредственно Ману, который, таким образом, пришёл в Южную Африку, чтобы укрепить династию и подчеркнуть особенности Его второй подрасы; духовенство, естественно, возвело Его на трон по смерти Теодорусa.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The faithful Boreas married Nu, a white waiting maid of the household of Alcyone , and attached himself most especially to the service of Mizar a devotion brought over from unrememberd past. His sons, by an odd turn of the wheel of fate, married the daughters of his old master, the  Negro chief Markab, and became persons of importance in the newly established mulatto community. The two sons of Markab, however, married the Negro daughters of Scorpio, and Pollux thus came into possession of the not inconsiderable wealth amassed  by the late high priest, as well as that of his father Markab. This marriage drew him back into the ranks of the Negroes, but on the other hand established him in a leading position among them. Years later he engaged in a plot against Herakles, and when it was discovered his people forced him to lead an open rebellion, but he was promptly suppressed and put to death by corona.
</view>
<view lang="ru">
Отважный Борей женился на Ню, белой служанке в домашнем хозяйстве Алкион, и приступил к службе у Мицарa c величайшей преданностью, возможно, принесённой из очень далёкого прошлого. Его сыновья необычным поворотом колеса судьбы женились на дочерях его старого хозяина негритянского вождя Маркаба и стали важными людьми в недавно основанном сообществе мулатов. Два сына Маркабa, однако, женились на негритянских дочерях Скорпиона, и Поллукс, таким образом, вошёл во владение весьма значительным богатством, накопленным покойным главным жрецом, так же, как и богатством его отца Маркаба. Этот брак отодвинул его снова в разряд негров, но, с другой стороны, укрепил в ведущем положении среди них. Несколько лет спустя он участвовал в заговоре против Геракла, а когда заговор был раскрыт, сообщники вынудили его возглавить открытое восстание, но оно было быстро подавлено, а его лидер казнён.
</view>
</text>
</body>