<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 38
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 38-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Again we find ourselves in India, for Alcyone took birth this time in the Peshawar district, in the
      year 7852, in what appears to correspond to the Kshattriya caste, though it was then called rajan .
      I see evidence at this time of three castes only, brahman, rajan, and vis. They seem to have been
      originally clearly different races; the brahman was the almost unmixed Aryan, the rajan was the
      Aryan intermingled with the ancient ruling race of the Toltecs, and the vis was Aryan mixed with
      other Atlantean races, chiefly Mongolian and Tlavatli, with sometimes a certain intermixture of
      later Lemurian races. They were allowed at that time to intermarry among themselves, but not with
      any one outside of the three castes; and even already it was beginning to be thought more proper
      and fashionable to marry only in one's own caste.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone was the son of Aurora, a petty chieftain of considerable reputation as a warrior. His
      mother was Vajra, a brave and somewhat masculine woman. Fighting seems to be the only business of
      this caste, and it was most persistently pursued. There was a vast amount of apparently needless
      bloodshed. The part of the country in which we find ourselves was divided into a number of tiny
      principalities, and among these perpetual warfare went on. Occasionally a stronger man appeared
      among the princes etc and conquered several others, and thus made himself overlord for a time ,but
      at his death his kingdom almost invariably broke up, and the same dreary cycle of ceaseless war
      repeated itself.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      On the whole it affected the mass of the population much less than might have been expected. Trade
      and agriculture went on to a certain extent all the time, and only the professional soldiers fought
      as a rule,though of course no man's life was ever really safe. It was a very curious state of
      affairs, the people being in certain ways so highly civilised , and yet life being absolutely
      uncertain. There was no really settled law or order, but endless years of combat constant sieges,
      constant expeditions. The Aryans were not yet settled in fact, it may be said that the final
      immigration was still pressing on. by about 9700 B.C. the last Aryan inhabitant had withdrawn from
      the Central Asian kingdom round the Gobi Sea; but India was already settled and thickly populated,
      and these later bands were by no means welcome. For two thousand years they were held back in
      Afghanistan and Baluchistan, and most of them only gradually, individually, peaceably, made their
      way down to the plains. Sometimes, however, raids were made by organised bands, and occasionally
      also there was an incursion of Mongols of various kinds, who massacred everybody. Certainly, at
      this period, this was an uncomfortably turbulent part of the country. A large kingdom, such as I
      have described, had just recently broken up, and determined struggles for the overlordship were
      still going on.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The belief of the time was in some ways not quite the same as that in modern Hinduism. There was a
      trinity, but it was of Agni, Indra and Surya, and the higher idea of Shiva, Vishnu and Brahma had
      not yet been reached or known. Sacrifices on a large scale were painfully common, and the
      Ashwamedha or horse sacrifice was highly esteemed. It was even said that a hundred such sacrifices
      would make a man higher than Indra.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone and his father and mother were in close association with a Brahman family who had a great
      influence over his life. The heads of this family were Saturn and his wife Mercury; their sons were
      Brihat and Naga, and Neptune, Orpheus and Uranus were their daughters. The close friendship of this
      family formed the one redeeming feature of this life; otherwise, however necessary it may have been
      for the evolution of the ego, it is not one that we can find much pleasure in contemplating. It
      will be recollected that in the previous birth Alcyone, though enjoying a wide influence as a
      spiritual teacher, used sometimes to yearn for the more active life of the soldier; probably this
      incarnation was a direct response to those desires, given in order to cure the ego once and for all
      of such dissatisfaction, by offering him his fill of the ephemeral glory of the battle-field.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He began with some little enthusiasm for the military life, but soon sickened of it, and when the
      reaction set in he would have been glad to return to that with which eight hundred years before he
      had not been fully content. Even when still quite a young man, he felt that he had had enough of
      this ceaseless slaughter; he was a brave and capable man, but he lacked the ruthlessness which is
      necessary for the great military leaders; he was too full of sympathy for the wounded and the
      suffering, whether they were on his side or that of his enemies. He expressed something of this to
      his mother, but she checked his further confidence by treating his scruples as effeminate; so he
      turned to his friends and companions Brihat and Naga, who, being Brahmans, fully, sympathised with
      his feelings as to the usefulness and wickedness of all this organised murder. Brihat took him to
      his mother Mercury, who was always affectionate and wise in counsel, and he had a series of long
      talks with her. She did not make the mistake of discouraging or ridiculing him, but admitted at
      once that his attitude was a reasonable one, and indeed agreed entirely with her own ; but she
      pointed out to him that he had been born in the rajan caste, not by chance but as the result of
      some previous thought or action, and her opinion was that, distasteful as it all was to him, he
      should yet uphold the traditional honour of his house, and fulfil the duties of his position until
      such time as the gods should see fit to release him from it, as they easily could if they chose;
      and she believed and hoped that they would do so when they saw that the time had come.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      So he went on through many years of all sorts of stormy, horrible, impossible scenes, always tired
      of it all and yearning for a life of learning and meditation, till at last at the age of fifty he
      lost his right arm in a battle, and was in other ways so crippled as to render further fighting
      impossible. When he recovered, at the earnest invitation of Mercury and Brihat he took up his abode
      with them, and may be said to have passed practically into the Brahman caste a change which was
      quite possible in those days. Thus began the really happy period of his life, and he felt rather
      thankful than otherwise for the accident which had forced him into retirement from the field. His
      experience of the soldier's life had bred a permanent distaste for it, so that he never wished for
      it again in any future life, and though sometimes, when he had to do it as a matter of duty he did
      it bravely and honourably, he never again felt any delight in it.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      His attachment to Mercury was specially strong, and when she died he mourned her long and
      sincerely. He remained with Brihat and Naga, taking part in the temple ceremonies(though apparently
      there were some from which his crippled condition was considered to debar him), and studying with
      keen interest such philosophy as was available, till in 7774, when he had already reached the age
      of seventy-eight, the Tarters once more descended upon his district, dealing death and destruction
      everywhere. Against a foe, so barbaric as this Alcyone felt it right to fight, and when after many
      days of siege and the most awful massacres it seemed certain that the town must soon fall into the
      hands of these savage marauders, he went to the fort and, old and crippled though he was, offered
      himself to share the fate of his old comrades in arms, and die since all must die fighting as well
      as a man in his condition could. When, however, the fort was captured and destruction certain, the
      rajans saved themselves from the disgrace of defeat by simultaneous suicide, and it was thus
      Alcyone died. His sons Percy and Mizar both perished with him.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
