<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 7
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 7-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In the lives which have just been described we have seen glimpses of the work, which the Manu did
      with and through his second sub-race. In following the fortunes of our hero we now find ourselves
      brought similarly into contact with the beginnings of the third. The plan of preparation was the
      same, though in a different valley a valley of rolling downs, which lent itself rather to pasture
      than to agriculture on a large scale. The Manu was himself ruling the city of Manoa at the time; He
      had married Mercury and had two sons, Osiris and Sirius. The latter married Mizar, the daughter of
      Mars and Siwa, and they had seven children, of whom Alcyone was the eldest, born this time in a
      male body. He was a sensitive child, given to dreaming and fond of solitude, sufficiently psychic
      to feel the presence of nature spirits and dead people, and sometimes to see them. Snatches of past
      lives came before him from time to time in dreams; he did not then know whence they came or what
      they were, but we (who have been following him through them) recognize at once the bands of people
      who marched singing up a long straight path from the sea to the mountains, ages before the building
      of the city; the envoys who set out for the court of the King of Persia, and afterwards across the
      desert to Arabia; and the weird events of the life last described, when in female form he had
      delivered a son (who was now his mother) from the horrors of the Lemurian magic. Six thousand years
      had elapsed since then, and he must have had seven or eight intervening lives, yet in his dreams it
      was clear as a happening of yesterday; and he experienced once more the curious mixture of
      irreconcilable feelings of repulsion and attraction, of fear of the unknown and yet the certainty
      of triumph.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      В только что описанных жизнях мы увидели примеры работы Ману в отношении его второй подрасы. Следуя
      за судьбой нашего героя, мы обнаруживаем себя в похожей ситуации в начале третьей подрасы. План
      подготовки был тем же, хотя и применялся в другой долине, жизнь которой основывалась, в основном,
      на скотоводстве, а не на земледелии. Сам Ману в то время управлял городом Маноа; он женился на
      Меркурии и у него было два сына: Осирис и Сириус. Последний женился на Мицар, дочери Марса и Сивы,
      и у них было семеро детей, среди которых самым старшим был Алкион, в тот раз рождённый в мужском
      теле. Он был чувствительным ребёнком, мечтательным и любящим одиночество, с достаточно развитой
      психикой, чтобы чувствовать присутствие духов природы и умерших людей, иногда видя их. Отрывки
      прошлых жизней время от времени появлялись перед ним во сне; тогда он не знал откуда они приходили
      и чем они были, но мы (те кто следует за ним через них) сразу же узнали группы людей, которые
      распевая песни, шли по прямому пути от моря к горам, задолго до строительства города; посланников,
      которые отправились ко двору короля Персии и далее через пустыню к Аравии; и странные события из
      последней описанной жизни, где он в женском теле родил ребенка (который сейчас стал его мамой)
      посреди ужасов лемурийской магии. 6 тысяч лет прошло с тех пор и он должно быть прожил 7 или 8
      жизней, но в его снах эти события были ясны так, будто они произошли вчера; он снова чувствовал
      смесь непримиримых чувств отвращения и симпатии, страха неизвестного и уверенного триумфа.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The Manu's theories of education were still the same, and Sirius followed them devoutedly, so
      Alcyone and Apollo were less harassed and misunderstood than the modern boy usually is, and
      consequently they retained through life a certain amount of their sensitiveness.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Методы Ману в обучении были всё теми же и Сириус тщательно следовал им, так что Алкион и Аполло
      были в меньшей мере непонимаемы и меньше уставали чем современные дети и потому они сохранили на
      протяжении жизни некоторую степень чувствительности.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He talked often and eagerly of his dreams to his father and mother, but they had not his memory,
      though they often had a feeling that they were on the brink of remembering while they listened to
      his vivid descriptions, and once when Mizar was slightly feverish, she had a very clear vision of
      one of the scenes an endorsement of his accuracy which greatly pleased Alcyone. He also discovered
      that when he related one of his dreams in the presence of his younger brother Apollo, the latter
      was able to catch the thought picture from his mind and to make a drawing of what he described,
      sometimes including details which he himself had omitted to mention. The younger brother had an
      intense admiration for the elder, and during their youth they were always together, living a life
      of great happiness and full mutual comprehension.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Он часто с интересом рассказывал о своих снах маме и папе, но у них не было его памяти, хотя они
      часто ощущали будто помнят что то похожее когда слушали его пылкие рассказы, а однажды, когда Мицар
      была слегка взволнована, у неё было ясное видение одной из сцен, которая подтверждала точность его
      слов, что было очень приятно Алкиону. Он также обнаружил, что когда он рассказывал о своих снах
      своему младшему брату Аполло, тот мог ухватить картину в его уме и сделать рисунок того, что он
      описывал, иногда с такими подробностями, который он забыл упомянуть. Младший брат был в большом
      восторге от старшего и на протяжении их детства они всегда были вместе, живя счастливо и в полном
      взаимопонимании.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      In due course they both married. And this introduced into their lives new interests which made
      their previous inseparability impossible, but caused no diminution in their affection, their
      marriage call for no special comment, but that of their sister Orion caused a good deal of
      excitement in the family. This sister came between them in age a handsome and striking-looking
      girl, beloved by both, and also by various other young men. One of the most passionate of these
      suitors was Gamma, the son of a neighbor in humble position, named Thetis, who was regarded as
      under a cloud in consequence of a wicked action committed many years before. Mizar had a sister
      Helios, who from an early age had been destined to become a priestess of the temple, and was
      receiving the somewhat rigid training which was imposed upon those who were aspirants for that
      office; and Thetis having seen this girl, became the victim of an overmastering passion for her.
      Helios repulsed his advances with disdain: he swore to be revenged upon her and make a determined
      effort to seize her and subject her to his will. Fortunately his scheme was discovered and the
      calamity averted; but the matter could not be kept altogether private, and Thetis became a social
      outcast in consequence. Later he married a woman of lower caste, and had a son Gamma, who to some
      extent inherited his lack of control in these matters. Orion and Gamma had sometimes played
      together as little children without any objection on the part of Sirius, who was disposed to think
      that Thetis had by this time atoned for his sin; but he would certainly not for a moment have
      contemplated the idea of an alliance so unsuitable for his daughter, so Gamma pursued his suit in
      secret, and even Orion herself, though feeling kindly towards him, did not regard it as serious.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Со временем они оба женились и это привнесло в их жизнь новые интересы, которые сделали их прежнюю
      неразлучность невозможной, но нисколько не уменьшив их привязанность друг к другу. Их свадьбы не
      требуют отдельного замечания. Свадьба же их сестры Орион вызвала заметное возбуждение в семье. Их
      сестра была между ними по возрасту, была любима братьями и изумительно выглядела, чем привлекала
      внимание многих молодых людей. Одним из наиболее преданных её поклонников был Гамма - сын одного
      соседа незнатного происхождения (назовём его Тетис), который был под подозрением из за одного
      безнравственного поступка совершённого несколько лет назад. У Мицар была сестра Гелиос, которой с
      раннего детства было суждено стать жрицей храма и потому проходящей несколько жесткое обучение,
      которое давалось всем подобным ученикам; и Тетис, заметив эту девочку, стал жертвой непреодолмой
      страсти к ней. Гелиос отвергла его попытки с презрением: он поклялся отомстить и сделал
      определённые попытки схватить её и подчинить своей воле. К счастью, его план был обнаружен и беду
      предотвратили, но всё это не смогли удержать в секрете, из за чего Тетис стал впоследствии изгоем.
      Позже он женился на женщине из более низкой касты и у него родился сын Гамма, который в некоторой
      степени унаследовал недостаток контроля над подобными желаниями. Орион и Гамма иногда играли вместе
      как дети и Сириус не возражал против этого, потому что сколнялся к мысли, что Тетис к тому времени
      загладил свой поступок; но он тогда определённо не предполагал союз столь неподходящий для его
      дочери, так что Гамма попросил его одобрения в тайне, и даже сама Орион, хотя и благосклонно
      расположенная к нему, не рассматривала всё это так серьёзно.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      About this time a dashing young foreigner arrived with a caravan from Mesopotamia, bringing a
      letter of introduction to Sirius, who at once received him as his guest, and put all his resources
      at his disposal. It was speedily evident that this, handsome stranger was captivated by the graces
      of his host's daughter, and presently her watchful mother Mizar sounded Orion on the subject, and
      she blushingly confessed that her happiness was bound up with the life of this new-comer. Mizar
      communicated her discovery to Sirius, for he had felt strongly attracted to his visitor as indeed
      might have been expected, for this was Herakles, who had been especially sent by the Manu himself
      to take incarnation abroad in order that an infusion of the noblest Akkadian blood might be
      introduced into his projected sub-race. But in their physical bodies neither Herakles nor Sirius
      knew anything of all this, so the latter sought his guest sadly, and spoke frankly though
      delicately about the subject. Herakles at once admitted his strong affection for Orion, and
      explained the rank and wealth of his family; in order to show that as far as such qualifications
      went he was an eligible suitor.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Примерно в то время с караваном из Месопотамии прибыл молодой иностранец; он привёз с собой
      рекомендательное письмо для Сириуса, который сразу же принял того как гостя, предоставив ему все
      удобства которые были. Сразу же стало ясно, что этот симпатичный странник был очарован красотой
      дочери хозяина дома, и она смущённо признала, что её жизнь теперь связана с этим странником. Мицар
      поведала о своём открытии Сириусу; последний чувствовал сильную привяанность к своему гостю, что
      была вполне ожидаемо, потому что тем гостем был Геракл посланный самим Ману, чтобы тот родился
      вдалеке и привнёс в создаваемую подрасу примесь благороднейшей аккадской крови. Но в их физических
      телах ни Геракл ни Сириус ничего об этом не знали, поэтому последний грустно подошёл и прямо, но
      вежливо, сказал, что думает. Геракл сразу же признал свою сильную симпатию к Орион и описал статус
      и богатство своей семьи, чтобы показать, что если подобные требования есть, то он подходящий
      кандидат.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Sirius replied: "Both of wealth and rank I have amply sufficient to leave my daughter entirely free
      to select her future husband where she will, and I desire above all things that she should be
      happy, as I clearly see she would be with you. Indeed I may confess to you openly that never have I
      felt towards any stranger as I do towards you never have I thought it possible that I could so feel
      towards one not of our Aryan blood; you are to me as a brother, and nothing could please me better
      than this alliance if it were possible. But it is unthinkable, because our race is a race set
      apart, a sacred race upon which many restrictions are laid; therefore it would be impious and
      unpatriotic of me to yield in this matter to the dictates of my heart, however deeply you and I and
      my daughter may suffer from my inflexibility. Do not think me unsympathetic in this; I know that to
      you I must seem proud and heartless, yet try to believe me when I tell you that I am doing at heavy
      cost to myself what I know to be a religious duty."
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Срирус ответил: "Статус и богатство, что у меня есть, вполне достаточны, чтобы оставить моей дочери
      полностью свободный выбор будущего мужа где она пожелает; больше всего я хочу, чтобы она была
      счастлива и я хорошо вижу, что она будет счастлива с тобой. В самом деле, я открыто признаю, что я
      ни разу не был в таких отношениях с странником в каких я нахожусь с тобой и я думал, что не мог
      иметь таких отношений с представителем не арийской расы. Ты мне как брат и я был бы рад если был
      возможен лучший союз чем этот, но это невозможно, ибо наша раса находится отдельно от других - это
      священная раса на которую наложены многие ограничения. Потому это было бы бесчестно и непатриотично
      с моей стороны уступить сейчас требованию моего сердца, но из за этого ограничения, мы - я, ты и
      моя дочь - будем сильно страдать. Я знаю, что кажусь тебе гордым и бессердечным, но всё же
      постарайся понять когда я говорю, что мне даётся большой ценой то, что для меня - религиозный долг."
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      But Herakles could not be convinced of the necessity of this rejection of his suit, nor was Orion
      to be comforted by any suggestions of the heroism of the sacrifice required of her; so the lovers
      remained disconsolate. Now Alcyone also felt as a brother towards Herakles, and moreover he had
      recently married Achilles, who was the bosom friend of Orion; so naturally this newly wedded couple
      felt deep sympathy with these unfortunate lovers, and desired very earnestly to find for them some
      honorable way of attaining the happiness which seemed at the same time so near them and yet so
      unreachable. At last Alcyone, greatly daring, went (without telling anyone of his intention) and
      solicited a private audience of his grandfather, and laid the whole case before Him, telling Him
      that he knew quite well the impossibility of the union, but that his beloved sister's life and
      happiness were at stake, and he felt that there ought to be some solution of the difficulty.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Но Геракла не убедила необходимость отказать в его притязаниях, и Орион не утешал героизм в такой
      жертве с её стороны, так что влюблённые остались несчастны. Теперь и Алкион чувствовал себя как
      брат Геракла; более того, он недавно женился на Ахиллес - давней подруге Орион - и естественно,
      новая пара ощущала глубокую симпатию к несчастным влюблённым и решила очень самоотверженно найти
      для них некий достойный способ обрести счастье, которое казалось так близко и в то же время было
      таким недоступным. В конце концов Алкион очень дерзко, никому не говоря о своём намерении, попросил
      личной встречи с дедушкой и изложил ему всю ситуацию, сказав, что хорошо знает о невозможности
      союза, но поскольку на кону было счастье его любимой сестры, он чувствовал, что должно быть какое
      то решение этой проблемы.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And the Manu replied: "Grandson you have done well to come to me in this matter. Be of good cheer,
      for I can solve your difficulty, and bring happiness to all concerned, go and tell this to your
      sister and to her noble lover, and bear to your father my command that he shall wait upon me
      without delay. "
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      И Ману ответил: "Внук, ты хорошо поступил придя ко мне с этим вопросом. Я могу решить данную
      проблему и сделать их счастливыми. Иди и скажи это своей сестре и её достойному возлюбленному и
      передай отцу мой приказ, что ему следует прийти ко мне без промедления."
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      So delighted were they to hear this unexpected, this incredible news, and so eager to understand
      what it could mean, that they all came at once to the palace, though only Sirius went in before the
      King. And the Manu then unfolded to His son part of His wondrous plan how He intended now to start
      a new sub-race, and to put the preparations for it into the hands of His second son, the eldest
      being required to act as His successor at Manoa; how for the purposes of that sub-race he needed
      the slight admixture of foreign blood, and how therefore he had Himself planned and arranged for
      all that had happened, so that the seeming stranger was in reality no stranger, but a brother from
      ages long past to be admitted with rejoicing into what was truly his home the home of his soul, if
      not this time the birthplace of his body.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Столь восторженны они были услышать эту неожиданность и столь жаждали узнать значение всего этого,
      что все они пришли в замок одновременно, но лишь Сириус подошёл к царю. И тогда Ману раскрыл перед
      сыном свой удивительный план того, как Он собирался создать новую подрасу и доверить её подготовку
      своему второму сыну - самому старшему, которому предназначалось стать Его наследником в Маноа; как
      ради той подрасы Ему требовалась небольшая примесь иностранной крови и как Он сам всё спланировал,
      что казавшийся странник оказался вовсе не странником, а далёким членом семьи который возвращается в
      свой истинный дом - в дом своей души, ибо в тот раз он родился в другом месте.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Then Sirius, overcome with joy, understood and obeyed, and withdrew his opposition; and the lovers
      were called before the Manu, who repeated to them the explanation which He had given to Sirius,
      and, turning to Herakles, said:
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Тогда Сирирус, справившись с восторгом, понял и подчинился. Влюблённых позвали к Ману, который
      повторил перед ними то, что рассказал Сириусу и, повернувшись к Гераклу, сказал:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      My son, you have followed me throughout the ages, although you know it not; will you follow me now
      once more, giving up for my sake the country in which this time you were born, and taking up
      instead the work that I shall give you?
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Сын мой, ты следовал за мной на протяжении эпох, хотя ты об этом и не знаешь. Пойдёшь ли ты за мной
      ещё раз, бросая ради меня свою страну где ты в этот раз родился, чтобы выполнять работу которую я
      тебе дам?
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And Herakles bowed his head and gave his promise, feeling that in doing this he was returning to
      his true fatherland and accepting a religious duty as well as entering upon a life of happiness.
      Then the Manu blessed them and gave them permission to marry; but in order that His law might not
      be broken, He sent for His eldest son Osiris, and asked him whether he was willing to adopt
      Herakles into his family. Osiris gladly consenting, the ceremony of adoption was at once performed
      and duly registered so that all formalities preliminary to the marriage might be complied with; and
      there was great rejoicing among those who had before been so sad, and all their friends were glad
      too, for Herakles had made himself universally popular.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      И Геракл поклонился и дал обещание, чувствуя, что делая это, он возвращается на свою истинную
      родину и выполняет религиозный долг, как и начинает жизнь полную радости. Тогда Ману благословил их
      и дал разрешение жениться, но чтобы его закон не был нарушен, он послал за своим старшим сыном
      Осирисом и спросил у того, готов ли он принять Геракла в свою семью. Осирис с удовольствие
      согласился, после чего сразу же должным образом провели церемонию принятия, тем самым завершив все
      формальности предшествующие свадьбе. И все те кто был столь опечален, стали полны радости, как и их
      друзья, а Геракл сразу же оказался в центре внимания.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      That same evening, as Herakles and Alcyone walked together in the great garden of Sirius, talking
      reverently of what had happened that day and of the plans which the Manu had disclosed, a man
      suddenly leaped forth from behind a tree, and struck savagely at Herakles with a knife. Herakles
      was not looking in that direction at the moment, and might have fallen an easy prey to the
      assassin, but to reach him he had to cross in front of Alcyone, who, seeing the gleam of the knife
      in the starlight, dashed himself against the man and hurled him to the ground, so that Herakles
      received only a slight scratch. Before the ruffian could rise both gentlemen had seized him, and
      Alcyone had twisted the knife out of his hand. When they dragged to the light they found him to be
      Gamma, who had been maddened by the idea that his adored one should thus be borne off by another
      and not even an Aryan ! He was handed over to the officers of justice, and the Manu sentenced him
      to lie banished from the empire of Manoa, telling him that he came from a bad stock, and was
      unworthy of the privilege of being an Aryan. So he was sent forth into what the Aryan poets called
      the outer darkness,  where the religion of the light was not professed; and his place knew him no
      more.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      В тот же вечер Геракл и Алкион прогуливались по великолепному саду Сириуса, с благоговением
      обсуждая случившееся за день и планы Ману который тот им раскрыл, как некий человек выпрыгнул прямо
      перед ними из за дерева и яростно кинулся на Геракла с ножом. В тот момент Геракл не смотрел в том
      направлении и мог стать лёгкой добычей убийцы, но чтоб достигнуть его, ему пришлось бы пройти перед
      Алкионом, который заметил блеск ножа в свете звёзд и кинулся на человека, сумев опрокинуть его на
      землю, так что Геракл отделался царапиной. До того как бандит смог подняться, они схватили его и
      Алкион выкрутил нож из его рук. Вытащив его на свет, они обнаружили, что это Гамма, которого свела
      с ума мысль о том, что его любимая будет отдана другому и даже не арийцу! Его передали офицерам и
      Ману приговорил его к изгнанию из империи Маноа, сказав, что тот недостоин привелегии быть арийцем.
      Таким образом его отправили в то место, которое арийские поэты называли внешней тьмой, где религия
      света была неизвестна, после чего о нём ничего не слышали.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Sirius with his children moved into the chosen valley, and the history of ten thousand years before
      repeated itself. The same work of reclaiming the ground and bringing it under cultivation, of
      mapping it out into estates and gradually building palatial country houses; even the very plan of
      terracing which Corona had adopted in the other valley was closely followed, for naturally all
      those who were doing the work had made a special study of the plan, and were familiar with its
      results and with all the improvements which later centuries had introduced. The character of this
      new valley rendered desirable certain modifications of the scheme, but Alcyone's cleverness at this
      work had not deserted him, and results soon began to show. Herakles had joyously accompanied his
      brother-in-law, and threw himself into the pioneer work with his characteristic assiduity.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Сириус со своими детьми отправился в выбранную долину и история прошедших десяти тысяч лет
      повторилась вновь. Та же самая работа по возделыванию земли, превращение её в обитаемое место и
      постепенное возведение деревенских домов. Даже план террасирования земли, который Корона перенял с
      другой долины, был тем же, так как все участвующие в работе изучили тот план и были знакомы с его
      результатами и улучшениями, привнесёнными на протяжении последующих столетий. Особенности долины
      сделали желательными определённые изменения в схеме, но сообразительность не покинула Алкиона и
      результаты не замедлили себя показать. Геракл радостно присоединился к своему новому брату и
      погрузился в работу с характерным ему прилежанием.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      As the years rolled on stalwart sons and daughters gathered round them, many of our old friends
      appearing with new faces. Among the twelve children of Alcyone we find Corona, ready once more, as
      ever, to become a mighty leader of men, whether in the arts of war or of peace; and also a daughter
      Selene, destined to meet with a very curious adventure, which we must describe, since it brought
      about what is perhaps the most noteworthy incident of Alcyone's later life. Selene, like her aunt
      Orion, had two suitors, but in this case both were equally eligible, for both belonged to the
      highest families, and as regards courage and ability there was little to choose between them.
      Selene's decision was in favour of Viraj, and an engagement was announced; but as she was still
      quite young, it was thought best to postpone the marriage for a time. The other suitor, Deneb, felt
      himself ill used; he declared that if Selene knew him better, she would not refuse him. He wanted
      nothing but fair play, he said, and equal opportunity, and somehow or other he meant to have them.
      Little attention was paid to his remarks, as they were put down simply as the expression of acute
      disappointment; but later they were remembered. The design which he formulated was old-fashioned
      enough; he wished to follow the custom of some of the Mongolian tribes, and carry off his future
      wife by force not with least idea of injuring her in any way, or even of compelling her to accept
      him, but with the conviction that all he needed was an opportunity of showing himself to her as he
      really was, and she must certainly succumb to his fascinations. A crazy scheme, truly; but
      disappointed love and overweening self-conceit are bad counsellors.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Со временем здоровые дети собирались вокруг них, среди которых появились многие наши старые друзья
      с новыми лицами. Среди дюжины детей Алкиона мы находим Корону, вновь готового как и всегда стать
      могущественным лидером людей в искусстве войны или мира; а также дочь Селену, с судьбой
      предназначенной встретить очень любопытное приключение, которое мы должны описать, так как оно
      стало причиной одного, возможно наиболее заметного, события в дальнейшей жизни Алкиона. Селена, как
      и её тётя Орион, имела двух ухажёров, но в её случае они были одинаково достойны, ибо оба были из
      знатных семей и в отношении мужества и способностей было трудно кого либо выбрать. Выбор Селены пал
      на Вирэя и уже объявили о помолвке, но поскольку она была ещё молода, было решено отложить свадьбу
      на время. Другой ухажёр, Денеб, чувствовал, что с ним плохо обошлись и заявил, что если бы Селена
      знала его лучше, она бы не отказалась от него. Он говорил, что хотел лишь, чтобы всё было по
      честному, чтобы у всех были равные возможности, и что он добьётся этого так или иначе. К нему мало
      кто прислушался, потому что его слова восприняли лишь как выражение крайнего разочарования; но
      позже о них вспомнили. То что он придумал было весьма старомодно; он желал последовать традиции
      некоторых монгольских племён и силой забрать свою будущую жену, но не с целью поранить её в каком
      либо смысле или заставить её выбрать его, а с уверенностью, что всё что ему нужно это возможность
      показать себя таким, каков он есть на самом деле, чего будет достаточно, чтобы она поддалась его
      обаянию. Его идея была по настоящему безумной, ибо отвергнутая любовь и чрезмерная самоуверенность
      - плохие помошники.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He managed the plan of abduction rather cleverly, choosing a time when Selene was about to pay a
      long visit to some relations in the city. On various pretexts he got rid of the escorting servants,
      substituting some of his own, who were quite ready to assist him; and then he contrived to have
      false messages sent to the friends at each end of her journey to her own family that she had
      arrived in safety, to the others that her visit was postponed for a time. Thus he gained a whole
      week's start before his treachery was discovered, and at the end of that time it was impossible to
      find any trace of his movements. Viraj was naturally furious, and Alcyone and Mizar exceedingly
      anxious; they all knew that Selene would not willingly have fled with Deneb, and they all could not
      understand what had occurred. Several days were wasted in exhaustive enquiries, but no reliable
      information could be obtained. Then it occurred to Mizar that her sister Helios, the priestess
      might be able to help them, as she was in the habit of going into trances occasionally and
      prophesizing cryptically; so she paid her a visit and invoked her aid to discover the direction in
      which Selene had been taken. Helios was at once greatly interested and promised to do her best for
      them; she threw herself into a receptive condition, and emerged with the reassuring information
      that the girl was safe and well, and in no danger of any sort; but that she was being carried far,
      far away to the south, and that her pursuers would have to cross the great sea before they would
      overtake her.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Он спланировал похищение весьма умно, выбрав время когда Селена собиралась на длительный визит
      своих родственников в городе. Под разными предлогами он избавился от сопровождающих слуг, часть
      которых заменил на своих собственных, вполне готовых помогать ему; и он сумел доставить ложные
      послания её друзьям с обоих концов: её семье что она добралась в безопасности, а её подственникам
      что её визит откладывается. Таким образом он получил целую неделю форы в течении которой о его
      предательстве не знали, а к её концу уже было невозможно найти какие либо следы его передвижений.
      Вирэй был в настоящей ярости, а Алкион и Мицар были крайне обеспокоены; они все знали, что Селена
      не убежала бы добровольно с Денебом и никто не мог понять что произошло. Несколько дней было
      потрачено впустую на тщательные поиски, но ничего достойного внимания найти не удалось. Тогда
      Мицара озарило, что его сестра Гелиос - жрица и могла бы им помочь, ибо она имела особенность
      впадать в транс и что то видеть; так что она нанесла её визит и попросила её помощи в поиске
      направления куда забрали Селену. Гелиос сразу же заинтересовалась и пообещала сделать всё
      возможное; она ввела себя в восприимчивое состояние и вышла из него с уверенностью, что девушка в
      безопасности и ей не угрожает какая либо опасность, но её увезли далеко, очень далеко на юг и что
      её преследователи должны пересечь великое море прежде чем смогут перехватить её.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      On this somewhat meagre indication Alcyone and Viraj set out southward with a small escort of
      faithful attendants; they enquired constantly whether any such party as they sought had been seen,
      but for a long time found no trace of it. The fact was that Deneb had taken special precautions as
      long as he was in the land directly governed by the Manu, but had somewhat relaxed his vigilance
      when he entered the tributary States, so when they had crossed the frontier the pursuers at last
      heard news of those whom they were following, and so learnt that they were on the right road. That
      road however was no easy one, and many weeks had passed before they reached the ocean. There again
      some time was wasted in futile enquiries but finally they ascertained that whom they sought had
      embarked upon a vessel which traded to the great islands of the south those which we now call the
      Dutch Indies. They took the next ship going in the same direction, and at each port of call they
      made careful enquiries, and at last, at a port in the island, which we now call Sumatra, they heard
      that their predecessors had disembarked and gone up into the hills in the interior. Now the
      condition of that island differed little in those days from what it is at present; that is, the
      coasts were settled and civilised and occupied by a keen race of traders; but the hills in the
      interior were to a large extent in the hands of various savages tribes, who, though they had learnt
      by experience to let the coast people alone, were frequently at war among themselves; so that the
      country was distinctly unsafe for travellers.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      С этой скудной информацией Алкион и Вирэй отправились на юг с маленькой группой преданных
      помошников; они постоянно проверяли наличие следов того, что они искали, но таких следов в течении
      долгого времени не было. Денеб предпринял особые меры предосторожности пока был на земле прямо
      управляемой Ману, но несколько ослабил бдительность когда перешёл на территорию подданых
      государств, так что как только они перешли границу, они тут же услышали новости о тех кого
      преследовали и таким образом определили, что шли по верному пути. Та дорога, однако, была не
      простой и прошло много недель врежде чем они достигли океана. Вновь некоторое время было потрачено
      впустую в поисках, пока они окончательно не убедились, что те кого они преследовали отплыли на
      судне на великие острова на юге, на те, которые мы сейчас называем Голландской Индией. Они сели на
      следующий корабль в том направлении и в каждом порту, что они посещали, тщательно всё узнавали, и
      наконец в порту осторова, который сейчас зовётся Суматра, они услышали, что преследуемые сошли с
      корабля и отправились вверх на холмы. Сейчас условия на том острове несколько отличаются от тех,
      что были раньше; побережье острова было заселено цивилизованной и проницательной расой торговцев, а
      холмы внутри были в основном в руках разнообразных диких племён, которые хотя и сделали вывод из
      своего опыта, что людей на побережье лучше оставить в покое, всё же часто воевали между собой, так
      что те земли были определённо опасны для путешественников.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      However there was nothing to be done but to follow, so Alcyone took with him an interpreter who
      understood the language of the tribes, and plunged bravely into the mountains. There was no
      semblance of a road and the party had much difficulty in making its way over the rugged country.
      Inquiring after a white fugitive, they were directed to a tribe in a peculiarly inaccessible
      region; but as they drew nearer to it and the rumors became more definite, they saw that they were
      on a wrong track, for the story was of a white man who came there alone many years before, and had
      joined himself to that valley and pursued their quest elsewhere, offering a large reward for
      information. Travelling round the same mountain at a lower level, they at last heard news which
      seemed unmistakably to refer to those whom they sought, for they were told that a small body of
      white people guarding a lady had recently appeared among them, and had been attacked by a
      neighboring tribe, but had contrived to make friends with its chief. The people were now living
      unharmed among the members of that tribe regarded as semi-divine beings, or great heroes, with a
      wonderful power of fighting. But it was said that the lady sat always apart, and hardly ever spoke,
      but seemed enveloped in sadness, though treated by all with the most distinguished consideration.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Однако им ничего не оставалось делать кроме как следовать дальше, так что Алкион взял с собой
      переводчика который понимал язык племён и храбро отправился в горы. Там не было ничего похожего на
      дорогу и преследователи с трудом шли вперёд по труднопроходимой местности. Спрашивая про белого
      беглеца, их направили к племени расположившемся в примечательно труднодоступном месте; но чем ближе
      они подбирались и чем больше появлялось слухов, тем яснее становилось, что они сбились с пути,
      потому что слухи были о белом человеке пришедшем туда в одиночестве много лет назад и
      присодинившемся к долине; так что они продолжили поиски дальше, предлагая большую награду за
      информацию. Огибая ту же гору уровнем ниже они наконец услышали новости, которые казались явно
      указывали тех кого они искали, и им говорили, что небольшая группа белых людей, охраняя леди,
      появилась среди них и была атакована соседним племенем, но сумела подружиться с его вождём. Теперь
      те люди живут невредимые среди членов того племени и почитаются как полубоги или как великие герои
      с удивительной силой сражаться. Но они также сказали, что леди всегда сидит в стороне и едва
      говорит, и казалось в печали, хотя и почитается всеми с наибольшим вниманием.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      On receipt of this news our party pushed forward rapidly up that valley, but about half way up they
      were received by a flight of arrows, which killed a servant and two horses, causing a momentary
      disorder, while they were hurriedly arranging themselves for a conflict, Deneb suddenly showed
      himself upon the top of a rock overlooking the position, and called out to them to hold their hands
      and retire. If they did this, he said, they would be left unmolested, but if they advanced further
      they would certainly all be killed, as he had posted his savages with the military genius of the
      Aryan. He told them that Selene was in good health and entirely unharmed, and that if she were left
      alone he was quite sure that he could presently prevail upon her to accept him as her husband; but
      that he intended to have fair play and would brook no interference.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      С этими новостями наши герои быстро отправились к той долине, но на пол пути их встретил дождь из
      стрел, который убил слугу и двух коней, моментально вызвав беспорядок. Пока они торопливо
      готовились к бою, Денеб внезапно показался на вершине скалы и осмотрев позицию, призвал сложить
      оружие и убираться. Он сказал, что если они последуют его совету, то будут оставлены в покое, но
      если подойдут ближе, то будут несомненно убиты, ибо у него были в распоряжении дикари и военный
      гений арийцев. Он сказал, что Селена здорова и невредима, и что если её оставить одну, то он
      уверен, что сможет убедить её принять его в качестве мужа; но он хочет, чтобы всё было всё по
      честному и не было никакого вмешательства.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone and Viraj would have none of this, but shouted back defiance to him, and ordered their
      followers to charge in open order up the valley. This they did in the face of another discharge of
      arrows, and as soon as they got to close quarters with the savages the latter broke and fled, for
      they were unable to stand before the better arms and greater valour of the civilised men. But
      though they would not fight man to man, they dodged behind rocks and trees and kept up a shower of
      Parthian shafts, and the small party of Aryans had suffered considerably before they finally put
      them to fight. Deneb had cheered on his savages at first, and some of his Aryan attendants were
      among them trying to check their flight; but when he came down from his rock and Alcyone sprang to
      meet him, he lowered the point of his sword and said:
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      У Алкиона и Вирэя ничего из этого не было, но они прокричали в ответ с вызовом и приказали своим
      помошникам готовиться к битве. Их встретил ещё один шквал стрел, но чем ближе они подходили к рядам
      дикарей, тем больше последние разбегались, ибо не могли выдержать натиска более отважных и сильных
      цивилизованных людей. Хотя они не бились один на один, а прятались за деревьями и скалами от дождя
      парфянских дротиков, всё же маленькая группа арийцев сильно пострадала до того как начала биться.
      Денеб подбодрил своих дикарей и некоторые из его арийских помошников наблюдали за теми, но когда он
      сам спустился со скалы и Алкион выпрыгнул перед ним, тот опустил остриё меча и сказал:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Friends, I thought to withstand you because it seems to me that I have not been treated fairly; but
      I find that I cannot fight along with savages against a nobleman of my own race.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      "Друзья, я решил встать против вас, потому что мне казалось, что со мной обошлись нечестно, но я
      также нахожу невозможным биться вместе с дикарями против представителей моей собственной расы."
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Thus the indomitable pride of the Aryan blood told when a crisis came, and Alcyone understood and
      recognised the sentiment, even though he was angry at the unnecessary slaughter both of his own men
      and of the barbarians. He said:
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Таким образом себя проявила неудержимая арийская гордость, и Алкион понял его, хотя и был зол из за
      ненужной резни своих людей и варваров. Он ответил:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      But you have caused the death of many men at the hands of these creatures; is that conduct worthy
      of an Aryan? Do you not know that for that alone you should be banished from the company of men?
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      "Но из за тебя погибло много людей от рук этих созданий; достойно ли это арийца? Разве ты не
      знаешь, что лишь за это ты должен быть изгнан из рядов людей?"
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      (For it was the custom of the Aryans to speak of themselves as the noble that indeed being the
      meaning of the word Aryan; of the highly civilised Atlantean races as  men' or as foreigners; and
      of the savage tribes simply as barbarians, not using for them the term  men' at all.)
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      (Арийцы имели привычку говорить о себе как о знати, что в самом деле было значением слова "арий", о
      высокоцивилизованных атлантах как о людях или чужаках, а о дикарях просто как о варварах, не
      применяя слово "человек" в их отношении вообще.)
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      I know,  replied Deneb,  that that is against good morals because it is not our custom; but it has
      happened because you have pursued me thus into far countries and have not left me alone to carry
      out my plan.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      "Я знаю, ответил Денеб, что это аморально, потому что не согласуется с нашими традициями, но это
      случилось потому что вы преследовали меня, а не оставили в покое, чтобы я выполнил свой план."
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      But Viraj broke in:  Your plan is a wicked one, for none who is worthy of the name Aryan would thus
      try to coerce a free- born lady; you know quite well that your father, your mother, your brothers
      disapprove of it and are much ashamed because of you; you know that you yourself would be full of
      anger if anyone thus treated your sister Aulus. I demand therefore that you shall at once yield the
      young lady to me whom she has chosen , and if you will not I shall kill you here and now.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Но Вирэй перебил: "Твой план омерзителен, ибо ни один достойный называться арийцем не попытается
      принуждать свободнорождённую леди. Ты хорошо знаешь, что твой отец, твоя мать и твои братья
      осуждают тебя и стыдяться из за того, что ты сделал. Ты знаешь, что сам будешь в ярости если кто то
      будет так обращаться с твоей сестрой Аулис. Потому я требую, чтобы ты сейчас же отпустил молодую
      леди ко мне - к тому, кого она выбрала - или я убью тебя здесь и сейчас."
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      No,  interposed Alcyone,   I cannot allow that; there has been killing enough, and it is a shame
      that the hand of an Aryan should be turned against his brother. But you must give up my daughter to
      me, and she shall be free to choose whom she will.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      "Нет" - перебил Алкион - "Я не могу позволить это, ибо уже достаточно было убийст, и это было бы
      позором, если бы рука одного арийца обернулась против своего брата. Но ты должен отдать мне мою
      дочь и она должна быть свободна в выборе того кого пожелает."
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      I am willing to agree to that, replied Deneb;   for what he says as to my sister Aulus is true,
      though I had not thought of it in that way before. I thought only of giving the Lady Selene an
      opportunity of knowing me thoroughly, feeling sure that my devotion would win her; but if it will
      not, I am far from desiring her unhappiness. I will abide by her decision.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      "Я склонен с этим согласиться" - ответил Денеб - "ибо то, что он сказал про мою сестру Аулис -
      правда, хотя я не думал об этой с такой стороны. Я лишь хотел дать леди Селене возможность узнать
      меня лучше, и уверен, что моя преданность её завоюет. Но если не так, то я далёк от того, чтобы
      желать её несчастья. Я последую её решению."
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      So they all climbed up the hill together, calling the scattered savages to them, and telling them
      that peace had been arranged. But the barbarians grumbled much, saying that many of them had been
      killed, and yet they had gained nothing. Their settlement was a collection of curiously-shaped
      wooden huts, surrounded by a defense of thorn-bushes, partly natural and partly artificial, but not
      quite  effective; and our party had to climb over this by a rickety bamboo framework. The chief
      came somewhat sullenly to meet Deneb, not understanding how he had made friends with the enemy, and
      (like his people) not seeing what he had gained by the fray. He could not understand why  so much
      fuss should be made about a woman, and regarded the whole affair as incomprehensible, but if the
      white stranger gave him money with which weapons could be bought, he was willing to sacrifice the
      lives of his people up to a certain number.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Так что они забрались вместе на скалу, позвав разбежавшихся дикарей с собой, сказав им, что было
      достигнуто перемирие. Но варвары начали ворчать, что многие из них погибли, а они ничего не
      получили взамен. Их поселение состояло из жилищ любопытной формы, окружённых для защиты колючими
      кустами, частично искусственными, но не очень эффективными, так что нашей компании пришлось
      забираться через них по шаткому бамбуковому каркасу. Вождь несколько угрюмо подошёл к Денебу, не
      понимая как тот сумел подружиться с врагом, и (как и остальные) не видя смысла в этой стычке. Он не
      понимал почему столько шума из за женщины, и считал всё это весьма странным, но если бы белый
      странник дал ему денег на которые можно было бы купить оружие, он согласился бы пожертвовать
      некоторым числом жизней своих людей.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Our friends gave him scant attention, for Deneb was conducting them to the hut in which he had
      lodged Selene; but when they called her to come forth there was no answer, and she could not be
      found anywhere. There excited enquiries presently elicited the fact that the savage women set to
      guard the hut had felt it to watch the fight in the valley below, and meantime the prisoner had
      evidently escaped. the chief at once offered to behead the neglectful sentinels, and thought the
      Aryans less comprehensible than ever when they rejected his proposal with obvious disgust and
      horror. But the problem was, where could Selene have gone? The only way out of the valley was
      downward, and she had not passed them as they climbed up; there was nowhere where she could hide,
      and the rocks above and at the sides were plainly inaccessible.
    </view>
    <view lang="ru"></view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The chief attributed the disappearance to diabolical intervention, but Alcyone, though not entirely
      incredulous as to mysterious possibilities of that sort, was inclined to accept the suggestion, and
      sought persistently for a more commonplace explanation. The end of the valley was but small in
      area, and lay open before them, and there seemed no possibility of escape from it, as it was
      surrounded by a wall of sheer rock many feet in height, at the end of the valley, as is so often
      the case in similar formations,  a cascade fell from still greater height. At the end of the
      valley, as is so often the case in similar formations, a cascade fell from still greater heights,
      making at its foot a pool in which the  bolder spirits of the tribe sometimes bathed, though with
      circumspection, because of a tradition that some sinister creature dwelt there, who at some remote
      era of the past had seized two young men and carried them away at least so it was supposed, for the
      young men had gone to bathe there and had never been seen again, nor could their bodies be found.
      Our friends were told that Selene, who had been allowed full liberty within the settlement, except
      when actual fighting was going on, had seemed attached to this pool and had swum in it daily,
      exciting the admiration of the barbarians by her courage and proficiency. No trace of her was now
      to be seen, however ; but Viraj had gloomy suspicions that somehow her disappearance might be
      connected with this pool. He argued with some show of reason that there was absolutely nowhere else
      in the valley where a body could be concealed; he had been into every hut in the village and they
      were all entirely without furniture . Alcyone had his suspicions of the savage chief, but could not
      accuse him, as it was impossible to formulate any reasonable theory of what he could have done with
      the missing  young lady.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      They returned to the hut which had been assigned to Deneb and his party to discuss the mystery; but
      Viraj prowled restlessly back to the cascade and its pool, muttering to himself that she might some
      how have fallen in, in some wild attempt to climb the rocks (though that looked manifestly
      impracticable); that the mythical monster might after all be real, and might have carried her off;
      that her body might be entangled in some weeds; and above all that there simply was not anywhere
      else where she could be. He had with him a confidential servant Boreas, a young man who was
      Alcyone's special personal attendant; and the man offered to dive into the pool and make a thorough
      examination of the bottom if he could reach it. Viraj agreed, and Boreas threw off his clothes and
      jumped in. He presently reappeared, reporting that the sides of the pool were shelving, but that he
      had not been able actually to reach the bottom.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Twice more he tried, but without success, and Viraj told him that he was only risking his life
      uselessly by trying to penetrate to depths beyond human reach. But he carved leave to try once
      more, because as he came up the last time he had observed a curious rock formation that he did not
      understand, and he thought there might be a shelf there under which a body might lodge. So after
      resting a few minutes he jumped in again; but this time he did not reappear as usual. After waiting
      fully five minutes, Viraj became convinced that some accident had happened, and he was just
      tearing off his own garments to spring in with a vague hope of discovering what had become of the
      faithful fellow, when Boreas came to the surface looking none the worse for his protracted
      immersion.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Viraj pronounced excitedly upon him, demanding an explanation; and a curious explanation it was.
      Boreas told him how he had investigated the shelf which he had noticed, and found that it overhung,
      and that there was an opening behind it. He had feared much that this might be the lair of the
      mythical beast, but nevertheless made up his mind to swim into it, lest the body, which he feared
      to find, might be concealed there. To his great surprise, a few strokes trough the darkness brought
      him into a place where there was a faint but unmistakable light, so he struck up instantly to the
      surface, and found himself in another pool, evidently in some sort of cave. The faint light
      filtered down from a great height, and both the cave and the pool appeared to be of considerable
      extent. Boreas was greatly surprised and awed, and still more decidedly of opinion that he had
      chanced upon the dwelling place of some destructive monster; but after a few minutes, spent in
      nervous contemplation, he recollected that Viraj must be wondering about him, and so he dived back
      again through the passage into full daylight and told his story.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Naturally Viraj at once went to see this wonder for himself, and returned much impressed and
      convinced that Selene must  undoubtedly have discovered this strange way of escape when bathing,
      and waited to utilize it until opportunity offered. He hurried back to the hut where Alcyone and
      Deneb were still occupied in profitless speculation, and unfolded before them his discovery (or
      rather that of Boreas) and his ideas, and announced his intentions of following up this possible
      clue and thoroughly investigating the cave, in which he thought it probable that Selene might be
      hidden. He had called her and obtained no answer; but the extent of the fissure was unknown, and
      along this line there was at least hope and something definite to do. Alcyone and Deneb agreed with
      him, and decided forthwith to divide their party, leaving a considerable guard under a trusty
      subordinate to look after their horses and other property, while the leaders, with a few followers
      who were good swimmers, were to follow the track so strangely discovered, and either find Selene or
      prove to themselves that she had not taken the very unusual road.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Deneb, horrified at the unexplained disappearance of Selene, was now thoroughly on the side of our
      friends, and begged to be allowed to accompany them in the adventure, so Alcyone accepted him with
      full faith that he would prove himself a loyal comrade. They could take but little clothing, but
      they they armed themselves fully, in case the mythical monster should prove to have an unpleasantly
      real existence. They had not taken the savage chief into their confidence as to their intentions,
      telling him only that they meant to leave their horsed encamped outside his village while they made
      some further researches; but some of his people undoubtedly saw the extraordinary spectacle of a
      number of warriors leaping one after another into a pool and vanishing utterly from mortal sight
      which may well have been the basis for many a marvelous legend for centuries to come.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Viraj led the way, as one who knew it ; Alcyone followed him, then Deneb, and then their men,
      Boreas bringing up the rear. Alcyone waited until all his men had emerged into the curious
      half-light of the cave and then ordered them to swim straight out from the wall through which they
      had entered. In this way they soon came to the other side of the cavern, and landed on a sloping
      rock, at one side of which a small stream of water was running into the pool. Alcyone decided to
      follow this stream of water as far as possible, as in doing that he would be safe from falling into
      some bottomless crevasse a danger which he apprehended because of the insufficient light which
      filtered through some crevice high above them. Presently they lost even that, for the stream flowed
      along a kind of tunnel, but by wading in it they made their way safely; and after what seemed a
      long time they emerged into another cavern of different character scarcely more than a grotto, but
      with much more light than the other. This time the opening through which it came was visible, and
      Alcyone resolved to abandon the friendly little stream, and try to climb to it. Finding the ascent
      possible, though hazardous, he called his men to follow him, and they emerged into daylight once
      more, at the bottom of a kind of cup or small basin among the rocks.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Climbing to the rim of this in the only place where it seemed feasible to attempt it, they found
      themselves on a little platform on the side of a steep rock. To go upwards was clearly out of the
      question; downwards was smooth as glass, and sloped at an alarming angle, but only for about twenty
      feet, beyond which lay  an ordinary rocky hillside, perilously steep but quite negotiable. As there
      was nothing else to be done, our party let themselves slide down one by one, and all arrived among
      the boulders without mishap. They did not know in the least where they were, but they had followed
      the only track that it seemed to them practicable for Selene to have taken; and at any  rate, as
      Viraj remarked, they certainly could not return the same way! They had come out at the head of a
      different ravine; and as they watched from among the rocks they saw men moving some distance below
      them, and presently they were able to make out the village, which seemed, however, to be without
      the usual defense of a thorn-hedge. They afterwards discovered that this settlement, into which
      they had found their way by an unsuspected back-door, was considered absolutely inaccessible, and
      was consequently never attacked by the surrounding tribes. The only way into its valley was by a
      narrow and giddy path running along a shelf half-way down a stupendous precipice a path along which
      men could advance only in single file, which could be blocked in a moment by a few boulders, and
      defended by one man against an army only if it possessed savage's weapons. Its people therefore
      dispensed with the inconvenience of the thorn-hedge and for all-sufficient defense kept two
      sentinels watching always night and day at the nearer end of their path.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Our friends from their nest of rocks, watched the life of the village below them while they
      discussed how they should advance into it. Advance it was clear they  must, as they could not sit
      there and starve among the rocks, and they could not get back up that slippery slope. They argued
      that Selene must have found the way that they had found, because there was practically no other.
      She might have hidden somewhere in the cave, but there seemed no reason why she should, and besides
      they had shouted at intervals as they came through. So the probabilities were that she was in the
      village in front of them. But how would she have been received by the savages? For it is to be
      noted that many of these tribes had a decidedly unsavoury reputation, and a wandering damsel in
      distress might well excite in them emotions other than chivalry. She had already been missing for
      some hours, so clearly it behoved our friends to act without delay. It appeared probable that by
      making their way carefully among the rocks they could approach a good deal nearer the village
      without being observed, so they began to move cautiously forward.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      No one in the tribe had the faintest conception that they might be attacked from above from the
      sky, as they would have phrased it; so no sort of watch was kept on that side, and all the huts
      faced down the ravine. So our party, moving circumspectly, attained unnoticed a position hardly
      more than a hundred yards from the rearmost  house. There they called a halt, and watched for an
      indication that anything unusual was happening; when suddenly their ideas were all upset by seeing
      a white man step out into the sunlight in little open space in the town. The man wore the insignia
      of a chief, and was obviously not a prisoner; so Alcyone raised a great shout in his own language,
      and the whole party broke cover and rushed downwards as quickly as the nature of the ground
      permitted. In doing this they lost sight of the white man, but they took it forgranted that he
      would accept them as friends; yet there were wild cries of surprise and alarm, and a hurried
      beating of a drum, so they realised that they were perhaps acting too precipitately, and at the
      foot of the rocks they called a halt for a moment. It was time, for though they could not see a
      single person, there came from behind the huts a flight of arrows fortunately harmless, but showing
      what sort of welcome they might expect. Alcyone walked forward alone, holding out his hand as a
      sign of peace, and calling out in his own tongue that he was a friend; but at that a figure with a
      white cloth drawn over its face, having holes for the eyes, stepped forth from behind a hut, and
      shouted in the same language.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      No friend, but an enemy ever! But for you I should have gained my revenge; but for you I might have
      won my bride!
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Shouting some word of command which brought forth another shower of arrows, and then a charge of a
      horde of savage warriors, he rushed upon Alcyone and attacked him furiously. Alcyone realised at
      once that this was a dangerous antagonist, and he had to employ all his skill to defend himself
      against this savage onslaught. A barbarian from the side struck at him with a spear; as he sprang
      back to avoid that, the savage, overreaching himself, stumbled for a moment between the
      antagonists. With a quick push and twist Alcyone threw him against the veiled man, and with one
      mighty stroke slew them both. A sharp hand-to-hand fight was by this time going on all round him,
      and he saw Deneb, at the head of a small band of his own followers, cutting his way heroically
      through the crowd of savages and driving them before him round the angle of the nearest hut. The
      fall of the veiled man evidently dispirited the black men, and they began to give way in all
      directions before the determined rush of the hand full of Aryans. As soon as the flight became
      general, and the largest group of huts was in the hands of the conquerors, Alcyone called back his
      pacific intentions by signs. The interpreter had been afraid to join the swimming party, so he had
      no ready means of communication with them; for the most part they remained in hiding, but at least
      they  ceased to offer any resistance to his advance. further shouting was heard in front, and at
      first they thought it betokened a renewal of the fight but in a moment appeared Deneb, leading
      Selene by the hand (this was the first time during the whole of her adventure that she had
      permitted him to touch it) and he brought her to her father and said:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      There, Sir, I restore to you that of which I had robbed you, with many regrets and apologies; for I
      see now what I did was ill done, and that I was thinking of myself and of my desire only. And not
      of the wishes of her whom, nevertheless, I truly and loyally loved.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He would have said more, but at this point he felt a faint, for he was sorely wounded, and it was
      over his body that Selene was clasped in her father's arms. But a moment later he turned her over
      to her lover Viraj, and raised the unconscious form of Deneb. They  bound up his wound as well as
      they could, and sprinkled water upon his face, and presently he recovered  somewhat. They found
      that Selene during her enforced stay in that country had picked up a few words of the language of
      the barbarians, and knew, among other things, their peace-cry; so she was able to call some of them
      from their hiding-places, and explain that no harm would be done to them.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      They knew of a plant whose leaves when chewed made an excellent application for wounds, and they
      soon had a sort of cataplasm of them prepared for Deneb and the other wounded men, and they cleaned
      out one of the largest huts sufficiently to enable them to use it as a shelter from the rays of the
      sun, and convert it into a temporary hospital. There was a point about which Alcyone had some
      curiosity, so he sought for the corpse of the first man who had opposed him, and dragged the veil
      off his head, to discover that this white chief of a savage tribe was none other than Gamma, whom
      long ago he had prevented from killing his brother-in-law Herakles.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Then Selene told them the story of her abduction, and of the intensity of her indignation and
      despair. She admitted that, except for the one all-important fact of thus carrying her off against
      her will, Deneb had behaved most chivalrously, and had done everything in his power for her
      comfort. Nevertheless, she would have none of him at any price, and she was always watching for an
      opportunity to escape. Deneb had expected pursuit, but thought that by burying himself for a time
      amidst the barbarians of this far-away island he would successfully conceal himself from it; and as
      soon as Selene had made up her mind to marry him he intended to return home and be forgiven for his
      escapade. Therefore he had made friends with the chieftain of the first tribe, and arranged to stay
      with him for a while and help him in his petty wars against neighboring tribes in return for his
      hospitality.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Selene when bathing and diving in the pool, had discovered the passage inside the cave only on the
      very day of the attack, and had intended to make use of it that same night, as soon as she had got
      together the jewels that she was wearing when abducted. By leaving at night she hoped to secure a
      good start, and, she trusted that no one would guess the manner of her flight. When the attack
      came, and everyone's attention was attracted by it, she saw opportunity and profited by it. She had
      no certainty that there was another way out of the cave, though she hoped there might be; but if
      she could find one, she had formed the plan of living in the cave, and diving out through the
      passage at night to obtain food, until such time as a chance might offer for escaping from the
      valley altogether.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      That the cave should open into another territory on the other side of the mountain had occurred to
      her, but she was not slow to take advantage of it. She also had slid down that smooth rock, and
      when she found a white chief who understood her language, she thought all her troubles were at an
      end. But Gamma, though he received her with great respect, evidently thought that providence had
      sent her as mate for him, and was already dreaming of founding a white dynasty that should conquer
      all these barbarous tribes and unite them into one empire. He was at first perturbed to hear of  a
      back-door into his impregnable valley, but on consideration begged her to keep the secret from his
      followers, as he saw that he might be able to use it to impress his people with an idea of his
      supernatural powers. Selene saw that she had escaped from one too persistent a suitor only to fall
      into the hands of another even less desirable, and her situation would still have been very
      difficult if it had not been for the opportune arrival of her father.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      But now the question was how to bring together the two halves of their expedition, and how to
      manage with their wounded men. It was manifest that these latter could not be carried back by the
      route which they already knew, even though the construction of a rough bamboo ladder enabled them
      to overcome the difficulty of the smooth rock, and as inspection of the only  way into the valley
      had satisfied Alcyone that so large a burden as a helpless man could not possibly be conveyed
      safely along so dangerous a path. There was, therefore no alternative but to stay where they were
      until their wounded recovered, and to try to bring the other section of their party from some other
      way. Such enquiries as Selene was able to make with the tribe on the other side of the mountain
      elicited only the vague reply that it lived in a different country at a distance of many days
      journey. Viraj volunteered to return through the tunnel with a single armament and bring the horses
      and the rest of the party round to the lower part of  the valley where they now were ; and after
      much anxious consideration Alcyone decided that there was nothing better to be done than to accept
      the suggestion. So the ladder was rigged up, and the two men went back to the valley they had left
      and rejoined their comrades there.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      By heavy bribes they induced two men of that tribe to go with them as guides to show the shortest
      way round the base of the mountain,  but the country was so rugged, and such wide detours had to be
      made to avoid hostile tribes, that it was fully two weeks before Alcyone's sentinels at the other
      end of the rock-ledge announced the approach of Viraj. They regarded it as too great a risk to try
      to bring their horses along that impracticable path, so a camp had to be made at other end of it;
      but that naturally lay open to attack, and they deemed it wise to take some trouble to fortify it.
      No one interfered with them, however, for curious stories of their strange powers were already
      beginning to circulate among the savages, who were at the stage of development at which witchcraft
      always seems the simplest explanation of any unusual fact.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      As tribal affairs had been disorganized by the death of their chief, Alcyone temporarily took his
      place, and endeavored to do simple justice as well as he could in circumstances which he often but
      practically comprehended. Gamma, it appeared, had taken a wife from among the savages, and had
      several children, the eldest being a boy of sixteen. Gamma had taught his children to speak the
      Aryan tongue, so Alcyone offered to take them to Manoa, but they all agreed in preferring to cast
      in their lot with the tribe whose customs and life they knew; so Alcyone demanded from the people
      whether they were prepared to recognize Gamma's eldest son as their chief when he himself left, and
      they all agreed to this, being full of reverence for the white men, whom they  regarded as
      peculiarly favored by the gods. They had thought of Gamma as invulnerable and even now held that he
      could not have been killed except by superior white man, who, as they believed, came down
      mysteriously from heaven to execute upon him some divine decree.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      So Alcyone took Gamma's son to live with him during his stay, and tried to give him some
      rudimentary education in the ways of the Aryan, especially indicating principles of justice and
      gentleness, and emphasizing the responsibility of the chief for the welfare and happiness of his
      people. The boy absorbed all this eagerly, and promised faithfully to observe this teaching all his
      life long, and to hand it on to his children in turn. with regard to this question of the
      succession, the boy spoke eagerly to Alcyone, begging him to send him from Manoa a white girl to be
      his wife, for he felt that the inspiration of these new ideas would fail him if his household
      became as that of the savages over whom he was to rule. Alcyone had gently explained that the
      conditions of life in far-away Manoa were so utterly different that no woman would consent
      permanently to leave them for the sake of sovereignty over a sumatran tribe; but as he found that
      the custom of the tribe permitted and even encouraged the marriage of brothers and sisters, and as
      gamma's eldest daughter only a year younger than the boy, had the same deep-rooted repulsion
      against accepting a barbarian husband, it seemed to him that it would be the lesser of two
      difficulties to allow these two to follow the habit of the tribe, and so perpetuate a mulatto line
      of chiefs who might, he hoped, be trusted at least to carry on the traditions he was endeavoring to
      implant.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This ,then, was the arrangement finally made; and when, after some months, Deneb seemed
      sufficiently strong to make the perilous journey along the rocky shelf with safety, Alcyone himself
      celebrated the nuptials of these two strangely situated young people, and solemnly installed them
      as king and queen of the tribe, making a speech on the occasion (through the new king as
      interpreter) in which he gave the people much good advice, and promised them great prosperity if
      they followed it. He had previously exhorted them to refrain from useless attacks on their
      neighbors, and to make the most of their great natural advantages by cultivating their valley to
      the utmost, so that it would be entirely self supporting.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      So, with many farewells from the new chief and chieftains, the Aryans at last set out on their
      homeward journey, which they accomplished without special incident. Alcyone had been away from home
      so long that there was great interest in his return, and he was forced to give a public account of
      his travels which practically amounted to a course of lectures. Sirius and Mizar were delighted to
      welcome back their son, and the wedding of Viraj and Selene was immediately (organized) with much
      pomp and rejoicing, the chief actors being popular public characters on account of their romantic
      experiences. During his recovery from his wounds Deneb had learned to reconcile himself to his
      fate, when after a year or two he married Castor, and settled down into a meek husband and father.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This may be described as the principal adventure of Alcyone's life, which for the rest followed an
      even course of happiness and usefulness. It seems curious that in this incarnation, as in the last
      which we examined, one incident should stand out so prominently from the rest of the life, and that
      in each case these incidents should be connected with the rescuing of a damsel, in distress.
      Electra, who had been the centre and cause of that strange adventure six thousand years before, was
      born this time as Alcyone's nephew, the son of Herakles, in order to obtain that infusion of
      Akkadian blood which the Manu required; but he married Alcyone's daughter Euphra, and was with him
      as much as though he had belonged to his family directly by birth.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Electra and Euphra had a son Echo, who was a strikingly handsome and most promising boy, but
      nervous and highly strung. Unfortunately his eager yearning for information led him to over-study,
      so that his health broke down, and he became the victim of some obscure nervous disease. They gave
      him complete rest and set him to live entirely out-of-doors, and it was part of his illness laid
      upon before him the whole realm of the nature spirits, who were greatly attracted by this wonderful
      beauty, so that he entered eagerly and unrestrainedly into their life, and absolutely lost interest
      in that of humanity. He became etherealised and spiritualized in the strangest way, yet from the
      physical point of view he was obviously losing strength daily, and drawing near to some unnatural
      euthanasia.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Euphra was in despair about him , and at last look him to her father Alcyone, who had a reputation
      for effecting mesmeric cures. Alcyone was deeply interested in the strange case of his grandson,
      for whom he had a strong affection; he took the boy to live with him for a while, and spent much
      time in the investigation of this unusual disorder. He did not in the least discourage his love for
      the woods and the company of the mature spirits, but made a point of accompanying and sympathizing
      with him for asking him to describe and explain everything to him fully. At the same time he
      watched carefully for the slightest symptoms of the dawning the purely human interest, and one day
      he, thought he detected it when his little granddaughter Ida paid him a visit. So he promptly
      borrowed her from her mother Herminius for a long visit and let the two children be always together.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Little by little by his wise direction, the influence of human child replaced that of the fairies,
      and Echo gradually regained the physical strength which has so nearly lleft him forever. Alcyone
      laid great stress upon achieving this with the full and hearty consent of all parties concerned,
      especially the fairies; for it this had not been done, if they had resigned their playfellow
      unwillingly, they would always have been trying to draw him back and there would have been a
      perpetual danger of relapse, and an unceasing feeling of resentment and hostility which would
      surely have led to disastrous results. But it was only after many months that Alcyone pronounced
      the boy fully cured and restored him to his parents, advising them to marry him to Ida ( since that
      was now the one dominant wish of his heart, and both she and her parents were agreeable to the
      match) as soon as ever they were old enough, this advice was accepted, and the young couple were
      ideally happy, all trace of Echo's nervousness having now completely disappeared, and his physical
      health being fully re-established, though something of the ethereality of aspect always remained to
      him.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      When the Manu left His body , Osiris ascended the throne of Manoa, but Sirius, his brother, ruled
      the little community in the newly reclaimed valley, and after the death of Sirius, Alcyone
      succeeded to the charge. When he also passed away, at his special wish authority was vested in his
      nephew Viraj, the companion of his great adventure of many years ago. After him in turn followed
      Dhruva his son, who married Ajax; and the Manu Himself honored them by re-appearing as their eldest
      son, and by His incarnation the new sub-race was definitely started on its way.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
