<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 11</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 11-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Yet again our band appears in the third sub-race and in the country of Persia, where there was by this time an old and well-established civilisation. Some fourteen centuries after the conquest of the country by the Manu, and about nine centuries after the visit of the Mahaguru, we find the same relative arrangement of the three main divisions of the kingdom still persisting. Neptune was at this time the King of Persia, while under him Sif was the ruler of Mesopotamia, and Elsa of the mountain district of Armenia. Each of these divisions had considerably increased in the intervening period, Persia having extended itself eastward, Mesopotamia south-eastward to the head of the gulf, and Armenia westward so as to include part of Asia Minor. But on this western side of the kingdom the frontier was ill-defined, and there was no exact determination of the prerogatives of the various local chiefs, who owed a rather vague allegiance to the central power. There were in several parts of the kingdom almost inaccessible mountain fastnesses, and in these still remained unconquered tribes, who lived their own isolated life. Mercury, whose body in the last life had been used by the Mahaguru, was in this incarnation one of the priests of the religion which had previously been founded through him; and our hero Alcyone appears as his second son.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Mercury was brother to Herakles the Queen, so his children were in constant association with the royal children, and when they grew up the natural results followed in the way of close friendships and matrimonial alliances. Mars, the heir to the throne, married Alcyone's sister Vajra, and the King's second son Electra espoused Sirius, another of Mercury's daughters. But when long before these alliances Alcyone and Electra were bosom friends, and a third who was often of the party was Alcyone's cousin Saturn, who afterwards married Mizar.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The three young men, Alcyone, Saturn and Electra, had at one time a remarkable adventure which narrowly escaped a fatal termination. It was the custom among the noble families of Persia at this time for young men to complete their education by a certain amount of travel, much as young Englishmen of the eighteenth century made the grand tour of Europe. The more impecunious contented themselves with visiting a few of the principal cities of their own empire, but the fashionable journey was that to the great Central Asian capital of Manoa. This trip was duly taken by three friends, and they were profoundly  impressed by what they saw; but after they returned from it they felt little disposed to adopt a settled life, and determined to make yet another expedition, first through the Armenian mountains, which in this incarnation they had not seen, and then on round the coast of Asia Minor and back through Palestine and Mesopotamia. This journey, though hardly a usual one, was supposed to be quite safe, for most of the Levantine coast was at that time in the hands of an Atlantean ruler named Rahanuha (our old friend Tripos), who, though he had the reputation of being a stern and remorseless tyrant, was friendly to Persia on account of the close mercantile relations which existed between the two countries. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Atlantean merchants who for some centuries before that time had been establishing colonies at the eastern end of the Mediterranean were chiefly of the fourth sub-race keen traders, but at the same time brave and adventurous men. Whenever there was any sort of a harbour one of their towns sprang up, and they soon opened up communications with Persia by means of caravans, thus furnishing its merchants with an outlet towards the countries of the west and an alternative route to Egypt, while at the same time they themselves introduced into Persia the wares of Atlantis. They suffered much in the early days from the depredations of the tribes of the interior, and they soon found it necessary to band themselves together into a confederation to resist the attacks. For some hundreds of years, however, they remained a cluster of practically independent cities, each gradually drawing under its sway more and more of the surrounding country. These cities adopted for themselves various schemes of government, but the commonest arrangement was for each of them to choose each year one of the principal merchants to be its governor.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Presently it happened in several cases that men who showed special aptitude for the office were elected to it for life. Then there arose in one of the cities a young man of military ability, named Al-hi (Known to us , however as Roxana); being the son of its governor he was put at the head of its troops, and organised them so well that, when the tribes made a determined attack upon it, he was able to inflict upon them a crushing defeat. The chieftain of one of the defeated tribes swore to be avenged upon it and spent several years in visiting all the other tribes and inducing them to join him in a colossal raid which should place all the coast towns in their power, and enable them to slaughter all the merchants and seize their gold. By this concerted action three of the seaside cities were simultaneously besieged, and were soon in serious difficulties, for the tribesmen descended upon them like a swarm of locusts. But Roxana was equal to the occasion ; he had been training his men and had evolved clever plans whereby he circumvented his enemies and destroyed them in detail. When he had entirely broken up and disposed of the army that had attacked him, he marched to the help of the nearest of the other cities, which he found besieged by another huge yelling mob of tribesmen. Attacking this crowd at the nearest point, he soon forced his way through it into the city, whose magnates acclaimed him as a deliverer. But he offered his assistance only upon certain definite terms; he demanded that this city should recognise his father as its King otherwise, he said, he would march his men home again and leave them to their fate. They were in desperate straits; they knew that they were themselves powerless against so great an incursion of hillmen, and so they soon decided to yield the conditions which Roxana required. This being settled, he at once took the offensive against the tribesmen, and after a long day of battle routed them utterly.Then after allowing his men a little rest, he moved on to the third city. There the enemy had already beaten down all resistance and stormed the town, and massacre and pillage were just commencing. He dashed in at once upon the victorious tribesmen, swept them out of the streets and houses, and soon changed defeat into victory. As the principal men of the place had already been killed, he had little difficulty in getting his father's authority recognised, and calmly announced to his father that he had brought two more cities under his rule.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
His father was at first a little perturbed, but Roxana soon won him over to his views, and induced him to call a meeting of all the leading merchants to whom he himself expounded the great advantages which would accrue from the consolidation of the three cities into one state, and the establishment of a permanent dynasty of capable rulers. His magnetic force carried the whole meeting with him, and his father was proclaimed King by acclamation. Wisely, as little change as possible was made in the practical daily routine of government, and as soon as the citizens were used to the merely nominal alterations, Roxana carried off his father on a visit to other cities, and contrived to make the new regime popular there also. When the modified machinery was working smoothly, this energetic young man set to work upon the construction of a good road to link together the three cities, and at the same time established an effective control over the intermediate tracts of country. When the new state was on a secure footing it was only a question of time to absorb the other Atlantean cities higher up the coast, and gradually to bring more and more of the hinterland into cultivation. After some years the father died, and Roxana himself came to the throne of the kingdom that he had built up. He ruled it for close upon half century, and during that time made it a powerful and prosperous state.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Unfortunately his successors had neither his capacity for organisation nor his sleepless devotion to the welfare of his country, and by the time that his great-grandson Tripos ascended the throne there was already bitter disaffection among his indocile subjects. Tripos was a tactless person, a veritable Rehoboam, and he tried to repress instead of to conciliate; and though during the first years of his reign his efforts were successful, he stored up against himself an amount of virulent hatred that could not but presently find savage expression. It came to the surface at last in an outburst of indiscriminate massacre not at all unlike the French Revolution, in which not only Tripos was murdered, but all who could by any stretch of the imagination be connected with him or with the upholding of his rule; and unfortunately this explosion occurred  while our three travelers were in the country. Being reasonably well dressed, they were at once seized by the first party of rebels whom they met, and when on being searched they were found to be in possession of a letter of introduction to Tripos, it was at once decided that they were dangerous people aristocrats worthy of death.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The Levantine revolution, like the corresponding horror in France thirty thousand years later, made a great parade of the forms of justice, though carefully  avoiding the reality; so our travelers were arrested and thrown into jail to await a trial which never came only because the self appointed officials who had signed the commitment were themselves murdered before they had time to go through the farce of examining the prisoners. Of course our travelers made indignant protests, but no manner of notice was taken of them; they were kept in close confinement for several months, receiving only the coarsest food, and even that irregularly and in insufficient quantity; and they owed their escape at last not to any form of trial, but to yet another ebullition of barbarity, in which it occurred to some ruffian who happened for the moment to be in power that it would save money and trouble to break open the jail and butcher the prisoners.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
These particular prisoners, however, were Aryans, fresh and keen, trained fighters, stronger, braver, and more agile(even after their long confinement) than the comparatively effete Atlanteans, and when once their cell doors were broken open they soon possessed themselves of the weapons and quickly turned the tables on their opponents and fought their way out through the confusion into the open air. Fortunately it was night, so the race difference was less conspicuous than it must have been in the daylight, and by mingling with the madly-yelling crowd and judiciously effacing themselves at the first corner they contrived to escape notice for the moment.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
While rejoicing in their recovered freedom they could not but recognise that they were still in a very awkward position. Their money had been stolen, their property confiscated, and their servant killed; they possessed nothing but the clothes on their backs and the swords  which they had just snatched from the foes whom they had overthrown; they were in the midst of a city in the throes of a revolution, and had some hundreds of miles of possibly hostile country to cross before they were out of the most immediate danger. Their first object was to get clear of the city, so as to avoid any probability of being rearrested; their second was to lay hands on some food. They knew nothing of the town, as they had been seized as soon as they entered it; they could never keep a straight course in any direction, because they were constantly compelled to turn aside and dive down some back alley to avoid bodies of armed men, generally half-drunk and brawling. Thus it happened that after what seemed to them to be hours in dodging about in this way they suddenly found themselves out on the sea-front of city, instead of on their way to the interior, as they had wished to be.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
As several people were hurrying along the road into which they had come so abruptly, they thought it wise not to hesitate, but to walk straight across it as though they had some business with the ship which lay against the quay opposite. As they could see no one on board, it seemed best to walk straight on to the half deck as though they had a right there, and their movements apparently excited no suspicion on the part of the passers-by. At first they had a wild hope that they might be able to seize the ship and escape by its means, but they saw men moving about on another vessel close by, and realised that these people's attention would be attracted by anything so unusual as an attempt to move a ship at night. Alcyone however caught sight of a small boat attached to the stern, and it at once occurred to him that though the larger craft certainly could not be moved without arousing curiosity, it would not strike anyone as unusual that a small boat should pass along from one vessel to another. He communicated his idea in a whisper to his companions, who highly approved; but Electra said:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
  Before we embark upon a voyage, let us see whether we can find anything to eat aboard here. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Searching quickly yet carefully, they soon came upon a store of food curiously shaped loaves of coarse hard bread, and masses of dates and figs, all crushed together into cakes. It was the fare of the common sailor, but our half-starved heroes recked   naught of that; Alcyone hastily stripped off his cloak and made a sort of bag of it, which they filled with bread and fruit, while Electra found and promptly appropriated a little of olive oil. Meanwhile Saturn, who was examining the after part of the vessel, came suddenly and excitedly to tell them that a man(probably the watchman) lay asleep there upon a heap of sails. They moved like cats to avoid waking him; and contrived to get safely into a boat, which was only just large enough for the three. They cast it silently and pushed themselves along by the side of the ship, and paddled quietly with their hands for a few yards, so as to make no noise. There were two oars in the boat, but they did not use these until they were well out of sight of the line of vessels, fearing to attract attention.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Moving with the greatest caution, they gradually drew to the mouth of the little harbour, and were presently well out of reach. Then they stopped rowing and attacked with great thankfulness their bundle of coarse provisions, and made the first satisfactory meal that they had had for months. Greatly strengthened by this, they discussed their plans, and decided that the best thing to do would be to row along the coast for a few miles until they came to some lonely part of it, and then abandon the boat and endeavour to make their way eastward to some less disturbed country. When dawn broke they found themselves opposite an apparently desolate shore, and after some searching discovered a spot where they could land-a few yards of sand with a small cave at the back. They dragged their boat ashore and into the cave, lest some inhabitants might see it, took a necessary and most refreshing bath, and then lay down beside the boat for a few hours of sleep.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Fortunately for our wanderers the revolutionary madness which was convulsing the towns had drawn into them a great number of the country people, so that they were able to travel unperceived and unmolested. During the day they saw several houses which appeared to be unoccupied and towards evening they ventured to enter one of these in search of food; but they found nothing but a little fruit. As the place was obviously abandoned they decided to spend the night there, and took the opportunity to wash  what was left of their clothing. In a dark inner room they found a chest containing some such garments as farmers wore in those times, and in their distressed condition they thought it justifiable to appropriate some of these, as being less likely to attract unfavorable attention than the rags to which their own foreign clothing had been reduced. They still retained the swords of which  they had possessed themselves in the fight at the time of their escape from prison, but had not scabbards for them, and so found them somewhat inconvenient.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Next morning they resumed their journey, still through a desert country, and after an hour's travel they were fortunate enough to encounter a flock of goats, from which they obtained some milk. About midday they came in sight of a small village, which they judged it prudent to avoid as they saw from some flags which were displayed in front of the houses that the spirit of unrest had penetrated even there. By evening they were again ravenously hungry, and they decided that they must find another farmhouse; and by climbing a hill and examining the surrounding country they were able to discover one a lonely homestead in a secluded valley. As smoke was rising from it they knew that it was still occupied so they resolved to go boldly down to it and ask for food and shelter, arguing that it was improbable that men who lived in so quiet a spot should be infected with the madness of the town, and that they were well able to defend themselves against any force which they were likely to meet in this sequestered nook.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
They found the house in possession of an old man and his wife, who received them most hospitably, but spoke some sort of provincial dialect which was by no means easy  to follow. They gathered, however, that the old couple had several sons who had gone off to the city in the hope of gaining much money through the revolution; but that the old people themselves distrusted all these new-fangled ways and intended to keep the farm going as a home to which their sons could return as a refuge when the temporary madness was over. They asked eagerly for news of their sons, and our friends had regretfully to admit that they had none to give. They could not convey their whole story to these good people, but they tried to make them understand that they were travelers who had no part nor lot in the revolution, but merely sought to be allowed to go on their way in peace; that they had been robbed of their money and their horses, and that their servant had been killed. The old couple nodded politely, though it is doubtful how much they really comprehended; but they pressed food and drink upon their unexpected guests, and presently showed them to comfortable sleeping places.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The next morning their host showed them great anxiety that his visitors should look round his farm, so they complied, and were able to reward his hospitality by demonstrating to him some of the improved Aryan methods of cultivation. Alcyone also made great friends with a little group of grandchildren, who followed him all over the estate. The good old housewife loaded them with provisions for the journey, and they parted from their kindly friends with many expressions of gratitude. They felt themselves now reasonably safe, though they were still nominally within Atlantean territory; but they were a long way from their own frontier, and the country which lay between was sparsely inhabited by half civilised tribes of uncertain temper. They found no more farm houses, but the food which had been given to them lasted  them for two days, and they supplemented it by various kinds of wild fruit. For a day or two after that they got very little, but then they had the good fortune to find a big patch of some kind of wild yam, which provided them with excellent nutriment. They did not care to eat locusts, as did John the Baptist thousands of years later as do many Arabs of the present day; but they did eat the locust-bean whenever they came across it, and when opportunity they willingly partook of the other item of the prophet's dietary wild honey. Still they had some ten days of distinctly unsatisfactory food before they next caught sight of a human being.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At the end of that time they came suddenly upon a body of horsemen, who surrounded them with evident curiosity, and addressed them in a tongue unknown to them. They replied in Atlantean language which they had been speaking for long, and one of the horsemen was called forward who knew a little of it, but so little that interchange of ideas seemed impossible. And when our friends spoke among themselves in the language current at that time in Persia the face of the leader of the band atonce lighted up, and he replied with a few words in that language to make inquiry whether he could understand it. A member of the band was soon produced  who could talk it with fair fluency, so he said, he had twice been into Mesopotamia with caravans. Through him our travellers promptly explained their position to the leader who seemed much interested in their adventure, and very ready to give them any help in his power. He ordered that such food as was available should be set before them, and when they had taken it he provided them horses by rearranging some of the baggage of the party.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
With newly found friends Alcyone and his companions journeyed for two days, until they came to the capital of that tribe-if one may give such a title to what was in reality little more than a kind of permanent camp, there being within its thorn defended walls more tents than hovels. Our friends were soon presented to the chief , who spoke their language with ease, and declared himself delighted to have the opportunity of serving some of the noble sons of a race which he greatly admired. He asked them to rest with him as long as they would, and promised to provide them with an escort to the capital of the tribe living eastward of him, from which they would have no difficulty in getting home, as caravans were frequently leaving for Mesopotamia. He also placed at their disposal all his resources, begging them to accept three fine horses, a whole outfit of rich garments, and a present of gold and jewels.They thanked him very heartily for his kindness, and expressed a hope that they would be able to return it when they reached their own land. Their adventures were now at an end, and the rest of the journey was safe though slow. Their absence, though somewhat longer than had been expected, had not caused any special anxiety, as nothing was yet known in Persia of the revolution in the Levantine towns.     
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 Neptune listened to their story with great interest, and at once acceded  to their request that an embassy might be sent to the chief who had so opportunely befriended them. Ida was put in charge of this expedition, which bore costly gifts to the chief, a letter of thanks from Neptune himself, and an offer of special felicities for any young men of the tribe who were willing to return to Persia for education and to the tribe who were willing to return to Persia for education and to enter the service of its King. A number of youths accepted this proposal, and in this way a custom was established which lasted for centuries and extended itself gradually to all the tribes of Asia Minor the fashion that all young men of position, such as the sons of chiefs and nobles, should go to the Persian universities for education. So the adventure of the three friends had a permanent result in the spreading over a wide tract of country of the Aryan  form of civilisation.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone specially asked that an effort might be made to find the old farmer in the secluded valley who had been first to befriend them so Ida added to his party as guides some young men from the country of the hospitable chieftain, and set out westward across the desolate lands. After some searching they came upon the valley, and found the old couple in great sorrow. They had been visited by a band of revolutionaries who had robbed them of everything, their three sons having been killed in the riots in the city, and they were left in destitution with three widowed daughters and eight or ten grandchildren. Ida was so much  impressed with the hopelessness of their position that he persuaded them to abandon their desolated home and undertake with him the return journey to Persia. He had some doubt as to how Alcyone and Electra would regard so drastic a measure, but they received the simple old people with open arms, and led them before King Neptune, who at once assigned to them from  his royal demesne a farm far larger and more valuable than that which they had left, though in order that they might not be troubled by the abrupt transition into a crowded and bustling civilisation, he chose for them a spot among the hills, remote from the capital city. Alcyone charged himself specially with the education of the grandchildren, and saw that places were eventually found for them either about the temple or the palace, and that they duly married into the Persian race. So all the members of that kindly farmer-family had reason to bless the day when they took in three hungry fugitives and sped them on their way rejoicing.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Meantime, the heir-apparent Mars had wedded Alcyone's sister Yajna, and soon after the return of our wanderers, Electra carried out an agreement which had been made in early childhood by marrying an elder sister Sirius; and a year or two later the third traveller, Saturn, married a younger sister Mizar. On their way through Mesopotamia Alcyone had been grately attracted by Apollo, the daughter of Sif, and as she was invited to the capital for the festivities in connection with the marriage of Electra, the young people met again, and very soon there was a third union to be celebrated. All these young people were special proteges of Queen Herakles, whose valuable advice was always at their disposal, and she exercised a great influence over their lives. She survived by a few years her husband Neptune, and lived to see her son Mars firmly settled on his father's throne.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
By that time also Uranus had taken the place of his father Mercury as High Priest, and his brother Alcyone was working as his assistant. He was presently appointed as his brother's representative in the second city of the kingdom a position which for a time divided him and his children somewhat from the rest of our characters, though frequent visits were interchanged. Though his eldest son Viraj had been born at the capital, most of his children were thus natives of the southern city. Of his four sons, Viraj and Corona chose the political and military life, while Orpheus and Norma were content to assist in administrative and educational work which appertained to the business of the priesthood. Alcyone had always a strong love for children and a deep interest in education, and he devoted a great deal of his time working out a scheme of universal training for all children in the country a plan  not unlike that of the Boy Scout of the present times except that it included girls as well. Many of our characters were engaged in the carrying out of that project, which Mars at once adapted and enforced over the whole of his kingdom as soon as it was laid before him. In his fiftieth year Alcyone was called back to the capital and appointed Minister of Education, a post which he filled with ardour and efficiency until his death at the age of seventy-four.
</view>
</text>
</body>