<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
  <title>
    <view lang="en">
      Life 46
    </view>
    <view lang="ru">
      Жизнь 46-ая
    </view>
  </title>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      We come now to the most momentous lives of this long series the lives to which all the others have
      been leading up. Even in these we will see much of suffering the final clearing away of such karma
      as remains; but the Great Ones come once more into close and constant touch with our hero never
      more to part from him through all the ages that lie before us, for he who joins the Great White
      Brotherhood can never again be alone. In this forty-sixth life and in the next we find him playing
      a humble part in the foundation of two of the great religions of the world; and so incidentally in
      studying his lives we obtain fascinating glimpses of some of the most important periods of human
      history.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The remnants of the great Persian empire, which had lasted for so many years, had been overthrown
      by the Mongol tribes, and the land which it had occupied had been devastated. But another Aryan
      tribe the speakers of Zend descended from the hills of the Susamir district and occupied the wasted
      territories, drawing round them such refugees as had escaped the massacre which had followed the
      victory of those savage Tartar tribes. In this country, still in quite an unsettled condition,
      Alcyone was born at a place called Drepsa, in Bactria, in the year 1528 B.C. His name was
      Maidhyaimaongha. (I may say that the names habitually used by this nation are the most
      extraordinary that I have encountered more formidable even. I think, than those of the Atlanteans,
      which we had previously supposed to bear away the palm for length and unpronounceability.) He was
      the son of a man of high family, named Arsati (Hector), who was the brother of Purushaspa (Siwa).
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      His mother (Bee) died while he was still young, so that he was chiefly in the care of his aunt
      Dughda (Vajra), who was the wife of Purushaspa, and had much to do with his upbringing. His chief
      companion was her son Zarathushtra, who was two years older, and Alcyone admired him immensely.
      Both families seem to have been wealthy that of Arasti perhaps more so. They possessed wide lands,
      which were mostly devoted to agriculture. Religion was a strong factor in the lives of both of
      families. We may say that Dugdha and Zarathushtra were the principal influences in modelling the
      boy's life, adding thereto their tutor Barzinkarus(Uranus), a man of strong character and wide
      learning.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The local king was named Duransaran (Aurora), but the King of all Bactria was Loharsp. The prime
      minister of the latter was a man named Jamaspa (Castor), who with his brother Phrashaostra (Aldeb)
      exercised great influence in the country. They were intimate friends of the brothers Siwa and
      Hector indeed they all belonged to the same great family or clan.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The condition of affairs in the country was rather peculiar. A large part of it seems to have been
      only half-settled; there as a certain number of agriculturalists, but also large tracts were still
      given over to nomadic tribes. The interests of these two sections of the community were often
      opposed, so that as time went on they tended more and more to separate.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It seems that even their religious beliefs differed considerably. Both had developed curiously in
      opposite directions from a common origin. Centuries before it would seem that some of the primitive
      Aryans, perhaps offshoots from the original first sub-race of our fifth Root-Race, had worshipped
      or reverenced two classes or types of entities, which they called respectively Daevas and Asuras.
      The Asuras were clearly at first regarded as higher and more spiritual, and Varuna, who was their
      head, as the principal of all their deities. The tribes of the great migrations which turned
      eastward into India gradually changed or modified these ideas, and they began to apply the title
      Daeva to all kings of non physical entities, but on the whole in a good sense, while they thought
      of the Asuras as turbulent and on the whole evil. They gradually allowed Varuna to sink into the
      background, and substituted Indra for him.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The tribe which, after centuries of seclusion in the Susamir Valley descended and occupied Persia,
      on the contrary preserved their reverence for Varuna and the Asura, and they presently began to
      think of the Daevas as evil spirits, or at any rate as comparatively low and materail. It would
      seem that the lower side of the Daevas became emphasised until they were mere personifications of
      the powers of nature, and were worshipped with animal sacrifices.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Unquestionably in Persia at this period with which we are now dealing, the Asura-worship had
      amalgamated with what remained of the teaching given by the original Zoroaster thousands of years
      before, and included far more spiritual conceptions than did the creed of the Daeva worshippers.
      The latter were at this time represented in Persia chiefly by the nomad tribes who killed and ate
      cattle, while the Asura worshippers were mostly settled agriculturists, who regarded the cow as a
      sacred animal, and its destruction as a serious crime. They themselves seem to have offered fruit,
      flowers, oil or butter, and curious cakes. Here in Persia the Indra conception was distinctly the
      more materialistic, and the Varuna the more Spiritual. The Asura worshippers said that the Daeva
      men were degrading the idea of deity, while the Daeva men on their side said that the others were
      refining it to a mere abstraction, and so were atheistic. Thus a bitter theological struggle was
      raging, to intensify the opposition created by the wide divergence of interests.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Loharsp's hold over his country does not seem to have been very definite, and Aurora was
      practically independent. Lohrasp's son Vishtaspa (Ulysses) was of about the same age as Alcyone,
      and as he often lived upon a big estate which Lohrasp had at Drepsa, he was an intimate friend of
      the two cousins, over whom he rather domineered. A lovely little girl, a small orphan cousin,
      Thraetaina (Mizar), came to live with Alcyone, and of course all three boys at once fell in love
      with her. Ulysses was imperious and thought nobody could resist him because he was the son of the
      overlord; Zarathushtra was impulsive, eager, poetical, flaming with ardour, yet often, by reaction,
      in the depths of despondency; while Alcyone was shy and retiring, loving perhaps more unselfishly
      than either of the others, but far less able to express it. they all felt great respect and
      affection for the tutor, Uranus, and Alcyone idolised Zarathushtra with all the devotion which a
      small boy can feel for one who is a little older.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Zarathushtra was handsome, forceful, striking in every way full of vitality, yet also a boy of
      trances and dreams . From earliest childhood he saw constantly in these dreams a man of commanding
      presence and of more than mortal power, surrounded always by glowing fire the great original
      Zoroaster, the founder of Sun-Worship, and the head of one of the great lines of human evolution.
      He frequently inspired and directed Zarathushtra, and on at least one occasion He so far
      materialised Himself that Alcyone also saw Him, and was profoundly impressed, taking Him for one of
      the great Star-angels about whom their religion taught them. This confirmed him more than ever in
      the conviction that his cousin was destined to be one of the greatest of men, and the sight gave
      him a burning enthusiasm for the higher work, and a living certainty of the reality of the unseen
      world which he never afterwards lost.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      As they grew up together Alcyone's reverence and love for Zarathushtra steadily increased, and they
      talked for many an hour over the religious problems of the time. Zarathushtra was an enthusiastic
      supporter of the spiritual Asura-worship as against the more materialistic followers of the Daevas;
      and though Alcyone was disposed to see good on both sides, he always ended by agreeing with
      Zarathushtra. It is small wonder that even as a youth the latter's fiery eloquence obtained a
      reputation for him as a coming power among the priestly families; small wonder also that he
      captured the heart of the young Mizar.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Deep down Mizar really loved Alcyone best as a mere human being, but the greatness of Zarathushtra
      dazzled her and attracted her, even while it half-frightened her. She had had something of a
      preference for Ulysses, based frankly on his commanding worldly position; and something might have
      come of it if his father had not heard of it. As Lohrasp had other plans for his son, he at once
      withdrew him from this dangerous fascination, and as soon as possible married him to a princess of
      his own selection named Hutaosa (Bella), a woman also beautiful but haughty, who at first reserved,
      but evidently soon realised the many good points in her husband, and wisely overlooked his faults
      and become deeply devoted to him.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Thus Mizar was reduced to two suitors; she was half-sorry and half-glad, for though she had coveted
      the position of Queen of Bactria she had really liked Ulysses least of the three. One day
      Zarathushtra, in a burst of confidence, told Alcyone how deeply he loved Mizar, and to poor Alcyone
      this open avowal came like a sentence of death. His heart was bound up with Mizar, yet he loved and
      adored Zarathushtra. He contrived not to show how severely the news wounded him, and went away and
      fought it all out with himself. He knew deep down within himself that Zarathushtra's mind was so
      full of mighty ideas, that for him love and marriage were in reality secondary matters, so that he
      did not really love Mizar as whole-heartedly as Alcyone himself did; but after a long and bitter
      struggle, he resolved to do at all costs what he thought to be his duty to his friend; so he
      withdrew himself entirely and went away on a visit for two months, and by the time he returned, the
      marriage of Mizar with Zarathshtra had been arranged.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      The marriage took place in the year 1510, and turned out happily enough; for Mizar was altogether
      dominated by the vivid personality of Zarathushtra, admired him intensely, and lived only to look
      after him, and make his life smooth for him. Soon she had a beautiful boy (Ajax), whom she called
      Isatvastra, and later on three daughters in succession, the last being Purochista (Demeter).
      Unfortunately, in connection with the birth of Purochista in 1505 she contracted an illness which
      proved fatal, so that the wedded life of Zarathushtra was at this time but short, and he was left
      with four young children upon his hands. He turned them over to the care of his mother Dughda
      (Vajra), which of course was exceedingly, fond of children, and spent a good deal of time over
      these, especially over the baby Puruchista.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Zarathushtra seems to have felt his wife's death somewhat acutely, but he was becoming ever more
      and more engrossed in his religious ideas and theories, and was full of projects for the reforms of
      the old Iranian religion. Feeling himself to some extent set free by his wife's death, or perhaps
      accepting it as a divine intimation to him, he betook himself to a hermit-life in a cave in a
      desert place, and set himself to most marvellous life for some ten years, a life which seems to
      have been an almost continuous succession of wonderful visions and ecstasies.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      During this period he was under the constant, the almost daily instruction of the original
      Zoroaster, and was guided by Him as to the truths which he was to place before the people. He still
      maintained quite definitely his support of the Asuras as against the Daevas; in fact, as time went
      on, he tended to exalt the idea of the Asuras, or Ahuras, more and more, and indeed the title which
      he used for the supreme deity is made from their name, with the addition of the word Mazda, which
      appears to signify wisdom. Thus he obtained the name Ahura-Mazda, which mean the Supremely-Wise
      Spirit, or the Spirit of Supreme Wisdom.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      It does not appear that at this period he had the conception of the personification of evil called
      Ahriman, which now holds so prominent a place in the Zoroastrian religion. He did to some extent
      personify evil, or at least the idea of opposition, such as showed itself in the actions and
      worship of the Daevas; but to this extent Dhruj seems also to have represented matter, for it was a
      part of his theory that Spirit and matter as it were fight for man, and that every action of man
      counts on one side or the other. The contrast between his theories and those of the Daevas
      worshippers seems not unlike that between the philosophy of Phythagoras and the popular worship of
      such deities as Apollo and Diana.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      He recognised the existence of good spirits, whom he called Ameshapentas, but there was some
      haziness about the conception, and they appear to have been partially personifications of the
      ethical ideals or principals. He quite understood reincarnation to be a fact, but seems not to have
      dwelt upon it, the practical side of his scheme being almost entirely the foundation or promotion
      of some sort of holy community, or agricultural State, in which thrift and settled tillage of the
      soil were the great social virtues.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      During his ten years' sojourn in the desert Alcyone went out often to see him, and saw to it that
      his wants were regularly supplied. Zarathushtra was grateful for this, and on one occasion told
      Alcyone that he had seen him in a prophetic vision acting as his lieutenant in the preaching of his
      reform. Alcyone brought him frequent news of his children, and even sometimes took them to see him,
      but Zarathushtra was so entirely absorbed in his gorgeous series of visions that he scarcely
      noticed them, and they soon came to cling far more to Alcyone than to their own father.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      At the end of ten years, in 1495, Zarathushtra was ordered by the Great One who appeared to him in
      his visions to return to the world, to take up the office of the priesthood, and to deliver to the
      people the truths which had been taught to him. It was prophesied to him that he should spread the
      faith over the whole of the mighty kingdom of Persia, but that before he began to travel abroad he
      must await the arrival of one who should come to him from the West,, and certain signs were given
      to him by which he was to recognise this illustrious stranger. Meantime he was to return to the
      priestly life in his own country of Bactria. His re-entry was somewhat dramatic, for just as he had
      left his cave a volcanic outburst took place which destroyed it, and the flames of the eruption and
      the accompanying earthquake were taken by the people as in some way connected with his return to
      ordinary life.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      By this time Lohrasp had abdicated in favour of his son, Zarathushtra's old friend Vishtapa
      (Ulysses). After the death of his first wife, vishtaspa quarrelled with his father, and left the
      country in a fit of anger. He travelled into the western part of Persia, made friends with a local
      King there, married his daughter, and came back home at the head of an army. He practically forced
      his father into abdication, and then made many changes in the administration of the kingdom. He
      had, however, the wisdom to retain his father's prime minister Jamaspa(Castor), and this gave the
      people a feeling of safety which reconciled them to some of his proceedings, to which they might
      otherwise have objected.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Ulysses eagerly welcomed Zarathushtra, and soon appointed him to the office of Zaohta, and later
      gave him the title of Dastur-I-Dastur. This gave him great influence, and he preached his reforms
      with splendid eloquence and fiery zeal. Since he had the vigorous support of the King, crowds of
      disciples gathered round him, and he had already a considerable following when the expected visitor
      from the west arrived in 1489.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Though Zarathushtra had returned to priestly work, he had by no means resumed family life. All this
      time his children had been growing up under the care of Alcyone, who was indeed now the recognised
      master and administrator of the household. All of Zarathushtra's children had turned out well under
      Alcyone's fostering care, and most of all his love had always gone out towards the youngest,
      Puruchista, who was now sixteen years of age, in the first flush of dawning womanhood, and
      physically the exact image of her mother. Indeed, just as in years gone by he had loved Mizar, so
      did Alcyone now enfold within his heart her daughter Puruchista. He yearned to make her his wife,
      but was restrained by the consideration of the great difference in their age. Her beauty brought
      her many suitors, but she rejected them all, telling Alcyone that she could never love anyone but
      him.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      For some time he put from his mind these avowals, fearing lest he should be tempted to take
      advantage of her youth, her gratitude, and her inexperience; but at last one day his feelings were
      too strong for him, and he asked her in faltering tones whether she really meant that she would be
      willing to line her fair young life with that of a man so far advanced towards middle age as
      himself. She eagerly and joyously accepted him,, and it seemed as though at last his happiness was
      assured; yet even now the strange karma which hung over him for so many lives overtook him once
      more, for when they went hand in hand to Zarathushtra, hoping to receive his blessing, he calmly
      told them that he had just arranged for the marriage of Puruchista with Jamaspa Kherami (Mira), the
      son of the old prime minister Castor, and that this marriage was absolutely necessary for the
      interests of his reform and the success of its propaganda.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      This was of course a terrible blow to both the lovers; they at first had wild thoughts of
      rebellion, yet for both of them submission imaged as a religious duty and they felt that this
      sacrifice was required of them by Ahura Mazda. Under such circumstances there could be but one end
      to the struggle, and Puruchista dutifully became the wife of Mira, though with little expectation
      of happiness. Her young husband, however, who had at first been attracted merely by her unusual
      beauty, soon learnt to love her for herself, and proved a brave, honourable and devoted man; so
      that her lot, after all, was by no means as sad as she had expected, and after a time she became
      able to return at least to some extent her husband's deep affection.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Alcyone, however, had no such comfort, and for a long time he suffered keenly. Comfort was brought
      to him by Mercury, the stranger from the West, who had been handed over to his care by
      Zarathushtra. This stranger had been a great surprise to them in many ways; instead of appearing as
      a reverend preacher, he came to them in the guise of a young man in the dress of a Greek fisherman;
      instead of partaking freely of the princely hospitality which Alcyone was more than ready to offer
      him, he insisted upon earning his own living, and worked daily at the trade of a goldsmith.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      A wondrous tale, too, he told them: how, until a year ago, he had been chief priest of a temple the
      temple of Pallas at Agade, in Asia Minor; and now, when his city was ravaged by barbarians, that
      body of his had been killed, and in its place he had entered into this vehicle of a young fisherman
      of the place, who had been drowned in attempting to escape the massacre.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      By the arrival of Mercury Zarathushtra seemed doubly inspired, and they began to make arrangements
      for the preaching tour which had been so long foretold, Zarathushtra had, all this time, maintained
      the closest relations with the king Vishtaspa (Ulysses), and the King was now as eager as
      Zarathushtra himself that his prophet, as he called him, should be the leader of religion for the
      while of Persia. Zarathushtra subordinated everything to what he considered the needs of his work,
      and by no means neglected to make all possible use of worldly links that he thought might be of
      value to him. Not only had he in this way married his daughter to the son of the prime minister,
      but he himself in turn, and for the same reason, had married Kavihusrava (Achilles), a cousin of
      the King, and by her had already two sons, named Hvarechithra and Urvatatnara. This second wife,
      however, did not live very long, and eventually Zarathushtra married a third time, still further
      cementing his alliance with the family of Castor by taking to wife Hvoghvi (Pindar), the youngest
      sister of the premier.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      So deep was the grief of Alcyone at his second terrible disappointment, so entirely was he filled
      with despair and weariness of life, that he thought seriously of suicide, and had all but decided
      upon it when Mercury's arrival changed the face of the world for him. Even at first he felt for
      Mercury a combination of affection and reverence, which from a proud Persian noble to one who was
      apparently a humble Greek fisherman was indeed passing strange. Almost at once Mercury spoke to him
      of the sorrow which so evidently sat heavily upon him, and drew forth from him the whole story of
      his life. Then Mercury rose from his seat, and for the moment his figure changed, and he stood
      before Alcyone in radiant glory in that gracious form that we know so well, and spoke with glowing
      words of deepest love:
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Great indeed had been your sorrow, not this time only, but many times; and even yet some sorrow
      remains, for he who moves swiftly must pay for his swiftness. But great in proportion shall be your
      joy. Yours shall be the bliss which no tongue can utter, for through you shall the nations of the
      world be blessed. This life of sacrifice is the culmination of many sacrifices; and because of
      this, even in the next life, your reward shall begin, and you shall take the vow which can never be
      broken. The path lies open before you, and upon it my hand shall guide you, and my blessing shall
      be with you in life and in death, until we stand in the presence of the King.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      So profound was the impression created upon Alcyone by this tremendous prophesy that from that
      moment his despair was gone, and though sometimes he thought sorrowfully of the mother and daughter
      whom he had loved so dearly, he turned always from that to the promise that through that sorrow
      they and all the world should one day be helped. In that faith he lived and worked through all that
      troublous time through all the wars of King Vishtspa; through the Tartar invasion which Prince
      Isgandehar(Deneb) repelled; through the reign of Vishtaspa into that of his grandson Baman; through
      the forty years of Zarathushtra's preachings, wanderings and administrations. That faith sustained
      him even when after ten years of arduous labour Mercury left them and passed on into India, leaving
      behind him the legend of Paishotan, the teacher who never dies, but shall return to found a new
      race and to lead his people to paradise. It helped to keep him brave during the dark periods of
      despondency which came not infrequently to the soul of Zarathushtra, when the prophet bewailed the
      lukewarmness of his followers, admitted doubts as to the success of his mission, or even the truth
      of his visions, and talked of flying the country because of the opposition of Prince Bendva, or the
      Grehma Clan, or other adherents to the older teaching; and it sustained him even under the news of
      the murder of his lifelong hero Zarathushtra, while officiating at the altar of the great temple at
      Balkh, when the city was stormed by the Tartars in 1449.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      Some two years before this, Alcyone had given up constant journeyings and public preachings,
      finding himself scarcely equal to the strain of them. During the last ten years of his life he was
      well cared for by two of the children whom he had so loved Phrem and Thrity (Regel and Betel), the
      widowed daughters of Zarathushtra and Mizar the sisters of Ajax and Demeter. Demeter had died soon
      after her husband Mira had been killed in battle fighting against the Tartars; but one of her
      daughters, Haoshyagha (Fomal), also wonderfully like the long-dead Mizar, the love of his youth,
      came constantly to see and to cheer him. She was at his bedside when he passed away in 1441, and at
      the moment of his death Mercury once more stood visibly materialised before him in that same
      radiant form, smiling on him in tender love. He joined his hands in reverent greeting, and the last
      words upon his lips were the concluding words of the prophesy: Until we stand in the presence of
      the King.
    </view>
  </text>
  <text>
    <view lang="en">
      And in the present life has that prophesy been fulfilled.
    </view>
  </text>
</body>
