<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
<title>
<view lang="en">Life 27</view>
<view lang="ru">Жизнь 27-ая</view>
</title>

<text>
<view lang="en">
In the year 16,876 B.C. there flourished a great Akkadian maritime oligarchy, which was situated somewhat to the south of the central part of Poseidonis. The people belonged to the sixth Atlantean sub-race, resembling the Etruscans or the Phoenicians essentially a race of merchants and sailors, opulent, business-like and inclined to be ostentatious. Mars was the Toltec Emperor at this time, as he had often been before, and this people owned him as suzerain, though practically independent of him. They were governed by a nominally elected council, but the members of this all invariably belonged to half-a-dozen great families, and though Mars nominated the chairman of the council he interfered but little in their affairs. The person who had by far the greatest influence in the country at this time was the High Priest Surya, a man of saintly life and great wisdom, who was known and revered throughout the whole Atlantean empire. As a matter of policy and in order to consolidate the empire, Mars had offered his son Herakles to marry Saturn, the daughter of Surya, and this offer had been accepted. In this way Herakles became, not exactly a subordinate King, but the permanent head of the Akkad council, and so virtually the ruler of the country. The sons of Herakles were Mercury and Venus, and these sons married respectively Brihat and Osiris, which brings us to the generation with which we have to deal, for Alcyone was the eldest son of Mercury, and Sirius and Mizar were the daughters of Venus.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone was thus the grandson of Herakles, and the great-grandson of Mars and Surya. The Emperor Mars was already some sixty years of age when Alcyone was born, and he saw him only three or four times on the occasion of the periodical State progresses of the Emperor through his country, and once when he himself visited the capital. With his other great-grandfather, Surya, he was in constant touch, and a close affection existed between the old man and the boy. Surya considered him a child of great promise, and devoted much of his time to superintending his education, so that he acquired a great deal more than the usual commercial training of the time. The priests were in a certain way highly educated men, for they were all expected to learn their scriptures by heart, and to have to use a book in any part of the service, even the most unusual, would have been considered a weakness. They were also the doctors and scientific men of the time, so that they had to spend many years in study. As a rule only the children of the priestly class became priests, and not by any means all even of them, for it was quite usual for the younger sons of priests to adopt the mercantile or maritime profession.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Herakles being the son of the Emperor, and therefore not of the priestly caste, was not considered eligible to succeed Surya, so that it was understood that when by death or resignation is office became vacant, it should be inherited by his grandson Mercury, who had been trained in the Temple from childhood with that view. As his mother Brihat was also a deeply religious woman, it was natural that Alcyone should find himself familiar with the Temple courts at an early age, and should learn to think the profession of a priest the most desirable in the world. As he grew, however he made many friends among the boys of the town, and soon found that most of them did not at all agree with him in this, but that all their desires were centered round quite another life the excitement of making good bargains and gaining much money, or the interest of sailing to distant lands where all sorts of strange adventures might be encountered. Thrilling stories of dangers surmounted and of fortunes quickly made were dinned into his ears, and there was a side of his nature which responded very rapidly to all this. But when he excitedly repeated these stories of his father and mother, or to his great-grandfather Surya, they gently told him that, fascinating as the life of a sailor or a merchant might be, it was still on the whole one of self-interest, while that of a priest was altruistic that the one worked for the physical life only, but the other for a higher life and for all eternity. They told him also that while both the sailor and the merchant sometimes met with strange and exciting adventures, these were after all rare, while the daily life of each involved a great deal of dull, plodding hard work.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So he grew up with two antagonistic ideals in his mind, and for years he was not quite sure whether he most desired to be a High Priest or a successful pirate. His boy-friends painted in vivid colors the delights of the swash-bucking life, while Surya spoke to him of the higher joys of self-sacrifice; and each in turn seemed desirable to him. Mercury and the gentle Brihat doubted much whether the companionship of his young friends was good for him, and debated whether it was not a duty to withdraw him from its fascination; but the aged Surya advised them to let him go his own way and decide for himself, pointing out that in him were mingled the blood of the Emperor and that of the High Priest, and that they must each have full play. For he said:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 I have seen in my long life many boys, and I believe in this lad and love him; and when the time of decision comes I think he will choose aright. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The old man's confidence was justified. When Alcyone came to the age at which he accepted as a postulant in the Temple, his great-grandfather sent for him and asked him whether he wished to enter it. He replied that he did; but instead of immediately accepting him, Surya told him to go once more among his boy and girlfriends and hear all the stories they could tell him, to go with them on board the vessels then in port and talk with the sailors, and then to come back to him a week later and tell him whether he adhered to his resolution. The boy did as he was told, and the struggle in his mind was a sore one. The tales of adventures had never seemed so attractive; the smell of pitch and of strange spices and far-away seas that hung round the great ships intoxicated him. Worst of all was the attraction of a certain young lady Phocea, the daughter of Alces, one of the rich merchants a little girl of about his own age; many boys were striving to be noticed by her, and she favoured those who boasted loudly of the adventures which they would seek, and the deeds of prowess they would do; and she had once spoken of him half-contemptuously as  only a young priest .
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He went to see her on this occasion, and found her as usual holding a little court of admiring friends near the harbour, and listening to and applauding the gasconde of the would-be sea-captains or pirate kings. One boy especially seemed for the moment to be high in the favour of their fickle young goddess, and he gave himself airs accordingly, and sneered at Alcyone for  his supposed want of dash and courage. Presently, however, his tone changed, for as the children all went on board one of the empty ships moored to the wharf, he, being intent upon showing off before his lady-love some boyish prank, slipped from a plank into the foul water of the dock. He screamed and struggled helplessly, and was in evident danger of drowning for he did not know how to swim; but Alcyone, who was a strong and practiced swimmer, at once plunged in and dragged him to some steps, though only with great difficulty, as the drowning boy clutched him round the neck and he could not free himself. They were both much exhausted, the rescuer being in rather worse condition than the rescued; but some men who had come running up carried them up the steps and into a neighbouring house, where they soon recovered. The little girl, who had fainted, remarked when she came to herself:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 The young priest is the best of them after all. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
But Alcyone blamed her in his mind for the accident, and never after that felt any attraction towards her.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He went back at once to his great-grandfather and said:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 Take me into the Temple, for to help others at home is a better thing than to seek adventure abroad. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
And Surya blessed him, and said:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 You have chosen wisely, as I knew you would. I have prayed much for you, and last night, as I was praying, the past and the future opened before my eyes, and I know what has been and what shall be. Just as today you saved another life at the risk of your own; so long ago did you save my life, even mine, at the cost of your own; and once more in the future you may give up your life for me if you will, and through that sacrifice all the kingdoms of the world shall be blessed. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The boy looked up at Surya in wonder and awe, for the old man's face was transfigured as he spoke, and it seemed as though mighty flames were playing round him; and though Alcyone could not then fully understand what he meant, he never forgot the impression which it made upon him. He was duly admitted into the Temple, and was very happy in his life there, for though the studies were arduous they were well arranged, and were made interesting to the postulants. Surya, wishing perhaps to show the boy that in the priestly life also one might have travel and adventure, offered him the opportunity of accompanying his father Mercury and some other priests upon a mission to a great library and  university in Northern Africa. Naturally Alcyone accepted with the greatest joy, and the voyage was a never-failing wonder and delight to him. It was a long and slow, but not too long for him; indeed, his excitement and interest wen land came in sight were somewhat tempered by the regret which he felt at leaving the vessel, every sailor in which was a personal friend to him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
As they sailed along the coast a curious feeling came over him that he had seen it all before, and it grew so strong that he amused himself by telling the sailors what would come in sight beyond each headland as they came to it; and the remarkable thing was that he was always right. He described in detail the city which was their port of disembarkation long before they reached it; and the sailors who knew it said that his description of the hills and valleys and the position of buildings was marvellously accurate, but that what he said as to the shape and size of the buildings themselves and the extension of the town was almost all of it wrong. When at last they came in sight of it his feelings were of the most mixed description; he recognised instantly all the physical features of the place, but the town was enormously larger than in his opinion it ought to be, and the buildings seemed all different. He was strangely excited at this astounding half recognition of everything, and constantly questioned his father about it, but at first Mercury could only say that he must have travelled  on in advance of the ship in his eagerness, and seen things in a vision.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Presently, when it became evident that the city which he knew was much smaller, it occurred to his father that they might be in the presence of the phenomenon of a memory from a past incarnation; and when they landed he became almost sure of this, because when Alcyone described how, according to his idea, the various streets ought to run or the buildings to stand, in several cases the inhabitants said:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 Yes, there is a tradition that it used to be like that. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When they were carried out to the University on a curious hydraulic rock tramway he became still more excited, and described exactly how it used to work, and the form of the old cars, which had for centuries been superseded by another type; and when they reached the University itself he was quite unable to contain himself, for he declared that he knew every walk in the garden, and dragged his father about to show it all to him. Presently his fullness of memory reawakened that of his father, and Mercury also began to see things as they used to be and to recollect events as well as scenes of a far-away past. Then father and son were able to compare notes, and to realise that in those old days they had been, not father and son, but father and daughter, and that the relative positions had been reversed. Then Alcyone said to his father:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 You are an advanced priest of the Temple, and I am only a beginner; how could I remember all this before you did? 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Mercury replied:   It is just because your body is younger than mine that it is easier for you to remember; I have changed sex too, and so have an entirely different outlook on life, while you have not. Besides, this University was your life work, and so it was impressed more strongly upon your mind than upon mine. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
They talked over all that time together, and marvelled greatly as they recalled incident after incident of the earlier life, and went from building to building, noting the changes. Most of all, perhaps, they were interested in the library, where they found some of the very books in which they used to read some even that they had copied with their own hands.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Among other recollections, the language of that country came back to them, but of course it used to be spoken fifteen hundred years before, so that to those who heard them it sounded archaic and almost unintelligible; indeed the professor of ancient language was the only man with whom they could converse quite freely. The University staff were greatly interested in this wondrous phenomenon, and they had an amusing argument with a professor of history, who insisted that their memory of various events must be wrong because it did not agree with his books. Alcyone found with great glee a statue of himself in that incarnation, and after much persuasion he induced the authorities to inscribe on its pedestal his present name, and a record of the fact that he was a reincarnation of the founder, and the date on which he had visited the University. From this it will be seen that after a searching enquiry the claims of our two travellers were admitted, and this unusual occurrence aroused a vast amount of interest, and was widely known and had a great reputation.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
After their work in connection with the library was completed, they started on their homeward voyage. The ruler of the country sent for them, and desired to persuade them to stay in his realm, but Mercury respectfully declined the invitation, alleging as excuse that he had undertaken in Poseidonis duties belonging to his present incarnation, and that he must return to fulfil them.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Their voyage home was accomplished without serious mishap, though a heavy storm carried them far out of their course and gave them some new experiences. The vessel this time called in passing at the great City of Golden Gate, and Alcyone was much impressed with its architectural splendour, though Mercury felt its moral atmosphere to be foul and degraded. Of course they took this opportunity to pay a visit to Mars, who received them with great kindness, and kept them with him for two months.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
By force of example and by stern repression of evil tendencies, Mars had kept his court at least outwardly decent; but he was well aware that the Toltec civilisation was even then decadent, and that a strong party among his subjects scarcely veiled their impatience of the restrictions which he imposed upon them. He felt that the outlook for the Empire was a gloomy one,and congratulated his descendents that their lot was cast in a part of the continent in which, though the inhabitants were often materialistic and avaricious, they were at least much freer from the darker magic and from what was called   refined' forms of sensuality. Even Alcyone, young though he was, felt that there was something wrong with the place, despite its magnificence, and was glad when the time came for them to pursue their journey.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
  Mars was deeply interested in the account of the remarkable recovery of memory on the part of both father and son at the North African University. He had no recollections of that nature himself, but said that in dreams he frequently found himself leading vast hosts through stupendous mountain ranges, and that he had speculated as to whether those might not be memories of actual achievements in some previous birth. As Alcyone sat and listened to all this, it seemed to him that he too could see those towering peaks and those slow-moving multitudes, with his great-grandfather riding at their head, and his vision added many details which Mars would certainly have recognised if Alcyone had not been far too shy to venture upon describing them in the presence of the Emperor. He did describe them afterwards to his father, but, as we know, Mercury  had not been in the emigration to which they referred, and so they awakened no memory for him.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
When at last they reached their native city, the aged Surya welcomed Alcyone warmly, and rejoiced to hear his visions of the past. The report of these, which had rejected to hear of his visions of the past. The report of these, which had preceded him, caused him to be regarded in the Temple as the most promising of its neophytes, and it was universally felt that he had a great future before him. One person at least reckoned upon that, and determined if possible to share it, and that was Phocea, the girl who had so nearly drawn him away from entering the Temple several years before. She had tried to attract him then; she tried with maturer arts to attract him now.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
But by this time he was trebly armed against her wiles, for immediately on returning from his voyage he had met his cousin Sirius, and at once felt so strong an attraction for her that he determined off hand to marry her at the earliest possible moment. She thoroughly reciprocated his feelings, and was just as eager for instant marriage as he was, but the parents on both sides did not quite understand such a violent case of love at first sight, and insisted kindly but firmly on a delay of at least a year. The young people unwillingly consented to this, because they could not help it, but this intervening period was one of severe trial to both of them, and this became so evident to the discerning eyes of Brihat that she contrived to get it shortened by almost half, to the great relief of the lovers. Surya himself performed the marriage ceremony, though it was but rarely that he took any personal part in the services, usually giving only his benediction to vast crowds from a lofty opening in the faade of the Temple, much as the Pope used to do at Rome. This marriage was indeed his last appearance at any public function, and only a few months later Alcyone and his wife were summoned to his bedside to  receive his farewell message. He said to Alcyone:
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
 Now I stand on the threshold of another world, and mine eyes can pierce the veil which hangs between this and that. I tell you that there lies before you much of tribulation, for all that has been evil in your past must be expiated, and you may be free. In your next birth you will pay something of your debt by a death of violence and after that you will return amidst surroundings of darkness and evil yet if, through that, you can see the light and tear away the veil which binds you, your reward shall be great. You shall follow in my footsteps, and shall fall at the feet of Him whom I also worship. Yes, and she also  (turning to Sirius),  she also shall follow me, and your father shall lead you, for you be all of one great Race the Race of those who help the world. And now I go down into what men call death; but though I seem to leave you, yet in truth I leave you not, for neither death nor birth can separate the members of that Race those who take upon them the vow that can never be broken. So take courage to meet the storm, for after the storm the Sun shall shine the Sun that never sets. 
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
A few days later Surya breathed his last, but Alcyone never forgot him through all his long life, and he often saw him in dreams and received blessing and help from him. So mercury took charge of the great Temple in his stead, and strove to carry on everything as Surya's wisdom had ordered it, his father Herakles co-operating in every way as the head of the temporal government.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The daughters of Venus had been a closely united family; indeed their feelings were so nearly identical that Sirius and Mizar were both in love with Alcyone, as well as with one another. When he married the former, the latter, incapable of any feeling of jealousy, loved both husband and wife just as dearly as before, and they so strongly reciprocated the affection that they invited Mizar to live with them. She joyously accepted , and no one could have been more loyal and loving coadjutor than she was to Sirius during all the years that followed. A more piteous case was to Sirius during all the years that followed. A more piteous case was that of Helios, a niece of Osiris, who had followed. A more piteous case was that of Helios, a niece of Osiris, who had been left an orphan at an early age, and consequently adapted by her uncle Venus. She had grown up with the family, and was so much one with it that she followed the example of the two elder girls in falling in love with Alcyone, and was quite heart-broken when he carried them both off, since she could not well offer to join his new household. She did, however, later came on long visits to the family, and in course of time accepted Alcyone's  younger brother Achilles, thus remaining in close touch with all those whom she loved so well.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The authorities of the North African University had never forgotten their reincarnation founder, the little boy who had told them so marvellous a story and exhibited such vivid enthusiasm. The tale had caught the popular imagination and been repeated in every home in the land, and when, some twelve years after his visit, the headship of the University fell vacant with no obvious successor, and somebody set on foot the idea that the post should be offered to the original founder, there was a tremendous outburst of enthusiasm over the whole country, and the ruler in consequence sent so pressing an invitation and made so generous an offer that Alcyone felt it would be churlish to refuse. Though he had now a wife and three children he consented to expatriate himself, and set up a home for them in a foreign land.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He was received in Africa with a perfect ovation; he landed at the capital city, by the special request of the ruler, and after being feted there for some time made a triumphal progress through the country to his ancient home. He was able to arrange to inhabit the very same suite of rooms or halls in which he had lived fourteen hundred years before, and he even had furniture constructed on archaic models, and endeavoured to reproduce as far as he could the exact appearance of the place in that previous life. The recollection of his earnest efforts then was a never-failing wonder and joy to him now, and he had such an opportunity as is given to few to see the permanent results of his own work after many generations. He threw himself into the university work with a vigour and enthusiasm which fourteen hundred years had not diminished, and his wife Sirius and his sister-in-law Mizar (who of course had accompanied them) co-operated with equal zeal.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Infected by his eagerness, both Sirius and Mizar began to remember something of that remote past, but they never attained to anything approaching his perfect familiarity with the older time. Vesta, who at that time was the youngest child, seemed as thoroughly at home in it all as his father, but Bella, though he also had been equally intimately associated with it all in that other life, had no memory of it whatever.  Alcyone soon found that to establish a university and arrange it all just as one wished was one thing, but that to administer it when all its customs had the weight of a thousand years of tradition behind them was quite another. Still, he was happy in his work, and he managed everything with such tact that no outcry was made against various reforms which he contrived by degrees to institute. He kept up a constant correspondence with his father Mercury, this being indeed one of the stipulations which the latter had made before giving his consent to his acceptance of the headship of the University. He had also made it a condition that his son should return whenever he had urgent need of him, or whenever he felt his own strength beginning to fail.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Some comparatively uneventful years of hard work followed, his children growing up around him. Though they had married so young, he and his wife were exceedingly happy together, and as closely united as when they were twin brothers in the same country in that other life. While Alcyone was working in Africa, his great-grandfather Mars passed away in the City of the Golden Gate, and his grandfather Herakles was called to assume the imperial purple. Venus then took the place of Herakles as temporal chieftain of the Akkads, since his elder brother Mercury was already in charge of the Temple work. Herakles found that the position of Emperor was on sinecure, for he did his best to carry on government on his father's lines, though the opposition of the party who demanded greater license in morals grew ever stronger and more restive. Various conspiracies were unmasked and suppressed, yet new ones were ever coming to light, and it seemed that the hostility between the few who wished to retain the semblance of decent living and the majority who cared little for such things must soon break out into open war.  Under these circumstances Herakles found the government of such things must soon break out into open war. Under these circumstances Herakles found the government of such an Empire a weary and thankless task, and often wished himself back again in the steady-going mercantile oligarchy.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Although the North African University was at that time probably the most famous in the world, the education of the poorer classes in that category was entirely neglected. This matter did not seem to occur at all to the upper classes, but it was brought prominently before Alcyone and Sirius by the fact that an especially faithful servant of theirs, who was really almost a friend, had an exceedingly bright-looking little boy (Boreas) to whom Alcyone's children took a great fancy. It was on enquiring about the education of this boy (in consequence of some remarks made by his own sons) that Alcyone first realised that there was absolutely no provision of this sort for the poorer classes. He arranged easily enough for the teaching of that particular child by a private tutor, and in due course admitted him as a free pupil of the University; but the incident suggested to him that there might well be many more equally bright children among the poor, for whom no such possibilities presented themselves. He and Sirius discussed the matter for a long time together, and finally worked out a tentative scheme, to the carrying out of which they resolved to devote some of the large income of the University.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
It was a sort of combination of a bording-school and an agricultural community, and his plan was that the university should acquire tracts of land in central positions all over the country, and on these tracts should build and operate free schools. Each tract was to be under the joint management of a school master and a farmer, and the boys were to live at the school and spend half of each day in learning and the other half in cultivation the land. The university was to support these colonies for the first year, after which it was expected that the sale of the surplus produce would be sufficient to maintain them. The feeding and clothing of the boys themselves was to be a first charge upon the school funds in either case. Girls were to be admitted to the extent to which suitable work could be found for them. If after a school-colony had worked successfully for some years it was found that it had a sufficient surplus, it was to be allowed the honour of founding branches or offshoots, but all to be under the direct control of the University. Boys who showed exceptional talent were to have facilities for entering other and higher schools, somewhat on the plan of the modern scholarship system, and if they could work their way up to the level required for the University itself, certain allowances were to be made to them, and remunerative work of some sort was to be made to them, when they had passed through its curriculum.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This scheme was first submitted to the ruler of the country, who was graciously pleased to approve of it and to recommend his subjects to take advantage of it. Then Alcyone set vigorously to work, bought land in various places and got other tracts given to him, and began to have schools built much on the general plan of the University itself that is, not one large building, but a number of isolated rooms in a garden. The poor were at first a little shy in taking advantage of the establishments, mainly because the boys who went there were unable to earn any money for their parents; but soon the vast benefits of the scheme began to be generally understood, and they were all filled to overflowing. Alcyone's plan for their management was an economical one, and as he was able to provide them with the right kind of seeds and cuttings form the vast estates of the University, they rapidly became financially independent, and a brisk competition arose among them for the honour of founding branches. Alcyone coupled with it his old idea of physical training, about which he was just an enthusiastic now as in the previous birth, so that the boys whom he turned out were not only far better educated but far healthier than the rest. To conclude this part of the subject here, Alcyone stayed altogether twenty-seven years in North Africa and, the ruler had issued a decree making attendance at them compulsory upon all boys under a certain age until they had reached a certain level, with, however, discretion to local officials to make exceptions where they saw good cause to do so.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
The plan on the whole worked exceedingly well, but it had one unexplained result. The care bestowed upon physical training and the direct affliction with the University gave the pupils of these schools for the poor a considerable advantage over the sons of richer parents who attended private schools. A few merchants consequently began to send their sons to the school-colonies, and presently several of them joined together, bought some land, erected a school of the Alcyone type exclusively for children of their own class, and then offered it to the University. Alcyone accepted it, and it proved a success, and soon there were many others like it. The natural result was that one after another of the old private schools closed for lack of pupils, and in a few years the whole education of the country was entirely under the management of the University, and Alcyone was practically Minister of Public Education.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
All this kept him very busy, and in such congenial toil the years slipped rapidly by. He and Sirius had agreed that their children should not be allowed to forget their native country, and so they had sent each of them back once or twice on visits to their grandfather Mercury. During these visits the three boys had found themselves wives to accompany them back to the country of their adoption. Selene, a younger brother of Alcyone, had married Uranus, but died young, leaving a son Leo and a daughter Mira. On his visit to Poseidonis, Vesta fell in love with and married Mira, and when Selene's death occurred; her brother Leo decided to return to Africa with his sister and brother-in-law. Alcyone at once found work for him in connection with the university, and he soon fell in love with and married Alcyone's eldest daughter Vega. Not long afterwards he met with a sad accident, being thrown from his horse, and receiving injuries which proved fatal; so Vega with her baby son Vajra returned once more to her father's house. After some years she married Pindar, a kind and capable man, and to them was born a daughter, Cygnus, who became a charming little girl and was always a prime favorite with her grandfather Alcyone. They had also a son, Iris.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone worked on steadily for a number of years, and might have spent the whole of his life in guiding the University to which he was so closely linked, but that his father Mercury and his mother Brihat, finding themselves growing old and less active than of yore, wrote begging him to return and solace their last days with his presence. He felt it his duty to obey this call, though it was a great struggle for him to leave his African work. He discussed the matter with his wife, and she also agreed with him that they ought to sacrifice their own wishes, however strong they were, to the desire of the parents whom they so revered. So Alcyone made a journey to the capital and had an audience with the ruler, in which he told him exactly the facts of the case, and what he felt he ought to do.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
At first the ruler flatly refused to give him permission to abandon the University; but after a night's sleep he sent for him again, and announced that if his son Bella (whom the ruler had seen and liked) would act as deputy manager of the University, Alcyone should still remain the nominal Head of the University, and that all important questions connected with it should be submitted for his decision. Alcyone thankfully accepted his arrangement, subject of course to its endorsement by Bella; of which however he had little doubt. On his return home he summoned his sons to a family council, and told them the ruler's'decision. Bella  was a business-like and capable man, and his wife Ulysses had also considerable administrative ability, so it seemed that the interests of the University would be safe in their hands; furthermore Vesta, who was psychic and impressionable, seemed in many ways better fitted for succession to the priestly office in Poseidonis than was his eldest son. After the first surprise of the proposal was over, they all agreed that it was under the circumstances the best that could be done, and Bella in his turn journeyed to the capital to place his formal acceptance of the office in the hands of the ruler, and to receive from him a solemn charge with regard to the conduct of the University. On his return Alcyone set sail for Poseidonis, in the year 16,823, taking with him Mizar, Vesta and Neptune.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
On the voyage a great blow fell upon him in the death of his dearly loved wife Sirius by an accident. She was enceinte at the time, and in very bad weather she was thrown off a couch and fatally injured. Her husband was overpowered by grief, and declared that he could not live without her, and should not know in the least what to do. But she tried to cheer him, and begged him to grant her one last request. Of course he promised to do so, and she asked him to marry her sister Mizar at once, so that the home might go on just as before, and she might feel satisfied that everything was being made comfortable for him. She said that if she knew that this would be soon she could die in peace, and she would also keep near them if it was permitted, and would even try to speak to them. Alcyone and Mizar finally yielded to her request, and promised to marry as soon as they reached home; and when this was settled Sirius peacefully passed away, telling them with her last words not to grieve for her. She was buried at sea, and, true to his promise, Alcyone married Mizar as soon as possible after they reached Poseidonis.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Mercury, who mourned much over the death of Sirius, performed the ceremony for them, and they felt the presence of the dead wife while the service was in progress. Indeed Brihat declared that she saw her standing smilingly beside them, and joining in some of the recitations. Brihat had had a dream or vision of the death of Sirius at the time when it occurred, and neither she nor Mercury was unprepared to hear the news of it on the arrival of the travellers. Mizar proved a true helpmeet for Alcyone; she knew his ways so thoroughly that every thing went on just as though Sirius had been still on the physical plane. She was also thoroughly in sympathy with all his interests and knew the whole of the University business, so that though he never forgot Sirius he soon settled down into the new condition of affairs, and his life ran smoothly along its grooves. His old pleasures in the priestly work was soon revived, and he found that the manifold interests of the Temple left him little time for sorrowing over his loss. As soon as he was little used to the management of affairs Mercury withdrew entirely into the background and lived the life of a recluse, coming forth only rarely and on special occasions.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Alcyone retained under these different conditions his strong interest in educational matters, and made an attempt to introduce into his native land a system similar to that which had been so successful in Africa. He founded a University on the lines of the old one, and opened a couple of his farm-colony schools for the poor. Both attempts may be said to have succeeded, but they were never taken up in the oligarchy with quite the same enthusiasm as in North Africa. Still, he worked hard at the arrangements, and his system slowly spread, and he was thanked by the council for introducing it; but as years passed on he was obliged more and more to delegate to others the business connected with it, for his priestly work became more and more engrossing.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
He kept constantly in touch by correspondence with Bella and the University work in Africa, and frequently and earnest invitations reached him asking him to pay another visit to the scene of his earlier labours. He always promised that he would do this some time of other, but for years no opportunity presented itself.  He was training his son Vesta to succeed him in the Temple work, but Vesta, though eager, zealous and psychic, was still somewhat too impulsive, and did not always distinguish impulses from intuitions, and so was sometimes hurried into unwise actions. His cousin and brother-in-law Augriga proved of the greatest assistance to him, and took up the educational work so enthusiastically that Alcyone soon turned over that department entirely to him. Auriga was a person of hard-headed commonsense, and a good organiser, so under his management the schools soon began to flourish exceedingly.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
Venus the father of Auriga, had long before been called to the City of the golden Gate to succeed Herakles, and he in his turn had summoned his eldest son Crux to support him in his old age, and to learn the way in which so cumbrous an Empire was managed, in preparation for the time when he himself should be called upon to hold the reins of power. In 16,811 Venus passed away and Crux came to the throne, and very shortly after that Mercury and Brihat died within a few months of one another. Though this was not unexpected at so great an age, it came as a shock to Alcyone, all the more so as he had been overworking himself for a long time and was therefore not at his strongest. He felt the need of rest and change, and with considerable difficulty he persuaded to pay the long promised visit to North Africa, the hope being that the sea-voyage and the absence of responsibility might set him up again in health.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
This expectation was to a great extent fulfilled, for his passage was a pleasant one, and he received a most enthusiastic welcome at the University, and was delighted to find that Bella had been managing everything with praiseworthy firmness and tact, so that both the University itself and the schools were in a most satisfactory state of efficiency. He declined to interfere in any way, or to take any share in the management, though he was of course feted everywhere, and expected to appear as a figure-head and make speeches on numerous occasions. He spent twelve months in Africa, and even then returned only because of an urgent request from Vesta. When he reached his native land he was already sixty seven years old, and he yearned much for a life of meditation and repose, so he encouraged Vesta to continue as far as possible the work to which he had grown accustomed during his father's absence, and he himself remained rather in the background, coming forth only on great festivals or when special advice was needed. He was regarded by all the people as a great saint and a person of marvellous wisdom, and those who could obtain his advice in their difficulties thought themselves highly favoured. On several occassions he mesmerically cured people suffering from various diseases, though e refused to make a regular practice of this, saying that he could help only those cases which he was specially inspired to help.
</view>
</text>

<text>
<view lang="en">
So he lived on for seventeen years, passing the evening of his life peacefully and contentedly, hale and vigorous, and keeping all his faculties to the last. Mizar remained inseparable from him (she had of course accompanied him to Africa) and their devotion to one another was touching. When Mizar died in the year 16,793 he seemed scarcely to mourn her, saying that it was not worth while to sorrow over so short a seperation, as he knew he should soon follow her almost immediately. His prediction was justified, for he passed quietly away the following year, leaving behind him a great reputation on two continents. Two exactly similar statues of him were made, and were set up in the Central Halls of his two Universities in that in Africa besides that other statue of his earlier personality on the pedestal of which in his boyhood he had had his present name engraved. The same sculptor produced the two statues, and each University presented  one to the other with a suitable inscription. The story of the founder who had so strangely returned and recognised his work was repeated in Africa for centuries, though later, when the statues had disappeared, it became confused, and ran that he was a great magician who had preserved the same body for fourteen hundred years, and so had revisited the scene of his former labours.
</view>
</text>
</body>